<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-21461</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061167</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Nucleic acids</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>RNA</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>RNA interference</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biotechnology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant biotechnology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Marker-assisted selection</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Dermatology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Skin neoplasms</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Malignant skin neoplasms</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Melanomas</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Epidemiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biomarker epidemiology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Oncology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cancer treatment</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Antibody therapy</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cancers and neoplasms</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Hematologic cancers and related disorders</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Leukemias</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject>
          <subject>Biotechnology</subject>
          <subject>Oncology</subject>
          <subject>Dermatology</subject>
          <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Inhibition of the Receptor Tyrosine Kinase ROR1 by Anti-ROR1 Monoclonal Antibodies and siRNA Induced Apoptosis of Melanoma Cells</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">ROR1 Inhibition in Melanoma</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hojjat-Farsangi</surname>
            <given-names>Mohammad</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ghaemimanesh</surname>
            <given-names>Fatemeh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Daneshmanesh</surname>
            <given-names>Amir Hossein</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bayat</surname>
            <given-names>Ali-Ahmad</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mahmoudian</surname>
            <given-names>Jafar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Jeddi-Tehrani</surname>
            <given-names>Mahmood</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Rabbani</surname>
            <given-names>Hodjatallah</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mellstedt</surname>
            <given-names>Hakan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Oncology-Pathology, Immune and Gene therapy Lab, Cancer Center Karolinska (CCK), Karolinska University Hospital Solna and Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Immunology, School of Medicine, Bushehr University of Medical Sciences, Bushehr, Iran</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Monoclonal Antibody Research Center, Avicenna Research Institute, ACECR, Tehran, Iran</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Rich</surname>
            <given-names>Benjamin Edward</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">mohammad.hojat-farsangi@ki.se</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Supervised the experiments: MHF HM. Reviewed the manuscript: MHF AAB AHD JM MJT HM. Designed the ROR1 peptides and provided the mAbs for this study: HR. Conceived and designed the experiments: MHF. Performed the experiments: FG AAB AHD JM. Wrote the paper: MHF HM.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>8</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <elocation-id>e61167</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Hojjat-Farsangi et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The receptor tyrosine kinase (RTK) ROR1 is overexpressed and of importance for the survival of various malignancies, including lung adenocarcinoma, breast cancer and chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL). There is limited information however on ROR1 in melanoma. In the present study we analysed in seven melanoma cell lines ROR1 expression and phosphorylation as well as the effects of anti-ROR1 monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) and ROR1 suppressing siRNA on cell survival. ROR1 was overexpressed at the protein level to a varying degree and phosphorylated at tyrosine and serine residues. Three of our four self-produced anti-ROR1 mAbs (clones 3H9, 5F1 and 1A8) induced a significant direct apoptosis of the ESTDAB049, ESTDAB112, DFW and A375 cell lines as well as cell death in complement dependent cytotoxicity (CDC) and antibody dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC). The ESTDAB081 and 094 cell lines respectively were resistant to direct apoptosis of the four anti-ROR1 mAbs alone but not in CDC or ADCC. ROR1 siRNA transfection induced downregulation of ROR1 expression both at mRNA and protein levels proceeded by apoptosis of the melanoma cells (ESTDAB049, ESTDAB112, DFW and A375) including ESTDAB081, which was resistant to the direct apoptotic effect of the mAbs. The results indicate that ROR1 may play a role in the survival of melanoma cells. The surface expression of ROR1 on melanoma cells may support the notion that ROR1 might be a suitable target for mAb therapy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was supported by grants from the CLL Global Research Foundation, VINNOVA, the Swedish Research Council, the Cancer and Allergy Foundation, the Swedish Cancer Society, the Cancer Society in Stockholm, the King Gustaf Vth Jubilee Fund, the Karolinska Institute Foundations, the Stockholm County Council and Avicenna Research Institute, ACECR, Tehran, Iran. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Melanoma is a skin cancer arising from melanocytes located in the epidermis. The incidence of melanoma is rapidly increasing. The frequency of melanoma is only 4% of all dermatological cancers but responsible for 80% of the mortality in skin cancer. Early detection and treatment may improve prognosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Paulitschke1">[1]</xref>. A series of melanoma-associated antigens (MAGE) has been identified on melanoma cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Lethe1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Sensi1">[4]</xref>. Large efforts have been done to use different MAGEs for immunotherapy of melanoma patients, but most clinical trials have failed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Poehlein1">[5]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs) are important structures involved in cell signaling, differentiation and proliferation of normal and malignant cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Bennasroune1">[6]</xref>. RTKs and their signaling pathways may contribute to the dysregulation of malignant cells, as self-sufficiency for growth factors, evasion from apoptosis, unlimited cell replication and metastasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Hanahan1">[7]</xref>. The receptor tyrosine-kinase-like orphan receptor 1 (ROR1) is a member of the RTK families <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Green1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Yoda1">[11]</xref> and a highly conserved receptor with no clearly identified ligand/s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Masiakowski1">[12]</xref>. Wnt5a has however been suggested as a candidate ligand for ROR1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Minami1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Zhang1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Endo1">[14]</xref>.</p>
      <p>ROR1 is a transmembrane protein consisting of 937 amino acid residues with an extra and intracellular part. The extracellular part consists of 3 regions, including the Ig-like, cysteine rich (CRD) and kringle (KNG) domains. The CRD and KNG domains might be ligand binding sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Zhang1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Yamaguchi1">[15]</xref>. The intracellular part contains a tyrosine kinase domain that might be triggered to phosphorylation by other cytoplasmic signaling proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>. ROR1 is expressed during the development of the nervous system and regulates survival and maintenance of neural progenitor cells in the brain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Endo1">[14]</xref>. It is also expressed in other organs during embryogenesis and of importance for the morphogenesis of several organs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Masiakowski1">[12]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The role of ROR1 in various malignancies is not well understood. No mutations have been noted <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh1">[17]</xref>. ROR1 is however considered to be a survival factor for various malignancies including chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Mellstedt1">[18]</xref>, breast cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Zhang1">[13]</xref> and lung adenocarcinoma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Yamaguchi1">[15]</xref>. ROR1 might be a promising antigen to be targeted. Anti-ROR1 monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) and ROR1 specific siRNAs have been shown to induce apoptosis and necrosis of malignant cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Choudhury1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh2">[20]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In the current study, we analysed the expression and phosphorylation of ROR1 in a series of malignant melanoma cell lines using RT-PCR, immunocytofluorescence (IF), flow cytometry and western blot. The cytotoxic effects of anti-ROR1 mAbs were evaluated in the absence or presence of complement (complement dependent cytotoxicity) (CDC) or immune effector cells (antibody dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity) (ADCC) and ROR1 siRNA was used for gene silencing.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Cell lines and controls</title>
        <p>The melanoma cell lines ESTDAB049, 075, 081, 094 and 112 were obtained from the European Searchable Tumor Cell Line Data Base (ESTDAB project, contract no. QLRI-CT-2001- 01325) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Pawelec1">[21]</xref>. The DFW melanoma cell line was derived from a metastatic lesion from a patient at Radiumhemmet, Karolinska Hospital University Solna, Stockholm, Sweden <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Cronwright1">[22]</xref>. A375 (melanoma cell line) and T47D (human ductal breast epithelial tumor cell line) were obtained from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC). After thawing, cells were grown in RPMI-1640 (Gibco, Life Technologies, Karlsruhe, Germany) containing 10% FCS (Gibco), 2% glutamine (Biochrom KG, Berlin, Germany) and 100 ug/ml penicillin/streptomycin (Biochrom KG) (complete medium) at 37°C in a humidified incubator with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Production of anti-ROR1 monoclonal antibodies</title>
        <p>Mouse monoclonal antibodies against ROR1 were generated against the extracellular part of ROR1 as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh2">[20]</xref>. Out of more than 20 clones, four clones including 1A8, 1E9, 5F1 and 3H9 (all of the IgG1 isotype) were selected. The characterization and specificity of the anti-ROR1 mAbs (Avicenna Research Center, Tehran, Iran) were checked by ELISA and after transfection of the HEK293 cell line with the extracellular domain of ROR1 in western blot as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh1">[17]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>RNA preparation, cDNA synthesis and RT-PCR</title>
        <p>Total RNA was purified from cells, using pure link RNA mini-kits (Ambion, Inc., Austin, Texas, USA). One ug of high quality RNA was reversely transcribed using a first strand cDNA synthesis kit (Fermentas, St. Leon-Rot, Germany) according to the manufacturer's instructions. PCR amplification was performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-HojjatFarsangi1">[23]</xref>, using 150 ng of cDNA for PCR amplification. ROR1 specific primers, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CTGCTGCCCAAGAAACAGAG-3′</named-content> (position 455–474) as the sense and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CATAGTGAAGGCAGCTGTGATCT-3′</named-content> (position 977–999) as antisense primers, with a PCR product of 545 bp (reference: g.b. M97675) were used for ROR1 amplification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh1">[17]</xref>. Beta-actin was used as a control for cDNA quality and integrity (Sense primer: <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">ATTAAGGAGAAGCTGTGCTACGTC</named-content>, Anti-sense primer: <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">ATGATGGAGTTGAAGGTAGTTTCG</named-content>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh1">[17]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Immunocytofluorescence (IF)</title>
        <p>Cells were grown on coverslips (Marienfeld GmbH &amp; Co, Lauda-Königshofen, Germany) placed in 35-mm dishes in an incubator with humidified air and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 37°C. After 24 h of incubation, medium was removed. Cells were dried at room temperature (RT) and fixed with cold neutral buffered formalin for 5 min. The slides were washed with tris-buffered saline (pH = 7.4), containing 0.1% Bovine Serum Albumin (TBS-BSA) and blocked with 5% sheep serum diluted in TBS-BSA for 30 min. Slides were then incubated with 5 ug/ml of ROR1 mAbs as well as with a non-relevant mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype) (eBioscience, Inc., San Diego, California, USA) for 1 h at RT. Following three washes, slides were incubated with FITC- conjugated sheep anti-mouse IgG (1∶100) (Avicenna Research Center) for 1 h. After three washes in TBS-BSA, the nuclei were counterstained with 1 ug/ml of 4′, 6-Diamidino-2-Phenylindole Dihydrochloride (DAPI) (Sigma-Aldrich Corp., Saint Louis, MO) for 5 min. Finally, cells were mounted in PBS-glycerol 50% and examined with a fluorescent microscope (Zeiss Axioplan2, Oberkochen, Germany).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Flow cytometry analysis</title>
        <p>Surface staining of cells was performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-HojjatFarsangi2">[24]</xref>. Briefly, 10<sup>6</sup> cells were washed in PBS and suspended in 100 ul of FACS buffer (PBS, 0.1% sodium azide, and 0.5% BSA). Five ug/ml of the respective anti-ROR1 mAbs or one ug/ml of polyclonal goat anti-ROR1 antibody (R&amp;D system, Minneapolis, MN, USA) was added to the cells and incubated at 4°C for 1 h. Cells were washed with FACS buffer and FITC conjugated sheep anti-mouse Ig or FITC conjugated rabbit anti-goat Ig (Dako, Glostrup, Denmark) (1∶100) were added and incubated at 4°C for 1 h. Finally, cells were washed with FACS buffer and fixed with 1% paraformaldehyde in PBS. A FACSCalibur flow cytometer (BD Bioscience, Mountain View, CA, USA) was used to analyse ROR1 expressing cells. 5×10<sup>4</sup> events were counted. Cells were analyzed using the FlowJo software program (Tree Star Inc. Ashland OR, USA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Western blot analysis</title>
        <p>10×10<sup>6</sup> cells were lysed in 200 ul of lysis buffer [0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 50 mM Tris- HC1, pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 1% protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich) and phosphatase inhibitor (Roche, Stockholm, Sweden)] and incubated on ice for 30 min with 5 min interval and vortexed for 10 sec. Bicinchoninic acid (BCA) protein assay kit (Thermo Scientific, IL, USA) was used to measure the protein concentration according to the manufacturer's instructions. Ten ug of the cell lysate or immunoprecipitated ROR1 (using goat anti-ROR1 antibody) was run on 10% Bis-Tris SDS-PAGE gel at 120V/90mA for 2 h (IP-WB). After electrophoresis, proteins were transferred to PVDF membrane (Millipore Corporation, Bedford, MA, USA) and blocked overnight at 4°C with 5% nonfat dry milk (skim milk) or BSA in TBS containing 0.1% Tween 20 (TBS-T). Filters were incubated with anti-phospho-tyrosine (0.5 ug/ml) (PY99, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., CA, USA), anti-phospho-serine mAbs (clone 4A4) (0.5 ug/ml) (Millipore Corporation) or goat anti-ROR1 polyclonal antibody (R&amp;D system) (0.2 ug/ml) for 1 h at RT. After washing with TBS-T, filters were incubated with peroxidase-conjugated rabbit anti-goat or rabbit anti-mouse immunoglobulin (Dako) for 1 h at RT followed by washings and developed using the advanced ECL chemiluminescence detection system (GE Healthcare, Uppsala, Sweden).</p>
        <p>Cleaved PARP as well as caspase-8 and 9 and MCL-1 expression were analyzed using cell lysates from the apoptosis experiments (see below). Briefly, 10 ug of the protein lysate was run in western blot. Filters were incubated with rabbit anti-PARP, cleaved caspase-8 (p 43/41 and p18), cleaved caspase-9 (p37) and MCL-1 antibodies (Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA) respectively overnight at 4°C, and subsequently with a peroxidase-conjugated goat anti-rabbit antibody (Dako). Finally, blots were developed with a chemiluminescence detection system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh2">[20]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Annexin-V/PI apoptosis assay</title>
        <p>5×10<sup>4</sup> cells/well were cultured in 6 replicates in 24 well plates. After 24 h, medium was replaced and cells were incubated with 5 ug/ml of the ROR1 mAbs in 1 ml of complete medium. Cells treated with a non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype) (eBioscience) or 1 uM staurosporine (Sigma-Aldrich) were used as controls, respectively. After 24 h of incubation at 37°C in humidified air with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, cells were collected (24 well plates were incubated on ice for 10 min and then cells were suspended by pipetting), washed twice with PBS and resuspended in 150 ul of binding buffer. Five ul of FITC-conjugated Annexin-V and PI (propidium Iodide) (BD Biosciences) was added to the cells, vortexed and incubated at RT in the dark for 10 min. Apoptosis was measured by flow cytometry (FACSCalibur, BD Biosciences). Cells were analyzed using the FlowJo software program.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>XTT cytotoxicity assay</title>
        <p>XTT (2,3-bis-(2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium-5-carboxanilide) cytotoxicity assay was used as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Roehm1">[25]</xref>. Briefly, 10<sup>4</sup> cells were incubated in 200 ul complete medium in 6 replicates using 96 well plates. After 24 h, medium was replaced and anti-ROR1 mAbs were added to the cells (5 ug/ml) as well as the non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype). The T47D cell line treated with mAbs was used as a negative control <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>. Cells were incubated for 24 h with mAbs and 20 ul of XTT (5 mg/ml) (Sigma-Aldrich) in PBS was added after activation of XTT with PMS (N-methyl dibenzopyrazine methyl sulfate) (Sigma-Aldrich). Cells were incubated for further 2 h at RT. Optical density (OD) was measured at 450 nm. Cytotoxicity was calculated as follows: % cytotoxicity = (Test OD - background OD)/(positive control OD - background OD)×100. The positive control OD was defined as the value of untreated cells at time zero and background OD as the value of medium alone.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>CDC and ADCC assays</title>
        <p>The effect of anti-ROR1 mAbs in CDC was evaluated as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Staff1">[26]</xref>. Briefly, 5×10<sup>4</sup> target cells were plated in V-bottomed microtiter plates (Nunc, Roskilde, Denmark) in 100 ul complete medium. Cells were incubated with 5 ug/ml of each of the anti-ROR1 mAb as well as with 5 ug/ml of the non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype) for 30 min at RT followed by washings with RPMI-1640. Twenty percent fresh normal human serum (NHS) in 100 ul complete medium was added and cells incubated at 37°C in a humidified air with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 2 h. Finally, cells were collected, washed twice with PBS and resuspended in 150 ul of Annexin-V/PI binding buffer. Five ul of PI was added to the cells, vortexed and incubated at RT in the dark for 10 min. The frequency of PI stained cells was measured by flow cytometry.</p>
        <p>ADCC assay was performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh2">[20]</xref>. Briefly, cells were labeled with 2.8 MBq sodium Cr51 (PerkinElmer Inc. Wellesley, MA, USA) for 3 h at 37°C. After 3 washes with RPMI-1640, 10<sup>4</sup> cells in 100 ul medium were added to each round-bottomed microtiter well (Nunc) and natural killer (NK) cells enriched from healthy donors buffy coat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Staff1">[26]</xref> were added to yield target: effector cell ratios of 1∶25 and 1∶50 to a final volume of 200 ul containing 5 ug/ml of the anti-ROR1 mAbs or the non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype). Each experiment was run in six wells. After 4 h at 37°C, the reaction was stopped by centrifugation. Cr51 release was measured by a gamma counter (Beckman Gamma 5500, Beckman Coulter, Fullerton, CA). The percentage of target cell lysis was calculated based on the following formula: % specific lysis = (experiment cpm- spontaneous cpm)/(maximum cpm-spontaneous cpm)×100. Maximum Cr51 release was determined by adding 1% of Triton X-100 to the target cells and spontaneous release was measured in the absence of antibodies and effector cells.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2j">
        <title>ROR1 siRNA transfection</title>
        <p>Downregulation of endogenous ROR1 mRNA was performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Choudhury1">[19]</xref>. The siRNA sequences used to target <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-ATGAACCAATGAATAACATC-3′</named-content> ROR1 mRNA with antisense <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GAUGUUAUUCAUUGGUUCAdTdT-3′</named-content> and sense <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-UGAACCAAUGAAUAACAUCdTdT-3′</named-content> sequences. Control siRNA (MISSION siRNA Universal Negative Control; Sigma-Aldrich) was used as a negative control. Cells were harvested after 6, 12, 24 and 36 h of incubation for mRNA preparation, the Annexin-V/PI apoptosis assay and for western blot.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2k">
        <title>Data analysis</title>
        <p>Statistical analyses were performed using student's t-test and Mann–Whitney U test as appropriate. Analyses were conducted using the SPSS statistical package (SPSS, Chicago, IL). P-values less than 0.05 were considered to be significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>ESTDAB (European Searchable Tumor Cell Line Database) contains more than 100 melanoma cell lines with defined HLA class I and II genotypes in the ESTDAB Melanoma Cell Bank (Tubingen, Germany). These cell lines also have been characterized for glycan composition in relation to clinical tumor progression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Pawelec1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Laidler1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Mendez2">[29]</xref>. In the current study, we randomly selected five cell lines (049, 075, 081, 094 and 112) from this collection and two other melanoma cell lines (A375 and DFW).</p>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>ROR1 expression and phosphorylation</title>
        <p>The expression of ROR1 mRNA was determined by RT-PCR. ROR1 was expressed in all melanoma cells at the mRNA level but not in the T47D cell line. The protein expression of ROR1 was assessed by IF. All melanoma cell lines expressed the ROR1 molecule (anti-ROR1 mAb clone 3H9). Representative results for the ESTDAB112 cells are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g001">Figure 1A</xref>. In IP-WB (immunoprecipitation followed by western blot), a 130 kDa band representing fully glycosylated ROR1 was detected using a goat anti-ROR1 polyclonal antibody for immunoprecipitation. This band could also be shown to be phosphorylated using anti-phospho-tyrosine and phospho-serine mAbs. No expression of ROR1 was seen in the T47D cell line <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0061167-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Protein expression of the receptor tyrosine kinase ROR1 in melanoma cell lines.</title>
            <p>Representative experiment (IF) showing the expression of ROR1 on the ESTDAB112 cell line using the anti-ROR1 (clone 3H9) mAb (40×). Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI (blue). A non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype) was used as a negative control (A). Western blot analysis of ROR1 protein expression and phosphorylation in melanoma cells detected by a goat anti-ROR1 antibody, anti-p-tyrosine (PY99) and anti-p-serine (clone 4A4) mAbs (B). ROR1 protein was shown to be phosphorylated in all cell lines using immunoprecipitation of ROR1. A 130 kDa band corresponding to the fully glycosylated/phosphorylated ROR1 was observed. The T47D cell line was used as a ROR1 negative control <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>ROR1 surface expression and intensity was also analysed by flow cytometry. All cell lines expressed ROR1 as detected by the four anti-ROR1 mAbs and a polyclonal goat anti-ROR1 antibody (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061167-t001">Table 1</xref>). However it should be noted that a proportion (about 50%) of the melanoma cells did not express ROR1.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0061167-t001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Frequency of ROR1 positive melanoma cells.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0061167-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ROR1 mAb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESTDAB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">049</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">075</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">081</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">094</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFW</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A375</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T47D</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1A8</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (17.1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5 (16)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (60.3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.1 (54.5)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.3 (19.7)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.4 (52.1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.9 (36.7)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1E9</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.3 (27)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6 (14)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5 (38.6)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.2 (113)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.6 (23)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (74)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (12.5)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>5F1</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.9 (29.3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.3 (22.3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5 (40.4)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.9 (46.6)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.8 (15.8)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3 (47.5)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.3 (86.4)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (5)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>3H9</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.1 (99.6)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.4 (22.2)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (74.2)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4 (46.7)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.7 (24.1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.4 (85.7)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7 (56.9)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>Frequency (%) of ROR1 positive cell lines and Geometric Mean Fluorescence Intensity, stained by 4 anti-ROR1 mAbs in flow cytometry.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Induction of apoptosis by anti-ROR1 mAbs</title>
        <p>Induction of apoptosis by the anti-ROR1 mAbs in the absence of complement or effector cells was analysed after 24 h incubation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). The frequency of apoptotic/necrotic cells (lower right, upper left and right quadrants) induced by a non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype) was deducted from the frequency of cells treated with the anti-ROR1 mAbs. Anti-ROR1 mAbs alone induced apoptosis of melanoma cells varying between 4% and 54% as determined by Annexin-V/PI staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>) and the XTT assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). Representative experiments are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g002">Figure 2C</xref>. Different anti-ROR1 mAbs had various effects on the individual cell lines. The anti-ROR1 mAb clones 5F1, 3H9 and 1A8 were the most effective using ESTDAB049, ESTDAB112, DFW and A375 cell lines, while anti-ROR1 mAb clone 1E9 was the most effective using ESTDAB075 cells. ESTDAB081 and 094 cell lines were resistant to the direct cytotoxic effects of the anti-ROR1 mAbs. The frequency of ROR1 positive cells did not differ significantly comparing the various melanoma cell lines. No effect on apoptosis of the non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype) was observed. The anti-ROR1 mAbs did not induce apoptosis of the ROR1 negative cell line T47D.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0061167-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Induction of apoptosis in melanoma cells using anti-ROR1 mAbs.</title>
            <p>Frequency (%) of apoptotic/necrotic cells in Annexin-V<sup>+</sup>/PI<sup>+</sup> (A) and XTT cytotoxicity assay (B) induced by anti-ROR1 mAbs in the absence of complement or immune effector cells [anti-ROR1 mAb clones 1A8 (□), 1E9 (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and 5F1 (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>)3H9 (▪)]. Dot plot diagrams of apoptosis induced by anti-ROR1 mAbs (clones 1A8 and 3H9) in melanoma cells and ROR1 negative cell line T47D (Annexin-V/PI) (C). Western blot for cleaved PARP, caspase 8, 9 and MCL-1 expression in apoptotic ESTDAB049 and ESTDAB112 cells induced by the anti-ROR1 mAb clone 5F1 (D). (−) cells treated with a non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype). (+) cells treated with the anti-ROR1 mAb clone 5F1. (S) cells treated with staurosporine.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Western blot analyses for cleaved PARP and caspase-8/9 as well as downregulation of MCL-1 were done using protein lysates prepared from the 24 h apoptosis experiments. The effects of the anti-ROR1 mAb clone 5F1 were tested on the ESTDAB049, ESTDAB112 and A375 melanoma cells. The anti-ROR1 mAbs induced cleavage of PARP, caspase 8 and caspase 9 as well as down-regulation of MCL-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>).</p>
        <p>Staurosporine was used as a positive control for apoptosis induction. More than 70% of cells had gone into apoptosis after 24 h incubation (data not shown). Staurosporine also induced a significant PARP, caspase 8 and 9 cleavage as well as MCL-1 downregulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Cytotoxic effects of anti-ROR1 mAbs in CDC</title>
        <p>The effect of anti-ROR1 mAbs in CDC was evaluated after 2 h incubation of cells in the presence of human complement. Anti-ROR1 mAbs could activate complement to lyse melanoma cells to a varying degree. The CDC activity of the various mAbs against the different cell lines are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g003">Figure 3A–C</xref>. The anti-ROR1 mAb clone 1E9 had the lowest CDC activity against the A375 cell line. Lysis of all mAbs in the presence of complement using the 7 melanoma cell lines (except for anti-ROR1 mAb clone 1E9 on A375 cell line) was statistically significant compared to no complement (p&lt;0.01). No CDC activity was seen using the ROR1 negative T47D cell line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). Comparison of 4 mAbs in CDC showed a significantly better effect of mAb 5F1 compared to 3H9 using ESTDA049 (p = 0.01), of 3H9 on the ESTDAB075 cell line compared to the other 3 mAbs (p = 0.01-0.001), of mAb 3H9 compared to 5F1 on ESTDAB094 (p = 0.01) and of mAbs 1A8, 5F1 and 3H9 compared to 1E9 mAb on the A375 cell line (p = 0.01-0.0001).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0061167-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Anti-ROR1 mAbs in complement dependent cytotoxicity (CDC).</title>
            <p>Frequency (%) (mean+SEM) of apoptotic/necrotic cells (Annexin-V<sup>+</sup>/PI<sup>+</sup>) induced by 4 anti-ROR1 mAbs with (▪) or without (□) human complement using various ESTDAB (A, B), DFW and A375 melanoma cell lines (C). The T47D cell line did not express ROR1. <bold><sup>*</sup></bold>P = 0.01; <bold><sup>**</sup></bold>P = 0.001. P-values refer to comparison with and without complement for the respective mAbs. NR mAb: non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype), C: Complement.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Antibody dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity (ADCC)</title>
        <p>Purified NK cells were used as effector cells. Various effects of the anti-ROR1 mAbs were noted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). The lowest and highest cytotoxic activity was observed for the anti-ROR1 mAb clone 5F1 on DFW (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>) and ESTDAB081 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). The effects of the anti-ROR1 mAbs on melanoma cell lines was statistically significant compared to the non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype) as well as in comparison to the ROR1 negative cell line T47D (P = 0.05-0.0001).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0061167-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Cytotoxic effects of anti-ROR1 mAbs in the presence of NK cells (ADCC).</title>
            <p>Frequency (%) (mean+SEM) of apoptotic/necrotic cells (Annexin-V<sup>+</sup>/PI<sup>+</sup>) induced by 4 anti-ROR1 mAbs and a non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype) in the presence of NK cells at different target: effector ratios. Target cells: ESTDAB049 (□), 075 (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), DFW (▪), A375 (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) (A) and ESTDAB081 (□), 094 (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), 112 (▪) melanoma cells and T47D (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) as a ROR1 negative cell line (B). ADCC of the melanoma cells induced by the anti-ROR1 mAbs compared to the non-relevant isotype control mAb (mouse IgG1 isotype) as wells as to the T47D cell line was statistically significant (P = 0.05-0.0001).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Silencing of ROR1 in melanoma cells by siRNA</title>
        <p>A ROR1 specific siRNA was used to suppress ROR1 expression in those melanoma cell lines that were most sensitive to the direct apoptotic effect of the anti-ROR1 mAbs (ESTDAB049, 075, 112, DFW and A375) as well as the ESTDAB081 melanoma cell line which was resistant to apoptosis by anti-ROR1 mAbs. Transfection of melanoma cells induced a marked decrease in the ROR1 gene-expression (RT-PCR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). ROR1 was also downregulated at the protein level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). Silencing of ROR1 induced apoptosis of the ROR1 positive melanoma cell lines but not of the T47D ROR1 negative cell line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061167-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Morphological changes of the cells typical for apoptosis were noted by light microscopy as well as loss of adherence to tissue culture plates (data not shown).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0061167-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Transfection of melanoma cells (n = 6) using ROR1 suppressing siRNA.</title>
            <p>Downregulation of ROR1 mRNA (RT-PCR) (A). Downregulation of the ROR1 protein (130 kDa) expression (B). (−) untreated cells, (C) control siRNA treated cells, (+) ROR1 siRNA treated cells.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0061167-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Apoptosis of melanoma cells treated with siROR1.</title>
            <p>Dot plot (frequency) of apoptotic/necrotic melanoma cells (Annexin-V<sup>+</sup>/PI<sup>+</sup>) treated with siRNA, control siRNA and untreated. Within each quadrant the frequency of apoptotic cells is shown. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Results</xref> are presented for the ESTDAB049, ESTDAB075, A375, ESTDAB112 (sensitive to apoptosis by anti-ROR1 mAbs) and ESTDAB081 (resistant to apoptosis by anti-ROR1 mAbs), The cell lines T74D cell line was used as a ROR1 negative control.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0061167.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>ROR1 is not only overexpressed in hematologic malignancies, but also in solid tumors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Zhang1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Yamaguchi1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Rabbani1">[30]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh3">[32]</xref>. ROR1 knockdown prevented growth of primary leukemic cells as well as of breast cancer cells in vitro and in vivo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Zhang1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Choudhury1">[19]</xref>. ROR1 was constitutively phosphorylated in CLL and cell lines of different origins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Mellstedt1">[18]</xref>. Current evidence suggests that ROR1 might play a role as a survival factor for various malignancies and to be an interesting target for therapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Zhang1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Yamaguchi1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh2">[20]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In the present study we could show that melanoma cell lines expressed a 130 kDa ROR1 protein, corresponding to the fully glycosylated isoform <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Kaucka1">[33]</xref>. A proportion of melanoma cell lines did however not express ROR1 on the surface or at least not detectable by our anti-ROR1 mAbs. This subpopulation might represent melanoma cells with a low proliferative activity as ROR1 has been shown to be expressed in less mature cells with a high rate of cell division <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Yamaguchi1">[15]</xref>. ROR1 was phosphorylated at serine and tyrosine residues. Transfection of melanoma cells using ROR1 siRNA, downregulated ROR1, which was proceeded by apoptosis. Specific anti-ROR1 mAbs induced apoptosis of the melanoma cells.</p>
      <p>Functional characteristics of cellular proteins are related to post-translational modifications, as glycosylation, forming a unique functional glycan in the tissue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Marth1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Ohtsubo1">[35]</xref>. Aberrant glycosylation has been demonstrated for various proteins in melanoma cells with functional consequences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Laidler1">[27]</xref>. The ESTDAB series of melanoma cell lines showed different glycan patterns which related to clinical characteristics of the patients from which the cell lines were derived <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Pawelec1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Laidler1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Mendez2">[29]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Depending on the glycosylation pattern of an antigen, a targeting mAb may induce various effects upon binding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gottlinger1">[36]</xref>. The frequency of ROR1 positive cells did not differ markedly between the various melanoma cell lines, but a significant variation in the cytotoxic effects of the different anti-ROR1 mAbs was noted. The ESTDAB081 cell line was resistant to the apoptotic effect of the anti-ROR1 mAbs, but not to siRNA. These variations might mirror post-translation modifications of ROR1, as well as the epitopes recognized by the mAbs in addition to other factors of importance for drug resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gottlinger1">[36]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Hu1">[37]</xref>. Gene silencing of ROR1 induced apoptosis also in mAb resistant cells indicating that some ROR1 mAbs may not mediate a proper apoptotic signal.</p>
      <p>The induction of direct apoptosis of melanoma cells is in agreement with recent findings demonstrating the same phenomenon in primary CLL leukemic cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Mellstedt1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh2">[20]</xref>. Targeting ROR1 in CLL with anti-ROR1 mAbs induced rapid dephosphorylation of ROR1 preceding apoptosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Mellstedt1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh2">[20]</xref>. Mechanisms of action for induction of apoptosis by anti-ROR1 antibodies are not well understood but pathways as AKT/CREB may be involved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Mellstedt1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh2">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Zhang2">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh4">[38]</xref>. The A375 melanoma cell line has been shown to express activated BRAF and mediate a strong BRAF/MEK/ERK signal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Hoeflich1">[39]</xref>. Whether ROR1 activation might be associated with the BRAF/MEK/ERK signaling pathway or if blocking of ROR1 may mediate cell death through this pathway is not known.</p>
      <p>Phosphorylation of serine and tyrosine residues is important for regulating protein activities including RTKs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gullick1">[40]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Huttlin1">[42]</xref>. ROR1 as well as ErbB2 are both members of the type I RTK subclass, contributing to the malignant transformation of various human cancers. High expression of HER1/2, VEGFR<sub>2</sub>/KRD and estrogen receptors and their tyrosine phosphorylation in breast cancer correlated with a poor prognosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gullick1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Slamon1">[43]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Paterson1">[44]</xref>. Our findings, showing phosphorylation of ROR1 at tyrosine and serine residues in melanoma cell lines is of interest. We have recently shown that ROR1 is highly phosphorylated in progressive compared to non-progressive CLL <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Mellstedt1">[18]</xref>. Furthermore, mouse ROR1 is phosphorylated at the serine position 652 located in the activation segment of ROR1 both in the human and mouse ROR1 protein and may be an important site to be triggered by serine/threonine kinases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Huttlin2">[45]</xref>. It is not clear if phosphorylation of ROR1 at tyrosine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Bae2">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Khoury1">[48]</xref> or serine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Baltensperger1">[49]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Noble1">[50]</xref> residues is due to autophosphorylation or not. Tyrosine and serine phosphorylation might be triggered by other kinases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Bennasroune2">[51]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Expression of ROR1 has previously been shown in 3 melanoma cell lines including SK-MEL 2, 5 and 28 and ROR1 was phosphorylated at tyrosine and serine residues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>. SiRNA transfection prevented cell growth only in a low numbers of cells, probably due to a low expression and phosphorylation of ROR1. However, a high degree of growth inhibition was observed in the ROR1 high expressing non-melanoma cell lines NCI-H1993 and HS746T <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>. These two cell lines had an abnormality in the Met oncogene inducing activation of Met. ROR1 might have been phosphorylated by Met as a result of transphosphorylation but a low degree of autophosphorylation could also be seen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>. To our knowledge, there is no report showing aberrant expression of the Met oncogene in those melanoma cell lines we used. Our data may support the suggestion that the Met RTK is not the only RTK to phosphorylate ROR1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Zhang1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Yamaguchi1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Gentile1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Zhang2">[31]</xref>. Other modifications might contribute to the functional properties of ROR1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Butenas1">[52]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Singh1">[53]</xref>. Furthermore, cells expressing endogenously upregulated ROR1 might be differently activated compared to transfected cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Chakrabarti1">[54]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0061167-Leeming1">[55]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In summary, we described for the first time the expression of ROR1 at the mRNA and protein levels in melanoma cells and could show that targeting melanoma cells by anti-ROR1 mAbs and ROR1 suppressing RNA induced apoptosis of the cells. Further studies on the biology of ROR1 in melanoma are warranted as well as to develop anti-ROR1 targeted therapy.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The secretarial help from Ms Leila Relander is highly appreciated. We thank Monoclonal Antibody Research Center, Avicenna Research Institute, ACECR, Tehran, Iran, for producing and providing us with the anti-ROR1 mAbs.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Paulitschke1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulitschke</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunstfeld</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slany</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Micksche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Entering a new era of rational biomarker discovery for early detection of melanoma metastases: secretome analysis of associated stroma cells</article-title>. <source>J Proteome Res</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>2501</fpage>–<lpage>2510</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Lethe1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lethe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michaux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Smet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Godelaine</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>LAGE-1, a new gene with tumor specificity</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>903</fpage>–<lpage>908</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Chen1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gure</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stockert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Identification of multiple cancer/testis antigens by allogeneic antibody screening of a melanoma cell line library</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>6919</fpage>–<lpage>6923</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Sensi1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sensi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Traversari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radrizzani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maccalli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte clones from different patients display limited T-cell-receptor variable-region gene usage in HLA-A2-restricted recognition of the melanoma antigen Melan-A/MART-1</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>5674</fpage>–<lpage>5678</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Poehlein1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poehlein</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruttinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urba</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Immunotherapy for melanoma: the good, the bad, and the future</article-title>. <source>Curr Oncol Rep</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Bennasroune1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennasroune</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aunis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cremel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Tyrosine kinase receptors as attractive targets of cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Hanahan1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The hallmarks of cancer</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Green1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuntz</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Ror receptor tyrosine kinases: orphans no more</article-title>. <source>Trends Cell Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>536</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Minami1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oishi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ror-family receptor tyrosine kinases in noncanonical Wnt signaling: their implications in developmental morphogenesis and human diseases</article-title>. <source>Dev Dyn</source> <volume>239</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Robinson1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The protein tyrosine kinase family of the human genome</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>5548</fpage>–<lpage>5557</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Yoda1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oishi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Expression and function of the Ror-family receptor tyrosine kinases during development: lessons from genetic analyses of nematodes, mice, and humans</article-title>. <source>J Recept Signal Transduct Res</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Masiakowski1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masiakowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>A novel family of cell surface receptors with tyrosine kinase-like domain</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>267</volume>: <fpage>26181</fpage>–<lpage>26190</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Zhang1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>ROR1 is expressed in human breast cancer and associated with enhanced tumor-cell growth</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e31127</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Endo1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Ror family receptor tyrosine kinases regulate the maintenance of neural progenitor cells in the developing neocortex</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>2017</fpage>–<lpage>2029</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Yamaguchi1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>NKX2-1/TITF1/TTF-1-Induced ROR1 is required to sustain EGFR survival signaling in lung adenocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Gentile1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentile</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lazzari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benvenuti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trusolino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Comoglio</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Ror1 is a pseudokinase that is crucial for Met-driven tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>3132</fpage>–<lpage>3141</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daneshmanesh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikaelsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeddi-Tehrani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bayat</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghods</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Ror1, a cell surface receptor tyrosine kinase is expressed in chronic lymphocytic leukemia and may serve as a putative target for therapy</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>1190</fpage>–<lpage>1195</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Mellstedt1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mellstedt H, Hojjat-Farsangi M, Mansouri L, Österborg A, Rabbani H (2011) ROR1 isoforms are constitutively phosphorylated in chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) - a survival factor for CLL cells. 53th American Society of hematology (ASH), San Diego, USA 10–14 December.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Choudhury1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Derkow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daneshmanesh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikaelsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiaii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Silencing of ROR1 and FMOD with siRNA results in apoptosis of CLL cells</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source> <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh2">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daneshmanesh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hojjat-Farsangi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeddi-Tehrani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akhondi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Monoclonal antibodies against ROR1 induce apoptosis of chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) cells</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1348</fpage>–<lpage>1355</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Pawelec1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pawelec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>ESTDAB: a collection of immunologically characterised melanoma cell lines and searchable databank</article-title>. <source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>627</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Cronwright1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cronwright</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Blanc</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gotherstrom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Darcy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehnman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cancer/testis antigen expression in human mesenchymal stem cells: down-regulation of SSX impairs cell migration and matrix metalloproteinase 2 expression</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>2207</fpage>–<lpage>2215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-HojjatFarsangi1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hojjat-Farsangi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeddi-Tehrani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifian</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mellstedt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Immunoglobulin heavy chain variable region gene usage and mutational status of the leukemic B cells in Iranian patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia</article-title>. <source>Cancer Sci</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>2346</fpage>–<lpage>2353</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-HojjatFarsangi2">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hojjat Farsangi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeddi-Tehrani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifian</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shamsian Khoramabadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Immunophenotypic characterization of the leukemic B-cells from Iranian patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia: association between CD38 expression and disease progression</article-title>. <source>Iran J Immunol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Roehm1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roehm</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasebrook</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>An improved colorimetric assay for cell proliferation and viability utilizing the tetrazolium salt XTT</article-title>. <source>J Immunol Methods</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Staff1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Staff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hojjat-Farsangi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mosolits</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liljefors</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Induction of IgM, IgA and IgE antibodies in colorectal cancer patients vaccinated with a recombinant CEA protein</article-title>. <source>J Clin Immunol</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>855</fpage>–<lpage>865</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Laidler1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laidler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Litynska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoja-Lukowicz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labedz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Przybylo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Characterization of glycosylation and adherent properties of melanoma cell lines</article-title>. <source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Mendez1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Del Campo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monge</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maleno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Characterization of HLA class I altered phenotypes in a panel of human melanoma cell lines</article-title>. <source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>729</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Mendez2">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aptsiauri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Del Campo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maleno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>HLA and melanoma: multiple alterations in HLA class I and II expression in human melanoma cell lines from ESTDAB cell bank</article-title>. <source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1507</fpage>–<lpage>1515</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Rabbani1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabbani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostadkarampour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danesh Manesh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeddi-Tehrani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Expression of ROR1 in patients with renal cancer–a potential diagnostic marker</article-title>. <source>Iran Biomed J</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Zhang2">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Onco-Embryonic Antigen ROR1 Is Expressed by a Variety of Human Cancers</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source> <volume>181</volume>: <fpage>1903</fpage>–<lpage>1910</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh3">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daneshmanesh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porwit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hojjat-Farsangi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeddi-Tehrani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamm</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Orphan receptor tyrosine kinases ROR1 and ROR2 in hematological malignancies</article-title>. <source>Leuk Lymphoma</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Kaucka1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaucka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krejci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plevova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prochazkova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Post-translational modifications regulate signalling by Ror1</article-title>. <source>Acta Physiol (Oxf)</source> <volume>203</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Marth1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mammalian glycosylation in immunity</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>874</fpage>–<lpage>887</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Ohtsubo1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohtsubo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Glycosylation in cellular mechanisms of health and disease</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>855</fpage>–<lpage>867</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Gottlinger1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottlinger</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Funke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gokel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riethmuller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>The epithelial cell surface antigen 17-1A, a target for antibody-mediated tumor therapy: its biochemical nature, tissue distribution and recognition by different monoclonal antibodies</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Hu1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shattock</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>High-mannose-specific deglycosylation of HIV-1 gp120 induced by resistance to cyanovirin-N and the impact on antibody neutralization</article-title>. <source>Virology</source> <volume>368</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Daneshmanesh4">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Daneshmanesh AH, Hojjat-Farsangi M, Sandin A, Khan AS, Moshfegh A, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2012) Monoclonal Antibody Against ROR1 In Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Cells Induced Apoptosis Via PI3-kinase/AKT/CREB pathway. 54th American Society of hematology (ASH), Atlanta, USA, 8–11 December.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Hoeflich1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeflich</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eby</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Oncogenic BRAF is required for tumor growth and maintenance in melanoma models</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1006</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Gullick1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gullick</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Love</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gusterson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>c-erbB-2 protein overexpression in breast cancer is a risk factor in patients with involved and uninvolved lymph nodes</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>438</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Bae1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schlessinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Asymmetric tyrosine kinase arrangements in activation or autophosphorylation of receptor tyrosine kinases</article-title>. <source>Mol Cells</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Huttlin1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huttlin</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jedrychowski</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A tissue-specific atlas of mouse protein phosphorylation and expression</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>1174</fpage>–<lpage>1189</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Slamon1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slamon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ullrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Human breast cancer: correlation of relapse and survival with amplification of the HER-2/neu oncogene</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>235</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Paterson1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danyluk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Correlation between c-erbB-2 amplification and risk of recurrent disease in node-negative breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Huttlin2">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huttlin</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jedrychowski</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A tissue-specific atlas of mouse protein phosphorylation and expression</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>1174</fpage>–<lpage>1189</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Bae2">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schlessinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Asymmetric tyrosine kinase arrangements in activation or autophosphorylation of receptor tyrosine kinases</article-title>. <source>Mol Cells</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Cole1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frame</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Further evidence that the tyrosine phosphorylation of glycogen synthase kinase-3 (GSK3) in mammalian cells is an autophosphorylation event</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>377</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Khoury1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dankort</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sadekova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naujokas</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Distinct tyrosine autophosphorylation sites mediate induction of epithelial mesenchymal like transition by an activated ErbB-2/Neu receptor</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>788</fpage>–<lpage>799</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Baltensperger1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baltensperger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woon</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vissavajjhala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Catalysis of serine and tyrosine autophosphorylation by the human insulin receptor</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>7885</fpage>–<lpage>7889</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Noble1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carragher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giblett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>CRAF autophosphorylation of serine 621 is required to prevent its proteasome-mediated degradation</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>862</fpage>–<lpage>872</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Bennasroune2">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennasroune</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aunis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cremel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Tyrosine kinase receptors as attractive targets of cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Butenas1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butenas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amblo-Krudysz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Posttranslational modifications of tissue factor</article-title>. <source>Front Biosci (Elite Ed)</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Singh1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Post-translational modifications of PTEN and their potential therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source>Curr Cancer Drug Targets</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>536</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Chakrabarti1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakrabarti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A review of the mammalian unfolded protein response</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>2777</fpage>–<lpage>2793</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0061167-Leeming1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leeming</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bay-Jensen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vassiliadis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Post-translational modifications of the extracellular matrix are key events in cancer progression: opportunities for biochemical marker development</article-title>. <source>Biomarkers</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>