<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-27931</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Long Noncoding RNA <italic>MEG3</italic> Contributes to Cisplatin Resistance of Human Lung Adenocarcinoma</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>MEG3</italic> in Cisplatin Resistance of Human Lung Adenocarcinoma</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Jing</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="econtrib001" ref-type="fn"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>Li</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="econtrib001" ref-type="fn"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Kaihua</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="econtrib001" ref-type="fn"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Ming</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>Xuan</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff004" ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Ping</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff005" ref-type="aff"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Binbin</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Guojian</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Zhaoxia</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Oncology, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, P.R. China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Department of Oncology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, P.R. China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, P.R. China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Department of Medical Oncology, Nanjing Medical University Affiliated Cancer Hospital of Jiangsu Province, Cancer Institution of Jiangsu Province, Nanjing,P.R. China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>Department of Pathology, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, P.R. China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>Jin Q.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>H.Lee Moffitt Cancer Center &amp; Research Institute, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JL ZXW. Performed the experiments: JL LW KHL. Analyzed the data: MS XP PZ BBL GJL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LW KHL. Wrote the paper: JL. Approved the final version: ZXW.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="econtrib001">
<p>‡ These authors are joint first authors on this work.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">zhaoxiawang88@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>20</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e0114586</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>30</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>11</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Liu et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<p>Long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) have been identified as oncogenes or tumor suppressors that are involved in tumorigenesis and chemotherapy drug resistance. Maternally expressed gene 3 (<italic>MEG3</italic>) is an imprinted gene located at 14q32 that encodes an lncRNA, and decreased <italic>MEG3</italic> expression plays an important role in multiple cancers. However, its biological role in the development of the chemoresistance phenotype of human lung adenocarcinoma (LAD) is unknown. This study aimed to observe the expression of <italic>MEG3</italic> in LAD and to evaluate its biological role and clinical significance in the resistance of LAD cells to cisplatin. <italic>MEG3</italic> expression was markedly decreased in cisplatin-resistant A549/DDP cells compared with parental A549 cells as shown by an lncRNA microarray. <italic>MEG3</italic> overexpression in A549/DDP cells increased their chemosensitivity to cisplatin both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> by inhibiting cell proliferation and inducing apoptosis. By contrast, <italic>MEG3</italic> knockdown in A549 cells decreased the chemosensitivity. Moreover, <italic>MEG3</italic> was decreased in cisplatin-insensitive LAD tissues while p53 protein levels were decreased and Bcl-xl protein levels increased. Furthermore, patients with lower levels of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression showed worse responses to cisplatin-based chemotherapy. These findings demonstrate that <italic>MEG3</italic> is significantly downregulated in LAD and partially regulates the cisplatin resistance of LAD cells through the control of p53 and Bcl-xl expression. Thus, <italic>MEG3</italic> may represent a new marker of poor response to cisplatin and could be a potential therapeutic target for LAD chemotherapy.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No.81272601,81372397,81472198), the Key Clinical Medicine Technology Foundation of Jiangsu Province (No.BL2014096), the Medical Key Talented Person Foundation of the Jiangsu Provincial Developing Health Project (No.RC2011080), Innovation Team Project of the Second Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, the Scientific Research Foundation of Jiangsu Province Health Department(No.H201310),“333 high class Talented Man Project” (No.2011-III-2630) and the School key Fund of Nanjing Medical University (2013NJMU054). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="8"/>
<table-count count="1"/>
<page-count count="16"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Lung cancer is one of the most prevalent neoplasms worldwide, ranking as the first and second leading causes of cancer-related deaths in males and females, respectively. Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) currently accounts for about 80% of all lung cancer cases [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114586.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], and more than 65% of NSCLC patients present with locally advanced or metastatic disease [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Lung adenocarcinoma (LAD) is the most common histological subtype of NSCLC [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], but affected patients have limited access to early detection and timely treatment. Platinum-containing drugs such as cisplatin and carboplatin are typically used in LAD chemotherapy [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], although cisplatin resistance is the greatest obstacle of clinical LAD treatment.</p>
<p>Recent improvements in high-throughput gene expression analysis have led to the discovery that transcription from &lt;2% of the human genome yields many short or long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) with limited or no protein-coding capacity because of a lack of open reading frames [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These show dysregulated expression in several human diseases but their exact biological functions are unclear. In our previous study, we reported that miR-224 could promote cisplatin resistance in A549/DDP cells via regulating G1/S transition and apoptosis by targeting p21<sup>WAF1/CIP1</sup> [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The dysregulation of lncRNAs has also been shown to participate in tumorigenesis through promoting cellular proliferation and inducing apoptosis in multiple tumors. For example, lncRNA uc002mbe.2 expression was significantly downregulated in hepatocellular cancer (HCC), and its overexpression contributed to the trichostatin-induced apoptosis of HCC cells [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Similarly, lncRNA AK126698 was thought to regulate the chemoresistance of NSCLC cells through the Wnt signaling pathway [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and our previous study found that lncRNA HOTAIR overexpression contributed to LAD cell cisplatin resistance via the regulation of p21 expression [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Moreover, in breast cancer patients with the single nucleotide polymorphism rs6983267 genotype, the novel lncRNA CCAT2 was demonstrated to reduce chemosensitivity to fluorouracil [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, although some studies have elucidated the lncRNA functions in tumor chemoresistance, the underlying mechanisms are less well documented. An understanding of these mechanisms would improve LAD treatment and enable new targets for tumor chemotherapy to be identified.</p>
<p>LncRNA <italic>MEG3</italic> is a maternally expressed imprinted gene that is part of the <italic>DLK1–MEG3</italic> locus located on human chromosome 14q32 [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It is expressed in normal human tissues, especially in brain and the pituitary, and is thought to be a tumor suppressor [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Recent studies showed that <italic>MEG3</italic> expression is disrupted in various human cancers, such as bladder cancer, glioma, and HCC [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Moreover, Zhang et al. demonstrated that <italic>MEG3</italic> expression was reduced in meningioma compared with normal controls, and that this loss was associated with tumor grade [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Conversely, increased <italic>MEG3</italic> expression was reported to regulate NSCLC cell proliferation and apoptosis through the activation of p53 [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. However, the functions and detailed mechanisms of <italic>MEG3</italic> in the cisplatin resistance of LAD remain elusive.</p>
<p>In this study, therefore, we investigated the role of <italic>MEG3</italic> in the chemosensitivity of LAD cells to cisplatin by analyzing its function both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. We demonstrated that <italic>MEG3</italic> expression was significantly decreased in cisplatin-resistant A549/DDP cells compared with that in parental cells, using lncRNA microarray and quantitative reverse transcriptase qRT-PCR. Ectopic expression of <italic>MEG3</italic> reduced A549/DDP cell cisplatin resistance, while <italic>MEG3</italic> knockdown increased this through regulation of cell proliferation and apoptosis. We further verified that overexpression of <italic>MEG3</italic> induced the mitochondrial apoptosis pathway via p53 and Bcl-xl activation. Our research confirms for the first time that, as a tumor suppressor, <italic>MEG3</italic> improves LAD chemosensitivity, and shows that it has potential to be used as a therapeutic target to reverse the cisplatin resistance of LAD patients.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Cell lines and culture</title>
<p>The human LAD cell line A549 was purchased from the Cancer Institute, Chinese Academy of Sciences. The cisplatin-resistant cell line A549/DDP was selected by continuous exposure to increasing concentrations of cisplatin followed by culturing in medium containing 1.0 μg/ml cisplatin to maintain the cisplatin resistance. All cell lines were cultured in RPMI 1640 medium (GIBCO-BRL, Grand Island, NY) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 100 U/ml penicillin, and 100 mg/ml streptomycin. They were grown under an atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> with humidity at 37°C. In all experiments, exponentially growing cells were used.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Patients and tissue samples</title>
<p>Forty-one tumor tissues were obtained from advanced LAD patients who underwent cisplatin-based chemotherapy at the First or Second Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University between April 2007 and November 2009. All patients were histopathologically diagnosed with LAD and accepted first-line chemotherapy with cisplatin in combination with gemcitabine or paclitaxel for a maximum of four cycles. Tissue samples were divided into “sensitive” (complete or partial response, CR+PR; n = 20) and “insensitive” (stable or progressive disease, SD+PD; n = 21) groups according to the patients’ responses, as assessed by medical image analysis and detection of serum tumor markers after four cycles of cisplatin-based chemotherapy. All tissues were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C until required for total RNA extraction. Tumor staging was determined according to the tumor–node–metastasis (TNM) classification of the International Union against Cancer. Written informed consent was provided by patients or their guardians. This study was approved by the Chinese Medical Association Society of Medicine’s Ethics Committee.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>RNA extraction and qRT-PCR</title>
<p>Total RNA was extracted from tissues or transfected cells using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). RT reactions were performed using <italic>MEG3</italic>-specific primers and a Takara Reverse Transcriptase kit (Takara, Dalian, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The <italic>MEG3</italic> expression level was quantified using SYBR Green-based PCR (Takara) using <italic>MEG3</italic>-specific primers: forward, 5′-CTGCCCATCTACACCTCACG-3′; and reverse, 5′-CTCTCCGCCGTCTGCGCTAGGGGCT-3′, and normalized to the expression of <italic>GAPDH</italic>, which was amplified using specific primers: forward, 5′-GTCAACGGATTTGGTCTGTATT-3′; and reverse, 5′-AGTCTTCTGGGTGGCAGTGAT-3′.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>LncRNA microarray</title>
<p>Total RNA was isolated from cisplatin-resistant A549/DDP cells and parental A549 cells as described above, and the quality and quantity of the RNA samples were assessed. LncRNA microarray V2.0 analysis supported by CapitalBio Corporation (Beijing, China) was performed to detect lncRNAs and protein-coding mRNAs in the genome. LncRNAs were purified from total RNA after repeat sequences and ncRNAs shorter than 200 bp were deleted. In total, information about 30,756 lncRNAs was obtained from authoritative data sources including UCSC, RefSeq, H-Invitational Database, and other related literature, and bioinformatic analysis of microarray data was performed by CapitalBio Corporation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Transfection of LAD cells</title>
<p><italic>MEG3</italic> was subcloned into the pCDNA 3.1 vector (Invitrogen, Shanghai, China), and this was purified using DNA Midiprep or Midiprep Kits (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany). Exponentially growing A549/DDP cells were seeded into 6-well plates and transfected with pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> vector or empty vector using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. <italic>MEG3</italic> overexpression was confirmed by qRT-PCR and western blot analyses 48 h after transfection.</p>
<p>Three small interfering (si)RNAs targeting <italic>MEG3</italic> (si-<italic>MEG3</italic> I, II, and III) were also transfected into A549 cells, and the most stable was chosen (si-<italic>MEG3</italic> II). A549 cells were then transfected with this si-<italic>MEG3</italic> or scrambled negative control siRNA (si-NC), and <italic>MEG3</italic> expression was detected by qRT-PCR 48 h after transfection.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Flow cytometric analysis of cell cycle or apoptosis</title>
<p>LAD cells for apoptotic analysis were double stained with Annexin V–FITC and propidium iodide 48 h after transfection and analyzed using a flow cytometer (FACScan; BD Biosciences, Shanghai, China) equipped with CellQuest software (BD Biosciences). Cells were classified as viable, dead, early apoptotic, or apoptotic. The percentage of early apoptotic cells was counted and compared between cells receiving different treatment. Cells for cell cycle analysis were stained with propidium iodide using the BD Cycletest Plus DNA Reagent Kit (BD Biosciences). The relative ratio of cells in G0/G1, S, or G2/M phase was counted and respectively compared with control groups. Each experiment was performed in triplicate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay and colon formation assay</title>
<p>The IC<sub>50</sub> was determined by an MTT assay. Transfected cells (3.5 × 10<sup>3</sup>/well) were seeded in 96-well plates and maintained in standard growth medium. Overnight, cells were exposed to different concentrations (0, 1, 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30, 35, and 40 ìg/ml) of cisplatin. After incubation for 48 h, 0.5 mg/ml MTT was added and incubated for another 4 h. The medium was then replaced with 150 μl dimethyl sulfoxide (Sigma–Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) and vortexed for 10 min. Absorbance at 490 nm was then surveyed by an automatic microplate reader. Cell viability was assessed at 0, 24, 48, 72, and 96 h with and without cisplatin treatment. For the colony formation assay, transfected cells (0.5 × 10<sup>3</sup>/well) were seeded in 6-well plates. After 14 d, cells were fixed with methanol and stained with 0.1% crystal violet (Sigma–Aldrich) and the number of colonies was counted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Hoechst staining assay</title>
<p>Cells were cultured in 6-well plates and Hoechst 33342 (Sigma–Aldrich) was added to the culture medium for 10 min. Cells were then washed with PBS, and changes in nuclear morphology were detected by fluorescence microscopy using a 365 nm filter for Hoechst 33342. The percentage of Hoechst-positive nuclei per optical field (at least 50 fields) was counted to quantify Hoechst 33342 staining.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Western blot assay</title>
<p>Cells were lysed using the mammalian protein extraction reagent RIPA (Beyotime, Shangahi, China), together with a protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche, Pleasanton, CA), and phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (Roche). Protein lysates were separated by 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis, transferred to 0.22 μm nitrocellulose membranes (Sigma–Aldrich), and incubated with specific antibodies against p53, mouse double minute 2 homolog (MDM2), Bcl-2, and Bcl-xl (Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA). An anti-GAPDH antibody was used as a control. Signals were visualized using the ECL chromogenic substrate and quantified by densitometry using Quantity One software (Bio-Rad, Berkeley, CA).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title><italic>In vivo</italic> chemosensitivity assay</title>
<p>Male athymic BALB/c nude mice aged 4 weeks were housed under specific pathogen-free conditions and manipulated according to protocols approved by the Shanghai Medical Experimental Animal Care Commission. Transfected A549/DDP cells (pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> and empty vector) were harvested and resuspended at a concentration of 2.0 × 10<sup>7</sup> cells/ml. Suspended cells (0.1 ml) were subcutaneously injected into a single side of the posterior flank of each mouse. Tumor growth was examined every 3 days, and tumor volume was calculated using the equation V = 0.5 × D × d<sup>2</sup> (V, volume; D, longitudinal diameter; d, latitudinal diameter). When the average tumor size reached approximately 50 mm<sup>3</sup>, cisplatin was administered by intraperitoneal injection at a dose of 3 mg/kg, once every other day, for a total of three doses. Four weeks after the injection, mice were killed and the subcutaneous growth of each tumor was examined. Primary tumors underwent hematoxylin and eosin staining and immunostaining analysis for proliferating cell nuclear antigen, p53, and Bcl-XL protein expression. All procedures were performed in accordance with the Nanjing University Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals formulated by the National Society for Medical Research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>All data are shown as means ± SE and were analyzed using Prism 5.0 software. Statistical analysis in the form of a Student’s <italic>t</italic>-test (two-tailed), one-way analysis of variance, and Mann–Whitney U test was performed using SPSS 16.0 software. <italic>P</italic> values less than 0.05 were considered significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Involvement of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression in cisplatin-resistant LAD cells (A549/DDP) and parental LAD cells (A549)</title>
<p>To identify the lncRNAs differentially expressed between cisplatin-resistant A549/DDP and parental A549 cells, we performed lncRNA microarray analysis. Of the 30,756 lncRNAs identified from databases, 664 showed differential expression between the cell types by more than 5-fold. Of these, 304 were downregulated and 360 were upregulated (<xref rid="pone.0114586.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), and <italic>MEG3</italic> showed the most downregulation in A549/DDP cells (by 61-fold). To validate the lncRNA microarray data, <italic>MEG3</italic> expression was determined in cisplatin-resistant A549/DDP and parental A549 cells by qRT-PCR and normalized to <italic>GAPDH</italic> levels. This found <italic>MEG3</italic> expression to be downregulated in A549/DDP cells by 4.5-fold compared with A549 cells (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0114586.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>The level of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression level in LAD cells.</title>
<p>(Fig 1A) qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression levels in A549 and A549/DDP cells. (Fig 1B) MTT assay of the IC<sub>50</sub> values of A549 and A549/DDP cells to cisplatin. (Fig 1C) qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression levels following the transfection of A549/DDP cells with empty vector or pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>. (Fig 1D) MTT assay of the IC<sub>50</sub> values of empty vector- and pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549/DDP cells to cisplatin. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pone.0114586.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Differentially expressed lncRNAs in A549/DDP cells compared with A549 cells as determined by microarray.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0114586.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lncRNAs</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lncRNAs</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIT000322758.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">914.2004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENST00000443252</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">192.118</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc002llc.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.9595</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MEG3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Down</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>61.61361</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc002bbp.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.9445</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BX537613</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.442579</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc003hsl.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">135.3685</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc001yia.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.626953</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIT000087455.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.1891</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14q(II-3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.406529</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASO1629</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.4334</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR_002766</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.985177</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASO3765</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.1581</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIT3318</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.487044</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NONE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.4499</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NONE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.117236</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc003wyd.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.9465</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR_033360</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.646661</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIT000326960.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.7971</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc010txc.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.913981</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc001luz.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.1428</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB074169</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9206</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc001uib.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.4206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14q(II-2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.540013</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc001lvd.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.9377</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc010txe.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.344072</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NONE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1377</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR_033358</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.038002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC032761</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0711</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NONE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.132646</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR_003503</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0497</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc002sag.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.316989</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc003kzj.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2284</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF070581</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.148076</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIT000076908.10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1488</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NONE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.847659</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENST00000410370</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0256</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NONE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.103947</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc002pec.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3612</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR_033359</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.112085</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc004edk.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.354</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc010txh.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.008096</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASO3473</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2485</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc010txd.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.722551</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR_036555</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1851</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14q(II-21)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.993253</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc001uie.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2843</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uc010txf.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.907636</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>We previously reported differences in morphological characteristics and biological functions of A549/DDP and parental A549 cells [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In the present study, the IC<sub>50</sub> of A549/DDP cells to cisplatin appeared to be higher than that of A549 cells (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>). We therefore explored the potential role of <italic>MEG3</italic> in the chemoresistance of LAD cells. <italic>MEG3</italic> was overexpressed in A549/DDP cells by transfecting them with pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> for 48 h. qRT-PCR analysis revealed that <italic>MEG3</italic> expression was significantly increased by 487-fold in pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549/DDP cells compared with A549/DDP cells transfected with empty vector (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref>). Furthermore, an MTT assay showed that the IC<sub>50</sub> of pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549/DDP cells to cisplatin was significantly decreased compared with respective control cells (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1D</xref>), indicating that the <italic>MEG3</italic> expression level of LAD cells affects their chemoresistance to cisplatin.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> overexpression inhibits A549/DDP cell apoptosis <italic>in vitro</italic></title>
<p>Because high <italic>MEG3</italic> expression appeared to increase the chemosensitivity of A549/DDP cells to cisplatin, we further investigated the biological role and mechanism of <italic>MEG3</italic> in LAD cell chemoresistance. We used Hoechst staining and flow cytometric analysis to determine whether apoptosis was a contributing factor in chemoresistance. A549/DDP cells transfected with pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> combined with cisplatin treatment showed a significantly increased rate of apoptosis with increasing doses of cisplatin (0.0, 1.0, and 2.0 ug/ml) compared with respective controls (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2A</xref>). Thus, <italic>MEG3</italic> appeared to significantly increase cisplatin-induced apoptosis in cisplatin-resistant LAD cells. Flow cytometric analysis was also consistent with these findings. When treated with increasing doses of cisplatin (0.0, 1.0, and 2.0 ug/ml), the apoptotic rate of A549/DDP cells transfected with pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> increased gradually compared with control cells transfected with empty vector (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2B</xref>). Thus, <italic>MEG3</italic> reversed the cisplatin resistance of A549/DDP cells through the enhancement of apoptosis.</p>
<fig id="pone.0114586.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> overexpression promotes A549/DDP cell apoptosis <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title>
<p>(Fig 2A) Hoechst staining assay for cell apoptosis; the percentage of Hoechst-positive nuclei per optical field (at least 50 fields) was counted. (Fig 2B) Flow cytometry analysis of apoptosis in transfected A549/DDP cells in combination with increasing concentrations of cisplatin (0.0, 1.0, and 2.0 μg/ml). *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> overexpression impairs A549/DDP cell proliferation <italic>in vitro</italic></title>
<p>We next performed MTT and colony formation analysis to examine whether <italic>MEG3</italic> could affect cell proliferation <italic>in vitro</italic>. The MTT assay revealed that cell proliferation was impaired in A549/DDP cells transfected with pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> combined with cisplatin treatment compared with control cells (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A</xref>). Similarly, colony formation analysis revealed that <italic>MEG3</italic> combined with increasing doses of cisplatin (0.0, 1.0, and 2.0 ug/ml) gradually decreased the number of colonies formed (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0114586.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> overexpression impairs A549/DDP cell proliferation <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title>
<p>(Fig 3A) MTT assay of A549/DDP cell proliferation with or without cisplatin. (Fig 3B) Colony formation analysis of cell proliferation in combination with increasing concentrations of cisplatin (0.0, 1.0, and 2.0 μg/ml). (Fig 3C) Flow cytometry analysis of cell cycle distribution in combination with increasing concentrations of cisplatin. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Flow cytometric analysis showed that the percentage of pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549/DDP cells in G1/G0 phase increased gradually and those in S phase decreased gradually with increasing doses of cisplatin compared with control cells (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3C</xref>). Thus, the overexpression of <italic>MEG3</italic> also seemed to reverse the cisplatin resistance of LAD cells through the inhibition of proliferation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> knockdown impairs A549 cell proliferation and apoptosis <italic>in vitro</italic></title>
<p>To further investigate the effect of <italic>MEG3</italic> on the cisplatin resistance of LAD cells, A549 cells were transfected with si-NC or siRNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> (si-<italic>MEG3</italic> I, si-<italic>MEG3</italic> II, and si-<italic>MEG3</italic> III). qRT-PCR showed that <italic>MEG3</italic> expression was significantly decreased in si-<italic>MEG3</italic> II-transfected cells compared with controls (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>). Moreover, <italic>MEG3</italic> knockdown significantly increased the IC<sub>50</sub> of A549 cells to cisplatin, as demonstrated by the MTT assay (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>). Flow cytometry revealed that <italic>MEG3</italic> knockdown by si-<italic>MEG3</italic> gradually decreased the cisplatin-induced apoptosis of A549 cells treated with increasing doses of cisplatin compared with respective controls (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0114586.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Knockdown of <italic>MEG3</italic> inhibits A549 cell apoptosis <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title>
<p>(Fig 4A) qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression levels following the transfection of A549 cells with si-NC and si-<italic>MEG3</italic>. (Fig 4B) IC<sub>50</sub> values of si-NC- and si-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549 cells to cisplatin. (Fig 4C) Flow cytometry analysis of apoptosis in si-NC- and si-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549 cells treated with increasing concentrations of cisplatin (0.0, 1.0, and 1.5 μg/ml). *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Cell proliferation was also found to be promoted in si-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549 cells with or without cisplatin treatment compared with si-NC-transfected controls (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>). Flow cytometric analysis revealed that the percentage of cells in G1/G0 phase decreased gradually and those in S phase increased in si-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549 cells with increasing doses of cisplatin (0.0, 1.0, and 1.5 ug/ml) (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>). These results therefore suggest that <italic>MEG3</italic> knockdown increases the cisplatin resistance of A549 cells through apoptosis inhibition and the promotion of cell proliferation.</p>
<fig id="pone.0114586.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Knockdown of <italic>MEG3</italic> promotes A549 cell proliferation <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title>
<p>(Fig 5A) MTT assay of the proliferation of si-NC- and si-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549 cells. (Fig 5B) Flow cytometry analysis of cell cycle distribution in combination with increasing concentrations of cisplatin (0.0, 1.0, and 1.5 μg/ml). *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> induces the activation of p53 and Bcl-xl in LAD cells</title>
<p>To highlight the impact of <italic>MEG3</italic> in reversing the cisplatin resistance of A549/DDP cells through the enhancement of apoptosis, we performed western blotting to detect apoptotic signals in the form of MDM2 and Bcl-XL proteins 48 h after <italic>MEG3</italic> transfection combined with cisplatin treatment. This was because <italic>MEG3</italic> is thought to function as a tumor suppressor by inducing the activation of p53, which can translocate to the mitochondria during apoptosis, and MDM2 is responsive to p53 activation [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0114586.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>, A549/DDP cells transfected with pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> showed increased p53 protein and decreased MDM2 protein expression compared with controls. We next determined whether <italic>MEG3</italic> could increase apoptosis by regulating the mitochondrial apoptosis pathway. When <italic>MEG3</italic> was overexpressed, western blotting revealed decreased Bcl-xl expression, but no significant difference in Bcl-2 expression. These data further suggested that <italic>MEG3</italic>-induced apoptosis in LAD cell cisplatin resistance is induced by the mitochondrial apoptosis pathway involving p53 and Bcl-xl.</p>
<fig id="pone.0114586.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> induces the activation of p53 and Bcl-xl proteins.</title>
<p>Western blot analysis of MDM2, p53, Bcl-xl, and Bcl-2 expression levels after pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> or empty vector transfection. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> improves the <italic>in vivo</italic> sensitivity of LAD cells to cisplatin</title>
<p>To further investigate the underlying roles of <italic>MEG3</italic> in enhancing the chemosensitivity of LAD cells to cisplatin, we used a nude mouse xenograft model. A549/DDP cells transfected with pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic> or empty vector were subcutaneously injected into mice, followed by treatment with cisplatin. Four weeks after the initial cisplatin administration, the volume and average weight of tumor xenografts was recorded (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7A and 7B</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="pone.0114586.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7C</xref>, the tumors formed from pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549/DDP cells grew significantly more slowly than those from controls following cisplatin treatment. It was also observed that the upregulation of <italic>MEG3</italic> led to the inhibition of tumor growth. qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression found it to be significantly higher in tumor tissues formed from pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549/DDP cells than those from controls (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7D</xref>). Additionally, immunostaining indicated that PCNA levels were lower in tumors formed from pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549/DDP cells compared with tumors from control cells, while p53 protein levels were increased and Bcl-xl protein decreased, respectively, in these tumor types (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7E</xref>). These results suggested that <italic>MEG3</italic> overexpression increased the <italic>in vivo</italic> chemosensitivity of LAD cells to cisplatin.</p>
<fig id="pone.0114586.g007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g007</object-id>
<label>Fig 7</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> improves the <italic>in vivo</italic> sensitivity of A549/DDP cells to cisplatin.</title>
<p>(Fig 7A, 7B) Four weeks after initial cisplatin administration, the tumor volume and average weight of mice receiving pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>- or empty vector-transfected A549/DDP cells were recorded. (Fig 7C) Tumor volume was calculated twice weekly after cisplatin treatment. (Fig 7D) qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression levels in tumor tissues formed from pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>- or empty vector-transfected A549/DDP cells. (Fig 7E) Tumors developed from pCDNA-<italic>MEG3</italic>-transfected A549/DDP cells showed lower PCNA protein levels, higher p53 protein expression, and lower Bcl-xl protein expression than those developed from control cells. Upper: H&amp;E staining; second, third row and lower: immunostaining. Original magnification, ×100 or ×200. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> correlates with the chemotherapy of LAD patients</title>
<p>We next used qRT-PCR to investigate the <italic>MEG3</italic> expression of tumor tissues from 41 patients with advanced LAD treated with cisplatin-based chemotherapy. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0114586.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8A</xref>, the average <italic>MEG3</italic> expression level of ‘‘insensitive” tissues was significantly lower than ‘‘sensitive” tissues. Thus, the level of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression was strongly positively correlated with the response of patients to cisplatin-based chemotherapy. However, correlation analysis of MEG3 expression level of two groups with their clinical pathological features revealed no significant association (<xref rid="pone.0114586.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). Kaplan–Meier survival analysis was performed to establish the association between <italic>MEG3</italic> expression and LAD patient progression-free survival (PFS). Those LAD patients with low <italic>MEG3</italic> levels (n = 17) had a shorter PFS than those with high <italic>MEG3</italic> levels (n = 24) (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8B</xref>). Finally, we observed that p53 protein expression was increased and Bcl-xl protein expression decreased in ‘‘sensitive” tissues compared with ‘‘insensitive” tissues (<xref rid="pone.0114586.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8C</xref>). Together, these data strongly indicated that <italic>MEG3</italic> expression in advanced LAD patients is correlated with the response of patients to cisplatin-based chemotherapy.</p>
<fig id="pone.0114586.g008" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g008</object-id>
<label>Fig 8</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>MEG3</italic> expression levels are positively correlated with the responses of patients to cisplatin-based chemotherapy.</title>
<p>(Fig 8A) qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>MEG3</italic> expression levels in cisplatin-sensitive (n = 20) and cisplatin-insensitive (n = 21) LAD tissues. (Fig 8B) Kaplan–Meier survival analysis of the association between PFS of LAD patients and <italic>MEG3</italic> expression (log rank <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). (Fig 8C) Cisplatin-sensitive tissues exhibited higher p53 and lower Bcl-xl protein expression than cisplatin-insensitive tissues. Original magnification, ×200 or ×400. ** <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec022" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>As the most common subtype of NSCLC, LAD is attracting considerable attention particularly because its acquired resistance to drugs makes treatment difficult. Although the dysregulation of some lncRNAs is thought to affect LAD chemoresistance, the underlying molecular mechanisms of this have not been fully elucidated. Cisplatin is a commonly used chemotherapy drug and is the first chemotherapeutic choice for NSCLC. However, acquired drug resistance is a major obstacle to clinical chemotherapy.</p>
<p>Some mechanisms of cisplatin resistance have been reported, for instance, the Nrf2/ARE pathway in NSCLC and the calcium signaling pathway in ovarian cancer [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114586.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Studies across a variety of cancer types demonstrate that misregulation of lncRNAs contributes to human disease or tumorigenesis, such as pituitary adenomas and gastric cancer [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Moreover, lncRNAs have been found to regulate a series of biological functions including genomic imprinting and transcriptional regulation. In this study, we found that the <italic>MEG3</italic> expression level was significantly decreased in cisplatin-resistant A549/DDP cells compared with parental A549 cells. This increased <italic>MEG3</italic> expression appeared to reverse the chemoresistance of A549/DDP cells to cisplatin. We found that lncRNA <italic>MEG3</italic> appeared to function as a tumor suppressor by regulating the p53 and Bcl-xl-induced mitochondrial apoptosis pathway, and showed that its increased expression was positively correlated with the sensitivity of LAD patients to cisplatin treatment.</p>
<p>Cell apoptosis is involved in the response of cancers to chemotherapy, radiation, or targeted therapy, and its induction may offer potential benefits to cancer therapeutics [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. However, apoptosis is just one of the responses to cisplatin treatment. Wang et al. demonstrated that cisplatin exerted its cytotoxic effect partially through regulation of the p53 signaling pathway [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. p53 is a DNA-binding tumor suppressor that plays a key role in many physiological processes, including DNA repair and apoptosis [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Furthermore, it can be induced by cisplatin to regulate cell cycle arrest [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. MDM2 may inhibit the p53 transactivation function by engaging its amino-terminal transactivation domain [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], while the reactivation of p53 is a viable strategy for cancer treatment [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. p53 is thought to act at multiple levels to induce mitochondrially-directed apoptosis [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], and triptolide was shown to be a potential chemotherapeutic agent for endometrial cancer via its actions on the p53-independent mitochondrial pathway [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</p>
<p>Bcl-xl is a member of the Bcl-2 family of proteins that suppresses tumor apoptosis. This family is also reported to play an important role in mitochondrial permeabilization-induced apoptosis particularly through the p53–Bcl-xl interaction [<xref rid="pone.0114586.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114586.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In the present study, we showed that p53 expression was increased and that of Bcl-xl was decreased in <italic>MEG3</italic>-overexpressing LAD cells, while apoptosis was increased and the chemoresistance was partially reversed. We speculate that these observations reflect changes to the mitochondrial apoptosis pathway via p53 and Bcl-xl, but further work is needed to confirm this.</p>
<p>Taken together, our data demonstrated that the dysregulation of lncRNA <italic>MEG3</italic> underlies the cisplatin resistance of LAD, indicating that its overexpression may contribute to increased cisplatin chemosensitivity via the p53 and Bcl-xl induced mitochondria apoptosis pathway. This study enables us to better understand the functions of <italic>MEG3</italic> in LAD chemotherapy and suggest that <italic>MEG3</italic> could be used as a novel marker of poor response to cisplatin and a potential therapeutic target for LAD chemotherapy. Future study should investigate the molecular mechanisms underlying the functions of <italic>MEG3</italic> in the chemoresistance of LAD.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec023">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0114586.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0114586.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Association between MEG3 level and clinicopathological features of LAD patients (sensitive e group and insensitive group).</title>
<p>There was no significant association between pathological features and MEG3 expression level of LAD patient tissues.</p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Center</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Global cancer statistics</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3322/caac.20107" xlink:type="simple">10.3322/caac.20107</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21296855</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devesa</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vizcaino</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parkin</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>International lung cancer trends by histologic type: male:female differences diminishing and adenocarcinoma rates rising</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15900604</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sculier</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Nonsmall cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir Rev</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1183/09059180.00007012" xlink:type="simple">10.1183/09059180.00007012</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23457162</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgensztern</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Govindan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Trends in stage distribution for patients with non-small cell lung cancer: a National Cancer Database survey</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/JTO.0b013e3181c5920c" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/JTO.0b013e3181c5920c</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19952801</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boni</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tiseo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boni</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baldini</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Recchia</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Triplets versus doublets, with or without cisplatin, in the first-line treatment of stage IIIB-IV non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients: a multicenter randomised factorial trial (FAST)</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>658</fpage>–<lpage>665</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/bjc.2011.606" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/bjc.2011.606</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22240782</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibb</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The functional role of long non-coding RNA in human carcinomas</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>38</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1476-4598-10-38" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1476-4598-10-38</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21489289</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapranov</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willingham</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gingeras</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide transcription and the implications for genomic organization</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17486121</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattick</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Makunin</surname> <given-names>IV</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Non-coding RNA</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>15</volume> Spec No 1: <fpage>R17</fpage>–<lpage>R29</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16651366</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brosnan</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voinnet</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The long and the short of noncoding RNAs</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ceb.2009.04.001" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ceb.2009.04.001</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19447594</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>ZX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>MiR- 224 promotes the chemoresistance of human lung adenocarcinoma cells to cisplatin via regulating G1/S transition and apoptosis by targeting p21(WAF1/CIP1)</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>111</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/bjc.2014.157" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/bjc.2014.157</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24921914</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Induction of the liver cancer-down-regulated long noncoding RNA uc002mbe.2 mediates trichostatin-induced apoptosis of liver cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1761</fpage>–<lpage>1769</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bcp.2013.04.020" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.bcp.2013.04.020</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23643933</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The noncoding RNA expression profile and the effect of lncRNA AK126698 on cisplatin resistance in non-small-cell lung cancer cell</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e65309</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0065309" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0065309</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23741487</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The long noncoding RNA HOTAIR contributes to cisplatin resistance of human lung adenocarcinoma cells via downregualtion of p21(WAF1/CIP1) expression</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e77293</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0077293" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0077293</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24155936</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Redis</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sieuwerts</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Look</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tudoran</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ivan</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>CCAT2, a novel long non-coding RNA in breast cancer: expression study and clinical correlations</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1748</fpage>–<lpage>1762</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24077681</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyoshi</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagatsuma</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wakana</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shiroishi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Identification of an imprinted gene, Meg3/Gtl2 and its human homologue MEG3, first mapped on mouse distal chromosome 12 and human chromosome 14q</article-title>. <source>Genes Cells</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10759892</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danila</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scolavino</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A pituitary-derived MEG3 isoform functions as a growth suppressor in tumor cells</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>5119</fpage>–<lpage>5126</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14602737</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Downregulated MEG3 activates autophagy and increases cell proliferation in bladder cancer</article-title>. <source>Mol Biosyst</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/c2mb25386k" xlink:type="simple">10.1039/c2mb25386k</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23295831</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of the long non-coding RNA MEG3 impairs in vitro glioma cell proliferation</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biochem</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>1868</fpage>–<lpage>1874</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jcb.24055" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/jcb.24055</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22234798</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anwar</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krech</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasemeier</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schipper</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schweitzer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Loss of imprinting and allelic switching at the DLK1-MEG3 locus in human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e49462</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0049462" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0049462</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23145177</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gejman</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahta</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Maternally expressed gene 3, an imprinted noncoding RNA gene, is associated with meningioma pathogenesis and progression</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>2350</fpage>–<lpage>2358</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-3885" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-3885</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20179190</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>XH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Long non-coding RNA MEG3 inhibits NSCLC cells proliferation and induces apoptosis by affecting p53 expression</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2407-13-461" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2407-13-461</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24098911</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Regulation of p53: a collaboration between Mdm2 and Mdmx</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22410433</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Batista</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Activation of p53 by MEG3 non-coding RNA</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>282</volume>: <fpage>24731</fpage>–<lpage>24742</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17569660</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname> <given-names>BY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>4-methoxychalcone enhances cisplatin-induced oxidative stress and cytotoxicity by inhibiting the Nrf2/ARE-mediated defense mechanism in A549 lung cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Cells</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10059-013-0123-9" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10059-013-0123-9</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24046186</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Bahlani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>AY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sayan</surname> <given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergeron</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>P73 regulates cisplatin-induced apoptosis in ovarian cancer cells via a calcium/calpain-dependent mechanism</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>4219</fpage>–<lpage>4230</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/onc.2011.134" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/onc.2011.134</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21516125</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huarte</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rinn</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Large non-coding RNAs: missing links in cancer?</article-title> <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gejman</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Batista</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Selective loss of MEG3 expression and intergenic differentially methylated region hypermethylation in the MEG3/DLK1 locus in human clinically nonfunctioning pituitary adenomas</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism</source>: <fpage>934119</fpage>–<lpage>934125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Downregulated long noncoding RNA MEG3 is associated with poor prognosis and promotes cell proliferation in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Tumour Biol</source> <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1065</fpage>–<lpage>1073</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s13277-013-1142-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s13277-013-1142-z</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24006224</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotter</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Apoptosis and cancer: the genesis of a research field</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrc2663" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrc2663</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19550425</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narsinh</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Molecular imaging of p53 signal pathway in lung cancer cell cycle arrest induced by cisplatin</article-title>. <source>Mol Carcinog</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>900</fpage>–<lpage>907</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/mc.21930" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/mc.21930</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22674879</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sontag</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional control of human p53-regulated genes</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrm2395" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrm2395</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18431400</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mdm2 and MdmX partner to regulate p53</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>586</volume>: <fpage>1390</fpage>–<lpage>1396</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.febslet.2012.02.049" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.febslet.2012.02.049</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22673503</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wade</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MDM2, MDMX and p53 in oncogenesis and cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrc3430" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrc3430</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23303139</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walia</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kakar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elble</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Micromanagement of the mitochondrial apoptotic pathway by p53</article-title>. <source>Front Biosci (Landmark Ed)</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>749</fpage>–<lpage>758</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21196200</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>XF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>YB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>ZH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Triptolide induces apoptosis in endometrial cancer via a p53independent mitochondrial pathway</article-title>. <source>Mol Med Rep</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3892/mmr.2013.1783" xlink:type="simple">10.3892/mmr.2013.1783</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24213358</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomita</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchenko</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erster</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nemajerova</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dehner</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>WT p53, but not tumor-derived mutants, bind to Bcl2 via the DNA binding domain and induce mitochondrial permeabilization</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>8600</fpage>–<lpage>8606</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16443602</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0114586.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orrenius</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial regulation of apoptotic cell death</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Lett</source> <volume>149</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15093244</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>