<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-03636</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018077</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Nucleic acids</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>DNA</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>DNA recombination</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Proteins</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>DNA-binding proteins</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genomics</subject>
              <subject>Sequence analysis</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genomics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genomic medicine</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Gene therapy</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Molecular cell biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Nucleic acids</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>DNA</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>DNA recombination</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Molecular Biology</subject>
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
          <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Genome-Wide Analysis of <italic>FRT</italic>-Like Sequences in the
                    Human Genome</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>FRT</italic>-Like Sequences in the
                    Human Genome</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Shultz</surname>
            <given-names>Jeffry L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Voziyanova</surname>
            <given-names>Eugenia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Konieczka</surname>
            <given-names>Jay H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Voziyanov</surname>
            <given-names>Yuri</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>School of Biological Sciences, Louisiana Tech
                    University, Ruston, Louisiana, United States of America</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Harvard University/Broad Institute, Cambridge,
                    Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Oshima</surname>
            <given-names>Robert</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Sanford-Burnham Medical Research Institute, United States of
                America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">voziyan@latech.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YV JLS. Performed the experiments:
                        JLS EV YV JHK. Analyzed the data: JLS YV. Wrote the paper: JLS YV. Designed
                        the software used in analysis: JLS JHK.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e18077</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Shultz, et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
                terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
                distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>Efficient and precise genome manipulations can be achieved by the
                        Flp/<italic>FRT</italic> system of site-specific DNA recombination.
                    Applications of this system are limited, however, to cases when target sites for
                    Flp recombinase, <italic>FRT</italic> sites, are pre-introduced into a genome
                    locale of interest. To expand use of the Flp/<italic>FRT</italic> system in
                    genome engineering, variants of Flp recombinase can be evolved to recognize
                    pre-existing genomic sequences that resemble <italic>FRT</italic> and thus can
                    serve as recombination sites. To understand the distribution and sequence
                    properties of genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like sites, we performed a
                    genome-wide analysis of <italic>FRT</italic>-like sites in the human genome
                    using the experimentally-derived parameters. Out of 642,151 identified
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences, 581,157 sequences were unique and
                    12,452 sequences had at least one exact duplicate. Duplicated
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences are located mostly within LINE1, but
                    also within LTRs of endogenous retroviruses, Alu repeats and other repetitive
                    DNA sequences. The unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences were classified
                    based on the number of matches to <italic>FRT</italic> within the first four
                    proximal bases pairs of the Flp binding elements of <italic>FRT</italic> and the
                    nature of mismatched base pairs in the same region. The data obtained will be
                    useful for the emerging field of genome engineering.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from NIH (NIGMS R01GM085848) to YV. The funders
                    had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish,
                    or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Site-specific tyrosine recombination systems, such as Flp/<italic>FRT</italic>,
                Cre/loxP and related systems catalyze conservative DNA rearrangements between their
                cognate recombination target sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Kilby1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Mills1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Wirth1">[3]</xref>. By manipulating the relative location and orientation of
                the recombination target sites, genome rearrangements catalyzed by recombinases can
                include integration, excision, inversion or recombinase-mediated cassette exchange
                (RMCE). As these recombination systems are active in all cell types tested, they
                became popular molecular tools for directed genome rearrangements, including
                specific DNA insertions or targeted DNA deletions in chromosomes, DNA translocation,
                gene replacement as well as expression of proteins from selected chromosomal
                locales, excision of large chromosomal DNA segments for sequencing, rescue of
                pathogenic islands and production of biofactories <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Kilby1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Mills1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Rodriguez1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Glaser1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Qiao1">[6]</xref>.</p>
      <p>For a directed recombination event to occur using current technology, native
                recombination target sites must be pre-introduced into a genome locale of interest
                by homologous, random or vector-mediated recombination. This requirement limits
                application of the site-specific tyrosine recombination systems in genome
                engineering mainly to modeling experiments. To expand the use of tyrosine
                recombination systems, variants of the recombinases have to be evolved to recognize
                pre-existing genomic sequences that resemble the respective native target sites.
                These pre-existing genomic sequences paired with the evolved recombinase variants
                can be then used in genome engineering experiments. Advances in changing target DNA
                specificity of Cre recombinase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Buchholz1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Santoro1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Rufer1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Sarkar1">[10]</xref>, Flp recombinases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Voziyanov1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Voziyanov2">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Konieczka1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref> and recently λ Int <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Tay1">[15]</xref> create an
                opportunity to develop genome engineering tools based on tailor-made variants of
                tyrosine recombinases.</p>
      <p>For genome engineering experiments to be successful, one needs data on sequence
                properties and distribution of target-like sites within the genome of interest. A
                pilot analysis of <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in selected contigs of the
                human genome and some bacterial and viral genomes using the TargetFinder program
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref>
                indicated that the frequency of <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in a genome
                depends on the genome's G/C content and can range from 1
                <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence per ∼1 Mb in a genome of thermophilic
                bacteria to 1–2 <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences per 10 Kb in mammalian
                genomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref> and Y.V., unpublished]. The parameters for
                identifying <italic>FRT</italic>-like sites incorporated into TargetFinder were
                based mainly on the results of exhaustive mutational analysis of each position of
                Flp binding elements of <italic>FRT</italic> and its spacer region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Senecoff1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Umlauf1">[17]</xref> and the results
                of our target-linked Flp evolution experiments (Y.V., unpublished). As shown in the
                present work, the search parameters incorporated into TargetFinder were not always
                able to correctly identify functional <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences –
                the ones that can serve as recombination targets for the evolved Flp variants. In
                addition, we noticed that TargetFinder worked efficiently only if the genomic DNA
                string analyzed was about couple of million base pairs long, making the program
                difficult to use for analyzing long genomic contigs. In fact, TargetFinder required
                about one month of machine time to scan the entire human genome for
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences. Therefore, we fine-tuned the parameters for
                identifying <italic>FRT</italic>-like sites based on the evolvability of Flp
                variants specific for genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like sites, incorporated these
                parameters into the search engine of a newly developed bioinformatics package
                TargetSiteAnalyzer and performed genome-wide analysis of <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                sites in the human genome (NCBI build 36.3). Like TargetFinder, TargetSiteAnalyzer
                is written in Java. TargetSiteAnalyzer is composed of three programs that
                sequentially scan all genomic contigs and sort the identified
                <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences into groups and subgroups. TargetSiteAnalyzer
                needs only several hours to perform the analysis of the human genome.</p>
      <p>We found that functional <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences can be found in the
                human genome roughly every 5 kb, although we identified genomic regions with a
                significantly lower density of <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences. The identified
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences were grouped into a limited number of unique
                classes and subclasses that have common sequence patterns. TargetSiteAnalyzer can be
                modified to search for target-like sequences for other site-specific recombinases.
                Our work will be useful for the emerging field of genome engineering.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Sequence features of functional genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sites</title>
        <p>Using the search program TargetFinder <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref>, we identified 18 model
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences: in the human interleukin-10 gene, the
                    human beta globin gene, the human and mouse ROSA26 regions and in the mouse
                    tyrosinase gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure 1</xref>).
                    According to TargetFinder, the identified <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    had high scores and were expected to be functional. To evolve variants of Flp
                    recombinase specific for the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure 1B</xref>, we used a one-step
                    recombinase evolution approach, which includes one round of DNA shuffling
                    between a library of Flp genes mutated at position 59 (S59G) and randomized at
                    positions 55 and 58, and the FV7 gene, which served as a source of core
                    mutations seen in Flp variants with evolved target specificity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref>. The DNA
                    shuffling was followed by selection for Flp variants with desired target
                    specificity using our standard deletion reporters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Voziyanov1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref>. The choice of amino
                    acids in Flp to be mutated (55, 58 and 59) was based on the
                        Flp/<italic>FRT</italic> co-crystal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Chen1">[18]</xref> and on our observations that
                    the first four base pairs of Flp binding elements of <italic>FRT</italic>
                    (positions −1 to −4 and 1 to 4, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure 1A</xref>), which interact with amino acids
                    at positions 55, 58 and 59, are the most critical in Flp/<italic>FRT</italic>
                    recognition (E.V. and Y.V., unpublished).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0018077-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>FRT</italic> (A), successful <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                            sequences (B) and unsuccessful <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                            (C).</title>
            <p><italic>FRT</italic>-wt  =  wild-type
                                <italic>FRT</italic>; <italic>FRT</italic>-cons
                             =  consensus <italic>FRT</italic> sequence that
                            reflects nucleotide changes known to be tolerated by Flp variants.
                                <italic>FRT</italic>-cons served as a query to scan the human
                            genomic sequences to identify <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences.
                                <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences <italic>FL-IL10A,
                                FL-2798</italic> and <italic>FL-IL871</italic> are from the human
                            interleukin-10 gene; <italic>FL-RS261</italic> and
                                <italic>FL-RS262</italic> are from human ROSA26 locus;
                                <italic>FL-61204</italic>, <italic>FL-63904</italic>,
                                <italic>FL-71362</italic>, <italic>FL-71818</italic>,
                                <italic>FL-73036</italic>, <italic>FL-74849</italic>,
                                <italic>FL-75708</italic>, <italic>FL-76938</italic> and
                                <italic>FL-78189</italic> are from the human beta-globin gene;
                                <italic>FL-98403</italic> and <italic>FL-99998</italic> are from
                            mouse Rosa26 locus; <italic>FL-10474</italic> is from the mouse
                            tyrosinase gene. Numbers in brackets indicate the scores the
                                <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences have according to the program
                            TargetFinder <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref>. Flp variants able to recombine the
                            respective <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with at least 10%
                            efficiency are shown next to the successful <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                            sequences. Flp variant FV7 able to recombine <italic>FL-IL10A</italic>
                            was reported earlier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Despite extensive experimenting, we were only able to evolve Flp variants for a
                    half of the selected <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences (marked
                    ‘+’ in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure
                        1B</xref>), which we consider true functional genomic
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences. Flp variants evolved to recombine these
                    genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences were tested in <italic>E.
                        coli</italic> and showed at least 10% efficiency in a standard
                    deletion assay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Voziyanov1">[11]</xref>. To demonstrate that true functional genomic
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences can also serve as substrates for the
                    respective Flp variants in mammalian cells, we tested Flp variants that can
                    recombine <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences located in the human b-globin
                    locus (<italic>FL-61204</italic>, <italic>FL-63904</italic>, and
                        <italic>FL-71362</italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure 1B</xref>) in CHO cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g002">Figure 2</xref>). For this, we used an episomal
                    reporter pEGFP-del, which bears the EGFP expressing cassette followed by a
                    promoterless DsRed gene. The EGFP gene was flanked by two recombination sites:
                    either <italic>FL-61204</italic> or <italic>FL-63904</italic> or
                        <italic>FL-71362</italic> and modified <italic>FRT</italic>, in which its
                    native spacer was substituted with the spacer from the respective
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence to allow recombination between the two
                    sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g002">Figure 2A</xref>).
                    Successful recombination between the recombination sites that flank the EGFP
                    gene leads to the activation of expression of the DsRed gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). As the results
                    show, all three Flp variants tested are active on their respective genomic
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in mammalian cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g002">Figure 2B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0018077-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Evolved variants of Flp recombinase are active in mammalian
                            cells.</title>
            <p><bold>(A)</bold> Schematics of the deletion assay used to test Flp
                            variants in CHO cells. An episomal reporter pEGFP-del bears the EGFP
                            expressing cassette followed by a promoterless DsRed gene. The EGFP gene
                            is flanked by two recombination sites: genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                            sequence (either <italic>FL-61204</italic>, <italic>FL-63904</italic>,
                            or <italic>FL-71362</italic>; these sites are shown as
                                ‘<italic>FL</italic>’) and modified <italic>FRT</italic>
                            (shown as <italic>FRT</italic>*), in which its native spacer was
                            substituted with the spacer from the respective
                            <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence. The choice of genomic
                                <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences and modified
                                <italic>FRT</italic> as recombination partners for the evolved Flp
                            variants was suggested by the results of our earlier experiments with
                            Flp variant FV7 which showed that this combination of recombination
                            sites works the best in the excision assay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref>. (<bold>B)</bold>
                            Evolved Flp variants efficiently recombine their respective
                                <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in CHO cells.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The comparative analysis of sequence features of functional genomic
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure 1B</xref>) vs. non-functional ones (marked
                    ‘–’ in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure
                        1C</xref>) suggested a set of rules that can distinguish between the two
                    groups. The three most important rules that describe functional genomic
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences are the following: (1) within the
                    proximal 4-bp DNA segments of both binding elements of an
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence (‘proximal–8 region’;
                    positions −4 through −1 and 1 through 4, which make eight base pairs
                    in total, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure 1A</xref>), there
                    should be at least five matches with the corresponding base pairs of
                        <italic>FRT</italic>; (2) there should not be consecutive mismatches within
                    the same 4-bp DNA segments; (3) at least one binding element should have a match
                    at position 7. In addition, we do not consider genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences as functional ones if they have mismatches at positions −1 and 1
                    simultaneously or a ‘G’ at position −1 or a ‘C’ at
                    position 1. We also noted that a functional genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequence should have at least 5 matches in one of its binding elements and at
                    least 6 consecutive matches within both of its binding elements. The above rules
                    along with a scoring system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g003">Figure
                        3</xref>) were integrated into the search engine of a newly developed
                    bioinformatics package named ‘TargetSiteAnalyzer’.
                    TargetSiteAnalyzer was used to screen the entire human genome for functional
                    genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0018077-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence identification
                            requirements.</title>
            <p>See text for details.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>TargetSiteAnalyzer</title>
        <p>TargetSiteAnalyzer is composed of three JAVA programs that are sequentially run:
                        <italic>GenomeScanner</italic>, <italic>TargetSorter</italic> and
                        <italic>SpacerSorter</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s003">Text S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s004">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s005">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s006">S4</xref>).
                    Together, these programs perform the task of identifying and then sorting
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences within a genome of interest. An overview
                    of these programs and the processing steps is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g004">Figure 4</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0018077-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Overview of TargetSiteAnalyzer bioinformatics package used to find
                                <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences within 2.8 Gbp of human genomic
                            DNA (NCBI build 36.3).</title>
            <p>Heavy-bordered boxes indicate the creation of a file. File format boxes
                            may have spaces added for readability in this figure.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p><italic>GenomeScanner</italic> sequentially screens each DNA contig file within a
                    genome build for <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences using the rules that
                    describe sites that can serve as functional recombination targets. A contig file
                    is successively read as overlapping 34-nucleotide segments in 1-nucleotide
                    increments. Each 34-nucleotide sequence is separated into three regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g003">Figure 3</xref>): two potential
                    inverted recombinase-binding elements (positions −13 through −1 and
                    positions 1 through 13) and a spacer (positions s1 through s8). As does
                    TargetFinder <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref>, <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> first checks if a
                    putative spacer has a ‘T’ at position s1 and an ‘A’ at
                    position s8 and whether GC content of the spacer equals or is below 50%.
                    These criteria for a functional spacer are based on the observations that
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with such spacers support efficient
                    recombination <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Umlauf1">[17]</xref>. If criteria for a functional spacer are met,
                        <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> tests positions −4 to −1 and 1 to
                    4 and also −7 and 7 of the putative binding elements of an
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence for the number of matches and mismatches
                    to the corresponding positions of <italic>FRT</italic>. In addition, the entire
                    34-nucleotide sequence of an <italic>FRT</italic>-like site is tested for any
                    single nucleotide repeat longer than four nucleotides. The putative binding
                    elements of an <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence are also checked for the
                    number of consecutive matches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Each position in the binding elements of an
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence (positions −13 to −1 and 1 to
                    13) that is matched to the corresponding position in <italic>FRT</italic>, is
                    given a weighted value and a total score for an <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequence is generated that includes the number of matches within the
                    ‘proximal-8’ sequence and the weighted value.</p>
        <p>During program execution, <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> writes each match to a
                    linear-order text file and to an internal array. After the last sequence file is
                    processed, <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> uses the array to determine which
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences are unique, then generates two
                    additional output files: one containing only unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences and a second containing <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with at
                    least one exact duplicate. <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> reports the position
                    of each identified <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence both within the sequence
                    contig files and within a chromosomal fragment map based on linear order of
                    files for each chromosome and the cumulative base pairs for each chromosome
                        (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s001">Figure
                        S1</xref>).</p>
        <p><italic>TargetSorter</italic> works with the <italic>GenomeScanner</italic>
                    generated files that contain both the unique and duplicated
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences. The program groups the records based on the
                    sequence of the most functionally important region of the <italic>FRT</italic>
                    putative recombinase binding elements (−4 to −1 and 1 to 4). In this
                    region, both complimentary strands are assigned a numeric value. The lowest
                    value is used to assign the record to a file.</p>
        <p>The <italic>SpacerSorter</italic> program sorts <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences within each output file generated by <italic>TargetSorter</italic>
                    based on spacer sequence. In similar fashion to the
                        <italic>TargetSorter</italic> program, both directions of the spacer
                    sequences are used to determine if a match exists. This final sorting step is
                    important since it allows identification of those <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences that can, in principle, recombine with each other by a single Flp
                    variant specific for a particular sequence pattern in the
                    ‘proximal-8’ region.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Unique and repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in human
                    genome</title>
        <p><italic>GenomeScanner</italic> identified 642,151 potentially functional
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in the human genome (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s007">Text S5</xref>).
                    Out of those, 581,157 <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences are unique and 60,994
                    have at least one exact duplicate. In the majority of human chromosomes, unique
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences can be found, on average, every 4 to 5
                    kb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Notable
                    exceptions are chromosomes 19 and 22, which average <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences every 9 to 10 kb and 8 kb, respectively. This average distribution of
                    the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences correlates very well with GC content in
                    human chromosomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Sellis1">[19]</xref>, where chromosomes 4 and 13 have the lowest GC
                    content (∼38%) and chromosomes 19 and 22 – the highest
                    (∼48%). Since overall GC content of <italic>FRT</italic> is about
                    33% and GC content of a functional spacer in an <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequence should be equal or below 50%, the dependence of average
                    distribution of <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences on GC content in a genome of
                    interest can be satisfactorily explained. Of note, thermophilic bacteria, with
                    their high GC content, usually have only about one <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequence per 1 Mb of their genomes (Y.V., unpublished).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0018077-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Average distance between <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in human
                            chromosomes.</title>
            <p>The highest density of <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences is in
                            chromosome 4; the lowest density is in chromosome is 19. The ratio of
                            unique to duplicated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences is indicated by
                            the relative size of the bars.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We did not investigate if there is a preference for <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences to be in exons or introns in a gene per arbitrary unit of DNA length.
                    We noted, however, an obvious preference for <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    to be in introns (most likely because they are, on average, significantly longer
                    than exons). It is possible, however, that there is a preference for
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences for introns in general since, on
                    average, GC content of introns is lower than that of exons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Kalari1">[20]</xref>. Also, for the same reason
                    of lower GC content, there might be a preference for <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences to be in longer, rather than shorter introns, and in terminal and
                    intermediate exons than in initial exons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Kalari1">[20]</xref>.</p>
        <p>12,452 of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences identified in the human genome
                    have at least one exact duplicate. The copy number of duplicated sequences
                    ranged from 2 to 6,387, bringing the total number of duplicated
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences to 60,994. On average, about 10%
                    of all <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in human chromosomes are duplicated,
                    however, as can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g005">Figure
                        5</xref>, chromosome Y is exceptional. About 50% of
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in this chromosome are duplicated. This
                    correlates well with the unusually high frequency (∼50%) of repeated
                    DNA elements, particularly LINE1, in chromosome Y <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Skaletsky1">[21]</xref>.</p>
        <p>In the vast majority of cases, duplicated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences are
                    part of repeated DNA (as judged by RepeatMasker [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.repeatmasker.org" xlink:type="simple">www.repeatmasker.org</ext-link>]): mainly LINE1, but also LTRs of
                    endogenous retroviruses, Alu sequences and some other repeats (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g006">Figure 6</xref>). The most frequently
                    duplicated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence (6,387 copies) is found in LINE1
                    at position 1990 of ORF2 that codes for reverse transcriptase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). This sequence is
                    present in all chromosomes averaging from one per 0.24 Mbp in chromosomes X and
                    Y (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s002">Figure
                        S2</xref>) to one per 1.9 Mbp in chromosome 18. There are multiple
                    variations of this particular sequence in different copies of LINE1 repeats
                    forming different groups of repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    originated at position 1990 of ORF2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g007">Figure 7</xref>). These groups of
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences have lower copy numbers than the
                    “main” one.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0018077-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in repeated DNA sequences in
                            human genome</title>
            <p>Examples of repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in
                                (<bold>A</bold>) LINE-1, (<bold>B</bold>) LTRs of endogenous
                            retroviruses, (<bold>C</bold>) Tc element, (<bold>D</bold>) Alu
                            repeats.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0018077-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Distribution of some <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences originated
                            in repeated DNA elements between repeated and unique pools.</title>
            <p><italic>FL-LINE-1990</italic> and <italic>Fl-LINE-599</italic> represent
                            groups of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that originate at
                            positions 1990 and 599 of ORF2 of LINE1, respectively (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g006">Figure 6</xref>).
                                <italic>FL-LTR-126</italic> represents a group of the
                                <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that originate at position 126
                            of LTR of transposon MER11a (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g006">Figure 6</xref>). <italic>FL-Alu-16</italic>
                            represents a group of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that
                            originate at position 16 of the left half of Alu sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g006">Figure 6</xref>). Consensus
                            sequence for <italic>FL-Alu-16</italic> has 33 nucleotides; red
                            “X” indicates any nucleotide.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Other repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences also form groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g006">Figures 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g007">7</xref>). Members of these groups
                    originate from the same sequence in a repeated DNA element but differ in one or
                    more nucleotides from each other. Groups of repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences are seen in all repeated DNA elements analyzed: LINE1, LTRs, Alu
                    sequences and others. Analysis shows that four <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences that form the most populous groups in their categories (two from
                    LINE1, and one each from LTRs and Alu; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g007">Figure 7</xref>) account for nearly half of all
                    duplicated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences.</p>
        <p>The number of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences located in repetitive DNA
                    elements in the human genome is underestimated since we noted that some
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences, although unique, originate from the
                    duplicated DNA elements and belong to the respective groups of repetitive
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g007">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Classes and subclasses of unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with
                    common sequence patterns</title>
        <p>Since we found that the proximal–8 region is the most critical for
                    determining the functional performance of a genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequence, we grouped all unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences (581,157
                    sites) based on the sequence of the first four proximal base pairs of their
                    putative recombinase binding elements (positions −1 to −4 and 1 to
                    4; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). Since,
                    according to our search criteria, functional <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    in the proximal-8 region can have 8, 7, 6 or 5 matches to the corresponding
                    nucleotides of <italic>FRT</italic>, we first grouped all unique
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences into four major classes based on the
                    number of matches in this region. <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in each
                    major class were then sub-classified based on the actual sequence of the
                    proximal-8 region.</p>
        <p>Although <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences of the class ‘8’ have,
                    by definition, only matching nucleotides in the proximal-8 region, this does not
                    mean that there is only one possible sequence in this region for the class.
                    Since the consensus sequence of <italic>FRT</italic> for the purpose of
                    identifying functional <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences,
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-mod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure
                        1A</xref>), allows A or G at position 1 (and, therefore, C or T at position
                    −1) and A or T at positions −2/2, there are 10 possible sequences in
                    the proximal-8 region that perfectly match those in <italic>FRT</italic>-mod.
                    All <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences of the class ‘8’ were in
                    fact sorted by the program into 10 subclasses. It should be noted that
                    calculation of the number of subclasses in major classes takes into account both
                    direct and inverse complement of a sequence in the proximal-8 region to
                    eliminate those subclasses that seem to represent two different sequences but in
                    fact are direct and inverse complement versions of the same sequence.</p>
        <p>When both number of matched and the nature of mismatched base pairs within the
                    proximal-8 region are taken into account, the number of subclasses for the
                    classes 7, 6 and 5 were found to be 116, 528 and 672, respectively.
                    Consequently, all unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences of the classes 7, 6
                    and 5 were sorted into their respective subclasses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s008">Text
                    S6</xref>).</p>
        <p>A final sorting was performed within each subclass: <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences were sorted based on their spacer sequences (in both direct and
                    inverse complement orientations) to identify those <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences that have identical spacers and therefore can potentially recombine
                    with each other (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s009">Text S7</xref>). A snapshot of a subclass file with
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences sorted based on the sequence of their
                    spacers is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g004">Figure
                    4</xref>.</p>
        <p>To help identify <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with similar sequences
                    patterns, we also grouped all 12,452 of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    that have at least one exact duplicate in the human genome. The grouping was
                    performed the same way as for the unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences:
                    into major classes and subclasses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s010">Text S8</xref>). Finally, duplicated
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences were sorted within each subclass based
                    on their spacer sequences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s011">Text S9</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title><italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences similar to FRT-like sequences of
                    interest</title>
        <p>Identification of all potential <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in the human
                    genome and their classification into classes and subclasses makes it easier to
                    locate <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that have the highest level of
                    homology to an <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest and that can serve as
                    counter-selection targets during evolution of a Flp variant specific for this
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like site. To locate homologous
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences, we developed an additional program called
                        <italic>CompareSequences</italic> that scans all identified
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences (unique and repeated) against an
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest and reports sequences that have
                    their level of homology above a set value (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s012">Text S10</xref>).
                    The output of the program also includes <italic>FRT</italic>-sequences from a
                    subclass, to which the <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest belongs; the
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-sequences from a respective subclass may not have the
                    highest level of homology to the <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest but
                    they have the perfect match in the functionally important proximal-8 region and,
                    therefore, should be considered as the first choice for selecting a
                    counter-selection target. As an example, we searched for counter-selection
                    targets for the <italic>FRT</italic>-like site <italic>FL-2798</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). The
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with the highest level of homology to
                        <italic>FL-2798</italic>, identified by the
                        <italic>CompareSequences</italic> program are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g008">Figure 8</xref>. <italic>FL-CS-2798</italic> is from
                    the general pool of the genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like sites and
                        <italic>FL-CS8-2798</italic> is from the proximal-8 subclass, to which
                        <italic>FL-2798</italic> belongs. When only putative recombinase binding
                    sites are considered, <italic>FL-CS-2798</italic> and
                        <italic>FL-CS8-2798</italic> differ from <italic>FL-2798</italic> by five
                    and eight nucleotides, respectively. The identified <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sites can be used as counter-selection sequences during evolution of Flp
                    variants able to recombine <italic>FL-2798</italic> with minimum off-target
                    effects.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0018077-g008" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g008</object-id>
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Two <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that are highly homologous to
                                <italic>FL-2798</italic>.</title>
            <p>Identical nucleotides between the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences are
                            shown in bold. Spacer sequences are shown in small letters. 8-proximal
                            regions in the sequences are underlined. <italic>FL-CS8-2798</italic>
                            has the same 8-proximal region as <italic>FL-2798</italic> but fewer
                            overall identical nucleotides than has <italic>FL-CS-2798</italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The main goal of the present work was to gain insight into sequence properties and
                distribution of <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in the human genome. To
                accomplish this goal we solved three tasks: (1) we developed a computer program able
                to quickly scan a mammalian genome for target-like sequences for tyrosine
                recombinases; (2) we analyzed genome-wide distribution of <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                sequences in the human genome, and (3) we sorted the identified
                <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences into groups that have common sequence
                patterns.</p>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>TargetSiteAnalyzer</title>
        <p>The bioinformatics package dubbed ‘TargetSiteAnalyzer’ is able to
                    quickly, within several hours using a regular office computer, search the entire
                    human genome for <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences and sort them according to
                    their sequence properties. We deemed it useful to separate the in-silico
                    analysis into three sub-programs. This separation allows the user to make
                    changes to an algorithm without the need to re-run the entire analysis. The
                        <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> program allows the processing of essentially
                    infinite number and sized files by searching for <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequence within a small string of 10,000 bp, well within the memory parameters
                    of most computers. <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> creates a large, single file
                    with <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that have three different scores:
                    overall, weighted and consecutive match scores; this allows the re-sorting of
                    match data as experimental results indicate which parameters are most predictive
                    of success. The <italic>TargetSorter</italic> program assigns a numeric value to
                    the nucleotides in the proximal-8 region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) in order to identify and group
                    similar <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences irrespective of their orientation in
                    a DNA contig. The <italic>SpacerSorter</italic> program allows the easy
                    identification of those <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence in a given subclass
                    that have identical spacers. All Java codes are provided so that
                    TargetSiteAnalyzer can be modified to search for and analyze other target
                    sequences for site-specific recombinases.</p>
        <p>To identify <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences, TargetSiteAnalyzer utilizes a
                    simple sequence scanning approach. In principle, other, more sophisticated
                    genome analysis approaches could be used to accomplish the goal. Since
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sites share conserved sequence patterns, these
                    patterns could be identified using probabilistic sequence analysis approaches,
                    such as a hidden Markov model, HMM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Eddy1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Yada1">[23]</xref>. HMM could also be useful in
                    grouping the identified <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Functional <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in human genome</title>
        <p>An important contribution of our work is the analysis of
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in the human genome. The analysis provides
                    not only an overview of the distribution of the sequences but also their
                    classification based on common sequence patterns. The analysis is a valuable
                    resource for designing genome engineering experiments using tailor-made variants
                    of Flp recombinases, since it assists in choosing <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences in the vicinity of a genomic region of interest by taking into account
                    which class and subclass it belongs to. By doing so, the closest
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence that can be used as a counter-selection
                    target during Flp variant evolution can be identified <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Voziyanov1">[11]</xref>. Such an approach to
                    designing experiments would minimize off-target effects of evolved Flp
                    variants.</p>
        <p>In theory, for each unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence, it should be
                    possible to evolve a unique Flp variant that would preferentially recombine this
                    sequence. The probability of finding a particular <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequence is ∼10<sup>−21</sup> (or ∼10<sup>−16</sup> if only
                    recombinase-binding elements are considered). The size of the human genome is
                        ∼3×10<sup>9</sup> so it should be virtually impossible to find a
                    duplicate for a given <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence in the human genome
                    unless this sequence is part of repeated DNA. Since roughly half of the human
                    genome is repetitive DNA (which can bear potential <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences), we, as a precaution, had to check if identified
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences have duplicates. It appeared that our
                    precaution was justified, as we found that around 10% of all
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in the human genome are duplicated and
                    originated mainly from LINE1, LTRs of retrotransposons and Alu sequences. We
                    also found that there are unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that
                    originate from the same locations in the repeated DNA elements as the respective
                    duplicated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences and, therefore, should belong to
                    the ‘duplicated’ group even though they do not have additional exact
                    copies.</p>
        <p>As in unique genomic regions, we did not find any apparent ‘role’ or
                    ‘function’ for the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in the
                    repetitive DNA in the human genome. Since we observed very good correlation
                    between average distribution of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences and GC
                    content in human chromosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g005">Figure 5</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Sellis1">[19]</xref>), and found that <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    are essentially absent in genomes of thermophilic bacteria (Y.V., unpublished),
                    we can satisfactory explain the presence of <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    in genomic localities with relatively low GC content (less than 50%).</p>
        <p>Although it was unexpected to find that <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences can
                    originate from more than one location in LINE1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g006">Figure 6A</xref>), on average,
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences are more rare in repeated genomic DNA than
                    in unique DNA: repetitive DNA constitutes about 50% of the human genome
                    but only about 10% of all <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences are part of
                    repeats. This observation is not surprising taking into account that the
                    majority of repeated DNA elements are relatively short. Indeed, only infrequent
                    full-length or near full-length units of LINEs or LTR transposons are long
                    enough to have a high probability of occurrence of <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g005">Figure 5</xref>), while
                    the majority of copies of LINEs are shorter than 1 kb and SINEs are only
                    100–400 bp long <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Lander1">[24]</xref>. Moreover, since different members of a family of
                    repeated DNA elements are usually not identical due to random mutations, one
                    repeated element might have an <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence but another
                    might not.</p>
        <p>Multiple identical copies of duplicated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences can,
                    in theory, present a challenge for targeting unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences of interest if the duplicated sequences have a high degree of homology
                    to a chosen unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like site. In this scenario, a Flp
                    variant evolved to recombine the unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like site could, to
                    a certain degree, recombine the repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences. To
                    prevent this and therefore minimize the off-target effects of the recombination
                    system, the repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence should be used as one of
                    the counter-selection targets during evolution of a Flp variant.</p>
        <p>To improve our understanding of the sequence properties of the unique
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences and to help identify the ones with
                    similar sequence patterns, we grouped both the duplicated and unique
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sites into classes based on the number of matches
                    (8, 7, 6, or 5) to the corresponding positions of <italic>FRT</italic> in the
                    proximal-8 region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g001">Figure
                    1A</xref>). This region contains the most important, but not all determining
                    factors for successful recombination of a genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequence. The least populous and the closest to <italic>FRT</italic> is the
                    8-match class, which has 8 matches in the proximal-8 region. The most populous
                    and the least close to <italic>FRT</italic> is the class 5, which have 5 matches
                    in the proximal-8 region.</p>
        <p>Classification of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences helps identify
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sites which have the highest level of homology to
                    an <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest and which can serve as
                    counter-selection targets during evolution of Flp variants specific for this
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like site. Ideally, the counter-selection
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences should come from a subclass, to which an
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest belongs, since all sequences in
                    this subclass have identical functionally important proximal-8 region. However,
                    due to a relatively low number of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in
                    this particular subclass, it is unlikely that it contains an
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence that has the highest level of homology to
                    an <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest. Therefore, in an effort to have a
                    broader picture, the computer program <italic>CompareSequences</italic>, which
                    we developed to identify homologous <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences, scans
                    all genomic <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences. From the output of the program,
                    two <italic>FRT</italic>-sequences can be chosen as counter-selection targets:
                    one from the subclass to which the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence of
                    interest belongs, and one from the rest of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences. The counter-selection <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences will help
                    evolve the most specific Flp variants able to recombine the
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <p>Our work is the first genome-wide analysis of the distribution and sequence
                    properties of target-like sequences for a site-specific recombinase in the human
                    genome. We found that <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences are located in the
                    human genome roughly every 5 kb. The identified <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences were divided into two groups, which contain either unique or
                    duplicated sequences. The duplicated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    originate mainly from such repeated DNA elements as LINE1, LTRs and Alu repeats.
                    All <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences were subdivided into classes and
                    subclasses based on their sequence features. The database of genomic
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences created can be used to identify
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that can serve as counter-selection
                    sites for evolving a Flp variant specific for an <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequence of interest. Our data will be useful for the emerging field of genome
                    engineering.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Human genome DNA</title>
        <p>Contig files containing entire assembled human genome (NCBI build 36.3) were
                    downloaded from NCBI web site: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genomes/genlist.cgi?taxid=2759&amp;type=8&amp;name=EukaryotaeCompleteChromosomes" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genomes/genlist.cgi?taxid=2759&amp;type=8&amp;name=EukaryotaeCompleteChromosomes</ext-link>.
                    Each of 473 files totaling 2.837 Gbp of DNA was identified by chromosome and
                    order, allowing the alignment of contiguous DNA fragments from each chromosome.
                    A map of these ordered DNA fragments is presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s001">Figure
                    S1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>TargetSiteAnalyzer Development and Execution</title>
        <p>The process is executed as three individual programs:
                        <italic>GenomeScanner</italic>, <italic>TargetSorter</italic>, and
                        <italic>SpacerSorter</italic>. An overview of these programs and the
                    processing steps is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g004">Figure
                        4</xref>. The programs were created and executed within the freely available
                    NetBeans IDE (version 6.8; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://netbeans.org" xlink:type="simple">http://netbeans.org</ext-link>). The JAVA
                    code is available for download (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s003">Text S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s004">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0018077.s005">S3</xref>).</p>
        <p><italic>GenomeScanner</italic> is designed to read all DNA sequence files (in
                    FASTA format) in a directory, create an array of sequence contig filenames, then
                    process each sequence file base-by-base to identify sequences that match a
                    particular profile. The first step in the process is to identify the sequence
                    file and set the chromosome and location of the sequence within the file within
                    context of the chromosome. Each sequence file is read line by line and added to
                    the end of a string, until the string reaches 10,000 bp in length. Each of these
                    strings is tested for a match to the <italic>FRT</italic> sequence by advancing
                    1 base, acquiring the 34 base sequence, then testing it as indicated below and
                    as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g003">Figures 3</xref> and
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g004">4</xref>. Once the string
                    length from the last position tested equals 39 bp, the next lines from the
                    sequence file are added until the string again reaches 10,000 bp and the process
                    is repeated.</p>
        <p>Once a potential <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence is identified, it is written
                    along with information such as file name, scores, position within the sequence
                    file and overall position on the chromosome to an internal array and a linear
                    order text file (which allows identification of nearby <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences regardless of sequence structure). At the end of the last sequence
                    file, the internal array of the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences is used to
                    identify exact forward and reverse matches within all identified
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences and write these repeated sequences to a
                    separate file. All other <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that do not have an
                    exact match are written to a file of unique sequences.
                        <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> has 2,795 lines of code, of which 1,892 use
                    the file name of each of the 473 human genome contig files (NCBI build 36.3) to
                    identify the chromosome and an offset number used for positioning each
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence within the linear chromosome sequence.
                    Using a regular office computer, this program executes in its entirety in
                    approximately 470 minutes, or 1 minute per input file.</p>
        <p>Using either the file with unique or repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    created by the <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> program,
                        <italic>TargetSorter</italic> creates general files that contains all
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with the same number of matches within
                    the proximal-8 region. Within each file, the nucleotides at the proximal-8
                    region are assigned a number with A = 1,
                    T = 2, G = 3 and
                    C = 4. For example, if a sequence in the proximal-8 region
                    is ATAC-spacer-AATA, its number is 12,141,121; the number of the inverse
                    complement of this proximal-8 region sequence (TATT-spacer-GTAT) is 21,223,212.
                    The numbers in both the forward and reverse complement orientation of the
                    proximal-8 region are compared, with the lowest value used for the filename
                    designation. Each resultant file contains only <italic>FRT</italic>-like
                    sequences that belong to a unique subclass. <italic>TargetSorter</italic> has
                    332 lines of code. The program execution speed varies based on input file size,
                    taking approximately one hour to sort the 581,157 unique
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences.</p>
        <p>Each subclass-specific file created by <italic>TargetSorter</italic> is processed
                    by the <italic>SpacerSorter</italic> program, which compares all spacer
                    sequences within the file and then creates a new file, which lists
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with identical spacers first, each group
                    of sequences delineated by a blank line, followed by a list of the
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with unique spacer sequences.
                    Subclass-specific files containing repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences
                    by definition do not have <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences with unique
                    spacers. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0018077-g004">Figure 4</xref> shows an
                    example output from <italic>SpacerSorter</italic>. This program has 154 lines of
                    code and typically executes in 1 minute or less when processing the 1,325 files
                    containing subclass-specific unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences.</p>
        <p>The <italic>CompareSequences</italic> program scans a group of files containing
                    all unsorted <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences (both unique and repeated) for
                    the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences homologous to an
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest. The level of homology is determined
                    by the number of nucleotides that are identical in a given
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence and in the <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of
                    interest. <italic>CompareSequences</italic> reports the
                    <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that have the number of identical
                    nucleotides above the set threshold. The program also reports all
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences from the subclass file, to which the
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest belongs, indicating the number of
                    identical nucleotides between an <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence and the
                        <italic>FRT</italic>-like site of interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Other methods</title>
        <p>The Flp-DNA structure (PDB code 1FLO) was analyzed using Swiss-PdbViewer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Guex1">[25]</xref>. General
                    genetic engineering experiments were performed as described in Sambrook and
                    Russell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Sambrook1">[26]</xref>. Molecular evolution of the Flp variant genes was
                    performed as described in Bolusani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">[14]</xref>. The evolved Flp variants
                    were tested using the lacZα deletion reporters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0018077-Voziyanov1">[11]</xref>, in which the lacZα
                    cassette was flanked by an <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence of interest and
                        <italic>FRT</italic> in which its native spacer was replaced with a spacer
                    from the <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequence.</p>
        <p>To construct the pEGFP-del reporter, the EGFP gene was PCR-amplified from the
                    pIRES2-EGFP vector (Clontech) with primers that contained either
                        <italic>FL-61204</italic> or <italic>FL-63904</italic> or
                        <italic>FL-71362</italic> sites (forward primer) and a modified
                        <italic>FRT</italic> site (reverse primer). The amplified EGFP gene was
                    cloned into pcDNA5/FRT (Invitrogen) under the control of the CMV promoter
                    between NheI and HindIII to obtain pcDNA5-EGFP. Then, the DsRed gene from
                    pIRES2-DsRed-Express (Clontech) was PCR-amplified and cloned into pcDNA5-EGFP
                    between BamHI and XhoI to obtain pEGFP-del.</p>
        <p>The mammalian expression vectors for Flp variants were constructed by cloning the
                    genes for the variants into pOG44 (Invitrogen) in place of the
                        <italic>FLP</italic>-F70L variant gene.</p>
        <p>Chinese Hamster ovary cells (CHO-K1, ATCC CCL-61) were propagated in F12-K media.
                    A Flp recombinase variant expressing vector and a respective pEGFP-del reporter
                    were co-transfected into CHO cells with a ratio of 8∶1 (w/w).
                    Transfections were performed using Polyfect (Qiagen) according to the
                    manufacturer's recommendations.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s001" mimetype="application/x-emf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Map of contiguous DNA fragments in NCBI build 36.3 of human
                            genome.</bold> File names are listed to the right of each chromosome.
                        The map was generated using the MapChart program. The map can be viewed and
                        magnified using, for example, the Windows Picture and Fax Viewer
                        program.</p>
          <p>(EMF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s002" mimetype="application/x-emf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold><italic>FRT</italic></bold><bold>-like sequences on human chromosomes X
                            and Y.</bold> Black horizontal bands within chromosomal bars indicate
                        unique <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences; red horizontal bands indicate
                        repeated <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences. Each number bar on the left
                        panel corresponds to 10,000 base pairs. The map was generated using the
                        MapChart program. The map can be viewed and magnified using, for example,
                        the Windows Picture and Fax Viewer program.</p>
          <p>(EMF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s003" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Java code for <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> program.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s004" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Java code for <italic>TargetSorter</italic> program.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s005" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Java code for <italic>SpacerSorter</italic> program.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s006" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>TargetSiteAnalyzer Installation and Run Parameters.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s007" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s007" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>All <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences in human genome identified by
                            <italic>GenomeScanner</italic> program.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s008" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s008" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Example of a file from the pool of files of unique genomic
                            <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences sorted into classes and subclasses.
                        Zip archive of the pool can be downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.latech.edu/~voziyan/index_files/TextS6.zip" xlink:type="simple">http://www2.latech.edu/~voziyan/index_files/TextS6.zip</ext-link>.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s009" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s009" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Example of a file from the pool of files of unique genomic
                            <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that have their spacers grouped
                        within each subclass file. Zip archive of the pool can be downloaded from
                            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.latech.edu/~voziyan/index_files/TextS7.zip" xlink:type="simple">http://www2.latech.edu/~voziyan/index_files/TextS7.zip</ext-link>.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s010" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s010" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S8</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Example of a file from the pool of files of duplicated genomic
                            <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences sorted into classes and subclasses.
                        Zip archive of the pool can be downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.latech.edu/~voziyan/index_files/TextS8.zip" xlink:type="simple">http://www2.latech.edu/~voziyan/index_files/TextS8.zip</ext-link>.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s011" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s011" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S9</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Example of a file from the pool of files of duplicated genomic
                            <italic>FRT</italic>-like sequences that have their spacers grouped
                        within each subclass file. Zip archive of the pool can be downloaded from
                            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.latech.edu/~voziyan/index_files/TextS9.zip" xlink:type="simple">http://www2.latech.edu/~voziyan/index_files/TextS9.zip</ext-link>.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0018077.s012" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0018077.s012" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S10</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Java code for <italic>CompareSequences</italic> program.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Kilby1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilby</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snaith</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>Site-specific recombinases: tools for genome
                        engineering.</article-title>
                    <source>Trends Genet</source>
                    <volume>9</volume>
                    <fpage>413</fpage>
                    <lpage>421</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Mills1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>From mouse to man: generating megabase chromosome
                        rearrangements.</article-title>
                    <source>Trends Genet</source>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                    <fpage>331</fpage>
                    <lpage>339</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Wirth1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gama-Norton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riemer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandhu</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schucht</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Road to precision: recombinase-based targeting technologies for
                        genome engineering.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                    <fpage>411</fpage>
                    <lpage>419</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Rodriguez1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sequerra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>High-efficiency deleter mice show that FLPe is an alternative to
                        Cre-loxP.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Genet</source>
                    <volume>25</volume>
                    <fpage>139</fpage>
                    <lpage>140</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Glaser1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anastassiadis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Current issues in mouse genome engineering.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Genet</source>
                    <volume>37</volume>
                    <fpage>1187</fpage>
                    <lpage>1193</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Qiao1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oumard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wegloehner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bode</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Novel tag-and-exchange (RMCE) strategies generate master cell
                        clones with predictable and stable transgene expression
                        properties.</article-title>
                    <source>J Mol Biol</source>
                    <volume>390</volume>
                    <fpage>579</fpage>
                    <lpage>594</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Buchholz1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Alteration of Cre recombinase site specificity by
                        substrate-linked protein evolution.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
                    <volume>19</volume>
                    <fpage>1047</fpage>
                    <lpage>1052</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Santoro1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Directed evolution of the site specificity of Cre
                        recombinase.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>99</volume>
                    <fpage>4185</fpage>
                    <lpage>4190</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Rufer1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rufer</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Non-contact positions impose site selectivity on Cre
                        recombinase.</article-title>
                    <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
                    <volume>30</volume>
                    <fpage>2764</fpage>
                    <lpage>2771</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Sarkar1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauber</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>HIV-1 proviral DNA excision using an evolved
                        recombinase.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>316</volume>
                    <fpage>1912</fpage>
                    <lpage>1915</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Voziyanov1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voziyanov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>A dual reporter screening system identifies the amino acid at
                        position 82 in Flp site-specific recombinase as a determinant for target
                        specificity.</article-title>
                    <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
                    <volume>30</volume>
                    <fpage>1656</fpage>
                    <lpage>1663</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Voziyanov2">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voziyanov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konieczka</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Stepwise manipulation of DNA specificity in Flp recombinase:
                        progressively adapting Flp to individual and combinatorial mutations in its
                        target site.</article-title>
                    <source>J Mol Biol</source>
                    <volume>326</volume>
                    <fpage>65</fpage>
                    <lpage>76</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Konieczka1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konieczka</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voziyanov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Recombination of hybrid target sites by binary combinations of
                        Flp variants: mutations that foster interprotomer collaboration and enlarge
                        substrate tolerance.</article-title>
                    <source>J Mol Biol</source>
                    <volume>339</volume>
                    <fpage>365</fpage>
                    <lpage>378</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Bolusani1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolusani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konieczka</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Evolution of variants of yeast site-specific recombinase Flp that
                        utilize native genomic sequences as recombination target
                        sites.</article-title>
                    <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
                    <volume>34</volume>
                    <fpage>5259</fpage>
                    <lpage>5269</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Tay1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Droge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghadessy</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Selection of bacteriophage lambda integrases with altered
                        recombination specificity by in vitro compartmentalization.</article-title>
                    <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
                    <volume>38</volume>
                    <fpage>e25</fpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Senecoff1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Senecoff</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossmeissl</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1988</year>
                    <article-title>DNA recognition by the FLP recombinase of the yeast 2 mu plasmid.
                        A mutational analysis of the FLP binding site.</article-title>
                    <source>J Mol Biol</source>
                    <volume>201</volume>
                    <fpage>405</fpage>
                    <lpage>421</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Umlauf1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Umlauf</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1988</year>
                    <article-title>The functional significance of DNA sequence structure in a
                        site-specific genetic recombination reaction.</article-title>
                    <source>EMBO J</source>
                    <volume>7</volume>
                    <fpage>1845</fpage>
                    <lpage>1852</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Chen1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narendra</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iype</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Crystal structure of a Flp recombinase-Holliday junction complex:
                        assembly of an active oligomer by helix swapping.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Cell</source>
                    <volume>6</volume>
                    <fpage>885</fpage>
                    <lpage>897</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Sellis1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sellis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Provata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almirantis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Alu and LINE1 distributions in the human chromosomes: evidence of
                        global genomic organization expressed in the form of power
                        laws.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
                    <volume>24</volume>
                    <fpage>2385</fpage>
                    <lpage>2399</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Kalari1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalari</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casavant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bair</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Comeron</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>First exons and introns–a survey of GC content and gene
                        structure in the human genome.</article-title>
                    <source>In Silico Biol</source>
                    <volume>6</volume>
                    <fpage>237</fpage>
                    <lpage>242</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Skaletsky1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skaletsky</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroda-Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minx</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordum</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>The male-specific region of the human Y chromosome is a mosaic of
                        discrete sequence classes.</article-title>
                    <source>Nature</source>
                    <volume>423</volume>
                    <fpage>825</fpage>
                    <lpage>837</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Eddy1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>What is a hidden Markov model?</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
                    <volume>22</volume>
                    <fpage>1315</fpage>
                    <lpage>1316</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Yada1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Totoki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Automatic extraction of motifs represented in the hidden Markov
                        model from a number of DNA sequences.</article-title>
                    <source>Bioinformatics</source>
                    <volume>14</volume>
                    <fpage>317</fpage>
                    <lpage>325</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Lander1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linton</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nusbaum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zody</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Initial sequencing and analysis of the human
                        genome.</article-title>
                    <source>Nature</source>
                    <volume>409</volume>
                    <fpage>860</fpage>
                    <lpage>921</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Guex1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guex</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peitsch</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>SWISS-MODEL and the Swiss-PdbViewer: an environment for
                        comparative protein modeling.</article-title>
                    <source>Electrophoresis</source>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                    <fpage>2714</fpage>
                    <lpage>2723</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0018077-Sambrook1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Molecular cloning: a laboratory manual.</article-title>
                    <publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor,N.Y.:</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>