<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163226</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-16-01069</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Ecology and environmental sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Wildfires</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Engineering and technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Energy and power</subject><subj-group><subject>Fuels</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Materials science</subject><subj-group><subject>Materials by attribute</subject><subj-group><subject>Fuels</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Computer and information sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Network analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Centrality</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Engineering and technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Fire engineering</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecosystems</subject><subj-group><subject>Forests</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Ecology and environmental sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecosystems</subject><subj-group><subject>Forests</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Ecology and environmental sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Terrestrial environments</subject><subj-group><subject>Forests</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Ecology and environmental sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Terrestrial environments</subject><subj-group><subject>Wilderness</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Plants</subject><subj-group><subject>Trees</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Plants</subject><subj-group><subject>Trees</subject><subj-group><subject>Pines</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Complex Network Theory Approach for the Spatial Distribution of Fire Breaks in Heterogeneous Forest Landscapes for the Control of Wildland Fires</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Fire Breaks Distribution Based on Network Information Flow</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Russo</surname>
<given-names>Lucia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Russo</surname>
<given-names>Paola</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Siettos</surname>
<given-names>Constantinos I.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Combustion Research Institute, Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche, Naples, Italy</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Department of Chemical Engineering, Materials and Environment, Sapienza University of Rome, Rome, Italy</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>School of Applied Mathematics and Physical Sciences, National Technical University of Athens, Athens, Greece</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Hanewinkel</surname>
<given-names>Marc</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Albert-Ludwigs-Universitat Freiburg, GERMANY</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> CIS LR.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> CIS LR.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> CIS LR.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> CIS LR.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> CIS LR PR.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Project administration:</bold> CIS.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Resources:</bold> CIS LR.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Software:</bold> CIS LR.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> CIS.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Validation:</bold> CIS LR PR.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Visualization:</bold> CIS.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> CIS LR PR.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> CIS LR PR.</p></list-item></list></p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">ksiet@mail.ntua.gr</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>25</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<elocation-id>e0163226</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>11</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>6</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Russo et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226"/>
<abstract>
<p>Based on complex network theory, we propose a computational methodology which addresses the spatial distribution of fuel breaks for the inhibition of the spread of wildland fires on heterogeneous landscapes. This is a two-level approach where the dynamics of fire spread are modeled as a random Markov field process on a directed network whose edge weights are determined by a Cellular Automata model that integrates detailed GIS, landscape and meteorological data. Within this framework, the spatial distribution of fuel breaks is reduced to the problem of finding network nodes (small land patches) which favour fire propagation. Here, this is accomplished by exploiting network centrality statistics. We illustrate the proposed approach through (a) an artificial forest of randomly distributed density of vegetation, and (b) a real-world case concerning the island of Rhodes in Greece whose major part of its forest was burned in 2008. Simulation results show that the proposed methodology outperforms the benchmark/conventional policy of fuel reduction as this can be realized by selective harvesting and/or prescribed burning based on the density and flammability of vegetation. Interestingly, our approach reveals that patches with sparse density of vegetation may act as hubs for the spread of the fire.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>We did not get financial support from any funder for this study.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="6"/>
<table-count count="1"/>
<page-count count="18"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files. GIS Data for the island of Rhodes are available from Google Earth (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.google.com/earth/" xlink:type="simple">https://www.google.com/earth/</ext-link>) and also the NASA observatory: (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/" xlink:type="simple">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/</ext-link>). Vegetation Data as well as the Data for the Fire Incident of 2008 are available from the Ministry of Reconstruction of Production, Environment &amp; Energy (former Hellenic Ministry of Rural Development and Food) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.minagric.gr/index.php/el/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.minagric.gr/index.php/el/</ext-link>.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Efficient wildland fire control is one of the most challenging and important problems in ecology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref001">1</xref>]. On the one hand, fire is an essential renewing contributor of the ecological cycle. On the other hand, wildfires have been the cause of irreversible environmental and socio-economic damages. Fuel management treatments have been extensively applied at the local scale, but they have had a limited influence on the evolution of wildfires at the landscape scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref002">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref003">3</xref>]. At this scale level, experimental work is prohibitory, and the majority of previous studies on the spatial distribution of fuel management activities have been theoretical [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref002">2</xref>]. Observations on real wildland fire cases have evidenced that fire size and severity can be mitigated by proper design of treatments such as fuel segmentation and prescribed burning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref003">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref006">6</xref>]. Hence, organizations like the USDA Forest Service, in their fuel managements plans, consider spatial fragmentation of the fuel crucial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref007">7</xref>]. The problem is how to spatially distribute the fuel management activities across the landscape. Factors such as weather/climate conditions (wind field, air humidity and temperature), characteristics of the distributed local fuel (type and structure of the vegetation, moisture and density), landscape/earth characteristics (slope, fragmentation and natural barriers) as well as fire-suppression tactics are considered to be key elements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref008">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref014">14</xref>]. The conventional/empirical approach is that of selective fuel reduction, i.e. the selective cutting/harvesting and/or prescribed burning to reduce ground fuel at specific locations, based primarily on the density and flammability of the vegetation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref015">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref017">17</xref>]. Recently, the US Forest Service started a massive forest thinning project for preventing devastating forest fires, especially in the Southwest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref018">18</xref>]. However, special care has to be taken not to disturb the landscape in order to maintain the structural and spatial heterogeneity of the forest including the preservation of wildlife habitat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref019">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref020">20</xref>].</p>
<p>There is a growing interest of developing and implementing rigorous mathematical methods to help designing better fuel treatments. The base of these approaches is the adoption of accurate and efficient simulation models. At the small scale, theoretical studies on the spatial distribution of fuel managements activities have shown that a random or compartmented distribution of fuel management activities reduce the spread rate of the fire when dealing with large portions of the landscape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref021">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref022">22</xref>]. It has been also shown that regular patterns such as parallel stripes work effectively if the fire moves perpendicular to the stripes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref023">23</xref>]. Although these approaches are very promising, relatively fewer studies have faced the problem at the real-world landscape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref002">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref024">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref027">27</xref>]. Both operational and fuel reduction management tactics are optimized at the landscape level, where spatial patterns of fuel management activities were scheduled using a heuristic optimization algorithm that was implemented in FARSITE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref002">2</xref>]. FARSITE is a complex wildfire growth and behaviour modelling system that can simulate fire spread on real heterogeneous landscapes using spatial information on topography and fuels along with weather and wind streams [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref028">28</xref>]. Several management activities, namely prescribed burning, thinning and timber harvesting have been evaluated and compared across four landscapes with increasing fuel content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref024">24</xref>]. The distribution of activities was achieved through optimization using SIMMPPLE (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fs.fed.us/rm/missoula/4151/SIMPPLLE/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fs.fed.us/rm/missoula/4151/SIMPPLLE/index.html</ext-link>), a platform including fire behaviour, insect disease and climate change models designed as a management tool in landscape ecology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref029">29</xref>]. Fire mitigation through the implementation of fuel breaks was simulated on in the Mara˜o mountain range, NW Portugal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref025">25</xref>]. Several intensities of fuel treating stands considering also spatial vegetation density and residential priorities on a 16,000 ha study area in Oregon, US were evaluated with respect to forest health and ecological restoration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref026">26</xref>]. The so-called minimum travel time (MTT) fire spread algorithm has also been used to simulate wildland fire spread [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref030">30</xref>]. In another study, the authors compared the relative effectiveness of thinning, a combination of thinning and burning, and solely burning on simulated stand-scale fire behavior as well as the effectiveness of three different arrangement of treatments, namely random, defensible fuel profile zones (DFPZ) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref031">31</xref>], and strategically placed area treatments (SPLATs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref023">23</xref>] on a simulated area of Southern Cascade range, California [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref027">27</xref>].</p>
<p>Here, we focus on the problem of the systematic- in terms of mathematical modelling and analysis-placement of fire breaks as realized by fuel reduction (e.g. selective harvesting or prescribed burning) for the management of wildland fires. Besides limiting fire spread, fuel reduction is also used to restore longleaf pine forests, enhance the growth rate of young trees reducing midstorey and shrub layers, while at the same time can be used for commercial thinning of woodlands. We propose a computational two-level framework, where fire is being modeled to spread through a weighted directed network whose edge weights are the state transition probabilities of a spatio-temporal Markov Cellular Automata (CA) process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref032">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref033">33</xref>]. The particular CA model incorporates detailed GIS, landscape and meteorological data and has been proved to be robust and efficient in predicting the fire spreading behaviour in several real-world cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref032">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref035">35</xref>]. Thus, the problem of the spatial distribution of fire breaks is reduced to the problem of finding the group of nodes through which the fire spreads most rapidly. This problem is closely and straightforwardly related to the analysis of information flow on networks. For the detection of fire spread hubs, we make use of the network centrality measures such as the Betweenness Centrality and Bonacich information flow criterion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref036">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref037">37</xref>]. Our approach is illustrated through two examples: (a) an artificial forest of randomly distributed density of vegetation, and (b) a real-world case concerning the island of Rhodes in Greece whose major part of its forest was burned in 2008. Simulations, over an ensemble of lattice realizations and multiple ignition points, show the approach to be very promising as it produces statistically significantly better outcomes than the benchmark/conventional policy of fuel reduction based on the density and flammability of the vegetation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>The proposed methodology aims at the systematic design of the spatial distribution of fire breaks for the inhibition of the propagation of wildland fires in heterogeneous forest landscapes. Fire propagation is being modeled as a random walk on a network (lattice graph of dimension NxN) with directed weighted edges; a CA model defines the transition matrix of the random walk processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref038">38</xref>]. Then, the spatial distribution of fire breaks is reduced to a flow information problem: that of finding a partition of network nodes that if removed from the network the propagation of fire through the network slows down the most (for a schematic see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0163226.g001">Fig 1</xref>). The terrain is tessellated into a number of small patches whose shape and size depends on the level of precision with respect to the spatial directionality (squares, hexagons etc.). Hence, the terrain is transformed into a lattice network, <italic>G</italic>(<italic>V</italic>,<italic>E</italic>), where <italic>V</italic> = {<italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>}, <italic>k</italic> = 1, 2, …, <italic>N</italic> is the set of nodes (the terrain patches), and <italic>E</italic> is the set of edges (links) between neighbor nodes. Each edge <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e001"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e001" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is directed and its weight is determined by the states of the nodes <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>,<italic>v</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> ∈ <italic>V</italic> associated with it as it will be explained below. The system state over the set of the nodes (edges) is denoted by <italic>S</italic>(<italic>V</italic>) (<italic>S</italic>(<italic>E</italic>)), where <italic>S</italic>(<italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>) ≡ {<italic>s</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>)} = {<italic>s</italic><sub><italic>ik</italic></sub>}, <italic>i</italic> = 1, 2, …, <italic>M</italic> is the set of <italic>M</italic> state variables of the node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>. The state variables can be continuous (<italic>s</italic><sub><italic>ik</italic></sub> (⋅) ∈ <italic>R</italic>) or discrete (<italic>s</italic><sub><italic>ik</italic></sub> (⋅) ∈ <italic>Z</italic>) and represent both terrain and vegetation characteristics such as elevation, type and density of vegetation, moisture content, vegetation height, etc. In general, the values of state variables can change over time. In addition to the landscape characteristics, they also include a component associated to the susceptible-burning-burned states: <italic>s</italic><sub>1<italic>k</italic></sub> = 0 if <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> is still susceptible to burning, <italic>s</italic><sub>1<italic>k</italic></sub> = 1 if <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> is burning, and, <italic>s</italic><sub>1<italic>k</italic></sub> = −1, if <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> has already been burned. Let us also denote the neighborhood of <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> as <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e002"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e002" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ℜ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. The neighbourhood of each node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> is defined by a set of the surrounding eight nodes (Moore-neighborhood). Thus, the system’s dynamics can be represented as a spatio-temporal Markov process of order two in space and order one in time with transition probabilities:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e003">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M3">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(1)</label>
</disp-formula>
(the above relation implies that a node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> that is burning at time <italic>t</italic> will be burned down at the next time step),</p>
<p>and,
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e004">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e004g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M4">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(2)</label>
</disp-formula>
where, <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e005"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e005g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e005" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ℜ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e006"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e006g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e006" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.10em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the probability that the fire spreads from <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e007"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e007g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e007" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ℜ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> and depends only upon all the other states of <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, <italic>s</italic><sub><italic>ik</italic>, <italic>i</italic> = 2, 3, …,M</sub>, and of all the other states of its neighbors, <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e008"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e008g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e008" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>ℜ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>M</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. The transition probability <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e009"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e009g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e009" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> defines the directed weight of the spatial connection <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e010"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e010g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e010" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. In the general case, we have <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e011"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e011g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e011" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, so thus the network is directed and self-contacts are not allowed, i.e. <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e012"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e012g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e012" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. Hence, the elements <italic>a</italic><sub><italic>lk</italic></sub> of the corresponding (weighted) adjacency matrix, <italic>A</italic>, of size <italic>N</italic> × <italic>N</italic> represent the weights of the links <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e013"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e013g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e013" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M13"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. Under the above formalism the system dynamics can be presented as a second order directed Markov field.</p>
<fig id="pone.0163226.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Schematic of the approach.</title>
<p>The fire propagation probabilities are computed using a Cellular Automata model; these constitute the elements of the adjacency matrix of the lattice. Then centrality measures such as the Betweenness Centrality, Closeness and Bonacich centrality can be implemented to find the nodes (patches of land) which contribute more to the spread of the fire. (With black color is depicted an empty cell (containing no fuel). For the particular adjacency matrix shown, the most “infuental” node for the spread of the fire is the cell (node) 5.)</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Having computed the adjacency matrix, centrality statistics such as the Betweenness Centrality (BC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref037">37</xref>] and the Bonacich information criterion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref036">36</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec011">Appendix</xref>) can be used for the identification of nodes that contribute more to the fire spread through the network. The BC centrality of a node is defined as the fraction of geodesic distances (shortest paths) from all other nodes. Bonacich centrality, which is closely related to Eigencentrality (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec011">Appendix</xref>) reflects the influence of a node on the spread of information through the network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref039">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref041">41</xref>]. Here the weights of the graph, i.e. the probabilities of fire propagation <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e014"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e014g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e014" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> are inversely proportional to the distances between a given node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> and its neighbors <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>. Thus nodes with a high value of centrality are connected with other nodes by relatively short paths (involving high values of probabilities of fire propagation) and so they are central to the information flow (and therefore to the fire spread) through the network.</p>
<p>Under this view, we rank cells according to their centrality values from higher to lower values and we remove (i.e. cut/burn the vegetation in the corresponding land patches) the first, <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> ⊂ <italic>N</italic>, of them.</p>
<p>At this point, we note that for large and very large scale problems the computation of the Betweenness centralities for all nodes is computationally expensive as it requires the derivation of all shortest paths in the graph. On the other hand, the Bonacich centrality can be computed efficiently using Arnoldi’s iterative method (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec011">Appendix</xref>).</p>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>The artificial forest model</title>
<p>To illustrate the efficiency of the above measures, we first consider a simplistic case of a square lattice with Moore Neighborhood and periodic boundary conditions, where the landscape is flat, the type of vegetation is homogenous, i.e. there is just one type of vegetation (e.g. pine trees) and the density of vegetation varies continuously from 1 (corresponding to empty/burned cells) to 0 (corresponding to very dense vegetation). The state (density of vegetation) of a node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> at time <italic>t</italic> is represented by <italic>s</italic><sub>2<italic>k</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) ∈ [0 1]. Dynamics advance from time <italic>t</italic> to time <italic>t+1</italic> for all nodes simultaneously according to the following rules:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e015">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e015g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e015" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M15">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.35em"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(3)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>This rule implies that a burning node at the current time step will be burned down at the next time step.</p>
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e016">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e016g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e016" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M16">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.35em"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>ℜ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(4)</label>
</disp-formula>
<p>This rule implies that if a node contains fuel then if there is also a burning node at its neighborhood, it will catch fire at the next time step with probability that is proportional to the density of the vegetation. Hence, according to the above definition, if <italic>s</italic><sub>2<italic>k</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = 1 (meaning that the cell is empty of vegetation or has been already burned) then <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub> = 0, while if <italic>s</italic><sub>2<italic>k</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = 0 (meaning that the cell contains a very dense vegetation) then <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub> = 1.</p>
<p>In the random field Markov process framework, the above CA rules can be written compactly as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e017">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e017g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e017" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M17">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(5)</label>
</disp-formula>
and
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e018">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e018g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e018" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M18">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>ℜ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(6)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>For illustrating our approach, we first considered a lattice of 50x50 cells with periodic boundary conditions. Random numbers were created by a uniform distribution in (0 1) using Matlab’s function rand. We used 100 realizations (ensembles) of randomly generated artificial forests and for each one of the realizations we created a corresponding distribution of fire breaks (randomly placed or network-based placed) and we run the simplistic CA model, until there were no burning cells. All simulations started by setting a fire at the center of the lattice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>The case of Rhodes island, Greece</title>
<p>We applied the proposed methodology to simulate the effect of the distribution of fire breaks in the south part of Rhodes island, Greece located in the southeastern Aegean Sea. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0163226.g002">Fig 2</xref> shows a stereoscopic image of Rhodes as acquired from the NASA Earth Observatory (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=77079" xlink:type="simple">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=77079</ext-link>). In July 2008, a wildland fire swept through Rhodes causing significant damages. The fire occurred on 22.07.2008 and broke out at 11.40 am at the Ag. Isidoros point (Latitude: 36.15, Longitude: 27.85). Thousands of Pinus brutia trees were burned. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0163226.g003">Fig 3</xref> depicts a map of the vegetation density of the area under study. The wind was NW 4–5 bf during the period of the incident. The consequences of the fire were 13,240 ha of burnt area and an inestimable environmental disaster.</p>
<fig id="pone.0163226.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>A stereoscopic image of Rhodes island, Greece (acquired from the NASA Earth Observatory (public domain): <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/" xlink:type="simple">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/</ext-link>).</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pone.0163226.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Map of the vegetation density of the area under study in Rhodes island, Greece as was before the wildfire incident of July 2008.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The key and crucial element for the extension of the above approach to real-world cases is the computation of transition probabilities that produce good approximations of real fire behaviour. Here, we employed a state-of-the-art CA model that has been developed over the past few years and has proven robust and efficient in predicting the fire spreading behaviour in several real-world cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref032">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref035">35</xref>].</p>
<p>The CA model takes into account major macroscopic factors that determine the spread of the fire such as the vegetation density and type, wind field and detailed terrain data. For each node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> we consider the following states:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e019">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e019g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e019" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M19">
<mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>impact of the type of vegetation, impact of the density of vegetation, node's elevation</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>In a nutshell, fire dynamics (considering no wind conditions) are propagated from a node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> (assuming that is burning) to its neighbors as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e020">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e020g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e020" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M20">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.15em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(7)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>Here, <italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub> is a nominal probability of fire spread under no wind, flat terrain, certain density and type of vegetation, and it is calculated from experimental data. The type and the density of vegetation in the area are split into a number of discrete categories. For the case of Rhodes island, the type of vegetation has been clustered into three categories (agricultural areas, pine trees, and other types of trees including shrubs), while the density of vegetation has been scaled into three categories (low, medium, high). The gain factor <italic>f</italic>(<italic>s</italic><sub>4<italic>k</italic></sub>, <italic>s</italic><sub>4<italic>l</italic></sub>) denotes the effect of the slope between nodes <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> and <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> and is calculated via:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e021">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e021g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e021" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M21">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(8)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic>θ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub> is the slope angle between <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> and <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> and <italic>a</italic> &gt; 0 is a constant that can be adjusted from experimental data. For a square grid, the slope angle is calculated in a different way depending on whether the two neighboring nodes are adjacent or diagonal to the burning node. More specifically for an adjacent node, the slope angle reads:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e022">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e022g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e022" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M22">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">tan</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(9)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic>l</italic> is the length of the square side. For diagonal nodes the formula becomes:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e023">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e023g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e023" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M23">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">tan</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:msqrt><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(10)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>Note that the gaining factors to in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0163226.e020">Eq 7</xref> can exceed 1. For example the factor related to the slope by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0163226.e021">Eq 8</xref> can exceed 1 for positive slopes <italic>θ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>. However, the final probability is constrained between 0 and 1.The effect of wind can be also considered by multiplying <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0163226.e020">Eq 7</xref> appropriately (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref032">32</xref>]).</p>
<p>The parameter values of the above model are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0163226.t001">Table 1</xref>. Keeping the same values of the model parameters as the ones found through optimization for the wildland fire that occurred in Spetses island in Greece in 1990 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref032">32</xref>], the model predicted quite well the dynamics of the large scale wildfire that occurred in the mountain of Parnitha, Greece in 2007, one of the most catastrophic fire incidents in Greece over the last 50 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref033">33</xref>], and that of wildland fire which devastated Rhodes in 2008 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref034">34</xref>]. More specifically, for the case of Spetses island the wildfire burned an area of about 590 ha in 11 hours; the CA simulator over 100 runs resulted to an average of 540 ha (std: 100 ha) burned area (almost equivalent to the actual burned area) in 11.3 (std: 2.5) hours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref032">32</xref>]. For the case of the wildfire in Parnitha, Athens, the CA simulator resulted to an almost equivalent spatio-temporal pattern to the actual evolution of the wildfire that burned 5,600 ha in 3 days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref033">33</xref>]. We note here that these areas belong to the same bio-geo-climatic domain. Furthermore both islands (Rhodes and Spetses) contain the same type of vegetation.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0163226.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Parameter values for the CA model.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Parameter</th>
<th align="left">Value</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Effect of Density (<italic>s</italic><sub>3<italic>k</italic></sub>)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Effect of Type (<italic>s</italic><sub>2<italic>k</italic></sub>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>p</italic><sub><italic>o</italic></sub></td>
<td align="left">0.58</td>
<td align="left">Sparse</td>
<td align="left">-0.4</td>
<td align="left">Agricultural</td>
<td align="left">-0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>a</italic></td>
<td align="left">0.078</td>
<td align="left">Moderate</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
<td align="left">Other types of trees including shrubs</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">Dense</td>
<td align="left">0.3</td>
<td align="left">Pines</td>
<td align="left">0.4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>The area was tessellated using a two dimensional grid. Each cell of the grid defines a node representing a small square patch of land, thus offering eight possible directions of fire spread. The side of the square was equal to ten meters. Thus, the size of the adjacency matrix was 1260000 x 1260000 reflecting the area of interest defined by the rectangular shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0163226.g004">Fig 4</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone.0163226.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>The “expected” map of relative burning frequencies for the case of Rhodes island, Greece.</title>
<p>This was constructed using the CA model over 100 simulations all starting from the ignition point of the real incident of 22.07.2008 (Ag. Isidoros: Latitude: 36.15, Longitude: 27.85)<bold>;</bold> the outline of the burned area of the real incident is also shown.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Performance evaluation</title>
<p>In order to access the effectiveness of the proposed approach, we measured the hazard intensity <italic>R</italic>, with respect to the density of fire breaks <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>, defined as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e024">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e024g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e024" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M24">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(11)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e025"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e025g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e025" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M25"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is defined as the ratio of the number of fire breaks <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>fb</italic></sub>, and the total number of nodes that contain flammable vegetation <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>v</italic></sub>. The parameter <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> denotes the number of simulations for a given initial condition, while <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub> (<italic>i</italic>) denotes the total number of burned nodes of the i-th simulation. For the artificial forest model, which is characterized by random distribution of densities in a flat terrain, the proposed approach is tested against the benchmark of random distribution of fire breaks, while for the real case of Rhodes island, the effectiveness of the approach was tested against the conventional fuel reduction treatment based on the density and flammability of the vegetation. For this case, the conventional tactic was implemented as follows: within the area of interest, nodes were sorted from high vegetation densities of pine trees to high densities of other types of trees including shrubs, to moderate vegetation densities of pine trees followed by other types of trees including shrubs, to sparse vegetation densities of pine trees followed by other types of trees including shrubs; then the first <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> percent of the sorted nodes was selected to be removed. In both approaches (proposed and benchmark/conventional), the removal of two neighboring (adjacent) nodes was not allowed even if were highly ranked to avoid the formation of clusters of empty zones.</p>
<p>We simulated <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> = 3,200 randomly placed ignitions (as e.g. in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref042">42</xref>]) letting the simulator to run until the fire stops. Statistically significant differences for a given <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> (discretized at levels of 0.1) between the proposed and conventional tactic were computed by implementing the t-test on the outcomes (<italic>R</italic>-statistic defined in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0163226.e024">Eq 11</xref>) of the simulations with a threshold set at <italic>a</italic> = 0.05.</p>
<p>It should be noted that as the model is stochastic, simulations will generally result in different <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub>s (number of burned cells). For this reason, we have chosen to run the model <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> = 100 times with the same ignition point (the point where the fire actually started) and depict all simulations by mapping the burning frequency of each cell in a gray-scale mode. Hence, for each cell we calculated the frequency of burnings out of the 100 simulation runs. Then, we created the corresponding histogram of average number of burnings for the area under study using 2<sup>4</sup> bins. Finally, we assigned—in descending order—2<sup>4</sup> levels of gray (from 2<sup>8</sup> to 2<sup>4</sup> with a discretization step of 2<sup>4</sup>) to the bins. We applied the proposed approach for the risk management of a particular area (defined by the rectangular shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0163226.g004">Fig 4</xref>) using the Bonacich measure with a <italic>β</italic> = 0.5 (choosing different values of <italic>β</italic> between 0 and 1 resulted to equivalent results). The performance of the methodology was compared to the benchmark approach of conventional fuel reduction.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Simulation Results</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>The artificial forest problem</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0163226.g005">Fig 5</xref> depicts the diagram of the hazard intensity, <italic>R</italic>(<italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>) for the centrality measures described at the Methods and Material section. The results obtained with the random distribution tactic are also shown for comparison purposes. The shaded area shows the range of fire breaks densities where differences between the Bonacich and the BC-based are statistically significant from the random-based distribution. As it is clearly shown, the proposed approach based on the Bonacich criterion for various values of <italic>β</italic>s (0.2, 0.5, 0.8) and the BC outperforms significantly the random-based distribution of fire breaks. The Bonacich criterion for the above mentioned range of <italic>β</italic> values gives equivalent results with the BC measure.</p>
<fig id="pone.0163226.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>The simple case of an ensemble of artificial forests.</title>
<p>Hazard intensity <italic>R</italic>(<italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>) as obtained using the Bonacich (with <italic>β</italic> = 0.2, 0.5, 0.8), BC, Eigencentrality and the random distribution of fire breaks. The shaded area marks statistically significant differences between Bonacich and BC vs. random distributions as computed by the t-test (at <italic>a</italic> = 0.05).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>For the Bonacich and the BC-based approach there is a relatively sharp phase transition from high to low hazard intensities (<italic>R</italic>s) around <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> = 0.22 while for the random-based distribution the phase transition occurs around <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> = 0.32. On the other hand, Eigencentrality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref036">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref037">37</xref>] performs poorer even when compared to the random-based distribution, thus resulting to higher fire hazard for bigger densities of fire breaks (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0163226.g005">Fig 5</xref>). This is in line with other studies reporting that the Eigencentrality criterion may not produce meaningful results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref036">36</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec011">Appendix</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>The real case of Rhodes island, Greece</title>
<p>The resulting “expected” map of relative burning frequencies as derived using the CA simulator is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0163226.g004">Fig 4</xref>. For comparison purposes we have overlaid the outline of the actual burned area. As it is shown, the “expected” burned area predicted by simulations is close enough to the real one: if one takes the upper 85% then the actual and simulated burned areas almost coincide.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0163226.g006">Fig 6</xref> depicts the diagram of average <italic>R</italic>(<italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>) over <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> = 3,200 runs (multiple ignition points). The results obtained with the conventional treatment tactic are also shown for comparison purposes; 90% percentiles of the burned area are also illustrated with bars. The t-test (with a threshold set at <italic>a</italic> = 0.05) showed that the mean <italic>R</italic>(<italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>)s of the two approaches differ significantly for all the values of <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> &gt; 0: the proposed approach results to lower wildland hazards. In particular, for <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> ≥ 0.14 the proposed approach results to a fire hazard at least 10% lower than the conventional approach. Furthermore, for all the range of <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>s the proposed approach results to significantly lower maximum values of burned areas. For example for <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> = 0.14 the proposed approach results to ~15% lower maximum (at the level of 90% percentile) value of burned area.</p>
<fig id="pone.0163226.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title>The case of Rhodes island, Greece.</title>
<p>Hazard intensity <italic>R</italic>(<italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>) using the proposed (circles) and conventional (squares) distribution of fire breaks, as computed over <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> = 3,200 simulations starting from equally-numbered ignition points. 90% percentiles are also illustrated with dotted bars. Statistically significant differences between distributions as computed by the t-test (at <italic>a</italic> = 0.05) arose for all values of <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> &gt; 0.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>At this point it is interesting to pinpoint the differences in the distributions of fire breaks with respect to the type and density of vegetation between the proposed approach and the conventional strategy. For example for <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> = 0.14, the proposed (vs. conventional) approach allocates (a) ~15% (~7.5%) of the fire breaks in nodes with sparse, ~15% (~18%) in nodes with moderate, ~14.5% (~19%) in nodes with dense density of <italic>pine trees</italic>, and, (b) ~12% (~0%) of the fire breaks in nodes with sparse, ~12% (~14%) in nodes with moderate, and ~21% (~26%) in nodes with dense density of <italic>other types of trees including shrubs</italic>. Similar outcomes hold for all values of <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>s. The above results reveal that targeting management activities mainly on the dense vegetation is not always so effective. It may be needed to consider managing patches with sparse density of vegetation which however may act as hubs for the spread of the fire.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>It has been recognized that fire is an essential element of forest renewal, enhancing the growth of young and old trees and improving plant resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref043">43</xref>]. On the other hand, uncontrolled wildfires have been the cause of numerous irreversible environmental damages with serious negative ecological and socio-economic consequences including loss of human lives, flora and fauna bio-diversity and rare-species destruction, habitant fragmentation, floods, loss of timber harvest capability, economic loses in the tourism sector, air pollution and climate change. Hence, one of the most challenging land management revolves around the design and implementation of efficient wildland fire-prevention as it has proven to be much safer and cost-effective than reactive responses to unplanned emergency fires [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref044">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref045">45</xref>].</p>
<p>The systematic-in terms of mathematical modelling and analysis–quantification of the fire spread dynamics is of outmost importance towards the risk assessment of a potential outbreak. However, due to the inherent complexity of such a phenomenon deploying at different time and space scales, risk assessment is far from simple.</p>
<p>The computational approach proposed here is devoted to the design of the distribution of fire breaks with the aid of complex network theory and detailed CA modeling. The proposed approach is based on the concept of centrality, a key statistical measure for the evaluation of information flow through complex networks. The approach involves the construction of the adjacency matrix whose elements are the strengths (weights) of the fire propagation. The CA-based model used to calculate the transition probabilities of fire spread among the land patches can deal with spatial heterogeneity in both the fuel and landscape characteristics and can take as input local meteorological data (even in real time). It has been proven to be robust and efficient in predicting the fire spreading dynamics both in space and time in several real-world large-scale wildland fires [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref032">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref035">35</xref>].</p>
<p>The proposed approach is here illustrated through: (a) a simplistic lattice configuration which encompasses a single type of vegetation with randomly varying density and (b) a wildfire occurred in the island of Rhodes Greece in 2008. Our approach is compared with the conventional tactic of fuel reduction (e.g. selective harvesting, prescribed burning) based on density and flammability of the vegetation. It is shown, through simulations, that the proposed approach outperforms the conventional forest management practice.</p>
<p>The methodology can be combined with contemporary forestry management that makes use of either properly designed surface fires to restore longleaf pine ecosystems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref017">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref046">46</xref>] or tree cutting/harvesting that can under certain restrictions enhance forest sustainability. For our illustrations, the comparison was made in the absence of wind. However, the effect of the direction and the speed of wind can be accommodated in a straightforward way [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref032">32</xref>]. It would be also interesting as a future work to compare the efficiency of the proposed approach with other proposed strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref002">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref024">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref027">27</xref>]. For example compartmentation of the landscape, i.e. the creation of bulkheads patterns enclosing forest patches has been proposed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref022">22</xref>]. However this approach, while effective may lead to significant distortion of the underlying landscape. To address this issue a creation of random distribution of firebreaks in landscape patterns that appear somewhat natural has been suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref047">47</xref>]. In recent years, various studies have turned their attention towards the optimal distribution of fire breaks within a multi-objective decision-making framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref002">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref048">48</xref>– <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref050">50</xref>]. The effect of four basic patterns of fuel management has been studied including regularly spaced, dispersed, clustered and random that were scheduled using heuristic optimization techniques with stand density and harvest volume goals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref002">2</xref>]. The study site was the Grand River Basin in northeastern Oregon. The performance of the four resulting patterns was examined using FARSITE. The number of simulations was limited due to the computational cost. Simulations showed only minor differences between patterns with marginal reduction in the level of wildfire hazard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref002">2</xref>]. The problem has been presented as a combinatorial simulation-optimization problem for minimizing the fire-risk subject to a limit on the total area of fuel breaks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref048">48</xref>]. The model was tested on a forest of 220,000 ha in north-western Ontario. Optimized results were compared with the random as well as the conventional approach that selects the highest ranking cells for fuel-treatment until the limit of the total area of fire breaks is reached. It has been shown that while the method outperforms significantly the random approach, it performs comparably with respect to the conventional approach having a fire-risk approximately 5% lower than the latter. Simulated annealing has also been implemented to schedule fuel treatment across time and space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref049">49</xref>]. This approach was applied to a 14,000-ha study landscape located on the west side of the Bitterroot Valley in Montana. The authors showed that optimized solutions outperform the randomly placed ones. An important obstacle that all the above studies indicate is the computational intensity of the stochastic optimization approach requiring a large numbers of iterations, while the “best” global optimal solution is not guaranteed.</p>
<p>Compared to the above approaches our methodology addresses a systematic, straightforward way for the spatial allocation of fire breaks and importantly for the identification of nodes that may act as hubs of the fire spread. The importance of the management of such sparse-density patches has not been highlighted yet in the literature.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Based on complex network theory, we proposed a systematic methodology for assigning the spatial locations of fire breaks to inhibit wildfire hazard in heterogeneous forest landscapes. The partition of the barriers is achieved using a two-level algorithm which involves: (a) the construction of a weighted lattice graph, where the weights correspond to transmission probabilities of fire propagation, (b) the identification of cells (network nodes) that contribute more to the fire spread through the network; these correspond to nodes with high centralities. The edge weights are computed using the relations of fire propagation probabilities through a detailed Cellular Automata fire propagation model which takes into account detailed terrain, meteorological data as well as vegetation characteristics such as type, density, flammability and moisture content. The efficiency of the approach was compared against the typical practice of fuel reduction (selection harvesting) based on density and vegetation flammability. The site of study was Rhodes island, Greece which suffered from a large wildland fire back in 2008; 3,200 simulations starting from equally numbered randomly placed ignitions were considered. Simulations results showed that the proposed approach results in statistically significant lower hazards. An important outcome of the analysis is that the effective management of patches of sparse density of vegetation that act as hubs of fire spread is the key in reducing the hazard. To this end, we should point out that such an approach (as other similar approaches) should not be considered as a “one-size-fits-all” one and/or as a stand-alone strategy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref004">4</xref>]. The appropriateness and the specifics of fuel treatment for wildland prevention remains a subject of debate among scientific community [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref051">51</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref053">53</xref>]. Questions related with the way treatments (such as reduction of tree density, thinning and prescribed burning) should be carried out need to be answered. Furthermore, important issues and restrictions related to the effects of fuel reduction management on the forestry ecosystem (e.g. such as its influence to biodiversity) have to be taken into account [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref026">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref054">54</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref058">58</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Centrality measures</title>
<p>Several measures have been proposed for the assessment of the information centrality in networks such the Betweenness centrality (BC), the closeness centrality (CC), the Bonacich centrality (BC) and the Eigen-centrality (EC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref036">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref038">38</xref>].</p>
<p>The BC of node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> is defined as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e026">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e026g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e026" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M26">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(12)</label>
</disp-formula>
<inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e027"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e027g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e027" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M27"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the number of shortest paths between nodes <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> and <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> passing from <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, and <inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e028"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e028g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e028" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M28"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the number of the shortest paths (as derived by the sum of the edge weights) between <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> and <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub>. Here, the weights of the network links should be inversed so that long walks count to slow spread directions, while, short walks count for fast spread directions.</p>
<p>The CC of node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> is defined as the inverse of the sum of geodesic distances (i.e. the shortest paths) from node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> to all other nodes in the network:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e029">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e029g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e029" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M29">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(13)</label>
</disp-formula>
<inline-formula id="pone.0163226.e030"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0163226.e030g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e030" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M30"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the geodesic distance from <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub>.</p>
<p>The Eigencentrality of node <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> corresponds to the <italic>k-th</italic> component of the eigenvector related to the largest eigenvalue of the adjacency matrix <italic>A</italic>. A node with a high Eigencentrality is adjacent to nodes possessing also high scores of eigencentrality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref040">40</xref>]. For very large scale directed weighted networks where <italic>A</italic> is asymmetric one can employ Arnoldi’s iterative method for extracting a low dimensional upper Hessenberg matrix whose eigenvalues of provide approximations of the outermost spectrum of the full matrix [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref059">59</xref>]. However for directed graphs, Eigencentrality may not produce meaningful results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref036">36</xref>]. An extension of Eigencentrality to directed weighted graphs comes from the Bonacich measure defined as the <italic>k-th</italic> component of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref036">36</xref>]:
<disp-formula id="pone.0163226.e031">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0163226.e031g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0163226.e031" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M31">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">I</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>Α</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(14)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <bold><italic>e</italic></bold> is a vector of ones and <italic>λ</italic><sub><bold><italic>max</italic></bold></sub> is the largest eigenvalue of <italic>A</italic> (that can be computed through the Arnoldi eigensolver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref059">59</xref>]). The notion of Bonacich centrality is that the power of a node depends on the power of the adjacent nodes. The parameter <italic>β</italic> can be regarded as an attenuation factor. Positive values of <italic>β</italic> give more weight to powerful connections while negative values to less powerful connections. Small values of <italic>β</italic> give more weight to the local network structure while larger values give more weight to the wider network structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0163226.ref041">41</xref>]. For <italic>β</italic> = 0, the above expression reduces to the degree centrality, while for <italic>β</italic> = 1 it reduces to the standard Eigencentrality.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank Marco Imparato (Combustion Research Institute, Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche) for his technical support.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albini</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mathematical modelling and predicting wildland fire effects</article-title>. <source>Combustion, Explosion and Shock waves</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>520</fpage>–<lpage>533</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF01998574" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/BF01998574</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bettinger</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spatial optimization of the pattern of fuel management activities and subsequent effects on simulated wildfires</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Operational Research</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>197</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ejor.2008.05.025" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ejor.2008.05.025</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The challenge of quantitative risk analysis for wildland fire</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>211</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2005.02.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2005.02.010</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agee</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bahro</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Omi</surname> <given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sapsis</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skinner</surname> <given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The use of shaded fuelbreaks in landscape fire management</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-1127(99)00116-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0378-1127(99)00116-4</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McHugh</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grenfell</surname> <given-names>IC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stand and landscape-level effects of prescribed burning in two Arizona wildfires</article-title>. <source>Can. J. For. Res</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1714</fpage>–<lpage>1722</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1139/x05-090" xlink:type="simple">10.1139/x05-090</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ascoli</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rigolot</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Prescribed burning in southern Europe: developing fire management in a dynamic landscape</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>e4</fpage>–<lpage>e14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1890/120298" xlink:type="simple">10.1890/120298</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">van Wagtendonk JW. Large fires in wilderness areas. In Brown JK, Mutch RW, Spoon CW, Wakimoto RH. Fire in Wilderness and Park Management, General Technical Report INT-GTR-320, USDA Forest Service Ogden, UT; 1995. pp. 113–116.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergeron</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flannigan</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Predicting the effects of climate change on fire frequency in the southeastern Canadian boreal forest</article-title>. <source>Water, Air, Soil Pollution</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF01182853" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/BF01182853</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vadrevu</surname> <given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eaturu</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Badarinath</surname> <given-names>KVS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fire risk evaluation using multicriteria analysis-a case study</article-title>. <source>Environmental Monitoring and Assessment</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10661-009-0997-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10661-009-0997-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19472063</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carmel</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jahshan</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shoshany</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Post-fire analysis of pre0fire mapping of fire-risk: a recent case study from Mt. Carmel (Israel)</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1184</fpage>–<lpage>1188</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2011.06.011" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2011.06.011</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identifying the Threshold of Dominant Controls on Fire Spread in a Boreal Forest Landscape of Northeast China</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>e55618</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0055618" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0055618</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23383247</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Penman</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Syphard</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keeley</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradstock</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Influence of fuels, weather and the built environment on the exposure of property to wildfire</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <year>2014</year>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>e111414</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0111414" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0111414</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25360741</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orzell</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slocum</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Seasonality of fire weather strongly influences fire regimes in south florida Savanna-Grassland landscapes</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>e0116952</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0116952" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0116952</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25574667</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vakalis</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siettos</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Detecting weak points of wildland fire spread: A Cellular automata model risk assessment simulation approach</article-title>. <source>Chemical Engineering Transactions</source> <year>2014</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3303/CET1436043" xlink:type="simple">10.3303/CET1436043</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agee</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skinner</surname> <given-names>CN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Basic principles of forest fuel reduction treatments</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>211</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2005.01.034" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2005.01.034</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">De Gomez T. Guidlines for thinning ponderosa pine for improved forest health and fire prevention, The University of Arizona, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Publication AZ1397, 2006. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://extension.arizona.edu/sites/extension.arizona.edu/files/pubs/az1397.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://extension.arizona.edu/sites/extension.arizona.edu/files/pubs/az1397.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botelho</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name>. <article-title>A review of prescribed burning effectiveness in fire hazard reduction</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Wildland Fire</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/WF02042" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/WF02042</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Stecker T. U.S. starts massive forest-thinning project, Scientific American, March 22, 2013. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/us-starts-massive-forest-thinning-project/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/us-starts-massive-forest-thinning-project/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">US Forest Service, Pacific Northwest Research Station. Fuel Treatments: Thinning and Prescribed Burns. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fs.fed.us/pnw/research/fire/fuel-treatments.shtml" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fs.fed.us/pnw/research/fire/fuel-treatments.shtml</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Churchillb</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Tree spatial patterns in fire-frequent forests of western North America, including mechanisms of pattern formation and implications for designing fuel reduction and restoration treatments</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>267</volume>: <fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2011.11.038" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2011.11.038</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <article-title>Calculation of fire spread rates across random landscapes</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Wildland Fire</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/WF03010" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/WF03010</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loehle</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Applying landscape principles to fire hazard reduction</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>198</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2004.04.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2004.04.010</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Design of regular landscape fuel treatment patterns for modifying fire growth and behavior</article-title>. <source>Forest Science</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>47</volume>; <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chew</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stalling</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slack</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Combining simulation and optimization for evaluating the effectiveness of fuel treatments for four different fuel conditions at landscape scales</article-title>. <source>Managing Forest Ecosystems</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-94-017-0307-9_4" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/978-94-017-0307-9_4</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loureiro</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botelho</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mateus</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>A simulation test of a landscape fuel management project in the Marao range of northern Portugal</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>234S</volume>, <fpage>S245</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2006.08.274" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2006.08.274</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ager</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaillant</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>A comparison of landscape fuel treatment strategies to mitigate wildland fire risk in the urban interface and preserve old forest structure</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>259</volume>: <fpage>1556</fpage>–<lpage>1570</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2010.01.032" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2010.01.032</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smidt</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skinner</surname> <given-names>CN</given-names></name>. <article-title>The influence of fuels treatment and landscape arrangement on simulated fire behavior, southern cascade range, California</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>255</volume>: <fpage>3170</fpage>–<lpage>3184</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2008.01.023" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2008.01.023</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Finney MA. FARSITE: Fire Area Simulator–Model development and evaluation. Research Paper RMRS-RP-4, Ft. USDA Forest Service, Collins, CO, 1998.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chew JD. Development of a system for simulating native patterns and processes at landscape scales. Ph.D. dessertation, Missoula: University of Montana 182 p. 1995.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fire growth using minimum travel time methods</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Forest Res</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1420</fpage>–<lpage>1424</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1139/X02-068" xlink:type="simple">10.1139/X02-068</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bahro B, Barber KH, Sherlock JW, Yasuda DA. Stewardship and fireshed assessment: a process for designing a landscape fuel treatment strategy. In: Powers, RF (Ed.), Restoring fire-adapted ecosystems: Proceedings of the 2005 National Silviculture Workshop. USDA Forest Service Pacific Southwest Research Station, General Technical Report PSW-GTR-203; 2007. pp. 41–54.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandridis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vakalis</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siettos</surname> <given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bafas</surname> <given-names>GV</given-names></name>. <article-title>A cellular automata model for forest fire spread prediction: the case of the wildfire that swept through Spetses island in 1990</article-title>. <source>Applied Mathematics and Computation</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>204</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.amc.2008.06.046" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.amc.2008.06.046</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandridis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vakalis</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bafas</surname> <given-names>GV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siettos</surname> <given-names>CI</given-names></name>. <article-title>Wildland fire spread modelling using cellular automata: evolution in large-scale spatially heterogeneous environments under fire suppression tactics</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Wildland Fire</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/WF09119" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/WF09119</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandridis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vakalis</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siettos</surname> <given-names>CI</given-names></name>. <article-title>Simulation of wildland fires in large-scale heterogeneous environments</article-title>. <source>Chemical Engineering Transactions</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>438</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3303/CET1124073" xlink:type="simple">10.3303/CET1124073</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vakalis</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siettos</surname> <given-names>CI</given-names></name>. <article-title>Simulating the wildfire in Rhodes in 2008 with a cellular automata model</article-title>. <source>Chemical Engineering Transactions</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1399</fpage>–<lpage>1405</lpage>. Doi: 0.3303/CET1335233.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonacich</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Eigenvector-like measures of centrality for asymmetric relations</article-title>. <source>Social Networks</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-8733(01)00038-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0378-8733(01)00038-7</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname> <given-names>MEJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The structure and function of networks</article-title>. <source>Siam Rev</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1137/S003614450342480" xlink:type="simple">10.1137/S003614450342480</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evaggelidis</surname> <given-names>IN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siettos</surname> <given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Complex network theory criterion to distribute fuel breaks for the hazard control of fire spread in forests</article-title>. <source>AIP Conf. Proc</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>1648</volume>, <fpage>100005</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.4912407" xlink:type="simple">10.1063/1.4912407</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname> <given-names>LC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Centrality in networks: I. Conceptual clarification</article-title>. <source>Social Networks</source> <year>1979</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgatti</surname> <given-names>S P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Centrality and network flow</article-title>. <source>Social Networks</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2004.11.008" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.socnet.2004.11.008</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prell</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Social network analysis</chapter-title>, <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Menning</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dillingham</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saah</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stine</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modeling hazardous fire potential within a completed fuel treatment network in the northern Sierra Nevada</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>310</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2013.08.015" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2013.08.015</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Fire and Vegetation Dynamics: Studies from the North American Boreal Forest</chapter-title>, <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, <year>1992</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaillant</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gebert</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stockmann</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantifying the potential impacts of fuel treatments on wildfire suppression costs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Forestry</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>111</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5849/jof.12-027" xlink:type="simple">10.5849/jof.12-027</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">The Nature Conservancy. Hazardous Fuels Program in FY2014 Budget: Proactive, Safer, Cheaper Fires vs. Reactive, Dangerous, Costly Fires, April 26, 2013. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.org/ourinitiatives/habitats/forests/newsroom/hazardous-fuels-program-in-fy2014-budget.xml" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nature.org/ourinitiatives/habitats/forests/newsroom/hazardous-fuels-program-in-fy2014-budget.xml</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brockway</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Long-term effects of dormant-season prescribed fire on plant community diversity, structure and productivity in a longleaf pine wiregrass ecosystem</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-1127(96)03939-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0378-1127(96)03939-4</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bevers</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Omi</surname> <given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hof</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Random location of fuel treatments in wildland community interfaces: a percolation approach</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Forest Res</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1139/X03-204" xlink:type="simple">10.1139/X03-204</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rytwinski</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crowe</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>. <article-title>A simulation-optimization model for selecting the location of fuel-breaks to minimize expected losses from forest fires</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>260</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2010.03.013" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2010.03.013</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bramel</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Contreras</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Optimising fuel treatments over time and space</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Wildland Fire</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1118</fpage>–<lpage>1133</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/WF12138" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/WF12138</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Optimizing fuel treatments to reduce wildland fire risk</article-title>. <source>Current Forestry Reports</source> <year>2015</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s40725-015-0005-9" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s40725-015-0005-9</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Carey H, Schumann M. Modifying wildfire behavior—the effectiveness of fuel treatments. Santa Fe, NM: National Community Forestry Center Southwest Region 2003, Working Paper #2.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoennagel</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veblen</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romme</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name>. <article-title>The interaction of fire, fuels, and climate across Rocky Mountain forests</article-title>. <source>BioScience</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>54</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>676</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1641/0006-3568(2004)054[0661:TIOFFA]2.0.CO;2" xlink:type="simple">10.1641/0006-3568(2004)054[0661:TIOFFA]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Martinson EJ, Omi PN. Fuel treatments and fire severity: a meta-analysis. Res. Pap. RMRS-RP-103WWW. Fort Collins, CO: U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station 2013, 38 p.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname> <given-names>RTT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Creating landscape patterns by forest cutting: Ecological consequences and principles</article-title>. <source>Landscape Ecology</source> <year>1987</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF02275261" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/BF02275261</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abella</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Springerb</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of tree cutting and fire on understory vegetation in mixed conifer forests</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecology and Management</source> <year>2015</year>; <volume>335</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2014.09.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.foreco.2014.09.009</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oeding</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>A meta-analysis on the impacts of partial cutting on forest structure and carbon storage</article-title>. <source>Biogeosciences</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>3691</fpage>–<lpage>3703</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5194/bg-10-3691-2013" xlink:type="simple">10.5194/bg-10-3691-2013</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burivalova</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Şekercioğlu</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Thresholds of logging intensity to maintain tropical forest biodiversity</article-title>. <source>Current Biology</source> <year>2014</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1893</fpage>–<lpage>1898</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2014.06.065" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2014.06.065</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25088557</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Temple</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gutierrez</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Battles</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fry</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reetz</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whitmore</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berigan</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peery</surname> <given-names>MZ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluating short- and long-term impacts of fuels treatments and simulated wildfire on an old-forest species</article-title>. <source>Ecosphere</source> <year>2015</year>; <volume>6</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), Article 261. Doi: 0.1890/ES15-00234.1.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0163226.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saad</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Numerical methods for large eigenvalue problems</chapter-title>, <publisher-name>Manchester University Press: Oxford-Manchester</publisher-name>, <year>1992</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>