<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-12503</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104185</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Brain mapping</subject><subj-group><subject>Functional magnetic resonance imaging</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Developmental neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurodevelopmental disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>ADHD</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Behavioral neuroscience</subject><subject>Neuroimaging</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychological stress</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social sciences</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Impact of Early Life Adversity on Reward Processing in Young Adults: EEG-fMRI Results from a Prospective Study over 25 Years</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Early Life Adversity Affects Reward Processing</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boecker</surname><given-names>Regina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holz</surname><given-names>Nathalie E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>Arlette F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blomeyer</surname><given-names>Dorothea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plichta</surname><given-names>Michael M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>Isabella</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer-Lindenberg</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banaschewski</surname><given-names>Tobias</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandeis</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laucht</surname><given-names>Manfred</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, CIMH Medical Faculty Mannheim/Heidelberg University, Mannheim, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, CIMH Medical Faculty Mannheim/Heidelberg University, Mannheim, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Neuroimaging, CIMH Medical Faculty Mannheim/Heidelberg University, Mannheim, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University of Zurich, Zurich, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Center for Integrative Human Physiology, University of Zurich, Zurich, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Neuroscience Center Zurich, University of Zurich and ETH Zurich, Zurich, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><addr-line>Department of Psychology, University of Potsdam, Potsdam, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antal</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University Medical Center Goettingen, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">manfred.laucht@zi-mannheim.de</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Dr. Banaschewski served in an advisory or consultancy role for Hexal Pharma, Lilly, Medice, Novartis, Otsuka, Oxford outcomes, PCM scientific, Shire, and Viforpharma. He received conference attendance support and conference support or received speaker's fee by Lilly, Medice, Novartis, and Shire. He is/has been involved in clinical trials conducted by Lilly, Shire, and Viforpharma. The present work is unrelated to the above grants and relationships. Dr. Meyer-Lindenberg received consultant fees and travel expenses from AstraZeneca, Hoffmann-La Roche, Lundbeck Foundation, speaker's fees from Pfizer Pharma, Lilly Deutschland, Glaxo SmithKline, Janssen Cilag, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Lundbeck, and AstraZeneca. All other authors report no financial relationships with commercial interests. This does not alter the authors' adherence to PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: ML D. Brandeis TB AML. Performed the experiments: RB NEH SB. Analyzed the data: RB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AFB D. Blomeyer MMP IW. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: RB ML D. Brandeis.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e104185</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Boecker et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Several lines of evidence have implicated the mesolimbic dopamine reward pathway in altered brain function resulting from exposure to early adversity. The present study examined the impact of early life adversity on different stages of neuronal reward processing later in life and their association with a related behavioral phenotype, i.e. attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). 162 healthy young adults (mean age = 24.4 years; 58% female) from an epidemiological cohort study followed since birth participated in a simultaneous EEG-fMRI study using a monetary incentive delay task. Early life adversity according to an early family adversity index (EFA) and lifetime ADHD symptoms were assessed using standardized parent interviews conducted at the offspring's age of 3 months and between 2 and 15 years, respectively. fMRI region-of-interest analysis revealed a significant effect of EFA during reward anticipation in reward-related areas (i.e. ventral striatum, putamen, thalamus), indicating decreased activation when EFA increased. EEG analysis demonstrated a similar effect for the contingent negative variation (CNV), with the CNV decreasing with the level of EFA. In contrast, during reward delivery, activation of the bilateral insula, right pallidum and bilateral putamen increased with EFA. There was a significant association of lifetime ADHD symptoms with lower activation in the left ventral striatum during reward anticipation and higher activation in the right insula during reward delivery. The present findings indicate a differential long-term impact of early life adversity on reward processing, implicating hyporesponsiveness during reward anticipation and hyperresponsiveness when receiving a reward. Moreover, a similar activation pattern related to lifetime ADHD suggests that the impact of early life stress on ADHD may possibly be mediated by a dysfunctional reward pathway.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from the German Research Foundation (DFG LA 733/1–2) to ML, DB, TB, and AML. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that, for approved reasons, some access restrictions apply to the data underlying the findings. Data are available on request from the ethics committee of the University of Heidelberg for researchers who meet the criteria for access to confidential data.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Accumulating evidence suggests that adversity in early childhood may impair human brain development and mental health later in life <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Lupien1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-McLaughlin1">[3]</xref>. Moreover, clinical studies have highlighted striking effects of early life adversity on the development and persistence of mental disorders such as attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Pheula1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Pressman1">[7]</xref>. Among the mechanisms mediating the detrimental impact of early adversity on psychopathology and brain development, alterations of the mesolimbic reward pathway have been suggested to play a major role <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Stark1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Dillon1">[10]</xref>. Several functionally related brain regions have been implicated in the processing of rewards by a large body of functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) findings and have been related to different stages of reward processing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Diekhof1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Haber1">[12]</xref>. These findings emphasize a functional dissection of reward processing. While anticipation or “wanting” of a reward addresses the motivational aspect to receive a reward, reward delivery or “liking” has been interpreted as the hedonic impact of a reward producing the feeling of pleasure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Berridge1">[13]</xref>.</p>
<p>Common regions that are preferentially activated during the anticipation of rewards encompass the ventral striatum (VS), including the nucleus accumbens, ventral caudate nucleus and ventral putamen. Another region suggested to be involved in the delivery of rewards covers the medial orbitofrontal cortex, adjacent parts of the ventromedial prefrontal cortex, medial and dorsal caudate as well as putamen. With regard to ADHD, most studies have demonstrated a reduced activation of the VS during reward anticipation in patients compared to healthy controls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Stark1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Scheres1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Furukawa1">[16]</xref>, while for the delivery phase, an increased activation of the caudate nucleus was observed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Strohle1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Paloyelis1">[17]</xref>. These effects are in line with the dopamine transfer deficit model, which postulates a diminished dopaminergic response shift from the actual reward to the anticipatory stimulus, but a remaining strong response during reward delivery <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Tripp1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Tripp2">[19]</xref>.</p>
<p>In contrast to neuroimaging research, fewer studies have examined electrophysiological correlates of anticipatory reward processing. One anticipatory event-related potential (ERP) which has been investigated more systematically measuring an electroencephalogram (EEG) is the contingent negative variation (CNV) type activity, a slow negative potential shift before target or feedback stimuli, with a maximum over central sites, elicited by preparation and anticipation paradigms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Walter1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Irwin1">[21]</xref>. If feedback immediately follows the response, the CNV reflects reward anticipation along with motor and cognitive preparation or time estimation. If feedback is delayed, reward anticipation is also postponed and is mainly reflected by the feedback or stimulus-preceding negativity (SPN) following the CNV and the motor response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Brunia1">[22]</xref>. So far, some findings have indicated higher CNV-like activity during reward anticipation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Capa1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Pierson1">[25]</xref>, although other studies did not find an effect of reward anticipation on the target-preceding CNV in tests in which feedback was postponed or predictable <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Broyd1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Goldstein1">[27]</xref>. In turn, several studies have shown a reduced CNV for children with ADHD or adults with a childhood diagnosis of ADHD, acting on a cued continuous performance test (CPT), investigating developmental effects of impaired cognitive brain functions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Banaschewski1">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-vanLeeuwen1">[31]</xref>.</p>
<p>Increasing evidence has implicated the neural circuitry of reward in altered brain function resulting from exposure to early life adversity. At the behavioral level, impaired responding to rewarding stimuli in maltreated individuals was reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Guyer1">[32]</xref>. These individuals exhibited faster reactions for risky options in a decision-making task than controls, but lacked the typical increase in response speed with the chance of winning. Further evidence for a reduced sensitivity to reward was provided in an fMRI study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Dillon1">[10]</xref>. Young adults maltreated during childhood showed a blunted basal ganglia response (left putamen, left globus pallidus) and less positive ratings of reward cues during reward anticipation. Another study underscored these results by demonstrating a decreased activation in the VS to reward-predicting cues in Romanian adoptees who had experienced global early deprivation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Mehta1">[33]</xref>. In these studies, no effect of early adversity on reward delivery was observed, suggesting that adversity might specifically affect responses to reward-predicting cues. However, a recent study by Kumar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Kumar1">[34]</xref> investigating the impact of acute stress found differential effects on phases of reward processing, with increased neuronal activation in the caudate and the amygdala during reward anticipation and decreased activation in the caudate and the putamen while receiving a reward. Hence, acute and early chronic stress seem to impact on the anticipatory and delivery stage of reward processing in specific ways, most likely mediated by alterations of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-UlrichLai1">[35]</xref>.</p>
<p>In the present study, the impact of early adversity on reward processing was examined in a large sample of young adults from an epidemiological cohort study followed since birth. Using a monetary incentive delay (MID) task offering either money or verbal feedback, simultaneous EEG-fMRI was recorded in order to detect alterations at different stages of reward processing. Given the fact that the verbal feedback (control condition) of the MID represents a special reward characteristic, such as if receiving a social reward <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Rademacher1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Delmonte1">[37]</xref>, modality-specific differences in rewarding quality will be examined. The use of EEG and fMRI provides both high spatial and temporal resolution of neuronal alterations during reward processing. Especially, the EEG enables a cue related analysis of time-resolved neurophysiological signatures within the anticipation phase as recently demonstrated by Plichta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta2">[38]</xref>. First, we hypothesized that activation of reward-related areas induced by the anticipation of a monetary reward, especially the VS, would decrease with the level of early adversity. Second, we expected the same effect for the EEG, i.e. that the CNV, reflecting the motivational signature of reward anticipation, would decrease with increasing adversity. Third, in line with previous research, no adversity-specific alterations of the neuronal response to monetary reward outcome were predicted <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Dillon1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Mehta1">[33]</xref>. Fourth, we hypothesized that reward-related neuronal activation was related to lifetime ADHD symptoms, showing decreasing neuronal activity during reward anticipation and increasing activation during reward delivery with the level of ADHD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Strohle1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Paloyelis1">[17]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p>The current assessment was approved by the ethics committee of the University of Heidelberg. After complete description of the study to the participants, written informed consent was obtained. For assessments during childhood (age three months to 15 years) written informed consent was obtained from parents on behalf of the children.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Sample</title>
<p>This investigation was conducted in the framework of an epidemiological cohort study examining the long-term outcome of early risk factors from birth into adulthood. Detailed information about this study has been published elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Laucht2">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Laucht3">[40]</xref>. The initial sample consisted of 384 infants born between 1986 and 1988 of predominantly (&gt;99%) European descent, who were consecutively recruited from two obstetric and six children's hospitals of the Rhine-Neckar Region of Germany. Only firstborn children with singleton births and German-speaking parents were enrolled in the study. Assessments were first conducted at the age of three months and subsequently at regular intervals throughout development, most recently in young adulthood. From the initial sample, 18 (4.7%) were excluded due to severe handicaps and 57 (14.8%) were dropouts, leaving a final sample of 309 for the current assessment. From these, 122 individuals had to be excluded due to usual contraindications for MRI and EEG, current psychopathology or psychotropic medication. This sample of N = 187 individuals participated in a simultaneous EEG-fMRI measurement. Another twenty-five participants were discarded due to movement artifacts (&gt;3 mm) or insufficient EEG quality, leaving a final sample of N = 162 participants (mean age = 24.4 years; 58% female).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Psychological assessment</title>
<p>Early adversity was assessed using a standardized parent interview according to an ‘enriched’ family adversity index as proposed by Rutter and Quinton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Rutter1">[41]</xref>. The interview comprised 11 items covering characteristics of the family environment (e.g., Overcrowding: More than 1.0 person per room or size of housing ≤50 m<sup>2</sup>), the parents (e.g., Parental psychiatric disorder: Moderate to severe disorder according to DSM-III-R criteria) and their partnership (e.g., Unwanted pregnancy: An abortion was seriously considered) during a period of one year prior to the assessment (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0104185.s004">Table S1</xref>). A total early family adversity (EFA) score was formed by counting the number of items present at the 3-month assessment [mean = 1.71±1.87; range: 0–7; Cronbach's alpha = .72]. The EFA index is a prospective and comprehensive measure of family adversity and does not exclusively focus on emotional and sexual abuse or neglect. Empirical evidence has largely confirmed the cumulative risk hypothesis that the likelihood of unfavorable child outcomes increases with the number of adversity factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Evans1">[42]</xref>. Furthermore, a series of studies conducted in the context of the Mannheim Study of Children at Risk have provided evidence of the current validity of the family adversity measure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Laucht2">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Laucht4">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Laucht5">[44]</xref>. The Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV (SCID-I German version) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Wittchen1">[45]</xref> was administered to measure young adults' psychiatric disorders. To examine current drug use, participants completed a substance use inventory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Mller1">[46]</xref>. Lifetime ADHD symptoms were assessed with the Mannheim Parent Interview (MEI) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Esser1">[47]</xref> at age 2, 4, 8 and 11 years and with the Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia for School- Aged Children (K-SADS-PL) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Kaufman1">[48]</xref>, German version <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Delmo1">[49]</xref> at age 15 years and sum scores were formed, indexing the severity and persistence of ADHD. The MEI is a highly structured interview adapted from Rutter's parent interviews to include all symptoms related to major DSM-IV diagnoses, and has been shown to be a sensitive measure of child disturbance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Laucht3">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Laucht6">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Holz1">[51]</xref>. With regard to ADHD, agreement with an independent child psychiatric examination was seen in 100% of cases. The K-SADS is a widely used structured diagnostic interview completed independently by parents and adolescents with established reliability and validity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Kaufman2">[52]</xref>. Information from different sources was combined by the logical operator OR.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Experimental paradigm</title>
<p>The fMRI paradigm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0104185-g001">Figure 1</xref>) was a modified version of the MID task <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Kirsch1">[53]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Knutson1">[54]</xref>, probing reward anticipation and delivery which was adapted to simultaneous EEG-fMRI measurements. Previous results using this paradigm have shown reliable and robust activation of the VS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta3">[55]</xref>. The task requires a fast button press directly after a flash target following a reward anticipation cue to win a potential reward. Targets followed cues which consistently signaled different types of reward anticipation (unlike in reversal-learning paradigm): either a happy smiley signaling that responding fast enough would yield a monetary feedback (0.50 Euro), or a scrambled smiley indicating only verbal feedback (“Fast reaction!”; usually treated as the control condition). Smileys were used to further minimize learning effects. After every trial, the participants were informed about the current account balance. Boost trials with a monetary reward of 2 Euro instead of 0.50 Euro were given approximately every eighth win trial in order to improve the participants' motivational level. In total, 50 monetary and 50 verbal trials were presented in a pseudo-randomized order. The cue duration (and consequently trial length) was jittered (3-5sec) to cover the whole hemodynamic response function (HRF). The reaction time window (common for both reward conditions) was adaptively tailored to account for inter-individual differences and to yield comparable winnings across participants.</p>
<fig id="pone-0104185-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>MID paradigm.</title>
<p>The task requires a fast button press after a flash, indicated by either a laughing or a scrambled smiley, to receive either monetary or verbal feedback.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Data acquisition</title>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item>
<p><bold>1. EEG.</bold> The EEG was recorded inside the scanner using an MRI-compatible EEG system with 5 kHz sampling rate, 32 mV input range and 0.1–250 Hz band-pass filters. The signal was measured by equidistantly spaced silver/silver chloride (Ag/AgCl) scalp electrodes using EEG caps with twisted and fixed electrode cables (Easycap, Munich, Germany). The 60-channel EEG montage included most 10–10 system positions (for further information see Plichta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta3">[55]</xref>). F1 served as recording reference, and F2 as the ground electrode. Four additional electrodes were placed to record the electrooculogram (EOG) and the electrocardiogram (ECG). Via optic fibers, the signal was transmitted from two MRI-compatible amplifiers (Brain Products, Gilching, Germany) outside the scanner room. Electrode impedances were kept below 20 kΩ, except for ECG and EOG electrodes (&lt;30 kΩ) as well as reference and ground (&lt;10 kΩ). The EEG was monitored while scanning using online correction software (RecView Brain Products, Gilching, Germany).</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>2. fMRI.</bold> The fMRI data was recorded on a 3 Tesla whole-body scanner (Magnetom Trio, Siemens Erlangen, Germany). fMRI data were measured using a T2*-weighted EPI sequence with the following parameters: 400 volumes, 36 slices in ascending order and oriented 20° steeper than AC-PC-plane, 3mm slice thickness, TR/TE = 2210/28 ms, FOV = 220×220 mm, 64×64 matrix, Flip angle = 90°. A T1-weighted anatomical 3D sequence (MPRAGE) was acquired for each subject. The paradigm was created with Presentation software (Neurobehavioural Systems Inc., Albany, USA) and presented via video goggles (Resonance Technology Inc., Northridge, USA). Performance of participants was recorded using response pads (Current Designs, Philadelphia, USA &amp; Presentation software).</p>
</list-item></list>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item>
<p><bold>1. Behavior.</bold> Reaction times (RT) were averaged across trials per condition (monetary, verbal) and the amount of win trials per condition was summed up. Condition differences were examined by means of paired t-tests, effects of EFA with linear regression analysis. The interaction between EFA and condition with regard to behavioral measures was obtained using repeated measures ANOVAs in SPSS Software package (Version 20, IBM Corp., Armonk, USA).</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>2. EEG.</bold> EEG data were corrected for MRI gradient <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Allen1">[56]</xref> and cardioballistic artifacts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Allen2">[57]</xref> using standard template subtraction procedures as implemented in the Brain Vision Analyzer software 2.0 (Brain Products, Gilching, Germany). EEG data were digitally low-pass filtered (70 Hz) and down-sampled to 500 Hz. After exclusion of physical artifacts via raw data inspection, infomax independent component analysis (ICA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Bates1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Makeig1">[58]</xref> was used to remove ocular (blinks, movements) and residual cardioballistic artifacts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Debener1">[59]</xref> related to gradient modulation. EEG data were re-referenced to the average reference, baseline-corrected to a 500 ms pre-stimulus interval and low-pass filtered with a cut-off of 30 Hz. Segmentation into ERP epochs of 3.5 seconds began 500 ms prior to cue onset. ERP averages for both conditions (monetary and verbal feedback) were calculated for each participant. The CNV at electrode Cz, commonly showing the highest amplitude and therefore the best signal-to-noise <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Albrecht1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta2">[38]</xref>, was measured as the mean amplitude for the 2–3-second time window following cue onset.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>3. fMRI.</bold> The fMRI data was analyzed using statistical parametric mapping (SPM8; Wellcome Trust Centre for Neuroimaging, London, UK). Preprocessing included slice-time correction, realignment (motion correction), spatial normalization into Montreal Neurological Institute space, resampling to 2×2×2 mm and spatial smoothing with an 8-mm full-width at half maximum (FWHM) Gaussian kernel. Spatial normalization was performed by coregistering the realigned mean image to the anatomical image, normalizing the anatomical image to the T1 template and applying these transformation parameters to the time series.</p>
</list-item></list>
<p>Individual first-level analysis was performed by linear regression analysis. A general linear model with eight regressors of interest (laughing and scrambled smiley, flash, response, monetary and verbal, win and no-win trials, respectively) was designed and convolved with the SPM hemodynamic response function (HRF). Six motion parameters were included in the design matrix and modeled as regressors of no interest. A high-pass filter with a cut-off frequency of 1/128 Hz was used to attenuate low-frequency components. All analyses were corrected for serially correlated errors by fitting a first-order autoregressive process (AR<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Lupien1">[1]</xref>) to the error term.</p>
<p>First-level contrasts were implemented in the second-level group analysis (monetary&gt;verbal cue; win&gt;no-win; monetary win&gt;monetary no-win; verbal win&gt;verbal no-win) with EFA embedded as a covariate of interest and controlling for gender. In a subsequent analysis, results were controlled for subclinical psychopathology as measured using the Young Adult Self-Report (YASR) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Achenbach1">[60]</xref> at the current assessment. A statistical threshold of p&lt;.001 (uncorrected) was applied in a whole-brain analysis and, a region of interest (ROI) analysis was performed. ROIs were anatomically labeled with WFU PickAtlas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Maldjian1">[61]</xref>, determining putamen, pallidum, ACC, thalamus, insula, hippocampus and substantia nigra as ROIs of interest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Diekhof1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Haber1">[12]</xref>. Results were thresholded at p&lt;.05; family-wise error (FWE) corrected. The VS mask was defined according to Plichta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta2">[38]</xref> as a fusion of the “caudate head” mask taken from the WFU-PickAtlas (human-atlas TD Brodmann areas+) and the “accumbens” mask from the Harvard–Oxford Subcortical Structural Atlas (implemented in FSLView 3.1.8; see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cma.mgh.harvard.edu/fsl_atlas.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cma.mgh.harvard.edu/fsl_atlas.html</ext-link>; probability threshold was set to 50%). The left and right VS were treated as separate ROIs. The hippocampus mask was divided along the y-axis in an anterior and a posterior part with MARINA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Walter2">[62]</xref> according to Poppenk et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Poppenk1">[63]</xref>. Mean beta values (across all voxels within ROIs) were imported into SPSS 20 for linear regression analysis. Post-hoc repeated measures ANOVAs, with <italic>Phase</italic> (Anticipation/Delivery) as the repeated factor and EFA as a covariate of interest were calculated for the left VS, right insula and left putamen ROIs. The same type of ANOVA was also conducted using the input of two different ROIs (left VS for reward anticipation/right insula for reward delivery), in order to directly examine the effects of phase in those regions which showed the highest activation in the separate ROI-analysis from each phase. In addition, a post-hoc factorial analysis provided a direct test of the interaction between condition (monetary vs. verbal) and outcome (win vs. no-win) during the delivery phase.</p>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item>
<p><bold>4. Association between early life stress, ADHD symptoms and neuronal activation.</bold> Pearson correlations were computed to establish the relationship of the significant cluster of neuronal activation with EFA and ADHD symptoms. A mediation analysis was conducted to assess whether a possible effect of EFA on ADHD symptoms is mediated by neuronal activation. Mediation was tested following previous work of our group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta2">[38]</xref> by means of the Sobel test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Baron1">[64]</xref> accompanied by a bootstrapping method with N = 5000 samples <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Preacher1">[65]</xref> using SPSS 20.</p>
</list-item></list>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Behavior</title>
<p>Behavioral data analysis showed a performance advantage for RT and number of win trials when contrasting the monetary with the verbal condition. Participants responded faster after the presentation of a monetary relative to a verbal cue (monetary: 195.81±26.78 ms; verbal: 225.52±41.96 ms; t<sub>(161)</sub> = −10.56; p&lt;.001) and won a monetary trial more often than a verbal trial (monetary: 28.55±2.97; verbal: 21.52±3.19; t<sub>(161)</sub> = 15.01; p&lt;.001). A significant effect of EFA on RT of monetary trials emerged (F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 9.22, p = .003), with RT increasing with the level of adversity. A similar effect was observed for the verbal reward condition (F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 6.45, p = .012), after exclusion of one participant who exceeded the 3-fold interquartile range. No effect of EFA on the number of win trials (monetary: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = .03; p = .863; verbal: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = .395; p = .531) and no interaction between EFA and condition on RT (F<sub>(7,154)</sub> = .609, p = .748) or number of win trials (F<sub>(7,153)</sub> = .076, p = .999) was found. All participants gained money (mean: 21.91 €±2.02; range: 16.00–26.50 €). No effect of EFA on payoff emerged (F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = .040; p = .843).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>EEG</title>
<p>A task effect on the contingent negative variation (CNV) revealed that the anticipation of a monetary reward induced a higher CNV than the anticipation of a verbal reward [t<sub>(161)</sub> = −7.18; p&lt;.001; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0104185.s003">Figure S3</xref>]. Furthermore, an effect of EFA indicated that the CNV (contrasting monetary to verbal reward) decreased when EFA increased (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0104185-g002">Figure 2d</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0104185-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<p>Left: neuronal activity (p<sub>FWE</sub>&lt;.05; ROI corr.) for the contrast monetary &gt; verbal reward during reward anticipation by early family adversity (EFA) in <bold>a</bold>) left VS, <bold>b</bold>) left putamen and <bold>c</bold>) left thalamus; right: scatterplots of the correlations between the mean BOLD response of the respective regions and EFA; <bold>d</bold>) left: Scalp distribution of CNV difference (monetary &gt; verbal condition; mean difference: 2–3 sec after stimulus presentation) dependent on EFA; right: scatterplot of the correlation between CNV difference at Cz (marked with an asterisk) and EFA [F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 9.14, p = .003].</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>fMRI</title>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item>
<p><bold>1. Effects on reward anticipation.</bold> Whole-brain analysis contrasting monetary to verbal reward anticipation revealed higher activation of reward-related regions (VS, supplementary motor area and anterior cingulate cortex, all p<sub>FWE</sub>&lt;.0001; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0104185.s001">Figure S1a</xref>). Furthermore, a ROI-analysis revealed a significant effect of EFA on the contrast (monetary&gt;verbal) in the VS, putamen, pallidum, left thalamus, left insula, left ACC and right anterior hippocampus (p<sub>FWE</sub>&lt;.05; ROI-corrected; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104185-t001">Table 1</xref>), indicating that activation in these regions decreased with the level of EFA. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0104185-g002">Figure 2a–c</xref> shows the respective activation maps together with corresponding extracted mean betas for the predefined ROIs, estimated by linear regression. Results remained constant or even improved (VS left: t = 4.65, p&lt;.001; putamen left: t = 4.36, p = .001; pallidum left: t = 4.37, p&lt;.001), when controlling for subclinical psychopathology at the current assessment.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>2. Effects on reward delivery.</bold> Whole-brain analysis of the reward delivery phase induced similarly robust activation of reward-related areas (for the win&gt;no-win contrast; task effect, pooling of monetary and verbal feedback), specifically the putamen, caudate, left inferior frontal gyrus, and right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (p<sub>FWE</sub>&lt;.0001; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0104185.s001">Figure S1b</xref>). In addition, a ROI-analysis indicated a significant effect of EFA on the former mentioned contrast, with increasing activation in the bilateral insula, right pallidum and bilateral putamen with the level of EFA (p<sub>FWE</sub>&lt;.05; ROI-corrected; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104185-t002">Table 2</xref>). Activation maps and extracted mean betas are displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0104185-g003">Figure 3</xref>. Separate analysis for verbal outcome revealed that with increasing EFA, participants showed higher activation in the bilateral insula, pallidum, substantia nigra and right posterior hippocampus (contrasting verbal win&gt;no-win; p<sub>FWE</sub>&lt;.05; ROI-corrected; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104185-t003">Table 3</xref>). Activation maps and extracted mean betas are displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0104185-g004">Figure 4</xref>. In contrast, there was no significant EFA effect on activation in reward-related areas for monetary outcomes (regression analysis for left insula: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 1.41, p = .24; right insula: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 1.47, p = .23; left putamen: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 1.42, p = .24; right putamen: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 2.7, p = .10; right pallidum: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 2.73, p = .10). Results for both contrasts (win&gt;no-win, verbal win&gt;no-win) were attenuated, when controlling for subclinical psychopathology at the current assessment, but still remained significant (win&gt;no-win: putamen right: t = 3.56, p = .021, pallidum right: t = 3.19, p = .021, insula right: t = 4.17, p = .005; verbal win&gt;no-win: pallidum right: t = 3.43, p = .011, posterior hippocampus right: t = 3.97, p = .003, insula right: t = 4.15, p = .006).The factorial interaction (directly testing increased EFA-related modulation of verbal&gt;monetary wins) revealed overlapping activation with the verbal outcome in a hippocampal area, indicating that the difference between the EFA-related activation for win&gt;no-win trials was higher for verbal than for monetary outcome.</p>
</list-item></list>
<fig id="pone-0104185-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<p>Left: neuronal activity (p<sub>FWE</sub>&lt;.05; ROI corr.) for the contrast win &gt; no-win trials during reward delivery by EFA in <bold>a</bold>) right insula, <bold>b</bold>) right pallidum and <bold>c</bold>) left putamen; right: scatterplots of the correlations between the mean BOLD response of the respective regions and EFA.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0104185-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<p>Left: neuronal activity (p<sub>FWE</sub>&lt;.05; ROI corr.) for the contrast <underline>verbal</underline> win &gt; no-win trials during reward delivery by EFA in <bold>a</bold>) right pallidum, <bold>b</bold>) right insula, <bold>c</bold>) left substantia nigra and <bold>d</bold>) right posterior hippocampus; right: scatterplots of the correlations between the mean BOLD response of the respective regions and EFA.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0104185-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Regional BOLD changes to monetary &gt; verbal reward by EFA.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104185-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">k</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">coordinates</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cluster size</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VS left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8 4 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VS right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 14 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.019</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putamen left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18 6 12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">434</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putamen right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 8 −2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">394</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pallidum left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10 2 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pallidum right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 4 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14 36 20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thalamus left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10 −2 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.018</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insula left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−38 18 −6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior hippocampus right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 −6 −12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.010</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>* FWE corrected at a threshold of .05, k≥10.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0104185-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Regional BOLD changes to win &gt; no-win trials by EFA.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104185-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">k</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">coordinates</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cluster size</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insula right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 8 −2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insula left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−46 4 −4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.016</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putamen left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−32 −4 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.011</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putamen right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 2 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.017</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pallidum right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 0 −4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.015</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>* FWE corrected at a threshold of .05, k≥10.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0104185-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Regional BOLD changes to <italic>verbal</italic> win &gt; no-win trials by EFA.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104185-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">k</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">coordinates</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cluster size</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pallidum right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 −8 −4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pallidum left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24 −12 −4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.012</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior hippocampus right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 −30 −10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insula left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−46 4 −4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insula right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 8 −2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substantia nigra left</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12 −20 −10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substantia nigra right</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 −18 −12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.010</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>* FWE corrected at a threshold of .05, k≥10.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Furthermore, a significant negative correlation between neuronal activation during reward anticipation and delivery emerged, indicating that activation of the left VS decreased during anticipation when activation of the right insula [r = −.189; p = .016] and right pallidum [r = −.225; p = .004] increased during delivery (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0104185.s002">Figure S2</xref>).</p>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item>
<p><bold>3. Interaction between <italic>Phase</italic> (Anticipation/Delivery) and EFA.</bold> A significant interaction between Phase and EFA was obtained in all three ROIs (left VS: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 7.36, p = .007; right insula: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 10.32, p = .002; left putamen: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 10.75, p = .001), when considering the same ROIs for both stages of reward processing. Post-hoc regression analysis revealed that the interaction effect in the left VS was driven by anticipation alone (anticipation: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 14.33, p&lt;.001; delivery: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 1.31, p = .255), while, in the other ROIs, it was driven by both anticipation and delivery (right insula: anticipation: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 4.33, p = .039; delivery: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 7.68, p = .006; left putamen: anticipation: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 11.58, p = .001; delivery: F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 4.22, p = .042). Additionally, a significant interaction between Phase and EFA emerged, when considering different ROIs for both reward processing stages (anticipation: left VS; delivery: right insula; F<sub>(1,160)</sub> = 17.72, p&lt;.001).</p>
</list-item></list>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Correlation of fMRI activation with behavioral measures and CNV</title>
<p>Negative correlations between RT to monetary trials and neuronal activation (VS, putamen, thalamus) during reward anticipation, contrasting monetary over verbal reward, occurred in several regions (VS: r = −.347; p&lt;.01; putamen: r = −.367; p&lt;.01; thalamus: r = −.345; p = &lt;.01). The analogous correlation emerged between RT and CNV contrasting monetary over verbal reward (r = −.215; p&lt;.01). No significant correlation for RT of verbal trials was found. Furthermore, the number of monetary win trials was positively related to neuronal activation during reward anticipation contrasting monetary over verbal reward (VS: r = −.321; p&lt;.01; putamen: r = −.360; p&lt;.01; thalamus: r = −.328; p = &lt;.01). A similar finding was obtained for the number of verbal win trials (VS: r = −.198; p&lt;.05; putamen: r = −.220; p&lt;.01; thalamus: r = −.187; p = &lt;.05). There was no significant correlation between the number of win trials and CNV. A significant negative correlation of fMRI activation with the CNV during reward anticipation (contrasting monetary to verbal cues for both measures) emerged (VS: r = −.215; p = .006; putamen: r = −.222; p = .004; thalamus: r = −.250; p = .001), showing that the CNV decreased when fMRI activity increased.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Correlation of neuronal activity (fMRI/CNV) and EFA with lifetime ADHD</title>
<p>There was a significant correlation of fMRI activation contrasting monetary to verbal cues during reward anticipation in the left VS with ADHD symptoms, revealing decreasing activity with the number of ADHD symptoms (r = −.160; p = .042). Moreover, a significant correlation of fMRI activation contrasting win to no-win trials during reward delivery of the right insula with ADHD symptoms was obtained, showing increasing activity with the number of ADHD symptoms (r = .203; p = .01). In contrast, the CNV was found to be unrelated to ADHD symptoms (r = .10; p = .207). Furthermore, EFA correlated significantly with ADHD symptoms (r = .285; p&lt;.001). The mediation analysis of the association between EFA and ADHD symptoms revealed no significant mediation by neuronal activation (left VS: Z = 1.01, p = .31, 95% CI: −.019 □ .084; right insula: Z = 1.52, p = .13, 95% CI: 0 □ .105).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The current simultaneous EEG-fMRI study investigated the long-term impact of early life adversity on neuronal alterations of the reward system into adulthood. Using data of an epidemiological cohort study from birth onwards, the results presented above provided evidence of altered reward processing later in life following exposure to early adversity. Specifically, our findings demonstrated a differential impact of adversity on neural responding to distinct phases of reward processing, indicating that the activation of specific reward-related brain areas (VS, putamen, thalamus) decreased with the level of adversity during reward anticipation, while there was an increase in activity of other reward-related areas (pallidum, insula, substantia nigra, right posterior hippocampus) with the level of adversity during reward delivery. The fMRI finding during reward anticipation converged with EEG results showing a negative association between the CNV and adversity, matching the negative correlation of CNV with fMRI activation. Further analysis of the single reward conditions revealed striking effects of early adversity on the processing of verbal reward, which accounted for major parts of the total reward-related activity during the delivery phase.</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Reward anticipation &amp; early life stress</title>
<p>The results of the present study replicate recent findings with regard to reward anticipation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Dillon1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Mehta1">[33]</xref>, highlighting deficits in the reward processing circuitry associated with exposure to early adversity. While in these studies, small samples of individuals exposed to severe childhood adversity (maltreatment, deprivation) were investigated, the present study extends these findings to a substantially larger number of individuals from an epidemiological cohort study who experienced low to moderate levels of adversity. Moreover, in contrast to these studies, which included maltreated individuals with a current psychiatric disorder, the present analysis focused on currently healthy individuals only. The observed activation of the VS, the putamen and the thalamus is in accordance with previous research, supporting the assumption of a specific reward circuitry affected by stress in early life <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Diekhof1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Haber1">[12]</xref>. Interestingly, while Dillon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Dillon1">[10]</xref> reported less activation for maltreated individuals in the left pallidum and putamen, we replicated this effect for the putamen and, additionally, for the thalamus and the VS, the latter serving as the core region of reward processing. The prominent role of the thalamus in the reward circuit has recently been established by the demonstration of a strong direct link to the nucleus accumbens in studies measuring effective connectivity using dynamic causal modeling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta2">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Cho1">[66]</xref>.</p>
<p>The finding of a negative association between the CNV and early adversity, which to our knowledge is new to the field, provides additional evidence to substantiate the hypothesis of an adversity-driven dysfunctional neuronal reward circuit, suggesting that reward processing is already impaired less than three seconds after cue onset. This result supports the notion of a reward-driven variability of the CNV-like activity preceding uncertain feedback, and is in accordance with previous findings of a relationship between CNV and reward anticipation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Capa1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Pierson1">[25]</xref>. Along the same lines, slower RTs with the level of EFA during reward anticipation were found to be linked with blunted neuronal activity and a reduced CNV.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Reward delivery &amp; early life stress</title>
<p>The finding that neural activity in reward-related areas increased with the level of early adversity during reward delivery is in contrast to previous studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Dillon1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Mehta1">[33]</xref>, which were unable to establish an effect of adversity on the processing of reward outcomes. Several reasons may account for this inconsistency: First, given our substantially larger sample, the present study had a considerably higher power to uncover effects of adversity. Second, a continuous, prospective measure of adversity such as applied in this study may enable the detection of subtle adversity-modulated reward activation in contrast to a case-control design. Third, differences in the MID tasks used to assess reward processing may contribute to the discrepant findings. While in our study, monetary reward was contrasted with verbal reward as a control condition, others included a loss condition or used different intensities of monetary reward as contrasts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Dillon1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Mehta1">[33]</xref>. This reduces the number of trials per condition and, in combination with small sample sizes, may lead to reduced effect sizes and less sensitivity to reward outcome.</p>
<p>The activation of the pallidum, insula, hippocampus and substantia nigra demonstrated here is in accordance with the assumption of the phasic transmission of reward information via dopaminergic projections from the midbrain to the VS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Schultz1">[67]</xref>. The hippocampal area plays a prominent role in regulating the reward circuit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Treadway1">[68]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Knutson2">[69]</xref> by showing afferent and efferent projections to the VS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Friedman1">[70]</xref>, regulating emotional, motivational and learning processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Murty1">[71]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Wise1">[72]</xref>. The observation of more pronounced EFA-related modulation following verbal reward may indicate a specific sensitivity for social reward appreciation in individuals exposed to high adversity in early childhood, which might be specifically represented by activation of the hippocampus. The VS directly projects to the pallidum, integrating reward information and driving action output <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Diekhof1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Frank1">[73]</xref>. Moreover, pallidum activation affected by early adversity, as previously found for reward anticipation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Dillon1">[10]</xref>, suggests a high involvement of the basal ganglia in reward processing, including both the anticipation and outcome phase. A specific activation of the medial orbitofrontal and ventromedial prefrontal cortex during reward delivery as proposed by Diekhof et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Diekhof1">[11]</xref> was not supported by the current study. This might be due to the absence of different magnitudes in monetary rewards in the present MID paradigm, which have been suggested to be processed by frontal activation.</p>
<p>Our finding that the impact of early adversity on reward outcome was only marked in the verbal reward control condition highlights the special reward quality of this condition, and may suggest that individuals exposed to early adversity are particularly prone to social rewards, such as verbal praise. This higher responsiveness to social rewards may result from the experience of poor parenting during childhood in individuals exposed to early family adversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Schmid1">[74]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Burchinal1">[76]</xref>, which may have increased the rewarding effect of social stimuli later in life. A retrospective cohort study by Baker and Hoerger <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Baker1">[77]</xref> has implicated dysfunctional parenting, including low parental warmth or high rejection and control, in the development of difficulty delaying gratification. Such findings may support the hypothesis that poor parenting may lead to a reward deficiency syndrome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Blum1">[78]</xref>, resulting in increased social reward retrieval.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Reward processing &amp; acute vs. early life stress</title>
<p>In contrast to our results, Kumar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Kumar1">[34]</xref>, when investigating the impact of acute stress on reward processing, reported an opposite activation pattern in regions (caudate [VS], putamen) partly overlapping with ours, indicating increased neuronal activation during reward anticipation and decreased activation while receiving a reward. These findings underpin the functional differences between the impact of acute stress vs. early life stress on reward processing. Specifically, it has been demonstrated that the stress (HPA axis) and the reward system show considerable overlap on both the structural and the functional level <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-UlrichLai1">[35]</xref>. Acute stress leads to an up regulation of HPA axis activity, thereby increasing motivation and approach behaviors, but blunting reward responsiveness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Berghorst1">[79]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Bogdan1">[82]</xref>. In contrast, early life stress may result in an adaptation of HPA axis activity with first increased cortisol release during stress exposure followed by later hypocortisolism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Fries1">[83]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Heim2">[84]</xref> which might be linked to decreased dopamine transmission during reward anticipation but increased when receiving a reward.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Reward processing, early life stress &amp; ADHD</title>
<p>Our findings provide additional insights into the relationship between altered reward processing in individuals exposed to early adversity and mental disorders related to dysfunction of the dopamine reward circuit, such as ADHD. The differential effect of early life stress on both stages of reward processing, characterized by hyporesponsiveness in individuals exposed to high early adversity when anticipating a monetary reward and hyperresponsiveness when receiving a reward, is in line with the literature on dysfunctional reward processing in ADHD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Stark1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Scheres1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Plichta1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Paloyelis1">[17]</xref>. Accordingly, there was a significant association between fMRI activation in reward-related regions and lifetime ADHD symptoms, showing the same differential effect on anticipatory and delivery phases as observed for early life stress. Given that the latter represents a major risk factor of ADHD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Laucht4">[43]</xref>, this might suggest an impact of EFA on ADHD via a dysfunctional reward pathway. Here, this pathway could not be confirmed by the mediation analysis. In contrast to fMRI, the CNV proved to be unrelated to ADHD. As the CNV has been identified as a stable ADHD marker for preparation deficits measured by cognitive paradigms such as the CPT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Albrecht1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Doehnert1">[30]</xref>, this result might be an effect of paradigm. Although there was a significant impact of EFA on the CNV, reward anticipation as part of an emotional paradigm might be less sensitive to ADHD effects than cognitive paradigms. However, given the significant correlation between CNV and fMRI activation, the different measures alone could not explain this differential effect.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Several limitations have to be considered in the interpretation of our results. First, due to reduced data quality following the button press, it was not possible to analyze EEG feedback components such as the feedback-related negativity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Broyd1">[26]</xref>. However, it would be most interesting to examine whether EEG feedback components would display a similar pattern of outcome-related EFA effects to that found for fMRI. Second, given the small effect size of EFA and the fact that several characteristics of EFA would not change during the individual's life course, the results cannot be attributed to early life stress alone but probably also reflects stress during later development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Heim1">[2]</xref>. Third, the present results do not provide evidence of the mechanisms mediating between exposure to EFA and altered reward processing in adulthood. Several mechanisms have been discussed as determining the transduction of environmental influences into changes in brain physiology and morphology. Among these, a major role has been attributed to epigenetic regulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Meaney1">[85]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Roth1">[86]</xref>. Hence, the investigation of epigenetic signatures induced by exposure to EFA that persist into adulthood appears to be a promising research perspective. Fourth, current research has highlighted the differential susceptibility of individuals to EFA. Greater insight into the interplay between environmental and genetic factors that affect reward processing may further contribute to a better understanding of the underlying mechanisms. Genes that have been shown to exert remarkable effects on the reward circuit include, among others, the dopamine transporter gene (DAT) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Hahn1">[87]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Dreher1">[88]</xref> and the catechol-O-methyltransferase gene (COMT) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Bates1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Camara1">[89]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104185-Yacubian1">[90]</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In sum, the present findings provide evidence of a differential long-term impact of early life adversity on two distinct phases of reward processing in adulthood, characterized by hyporesponsiveness during reward anticipation followed by hyperresponsiveness when receiving a reward. Moreover, a similar activation pattern related to lifetime ADHD may suggest that the impact of early life stress on ADHD may possibly be mediated by a dysfunctional reward pathway.</p>
</sec><sec id="s6">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0104185.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Whole-brain task effects a) during the anticipation of monetary vs. verbal rewards, indicating significantly higher activation in the ventral striatum (VS), thalamus, anterior cingulate cortex, supplementary motor area, primary motor area and occipital cortex and b) during reward delivery (win vs. no-win), yielding significantly higher activation in the putamen, caudate, left inferior frontal gyrus, right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, primary motor area, right medial frontal gyrus and occipital cortex (all p<sub>FWE</sub>&lt;.0001; k≥20).</bold></p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0104185.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Significant negative correlation of activation in the left VS during reward anticipation with a) right insula activation (pooled reward) [r = −.189; p = .016] and b) right pallidum activation (verbal reward) [r = −.225; p = .004] during reward delivery.</bold></p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0104185.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Grand average ERPs showing the stronger contingent negative variation (CNV) developing at electrode Cz (marked with an asterisk) after the presentation of monetary (happy smiley, black curve) compared to verbal (scrambled smiley, red curve) reward cues; p&lt;.001 in the analysis time window (blue, 2–3 sec following cue onset and preceding target onset on all trials).</bold></p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0104185.s004" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104185.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Definition of early family adversity (EFA) items.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Lupien1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lupien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gunnar</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effects of stress throughout the lifespan on the brain, behaviour and cognition</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>445</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Heim1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Current research trends in early life stress and depression: review of human studies on sensitive periods, gene-environment interactions, and epigenetics</article-title>. <source>Exp Neurol</source> <volume>233</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-McLaughlin1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greif</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaslavsky</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Childhood adversities and first onset of psychiatric disorders in a national sample of US adolescents</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1151</fpage>–<lpage>1160</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Pheula1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pheula</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Are family variables associated with ADHD, inattentive type? A case-control study in schools</article-title>. <source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Laucht1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laucht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Association between ADHD and smoking in adolescence: shared genetic, environmental and psychopathological factors</article-title>. <source>J Neural Transm</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>1097</fpage>–<lpage>1104</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Bates1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bates J, Bayles K, Bennet D, Ridge B, Brown M (1991) Origins of externalizing behavior problems at eight years of age. In: Pepler D, Rubin K, editors. The Development and Treatment of Childhood Aggression. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Pressman1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pressman</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asarnow</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Relationship of family environment and parental psychiatric diagnosis to impairment in ADHD</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Stark1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merz</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>ADHD related behaviors are associated with brain activation in the reward system</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>434</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Scheres1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sumiya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Temporal reward discounting and ADHD: task and symptom specific effects</article-title>. <source>J Neural Transm</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Dillon1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birk</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons-Ruth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Childhood adversity is associated with left basal ganglia dysfunction during reward anticipation in adulthood</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Diekhof1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diekhof</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaps</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The role of the human ventral striatum and the medial orbitofrontal cortex in the representation of reward magnitude - an activation likelihood estimation meta-analysis of neuroimaging studies of passive reward expectancy and outcome processing</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1252</fpage>–<lpage>1266</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Haber1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The reward circuit: linking primate anatomy and human imaging</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Berridge1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dissecting components of reward: 'liking', 'wanting', and learning</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Pharmacol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Plichta1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plichta</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vasic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lesch</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brummer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Neural hyporesponsiveness and hyperresponsiveness during immediate and delayed reward processing in adult attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Strohle1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strohle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wrase</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schlagenhauf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Reward anticipation and outcomes in adult males with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>966</fpage>–<lpage>972</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Furukawa1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bado</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tripp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Abnormal Striatal BOLD Responses to Reward Anticipation and Reward Delivery in ADHD</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e89129</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Paloyelis1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paloyelis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faraone</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asherson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuntsi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Striatal sensitivity during reward processing in attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>722</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Tripp1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tripp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Research review: dopamine transfer deficit: a neurobiological theory of altered reinforcement mechanisms in ADHD</article-title>. <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>704</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Tripp2"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tripp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Neurobiology of ADHD</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacology</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Walter1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCallum</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>Contingent negative variation: an electric sign of sensomotor association and expectancy in the human brain</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>203</volume>: <fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Irwin1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knott</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McAdam</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rebert</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>1966</year>) <article-title>Motivational determinants of the "contingent negative variation"</article-title>. <source>Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>538</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Brunia1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunia</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hackley</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Boxtel</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohgami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Waiting to perceive: reward or punishment?</article-title> <source>Clin Neurophysiol</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>858</fpage>–<lpage>868</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Capa1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Capa</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouquet</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dreher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Long-lasting effects of performance-contingent unconscious and conscious reward incentives during cued task-switching</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1943</fpage>–<lpage>1954</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Kotani1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiraku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Effect of positive and negative emotion on stimulus-preceding negativity prior to feedback stimuli</article-title>. <source>Psychophysiology</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>873</fpage>–<lpage>878</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Pierson1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ragot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ripoche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lesevre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Electrophysiological changes elicited by auditory stimuli given a positive or negative value: a study comparing anhedonic with hedonic subjects</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychophysiol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Broyd1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broyd</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helps</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chronaki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bamford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>An electrophysiological monetary incentive delay (e-MID) task: a way to decompose the different components of neural response to positive and negative monetary reinforcement</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Methods</source> <volume>209</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Goldstein1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cottone</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The effect of graded monetary reward on cognitive event-related potentials and behavior in young healthy adults</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychophysiol</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Banaschewski1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banaschewski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandeis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Association of ADHD and conduct disorder–brain electrical evidence for the existence of a distinct subtype</article-title>. <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Albrecht1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandeis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uebel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valko</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Familiality of neural preparation and response control in childhood attention deficit-hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>1997</fpage>–<lpage>2011</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Doehnert1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doehnert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandeis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drechsler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinhausen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A neurophysiological marker of impaired preparation in an 11-year follow-up study of attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD)</article-title>. <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-vanLeeuwen1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinhausen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Overtoom</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual-Marqui</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van't Klooster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The continuous performance test revisited with neuroelectric mapping: impaired orienting in children with attention deficits</article-title>. <source>Behav Brain Res</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Guyer1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guyer</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgdon</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masten</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jazbec</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Behavioral alterations in reward system function: the role of childhood maltreatment and psychopathology</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>1059</fpage>–<lpage>1067</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Mehta1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gore-Langton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golembo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colvert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Hyporesponsive reward anticipation in the basal ganglia following severe institutional deprivation early in life</article-title>. <source>J Cogn Neurosci</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2316</fpage>–<lpage>2325</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Kumar1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berghorst</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dutra</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goer</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Differential effects of acute stress on anticipatory and consummatory phases of reward processing</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source> <volume>266C</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-UlrichLai1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulrich-Lai</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Neural regulation of endocrine and autonomic stress responses</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>409</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Rademacher1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rademacher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krach</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohls</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irmak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grunder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Dissociation of neural networks for anticipation and consumption of monetary and social rewards</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>3276</fpage>–<lpage>3285</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Delmonte1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delmonte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balsters</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Social and monetary reward processing in autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Mol Autism</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Plichta2"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plichta</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boecker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Simultaneous EEG and fMRI Reveals a Causally Connected Subcortical-Cortical Network during Reward Anticipation</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>14526</fpage>–<lpage>14533</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Laucht2"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laucht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baving</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerhold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoesch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Behavioral sequelae of perinatal insults and early family adversity at 8 years of age</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child and Adolesc Psychiatry</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1229</fpage>–<lpage>1237</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Laucht3"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laucht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Developmental outcome of infants born with biological and psychosocial risks</article-title>. <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>853</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Rutter1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rutter M, Quinton D (1977) Psychiatric disorder - ecological factors and concepts of causation. In: McGurk M, editor. Ecological factors in human development. Amsterdam: North Holland. pp.173–187.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Evans1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whipple</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Cumulative risk and child development</article-title>. <source>Psychol Bull</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1342</fpage>–<lpage>1396</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Laucht4"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laucht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skowronek</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Interacting effects of the dopamine transporter gene and psychosocial adversity on attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder symptoms among 15-year-olds from a high-risk community sample</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Laucht5"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laucht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Treutlein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blomeyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Interaction between the 5-HTTLPR serotonin transporter polymorphism and environmental adversity for mood and anxiety psychopathology: evidence from a high-risk community sample of young adults</article-title>. <source>Int J Neuropsychopharmacol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Wittchen1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wittchen HU, Zaudig M, Fydrich T (1997) [Structured clinical interview for DSM-IV Axis I and II - SCID]. Göttingen: Hogrefe.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Mller1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Müller R, Abbet JP (1991) Changing trends in the consumption of legal and illegal drugs by 11-16-year-old adolescent pupils. Findings from a study conducted under the auspices of the WHO Europe. Lausanne: Swiss Professional Service for Alcohol Problems.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Esser1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Esser G, Blanz B, Geisel B, Laucht M (1989) Mannheim Parent Interview - Structured interview for child psychiatric disorders. Weinheim: Beltz.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Kaufman1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kaufman J, Birmaher B, Brent D, Rao U, Ryan N (1996) Kiddie-Sads-Present and Lifetime Version (K-SADS_PL) [Internet]. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.psychiatry.pitt.edu/node/8233" xlink:type="simple">http://www.psychiatry.pitt.edu/node/8233</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Delmo1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Delmo C, Weiffenbach O, Gabriel M, Poustka F (2000) Kiddie-SADS-Present and Lifetime version (K-SADS-PL) 3. Auflage der deutschen Forschungsversion. Frankfurt. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.adhs-essen.com/PDF/K-SADS_Fragebogen.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.adhs-essen.com/PDF/K-SADS_Fragebogen.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Laucht6"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laucht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Differential development of infants at risk for psychopathology: the moderating role of early maternal responsivity</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>292</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Holz1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Holz NE, Boecker R, Baumeister S, Hohm E, Zohsel K, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2014) Effect of Prenatal Exposure to Tobacco Smoke on Inhibitory Control: Neuroimaging Results From a 25-Year Prospective Study. JAMA Psychiatry.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Kaufman2"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birmaher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia for School-Age Children-Present and Lifetime Version (K-SADS-PL): initial reliability and validity data</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>980</fpage>–<lpage>988</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Kirsch1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schienle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sammer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blecker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Anticipation of reward in a nonaversive differential conditioning paradigm and the brain reward system: an event-related fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1086</fpage>–<lpage>1095</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Knutson1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hommer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Anticipation of increasing monetary reward selectively recruits nucleus accumbens</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>RC159</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Plichta3"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plichta</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boecker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Simultaneous EEG and fMRI reveals a causally connected subcortical-cortical network during reward anticipation</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>14526</fpage>–<lpage>14533</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Allen1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Josephs</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A method for removing imaging artifact from continuous EEG recorded during functional MRI</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Allen2"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polizzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krakow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemieux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Identification of EEG events in the MR scanner: the problem of pulse artifact and a method for its subtraction</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Makeig1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Makeig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Independent component analysis of electroencephalographic data</article-title>. <source>Adv Neural Inf Process Syst</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Debener1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Debener</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mullinger</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niazy</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowtell</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Properties of the ballistocardiogram artefact as revealed by EEG recordings at 1.5, 3 and 7 T static magnetic field strength</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychophysiol</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Achenbach1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Achenbach T (1997) Manual for the Young Adult Self-Report and Young Adult Behavior Checklist. Burlington, VT: Department of Psychiatry, University of Vermont</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Maldjian1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maldjian</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurienti</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kraft</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burdette</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>An automated method for neuroanatomic and cytoarchitectonic atlas-based interrogation of fMRI data sets</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1233</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Walter2"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Walter B, Blecker C, Kirsch P, Sammer G, Schienle A, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2003) MARINA: An easy to use tool for the creation of MAsks for Region of INterest Analyses [abstract]. Presented at the 9th International Conference on Functional Mapping of the Human Brain, June 19–22, New York, NY. Neuroimage <volume>19</volume> : Available on CD-Rom.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Poppenk1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poppenk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evensmoen</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moscovitch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nadel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Long-axis specialization of the human hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn Sci</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Baron1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: conceptual, strategic, and statistical considerations</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Preacher1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preacher</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>SPSS and SAS procedures for estimating indirect effects in simple mediation models</article-title>. <source>Behav Res Methods Instrum Comput</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>731</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Cho1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fromm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guyer</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Detloff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pine</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Nucleus accumbens, thalamus and insula connectivity during incentive anticipation in typical adults and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source> <volume>66C</volume>: <fpage>508</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Schultz1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Predictive reward signal of dopamine neurons</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Treadway1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Treadway</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buckholtz</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zald</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Perceived stress predicts altered reward and loss feedback processing in medial prefrontal cortex</article-title>. <source>Front Hum Neurosci</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>180</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Knutson2"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhanji</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooney</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atlas</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gotlib</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Neural responses to monetary incentives in major depression</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>686</fpage>–<lpage>692</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Friedman1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aggleton</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Comparison of hippocampal, amygdala, and perirhinal projections to the nucleus accumbens: combined anterograde and retrograde tracing study in the Macaque brain</article-title>. <source>J Comp Neurol</source> <volume>450</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Murty1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Murty VP, Adcock RA (2013) Enriched Encoding: Reward Motivation Organizes Cortical Networks for Hippocampal Detection of Unexpected Events. Cereb Cortex.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Wise1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Dopamine, learning and motivation</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>494</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Frank1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claus</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Anatomy of a decision: striato-orbitofrontal interactions in reinforcement learning, decision making, and reversal</article-title>. <source>Psychol Rev</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>300</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Schmid1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blomeyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trautmann-Villalba</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Quality of early mother-child interaction associated with depressive psychopathology in the offspring: A prospective study from infancy to adulthood</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Res</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1394</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Glascoe1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glascoe</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Parenting behaviors, perceptions, and psychosocial risk: impacts on young children's development</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Burchinal1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burchinal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vernon-Feagans</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <collab xlink:type="simple">Key Family Life Project I</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cumulative Social Risk, Parenting, and Infant Development in Rural Low-Income Communities</article-title>. <source>Parenting, science and practice</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Baker1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoerger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Parental Child-Rearing Strategies Influence Self-Regulation, Socio-Emotional Adjustment, and Psychopathology in Early Adulthood: Evidence from a Retrospective Cohort Study</article-title>. <source>Pers Individ Dif</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>800</fpage>–<lpage>805</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Blum1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Blum K, Braverman ER, Holder JM, Lubar JF, Monastra VJ, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2000) Reward deficiency syndrome: a biogenetic model for the diagnosis and treatment of impulsive, addictive, and compulsive behaviors. J Psychoactive Drugs <volume>32</volume> : Suppl: i–iv, 1–112.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Berghorst1"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berghorst</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pizzagalli</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Acute stress selectively reduces reward sensitivity</article-title>. <source>Front Hum Neurosci</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Lupien2"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lupien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maheu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fiocco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schramek</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The effects of stress and stress hormones on human cognition: Implications for the field of brain and cognition</article-title>. <source>Brain Cogn</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Cabib1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puglisi-Allegra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Stress, depression and the mesolimbic dopamine system</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Bogdan1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pizzagalli</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Acute stress reduces reward responsiveness: implications for depression</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1147</fpage>–<lpage>1154</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Fries1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fries</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hesse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellhammer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellhammer</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A new view on hypocortisolism</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1010</fpage>–<lpage>1016</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Heim2"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehlert</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellhammer</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The potential role of hypocortisolism in the pathophysiology of stress-related bodily disorders</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Meaney1"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meaney</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Epigenetics and the biological definition of gene x environment interactions</article-title>. <source>Child Dev</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Roth1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sweatt</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Epigenetic marking of the BDNF gene by early-life adverse experiences</article-title>. <source>Horm Behav</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Hahn1"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinzel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dresler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plichta</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Association between reward-related activation in the ventral striatum and trait reward sensitivity is moderated by dopamine transporter genotype</article-title>. <source>Hum Brain Mapp</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1557</fpage>–<lpage>1565</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Dreher1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolachana</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weinberger</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Variation in dopamine genes influences responsivity of the human reward system</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>–<lpage>622</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Camara1"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cunillera</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marco-Pallares</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cucurell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The effects of COMT (Val108/158Met) and DRD4 (SNP -521) dopamine genotypes on brain activations related to valence and magnitude of rewards</article-title>. <source>Cereb Cortex</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1985</fpage>–<lpage>1996</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104185-Yacubian1"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yacubian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glascher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Gene-gene interaction associated with neural reward sensitivity</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>8125</fpage>–<lpage>8130</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>