<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-03951</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Neurological system</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Neural pathways</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Model organisms</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal models</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Drosophila melanogaster</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Molecular cell biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Gene expression</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Neurochemistry</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Neurochemicals</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Serotonin</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavioral neuroscience</subject>
              <subject>Neurotransmitters</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Drugs and devices</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavioral pharmacology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Molecular Biology</subject>
          <subject>Physiology</subject>
          <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
          <subject>Pharmacology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Serotonin 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro Receptor Is Expressed in the Brain
                    of Drosophila, and Is Essential for Normal Courtship and Mating</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Drosophila 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro
                    Receptor</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Becnel</surname>
            <given-names>Jaime</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Johnson</surname>
            <given-names>Oralee</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>Jiangnan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nässel</surname>
            <given-names>Dick R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nichols</surname>
            <given-names>Charles D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Pharmacology and Experimental
                    Therapeutics, Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center, New Orleans,
                    Louisiana, United States of America</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Zoology, Stockholm University,
                    Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zars</surname>
            <given-names>Troy</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Missouri, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">cnich1@lsuhsc.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JB OJ DRN CDN. Performed the
                        experiments: JB OJ JL CDN. Analyzed the data: JB OJ DRN CDN. Contributed
                        reagents/materials/analysis tool: DRN CDN. Wrote the paper: JB DRN CDN.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e20800</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Becnel et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
                terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
                distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>The 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor remains one of the less well characterized
                    serotonin receptors. Although it has been demonstrated to be involved in the
                    regulation of mood, sleep, and circadian rhythms, as well as relaxation of
                    vascular smooth muscles in mammals, the precise mechanisms underlying these
                    functions remain largely unknown. The fruit fly, <italic>Drosophila
                        melanogaster</italic>, is an attractive model organism to study
                    neuropharmacological, molecular, and behavioral processes that are largely
                    conserved with mammals. Drosophila express a homolog of the mammalian
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor, as well as homologs for the mammalian
                        5-HT<sub>1A</sub>, and 5-HT<sub>2</sub>, receptors. Each fly receptor
                    couples to the same effector pathway as their mammalian counterpart and have
                    been demonstrated to mediate similar behavioral responses. Here, we report on
                    the expression and function of the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor in Drosophila.
                    In the larval central nervous system, expression is detected postsynaptically in
                    discreet cells and neuronal circuits. In the adult brain there is strong
                    expression in all large-field R neurons that innervate the ellipsoid body, as
                    well as in a small group of cells that cluster with the PDF-positive LNvs
                    neurons that mediate circadian activity. Following both pharmacological and
                    genetic approaches, we have found that 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro activity is essential
                    for normal courtship and mating behaviors in the fly, where it appears to
                    mediate levels of interest in both males and females. This is the first reported
                    evidence of direct involvement of a particular serotonin receptor subtype in
                    courtship and mating in the fly.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by NIH grants R21MH078454 and R01MH083689. The funders had
                    no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or
                    preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="14"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Serotonin (5-HT) is a monoamine neurotransmitter that regulates a variety of
                behaviors and physiological processes including circadian rhythms, sleep, appetite,
                aggression, locomotion, perception and sexual behavior in mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Breier1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Lucki1">[2]</xref>. In mammals,
                there are fourteen different receptors than can be organized into seven families.
                The many effects of serotonin are primarily mediated through G-protein coupled
                receptors, which initiate multiple effector pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Nichols1">[3]</xref>. Misregulation of serotonin
                signaling in humans has been implicated in neuropsychiatric disorders including
                depression, anxiety, anorexia nervosa, and schizophrenia.</p>
      <p>In mammals, 5-HT<sub>7</sub> mRNA has been observed in both the CNS and peripheral
                tissues including the suprachiasmatic nucleus of the hypothalamus, thalamus,
                hippocampus and cortex, as well as coronary artery, gastrointestinal tract, kidney,
                and spleen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Nichols1">[3]</xref>.
                    5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptors are expressed postsynaptically in the cortex,
                hippocampal formation and other parts of the brain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Neumaier1">[4]</xref>. They are, however, found both
                pre- and postsynaptically in the SCN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Belenky1">[5]</xref>. Studies using antagonists and
                a knock out mouse model show involvement of 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor activity in
                regulating mood, sleep, and circadian rhythms, as well as relaxation of vascular
                smooth muscles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Guscott1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Guscott2">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Hedlund1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Hedlund2">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Janssen1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Monti1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Monti2">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Sprouse1">[13]</xref>. With regard to sleep, 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptors
                modulate neuronal function in a number of areas of the brain that have been
                implicated in this behavior, including the SCN, DRN, thalamus and hippocampus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Thomas1">[14]</xref>. The systemic
                administration of 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor antagonist to rats at the beginning of
                light periods reduces total amount of REM sleep, and direct administration of
                antagonist into the DRN reduces REM sleep and the number of REM sleep periods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Monti1">[11]</xref>. Interestingly,
                    5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptors have also been implicated in the regulation of
                mammalian sexual behavior. Activation of this receptor in rats mediates an
                inhibitory effect of female sexual behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Siddiqui1">[15]</xref>.</p>
      <p><italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (the fruit fly) has proven to be a very
                effective model system for investigating the function of mammalian systems and
                diseases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Pandey1">[16]</xref>.
                About 70% of human disease genes have functional orthologs in Drosophila
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Bier1">[17]</xref>, and the
                fly expresses functional orthologs of most mammalian neurotransmitter receptors,
                including receptors for dopamine, glutamate, acetylcholine, GABA, and serotonin,
                which mediate conserved behaviors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Nichols2">[18]</xref>. The fruit fly expresses orthologs of three of the seven
                mammalian receptor families: 5-HT<sub>1A/B</sub>Dro, 5-HT<sub>2</sub>Dro and
                    5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro, and the molecular pathways linking serotonin receptor
                interactions with behaviors are likely to be conserved between the two systems.
                    5-HT<sub>1A/B</sub>Dro are expressed in adult mushroom bodies, as well as
                additional brain circuits (unpublished data; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Yuan1">[19]</xref>), and mediate aspects of sleep
                and aggression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Yuan1">[19]</xref>,
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Johnson1">[20]</xref>. We have
                previously characterized the 5-HT<sub>2</sub>Dro receptor, and found that it is
                expressed throughout the adult brain, including neurons within the protocerebrum and
                ellipsoid body, and mediates aspects of circadian behaviors and aggression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Johnson1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Nichols3">[21]</xref>. Here, we
                report on expression and function of the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor in
                    <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>. It is expressed within discreet
                circuits in the brain and ventral nerve cord, and is essential for normal courtship
                and mating.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Reagents</title>
        <p>General laboratory chemicals and reagents were obtained from Sigma (St. Louis,
                    MO). The 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor antagonist SB258719 was obtained from TOCRIS,
                    (Ellisville, MO).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title><italic>Drosophila</italic> strains and rearing</title>
        <p>Fly strains obtained from other sources were Canton-S (CS), and UAS-mCD8::GFP
                    (Bloomington Stock Center, Bloomington, IN). For routine maintenance, flies were
                    reared on standard cornmeal-molasses food at 25°C under 12 hour light/dark
                    conditions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Drug Administration in Courtship Assay</title>
        <p>For the mating assays, bottles of wild type CS flies were cleared and newly
                    eclosed, virgin females and males were collected and matured for 5-6 days prior
                    to testing in 15 mL conical tubes containing ∼300 µL of food
                    (10% sucrose, 1% agarose and the appropriate drug) and plugged
                    with cotton at the open end. In the courtship and mating assays, flies were
                    maintained on food + drug for 5 days to ensure that steady-state levels
                    were reached. To determine if the presence of SB258719 affected the feeding
                    behaviors of the flies, a CAFÉ assay was performed following established
                    protocols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Ja1">[22]</xref> and
                    feeding a 10% sucrose solution with or without 3 mM SB258719. No
                    statistical differences were observed in the feeding behaviors between the two
                    groups of flies over five days (data not shown).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Courtship and Mating Assay</title>
        <p>Between five and six virgin females were housed together during this process,
                    while sexually naïve males were individually housed. During the maturation
                    period, all flies were maintained at 25°C under a 12 hour light/dark cycle
                    until testing. Following the maturation period, one male and one female were
                    transferred to a single chamber of a mating wheel. The mating wheel is a
                    circular piece of 1.0 cm thick plexiglass 10.0 cm in diameter with ten circular
                    chambers are drilled into the wheel at the outer edge, approximately 1.0 cm in
                    diameter and 5.0 mm deep. A second circular piece of 2.0 mm plexiglass that is
                    able to rotate freely is attached to the lower plexiglass wheel and serves as a
                    cover for the mating chambers. A single 3.0 mm hole in the top is used to insert
                    flies into the chambers. Our mating chambers are slightly larger than those used
                    by Ejima and Griffith <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Ejima1">[23]</xref>, but are consistent with other chambers used in
                    published reports <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Neckameyer1">[24]</xref>. Heterosexual courtship in <italic>Drosophila
                        melanogaster</italic> involves a progression of behaviors occurring in a
                    defined order: orientation of the male toward the female, tapping, wing song,
                    licking of the female genitalia, and curling of the male (attempted copulation),
                    with successful copulation occurring shortly thereafter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Bastock1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Greenspan1">[26]</xref>. Each mating pair was
                    closely monitored for 10 minutes and scored for latency in performing
                    orientation, wing vibration, licking, curling and copulation. The frequency that
                    the behaviors occurred (number of pairs successfully performing a behavior out
                    of the total number of pairs tested), as well as the duration of copulation were
                    also determined. The number of copulation attempts, as well as the duration of
                    the copulation were also recorded. Flies that successfully copulated within the
                    initial 10-minute observation period were monitored until completion of
                    copulation or for a total of 20 minutes. If no copulation occurred within the
                    first 10 minutes, the pairs were observed for up to 60 minutes, but only for
                    successful copulation within this time. All testing was performed at 25°C at
                    70–80% relative humidity, and between the hours of 11 am and 4
                    pm.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Odor Avoidance</title>
        <p>Between 100 and 150 1–3 day old CS flies were collected and maintained on
                    standard food with or without 5-HT<sub>7</sub> antagonist (3.0 mM SB258719) for
                    48 hrs prior to testing for olfactory avoidance in a large 64 ounce commercial
                    juice bottle with the large end cut off and replaced with fine plastic mesh.
                    Flies were then transferred to the choice point of t-maze device (a standard
                    olfactory learning and memory apparatus), where they were presented with an
                    aversive odor (either 3-methylcyclohexanol or benzaldehyde, at varying
                    concentrations) in one arm of the apparatus paired with fresh room air in the
                    opposite arm of the apparatus for 120 seconds following established protocols
                    used in olfactory learning and memory assays <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Tully1">[27]</xref>. Performance indices are
                    calculated as the number of flies avoiding the aversive odor minus the number of
                    flies that do not avoid the aversive odor, and the difference divided by the
                    total number of flies tested. All experiments were performed at
                    70–80% relative humidity and 25°C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Locomotion Assay</title>
        <p>Male flies were collected less than 72 hours post eclosion and anesthetization on
                    ice. Individual flies were then placed into 5 mm diameter glass capillary tubes
                    with an agar plug at one end consisting of 1% agarose, 10% sucrose
                    and 3 mM drug (where appropriate), and then plugged at the other end with
                    cotton. Tubes were then placed into Trikinetics (Waltham, MA) activity monitor
                    arrays, which were subsequently placed into a humidified incubator at 25°C
                    with a 12 h light-dark cycle. Infrared beam breaks, as a measure of activity,
                    were monitored with the Trikinetics Drosophila Activity Monitor System (DAMS).
                    Sixteen males were used in each experiment for each treatment and monitored for
                    seven days. Only activity data for days 3 and greater were used for analysis,
                    omitting the first two days to allow for acclimation to the environment and to
                    build up steady state drug levels.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Generation of the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro GAL4 expression construct and
                    transgenic lines</title>
        <sec id="s2g1">
          <title>Preparation of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro promoter region</title>
          <p>Genomic DNA was prepared by homogenizing 25 wild type Oregon-R flies in 400
                        ml lysis buffer (30 mM Tris (pH 9), 100 mM EDTA, 0.6% SDS,
                        0.5% sucrose) followed by heat inactivation for 15 min at 70°C;
                        proteins were precipitated out by addition of 80 ml 6M KOAc on ice for 30
                        minutes followed by centrifugation at 4°C at maximum speed in a
                        microcentrifuge. The aqueous supernatant was extracted with an equal volume
                        of phenol, phenol-chloroform, then chloroform. Nucleotides was precipitated
                        by addition of 2 volumes of ethanol, incubation at room temperature for 5
                        minutes, and centrifugation for 10 minutes in a microcentrifuge at room
                        temperature. The pellet was washed in 75% ethanol, resuspended in 200
                        ml TE buffer +1 ml RNAse (Epicentre, Madison, WI), and incubated at
                        37°C for one hour. DNA was precipitated by addition of 0.1 volumes of 3M
                        NaOAc, 2.5 volumes of ethanol, incubation at –20°C overnight, and
                        centrifugation for 15 minutes at maximum speed in a microcentrifuge at
                        4°C. The pellet was washed with 75% ethanol, allowed to air dry
                        for 5 minutes, and resuspended in 25 ml sterile H<sub>2</sub>O.</p>
          <p>To isolate putative 5′ enhancer regions, which are normally contained
                        within the first few kb of genomic DNA upstream of the RNA transcription
                        start site, 5 kb of genomic DNA immediately upstream of the ATG start codon
                        within the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro locus was amplified from 1 µl of
                        genomic DNA using the Expand High Fidelity PCR System from Roche
                        (Indianapolis, IN) following manufacturers instructions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Primers
                        corresponding to the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro promoter region containing Not I
                        restriction sites at their 5′ end were ordered from Integrated DNA
                        Technologies (Coralville, IA). Forward primer
                         = 5′-gcggccgcGGTAGCCAAATGAACGTTGAGCGC-3′;
                        Reverse Primer  = 5′-
                        gcggccgcACGAATCGAATATCTGAATTCCGC-3′; annealing
                        T = 55.0°C, elongation
                        T = 68°C. The amplification product consisted of a
                        single band of 5 kb, which was gel purified using the Zymo Gel DNA Recovery
                        Kit (Orange, CA) following manufacturers instructions.</p>
          <fig id="pone-0020800-g001" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g001</object-id>
            <label>Figure 1</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Map of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro region.</title>
              <p>The 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro locus on the third chromosome is
                                approximately 40 kb with a large first intron that contains two
                                additional short annotated transcripts. The 5 kb region of genomic
                                DNA immediately upstream of the mRNA transcript start site used to
                                generate the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro GAL4 strain is shown (white box).
                                Grey boxes indicate untranslated regions of exons, darker boxes
                                represent translated regions. Arrows indicate direction of
                                transcription. Scale bar is shown.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2g2">
          <title>Construction of pERGP GAL4 expression vector</title>
          <p>The pCaSpeR4 plasmid (Dr. Bih-Hwa Sheih, Vanderbilt University, Nashville,
                        TN) was digested with Kpn I (Promega, Madison, WI) and blunt ended using the
                        End-IT DNA End Repair Kit (Epicentre, Madison, WI). The GAL4-hsp70 fragment
                        from the pGaTB vector (Dr. Norbert Perrimon, Harvard University, Boston, MA)
                        was excised by digesting with Not I and Bam HI (Promega), followed by gel
                        purification, and blunt ending. The GAL4-hsp70 fragment was ligated into the
                        blunt ended Kpn I cut pCaSpeR4 vector using the Fast-Link DNA Ligation Kit
                        from Epicentre following manufacturers directions. The resulting product,
                        pERGP (‘Enhancer-Ready Gal4-P element’), contains a unique Not I
                        restriction site 5′ of the GAL4 region, and a unique Eco RI
                        restriction site 3′ of the hsp70 terminator region for the subcloning
                        of enhancer elements into either, or both, unique restriction sites. The
                        3′ Eco RI site may be useful for inclusion of intronic enhancers when
                        generating GAL4 expression constructs.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2g3">
          <title>Generation of the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro construct and transgenics</title>
          <p>Both the purified 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro PCR product and pERGP were digested
                        with Not I and gel purified. Digested pERGP was dephosphorylated using Apex
                        Heat-Labile Alkaline Phosphatase (Epicentre) following manufacturers
                        directions. The 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro promoter fragment was ligated into the
                        Not I site of the pERGP vector using the Fast-Link DNA Ligation Kit
                        following manufacturers directions. The final construct was verified using a
                        panel of restriction enzymes, as well by sequence analysis of the cloning
                        site junctions. Five independent transgenic lines were generated from this
                        final product using the services of BestGene Inc. (Chino Hills, CA).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Generation of the sym-p5-HT<sub>7</sub>-RNAi construct and transgenic
                    lines</title>
        <p>To generate the sym-p5-HT<sub>7</sub>RNAi plasmid, we used the full length
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro cDNA (DGRC #4507) as template for a PCR reaction with
                    the forward primer
                     = 5′-ataagaattcCGCAGGACTTTAATAGCAGTAGC -3′
                    (with the restriction sequence for Eco RI added to the 5′ end of the
                    primer) and the reverse primer
                     = 5′-CTTCTCTTTGGCCAGTTGA - 3′ (Integrated DNA
                    Technologies) using the Expand High Fidelity kit from Roche. The PCR product was
                    digested with BglII and EcoRI (Promega), and the 800 bp fragment was gel
                    purified using the Zymo Gel DNA Recovery Kit (Orange, CA) per the manufacturers
                    instructions.</p>
        <p>The sym-pUAST vector contains two regions, each containing five UAS activating
                    sequences in opposite orientations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Giordano1">[28]</xref> (Gift of Dr. Wendi
                    Neckameyer, St. Louis School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO). The vector was
                    digested with BglII and EcoRI (Promega), and gel purified. Digested sym-pUAST
                    was then dephosphorylated using Apex Heat-Labile Alkaline Phosphatase
                    (Epicentre) following manufacturers directions.</p>
        <p>The prepared 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro cDNA fragment was ligated into the sym-pUAST
                    vector using the Fast-Link DNA Ligation Kit following manufacturers directions.
                    The construct was verified using a panel of restriction enzymes, and by sequence
                    analysis of the cloning site junctions. Independent transgenic lines were
                    generated from this final product using the services of BestGene Inc. (Chino
                    Hills, CA).</p>
        <p>QPCR was performed on the RNA isolated from the heads of F1 crosses and their
                    parentals between the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 and sym-pUAST-5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro
                    flies to determine knockdown efficiency. Total RNA from 20 combined heads was
                    isolated by Tri-Reagent (Molecular Research Center, Cincinnati, OH) following
                    manufacturers protocols. First strand cDNA synthesis was performed using the
                    Improm-II kit from Promega using 0.3 µg total RNA per reaction following
                    manufactures directions using random hexamer primers. Quantitative real-time PCR
                    assays were designed using the Universal ProbeLibrary system (Roche,
                    Indianapolis, IN; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.roche-applied-science.com" xlink:type="simple">https://www.roche-applied-science.com</ext-link>). Amplicon primers and
                    universal probes utilized for the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro mRNA and the reference
                    standard, <italic>ribosomal protein L32</italic> (<italic>RpL32</italic>) mRNA
                    were: RpL32 (U#105) F: <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CGGATCGATATGCTAAGCTGT-3′</named-content>, R:
                    5′--GCGCTTGTTCGATCCGTA-3′; 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro (U#44) F:
                        <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-AATGATTCTGAGGCTCGAAGA-3′</named-content>, R: 5′
                    TATGAGCAACCCAGTGCTGA-3′ QPCR was performed with the BioRad iCycler IQ5
                    (BioRad, Hercules, CA) using the HotStart-IT Probe qPCR Master Mix (USB,
                    Cleveland, OH) following the manufacturers instructions (25 µl reaction
                    volume; cycle parameters: initial 95°C for 2 min, followed by 44 cycles of
                    95°C 15 sec, 60°C 45 sec) in 96 well plate format. Reactions were
                    performed in quadruplicate for each gene and genotype. Expression of
                        <italic>RpL32</italic> was used as the reference control to normalize
                    expression between genotypes. Expression levels were calculated using the
                        ΔΔC<sub>T</sub> method (ABI: User Bulletin #2, ABI Prism 7700
                    Sequence Detection System, 10/2001).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
        <p>Larva and adult brains were dissected in 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.4)
                    and fixed in PLP (2% paraformaldehyde, 75 mM lysine, 10 mM sodium
                    periodate, pH 7.4) for 90 mins, permeabilized in 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer
                    (pH 7.4), with 0.1% saponin and 0.4% NP40 for 30 mins at room
                    temperature, followed by incubation overnight at 4°C with primary antibody
                    in 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.4), with 0.1% saponin and
                    0.4% NP40. The primary antibodies used were rabbit-anti-5-HT
                    (1∶750; Sigma), and mouse-anti-PDF (1∶50; Developmental Studies
                    Hybridoma Bank, Iowa City, Iowa). After three washes in 0.1 M sodium phosphate
                    buffer (pH 7.4), tissues were incubated in secondary antibody for one hour at
                    room temperature. Secondary antibodies used were mouse Alexa 633 conjugated
                    anti-rabbit (1∶750) (Invitrogen), and goat Texas Red conjugated anti-mouse
                    (1∶150) (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA). After staining, brains
                    were washed in 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer for 3×20 min, then cleared
                    through a series of glycerol (25%, 50%, 75%, 90%),
                    and mounted in 90% glycerol. To visualize the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro
                    circuitry in 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-gal4/UAS-mCD8::GFP flies, as well as conjugated
                    secondary antibodies, optical sections of whole brains were acquired on a Leica
                    TCS-SP2 confocal microscope (Leica Microsystems, Exton, PA, USA) at a thickness
                    of 0.25–0.5 µm. For the detailed analysis of serotonin, fruitless
                    and 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression in the central adult brain and ventral
                    nerve cord, 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-gal4/UAS-mCD8::GFP tissues were fixed in
                    4% paraformaldehyde in 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer. After thorough
                    washes in buffer, dissected brains were incubated in a mouse monoclonal antibody
                    to serotonin (Clone 5HT-H209; Dako, Copenhagen, Denmark) at dilution of
                    1∶80. For visualization of the male form of the Fruitless protein,
                        Fru<sup>M</sup>, expression we utilized a rabbit antiserum to
                        Fru<sup>M</sup>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Lee1">[29]</xref>, kindly
                    provided by Dr S. F. Goodwin (Univ. Oxford, UK). This antiserum was applied at a
                    dilution of 1∶2.500 and detected by an Alexa 546-tagged secondary antibody
                    (Invitrogen) diluted to 1∶1000. To visualize the serotonin antiserum, Cy2
                    conjugated goat anti-mouse antiserum (Jackson Immuno Research) was used at a
                    dilution of 1∶1500. To visualize the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro circuitry,
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4/UAS-mCD8::GFP flies were used. Confocal images were
                    collected on a Zeiss laser scanning microscope (LSM 510 META) based on an Zeiss
                    Axiovert S100 microscope with an Argon2/488 nm and HeNe 543 nm lasers. Images
                    were obtained at an optical section thickness of 0.5–0.9 µm,
                    assembled in the Zeiss LSM software and were edited for contrast and brightness
                    in Adobe Photoshop CS3 Extended version 10.0.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>The 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor is expressed in the larval and adult
                    brain</title>
        <p>Heterozygous flies carrying both the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 and UAS-mCD8::GFP
                    constructs were used to examine the expression patterns of the
                    5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 element. GFP expression, representing putative
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro expression, is observed in discreet populations of cells
                    in the hemispheres of the 3<sup>rd</sup> instar larva brain, as well as in
                    neurons in the ventral ganglia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Two independent insertion lines produced identical
                    expression patterns, two produced no expression, and one strain was lost before
                    expressing testing could be completed. The parental homozygous UAS-mCD8::GFP
                    responder strains did not demonstrate any detectable expression (data not
                    shown). To determine if 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro expression is pre- or post-synaptic,
                    immunohistochemistry was performed with anti-serotonin antibodies.
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GFP expression in the larvae brain does not co-localize
                    with anti-5-HT immunoreactivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g002">Figure 2</xref>), indicating postsynaptic expression in the larva.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0020800-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression in the brain of third instar
                            larva.</title>
            <p>5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 driven expression of GFP (green) is detected in
                            distinct circuits within the brain of wandering third instar larva as
                            well as in the ventral ganglia. Antisera to 5-HT detected with secondary
                            antibodies conjugated to alexafluor 568 (magenta) highlights the
                            presynaptic serotonergic circuitry. No overlap indicates that
                                5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression is postsynaptic.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In the adult brain, 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GFP is expressed at high levels in
                    large-field R neurons that innervate the ellipsoid body, and within discreet
                    populations of cells between the central brain and the optic lobes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). The location of
                    the small cluster of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-mCD8 expressing cells between the
                    central brain and the optic lobe are reminiscent of the location of PDF (peptide
                    dispersing factor)-expressing sLNvs and lLNvs described in Helfrich-Forster
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-HelfrichForster1">[30]</xref> that are members of the circadian clock circuitry. To
                    determine if these are indeed PDF-expressing clock neurons, we co-stained with
                    anti-PDF antibodies, and revealed that whereas 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4
                    expressing neurons are not the PDF neurons, they tightly cluster with the
                    PDF-expressing cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g003">Figure
                        3A</xref> inset). This clustering suggests that 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro neurons
                    may modulate or influence the function of the PDF-positive LNvs, and may have a
                    role in circadian behaviors. A close inspection of the cluster of large-field R
                    neurons within the central complex reveals 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression
                    in greater than 40 large neurons of each cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). Their neurites run in a tract to
                    the lateral triangle and thereafter to the ellipsoid body. Previously described
                    ring neurons have their cell bodies in this area <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Renn1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Young1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Hanesch1">[33]</xref>. Interestingly, as
                    exemplified by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g003">Figure 3B</xref>, we
                    detect more large-field R neurons per cluster than previously reported (∼48
                    per cluster). Previous studies utilizing GAL4 drivers to highlight various
                    subpopulations of large-field R neurons have only indicated the presence of
                    38–40 neurons per cluster <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Renn1">[31]</xref>. Our results suggest that not only does the
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 driver likely express in all known large-field
                    R-neurons, but that there may be additional yet to be defined subpopulations of
                    neurons within the clusters. Very weak 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-Gal4 expression in
                    the upper region of the fan-shaped body, but not in other substructures of the
                    central complex, was also detected (not shown).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0020800-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression in the adult brain.</title>
            <p>A) Expression of the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 driver is highly localized
                            to large field R-neurons of the ellipsoid body. There are additional
                            groups of cells that cluster with, but do not express peptide dispersal
                            factor (PDF, magenta), between the central brain and the optic lobes
                            (inset). B) High resolution cross-eyed stereo view of a typical cluster
                            of large field R-neurons expressing 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4. This
                            particular cluster consists of 48 large-field R neurons that express the
                            driver. (EB ellipsoid body; LTR  =  lateral
                            triangle, CB  =  cell bodies; ATL
                             =  antennal lobe).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We performed serotonin-immunolabeling on brains of adult flies expressing
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 driven GFP to study spatial relations between
                    ligand and receptor. Whereas the distribution of serotonin-immunoreactive
                    neuronal processes is abundant throughout most of the major brain neuropils,
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 mediated GFP expression is most prominent in part
                    of the central complex and in the antennal lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g004">Figure 4A</xref>i). In the central complex
                    serotonin-immunoreactive processes can be seen in the fan-shaped body and
                    ellipsoid body, as well as in the lateral triangles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g004">Figure 4Aii</xref>). Both serotonin-immunolabeling
                    and 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression is seen in the anterior and posterior
                    rings of the ellipsoid body and in the lateral triangles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The neural processes seen with the
                    two markers are clearly superimposed in these regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g004">Figure 4Biii</xref>). Again, the receptor appears to
                    be postsynaptic, since the R-neurons do not display serotonin-immunoreactivity
                        (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0020800.s001">Figure
                        S1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0020800-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Distribution of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression and serotonin in
                            adult Drosophila brain.</title>
            <p>Ai) Within the ellipsoid body (EB) of the central complex, the innermost
                            and outermost rings display 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression (green).
                            The lateral triangles (LTR) of the central complex also display GFP.
                            Expression is also seen more ventrally in antennal lobe neurons. Aii)
                            Serotonin-immunoreactive neuron processes highlight the presence of 5-HT
                            in the innermost and outermost rings of the EB as well as the lateral
                            triangles and antennal lobes (magenta). Bi) Close up view of
                                5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression in the central EB. Bii) The same
                            field as in Bi showing serotonin-immunoreactive neuron processes
                            (magenta). Biii) Merge of Bi and Bii. Note the prominent superposition
                            of receptor and serotonin distribution in the two rings of the EB and in
                            the LTR. Ci-Ciii) Distribution of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression
                            and serotonin-immunoreactivity in antennal lobes (AL). The receptor is
                            seen in select glomeruli of the lobes (Ci), whereas serotonin is
                            distributed in varicose processes throughout the lobes (Cii). The arrow
                            indicates the cell body of the left serotonergic antennal lobe
                            interneuron. The merged channels are seen in Ciii.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Two large centrifugal neurons with processes in most of the glomeruli of the
                    antennal lobe are known to produce serotonin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Dacks1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Roy1">[35]</xref>. Comparing serotonin
                    immunolabeling with 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression, GFP is observed in
                    select glomeruli, whereas the serotonergic neurons arborize in most, if not all
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>). As seen in
                        <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0020800.s001">Fig S1
                        B</xref> the large cell bodies of the serotonergic antennal lobe neurons do
                    not coexpress 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4. This GAL4 expression in the antennal
                    lobes is weak, but enhancement of the GFP signal reveals a large interneuron in
                    each hemisphere that supply branches to the glomeruli that is distinct from the
                    serotonergic interneuron (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0020800.s001">Fig. S1 C, D</xref>). In general, serotonergic
                    processes are far more abundantly distributed than those of the
                    5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expressing neurons, suggesting that serotonin acts via
                    other 5-HT receptors in most parts of the brain.</p>
        <p>Expression of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 is also detected in several neurons in the
                    ventral ganglion of the adult. The Gal4-driven GFP was seen in paired neurons in
                    all thoracic and abdominal neuromeres of the ganglion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g005">Fig. 5A, B</xref>). In each of the meso and
                    metathoracic neuromeres there are two pair of neurons with large lateral cell
                    bodies displaying GFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g005">Fig.
                        5A</xref>, Di). Neurons with smaller cell bodies were detected more medially
                    in each neuromere. In abdominal neuromeres larger and smaller
                    5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-expressing cell bodies were distributed without a strict
                    segmental organization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g005">Fig. 5A,
                        E</xref>). Altogether we could detect approximately 40 neuronal cell bodies
                    in the thoracic neuromeres and about 30 in the abdominal. GFP labeled neuronal
                    processes were seen in neuropil of the different neuromeres, some were organized
                    in distinct tracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g005">Fig.
                    5B</xref>). By applying antiserum to serotonin to 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4-GFP
                    expressing ganglia we could show that the two markers are not colocalized in any
                    neuron (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g005">Fig. 5D, E</xref>),
                    suggesting post-synaptic distribution of the receptor. The
                    serotonin-immunoreactive processes are very abundant in thoracic and abdominal
                    neuropils (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>) and
                    double labeling revealed superposition of these and the branches of
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4-expressing neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g005">Fig. 5D, E</xref>). Because of the potential role of
                    the receptor in courtship, as described next, we also examined
                    5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression in relation to the male form of Fruitless
                        (Fru<sup>M</sup>), a key protein involved in sexual behaviors. We did not
                    detect any colocalization between 5-HT<sub>7</sub>-GAL4 and Fru<sup>M</sup>
                    expression in the ventral nerve cord of adult flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0020800.s002">Figure S2</xref>).
                    This is the region where it was shown previously that a small population of
                    abdominal serotoninergic neurons co-express Fru<sup>M</sup>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Billeter1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Lee2">[37]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0020800-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Distribution of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression and serotonin in
                            adult Drosophila ventral nerve cord.</title>
            <p>Anterior is up in all panels and scale bar applies to all. GFP-expression
                            is shown in green and serotonin-immunolabeling in magenta. A) Overview
                            of ventral nerve cord with segmental distribution of
                            5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4-expressing neurons in pro-, meso- and
                            metathoracic and abdominal (Abd) neuromeres. Note the large lateral cell
                            bodies in meso- and metathoracic neuromeres. B) Different optical
                            section plane of pro- and anterior mesothoracic neuromeres. Note tracts
                            of GFP-labeled neuronal processes. C) Very dense distribution of
                            serotonin-immunoreactive processes in abdominal neuromeres. Di-iii) A
                            sagital view of the metathoracic and abdominal neuromeres with receptor
                            and serotonin distribution. Note that markers are not colocalized in any
                            neuronal structures, suggesting postsynaptic distribution of the
                                5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro. However, processes of the two types of neurons
                            superimpose in neuropil regions. At arrows: ant, anterior and d, dorsal.
                            Ei-iii) Horizontal views of the same neuromeres. No colocalized markers
                            can be detected, but overlap between fibers. At arrows: a, anterior and
                            lat, lateral.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor activity is essential for normal courtship and
                    mating behavior</title>
        <p>In Drosophila, complex behaviors such as learning and memory, aggression,
                    locomotor reactivity, circadian rhythm, olfaction, and sleep are mediated by
                    higher brain centers such as the mushroom body, ellipsoid body, and central
                    complex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-HelfrichForster1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-HelfrichForster2">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Rollmann1">[39]</xref>. The
                    mushroom body has been implicated in Drosophila courtship and mating behavior
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Fleischmann1">[40]</xref>,
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Popov1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Yamamoto1">[42]</xref>, however,
                    the precise role of the ellipsoid body, and other components of the central
                    complex has yet to be explored.</p>
        <p>The effects of the 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor antagonist, SB258719 (SB), on
                    courtship behavior were assessed after maintaining flies for five days on food
                    containing various amounts of drug ranging from 0.01 mM to 3.0 mM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figures 6 A-L</xref>). SB258719 is
                    approximately 100 fold more selective for the 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor than
                    other 5-HT receptors in mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Thomas2">[43]</xref>, however the specificity for the drug at Drosophila
                    receptors has not yet been defined. Courtship pairs were assayed for orient
                    latency, wing vibration latency, lick latency, curl latency, copulation
                    attempts, copulation latency, and copulation duration, as well as frequencies
                    for each behavior. Whereas the frequencies of behaviors were observed to
                    generally decrease with increasing drug, the latencies of flies still performing
                    a particular behavior at any given drug level were not significantly different
                    from that of controls with the exception of wing song and licking latencies at
                    3.0 mM SB, which were about double that of control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6 B, C</xref>). All pairs for a given
                    treatment exhibited normal orienting behavior except for pairs fed 3.0 mM SB,
                    where only 8 of 10 pairs exhibited this behavior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6H</xref>). All pairs also demonstrated wing
                    vibration at all drug levels except for 1.0 and 3.0 mM SB fed pairs, where only
                    8 of 10 pairs exhibited this behavior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6I</xref>). These relatively normal early
                    behaviors of courtship in flies fed higher levels of SB indicate that sensory
                    processes are not likely being disrupted by the SB antagonist. If they were, the
                    fly would not be expected to perform normally behaviors that rely upon visual,
                    auditory, taste, or olfactory sensory cues.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0020800-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro modulates courtship and mating.</title>
            <p>Mating pairs fed increasing amounts of the antagonist SB285719 (black
                            bars) were observed for ten minutes to assay the latency of orient, wing
                            vibration, licking, and curling (A, B, C, D, F), the number of
                            copulation attempts (E), the duration of copulation (G), and the
                            frequency at which each behavior occurs (H-L). The latencies of
                            SB-treated flies performing a specific behavior did not differ
                            significantly from untreated controls (gray bars) with increasing drug
                            doses (A, B, C, D, F) with the exception of curling and licking at 3 mM.
                            The number or copulation attempts (E) were significantly decreased at
                            doses above 0.7 mM, while the frequency of attempted copulations
                            decreased with doses above 0.05 mM. Whereas flies fed doses of SB
                            greater than 0.07 mM did not successfully copulate (F, L), the duration
                            of successful copulations at lower doses did not differ from controls
                            (G). (n = 10 pairs observed for each behavior;
                            * p&lt;0.01, ANOVA with Dunnett's post hoc test for multiple
                            comparison; φ = No successful copulation). M)
                            Wild-type OR male flies were loaded into the DAMS monitoring system and
                            maintained on 10% sucrose, 1% agarose (gray bar) or the
                            same medium supplemented with 3 mM SB (Black bars). Locomotion was
                            measured by counting the total number of beam breaks in a 24 hour
                            period. Number of beam breaks per hour were counted and averaged over a
                            three-day period. SB-treated flies exhibited only a slight increase in
                            levels of activity compared to control flies.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Decreases in licking frequency were observed at levels greater than 0.5 mM SB,
                    with an IC<sub>50</sub> = 0.47 mM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6J</xref>). The number of copulation attempts
                    were significantly reduced in pairs treated with 0.7, 1.0, and 3.0 mM drug
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6E</xref>), and the
                    frequency at which this behavior occurred decreased at drug concentrations
                    greater than 0.05 mM with an IC<sub>50</sub> = 0.47 mM
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6L</xref>). Remarkably,
                    only flies fed drug at or below 0.07 mM successfully copulated, with an
                        IC<sub>50</sub> = 0.05 mM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6L</xref>). The latencies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6F</xref>) and durations
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6G</xref>) of the few
                    pairs of flies that successfully copulated were not significantly different from
                    that of controls, however, these behaviors were observed in fewer pairs as drug
                    concentrations were increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6L</xref>). To determine if the observed effects of the SB drug were
                    simply due to drug-induced decreases in activity levels, general activity was
                    measured using the Trikinetics DAMS system. SB treated flies were observed to be
                    only slightly more active than untreated control flies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g006">Figure 6M</xref>).</p>
        <p>To determine if the observed impairments in mating behavior in SB treated flies
                    were due to dysfunction in the male, the female, or both, SB fed females were
                    paired with control males, and SB fed males and control females were paired. We
                    chose a dose of 3.0 mM to test, because this dose produced a maximal effect
                    across all behaviors. In the SB female and control male pairs, orient, wing
                    vibration, and lick, latencies were significantly increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g007">Figures 7 A–4C</xref>).
                    Interestingly, curl latencies were significantly reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g007">Figure 7D</xref>). Copulation attempts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g007">Figure 7E</xref>) were also
                    significantly reduced in these pairs. The frequencies at which these behaviors
                    were observed decreased as well compared to control (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020800-t001">Table 1</xref>). Whereas orient and wing vibration
                    frequencies were only slightly decreased, curl and copulation frequencies were
                    dramatically reduced or eliminated.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0020800-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro influences mating behaviors in both male and
                            female Drosophila.</title>
            <p>Courtship rituals were observed in pairs where either the female (SB-F,
                            white bars) or male (SB-M, black bars) were fed 3mM of the antagonist
                            SB285719 and paired with an untreated partner. Pairs consisting of two
                            untreated flies were used as controls (Gray bars). The time it took for
                            the pairs to perform the courtship behaviors and copulation, the number
                            of copulation attempts and the duration of copulations were measured. In
                            pairs with SB-treated females and untreated males, orient, wing
                            vibration and lick latency (A, B, C) were increased while curl latency
                            (D) was decreased. Pairs with an SB-treated male and untreated male
                            differed significantly only in curl latency (D). The number of
                            copulation attempts was significantly decreased for both experimental
                            sets and neither exhibited any successful copulation (F). Frequencies of
                            courtship behaviors and copulations are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020800-t001">Table 1</xref>. (n = 10
                            pairs observed for each behavior; *p&lt;0.01, ANOVA with Bonferroni
                            post hoc test for multiple comparison; φ = No
                            successful copulation)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0020800-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>The frequency of courtship behaviors between SB-treated flies and
                            untreated flies.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0020800-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Behavior</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SB-F</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SB-M</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orientation</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wing Vibration</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20% *</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Licking</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20% *</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Curling</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20% *</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20% *</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Successful Copulations</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0% *</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0% *</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>The frequency of courtship behaviors and successful copulations was
                                measured in pairs where either the male (SB–M) or female
                                (SB–F) was fed 3.0 mM of the antagonist and paired with an
                                untreated partner. The frequency of all early courtship behaviors
                                (orient and wing vibrations) was reduced only slightly, but later
                                behaviors (licking, curling and copulation attempts) was
                                significantly decreased in these pairs when compared to untreated
                                control flies. In both experimental sets, successful copulation was
                                never observed. (n = 10 observed pairs for each
                                behavior, *p&lt;0.001 by Fischer's Exact test).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>In experiments paring SB males and control females, orient, wing vibration, and
                    lick latencies were not statistically different from control pairs. Curl latency
                    was significantly reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g007">Figure
                        7D</xref>), and copulation attempts were significantly and dramatically
                    reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g007">Figure 7E</xref>). These
                    pairings, as with the SB female + control pairings, did not successfully
                    copulate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g007">Figures
                    7F–G</xref>). Together, these data indicate that 5-HT<sub>7</sub>
                    receptors may serve to modulate courtship and mating behaviors in both male and
                    females flies. There were some differences observed between these experiments
                    where only one fly was fed SB, and those where both the male and female have
                    been maintained on drug. Specifically, the performance of the SB male flies in
                    the SB male + control were reduced compared to the results of pairs where
                    both flies were exposed to drug. This could be due to differences in the
                    dynamics of the interactions between the male and female when only one partner
                    has been exposed to drug. For example, when both partners have been exposed, the
                    general lack of interest in courtship parallel each other, but there was no
                    active avoidance of one fly from the other. In contrast, when only the males
                    have been exposed, the males were never interested in the females, and tended to
                    stay clear of the females, and generally were never in the same vicinity of the
                    females. Furthermore, there were some instances where the females seemed to seek
                    the male and the male would run away from the female. When only the female was
                    exposed to drug, the male vigorously attempted to court. Whereas these female
                    did not exhibit overtly obvious actions to reject the male, such us wing
                    flicking, they generally avoided contact with the male.</p>
        <p>Serotonin has previously been implicated in courtship behaviors, specifically
                    male-male courtship. For example, ectopic expression of the <italic>white
                            (w<sup>+</sup>)</italic> gene, which encodes for the transporter
                    for tryptophan (the metabolic precursor for serotonin) has been shown to lead to
                    inter-male courtship <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Zhang1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Hing1">[45]</xref>. To determine if SB treatment affected male-male
                    courtship, in addition to normal male-female courtship, we examined interactions
                    between pairs of males fed SB. Control pairs only exhibited minimal male-male
                    courtship behaviors (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0020800.s002">Figure S2</xref>). No significant changes in the
                    courtship index (CI; the time engaged in all courtship behaviors divided by the
                    total time of the assay) in SB-treated males in comparison to untreated controls
                    were detected (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0020800.s003">Figure S3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>General olfaction is not altered by drug treatment</title>
        <p>We did observe moderate expression of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 GFP in the
                    antennal lobes of the adult brain. To ensure that the deficits in courtship and
                    mating induced by SB treatment were not simply due to general problems with
                    olfaction induced by the receptor antagonist, flies were checked for olfactory
                    avoidance and sensitivity using different concentrations of the odors
                    methylcyclohexanol (MCH) and benzaldehyde (BA). The SB treated flies had
                    performance indices equivalent to control flies at all concentrations of odor,
                    indicating that SB258719 does not impair general olfaction, or sensitivity to
                    odors (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020800-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0020800-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>The 5-HT<sub>7</sub> specific antagonist SB258719 does not affect
                            olfaction.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0020800-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCH</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control PI</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SB PI</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1∶1000</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47±2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41±1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1∶750</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49±3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47±2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1∶250</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59±7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55±1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1∶100</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83±3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79±4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BA</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1∶1000</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42±3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41±1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1∶750</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43±4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45±7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1∶250</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47±3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47±5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1∶100</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71±4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71±3</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>Untreated and SB-treated (3.0 mM) flies were assayed for olfactory
                                avoidance and sensitivity at different concentrations of the odors
                                methylcyclohexanhol (MCH) and benzaldehyde (BA). The performance
                                indices (PI) of the SB-treated flies are equivalent to control flies
                                at all concentrations.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>The effects of genetic knock-down of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro mRNA by RNAi are
                    consistent with the results of pharmacological studies</title>
        <p>Pharmacological and genetic knockdown experiments can provide complementary data
                    regarding the function of a receptor. With pharmacological studies we have
                    measured the effect of different levels of inactivation using different doses of
                    antagonist to show that 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor function is potentially
                    required more at the later stages of courtship than the earlier stages. In order
                    to validate our pharmacological results, we created a UAS-dsRNA strain to knock
                    down 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro mRNA expression. Quantitative RT-PCR was performed to
                    examine the levels of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro transcript in F1 flies carrying both
                    the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 and the UAS-sym-p5-HT<sub>7</sub>RNAi. Flies
                    carrying both transgenes show an approximately 80% decrease in transcript
                    levels when compared to flies carrying only one trangene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g008">Figure 8</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0020800-g008" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g008</object-id>
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>dsRNAi construct effectively reduces 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro transcript
                            levels.</title>
            <p>RNA from the heads of male flies carrying either the
                                sym-p5-HT<sub>7</sub>RNAi (white box), the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4
                            (gray box), or both (F1, black box) transgenes was used in quantitative
                            real-time PCR to examine 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro gene expression. Flies
                            carrying both transcripts show an approximately 80% decrease in
                                5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro transcript levels. Reactions were performed in
                            quadruplicate for each gene. <italic>RpL32</italic> expression was used
                            as the reference control to normalize expression between treatment
                            groups (Error bars indicate SEM).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>If the pharmacological agents (e.g. the SB antagonists) were specifically acting
                    at 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptors, as anticipated, then knockdown of
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro mRNA in putative 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro expressing cells
                    would be anticipated to recapitulate major aspects of the behavioral phenotypes
                    of the antagonist. Indeed, expression of double-stranded 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro
                    mRNA in cells defined by our 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 driver produced courting
                    and mating deficits consistent with the antagonist studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g009">Figure 9</xref>). Early behaviors like orienting and
                    wing vibration were not significantly affected, whereas later behaviors like
                    curling and copulation attempts were significantly reduced, with later events
                    like successful copulation events even eliminated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g009">Figure 9</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020800-t003">Table 3</xref>). To ensure that these decreases in
                    courtship were not due to decreased activity, the activity levels of flies
                    carrying either one or both of the transgenes were measured. The F1 flies with
                    both transgenes were found to be slightly more active than the
                    5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 insertion strain, but not the ds-RNA-UAS parental
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020800-g009">Figure 9C</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0020800-g009" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g009</object-id>
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro knock-down results are consistent with
                            pharmacological studies.</title>
            <p>A) The average latencies of courtship behaviors for flies that performed
                            those behaviors are shown. Transgenic F1 lines expressing
                                5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro double stranded RNA under the control of the
                                5-HT<sub>7</sub> Dro-GAL4 promoter (black bars) exhibit increased
                            licking and curling latencies, and did not copulate
                            (φ = no successful copulation; *
                            p&lt;0.01; **p&lt;0.001; two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post hoc
                            analysis). B) The average number of copulation attempts per mating pair
                            are significantly decreased in the F1 knockdowns compared to the
                            parental strains (n = 10 pairs observed per
                            behavior; * p&lt;0.01; one-way ANOVA with Tukey post hoc analysis).
                            C) The activity of male flies carrying either the
                            5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 element (GAL4, white bar), the
                                UAS-sym-p5-HT<sub>7</sub>RNAi element (UAS-RNAi, black bar), or both
                            (F1, gray bar) was measured using the DAMS system for five days. The
                            average daily count of beam breaks per 24 hours is slightly increased in
                            the F1 flies with respect to the GAL4 driver parental strain (*),
                            but there is no significant increase in activity when compared with the
                            UAS-RNAi parental. (n = 16 flies; * p&lt;0.05;
                            one-way ANOVA with Tukey post hoc analysis).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.g009" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0020800-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
            <title>5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro knock-down decreases frequency of courtship
                            behaviors.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0020800-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Behavior</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gal4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UAS</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F1</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orientation</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wing Vibration</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Licking</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20% *</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Curling</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20% *</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Successful Copulations</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0% *</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label/>
              <p>The frequency of courtship behaviors was measured in transgenic F1
                                lines expressing the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>-dsRNA under control of the
                                    5-HT<sub>7</sub>-gal4 promoter (F1). When compared with the
                                parental lines 5-HT<sub>7</sub>-Gal4 (Gal4) and
                                    UAS-sym-5-HT<sub>7</sub>-dsRNA (UAS), the frequency of licking,
                                curling and copulation attempts was significantly decreased. In the
                                F1 lines, flies were not observed to successfully copulate.
                                (n = 10 observed pairs for each behavior,
                                p&lt;0.001 by Fischer's Exact test).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>If either the GAL4 driver strain was not a valid representation of
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro expression, or the SB antagonist was not acting at this
                    receptor to inhibit courtship and mating, or the RNAi studies were producing
                    their effects through off target effects or not producing efficient knockdown,
                    expression of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro double stranded RNA to produce RNA
                    interference within the circuits defined by our 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 driver
                    would not produce behavioral effects consistent with the pharmacological
                    studies. Therefore, we believe that these methods cross validate each other, as
                    well as the driver strain, to demonstrate that we are indeed examining
                        5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor function within the brain.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>To explore the role of the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor in the fly, we have created
                an enhancer GAL4 driver strain and used it to characterized the putative CNS
                expression and function of the receptor. Using our 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 driver
                to drive expression of a UAS-mCD8::GFP transgene, we have found GFP expression in
                third larval instar brain localized to discreet circuits within the brain
                hemispheres, as well as to specific neurons in the ventral ganglion. In the adult
                brain, there is a high level of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression in large-field R
                neurons that innervate the ellipsoid body, as well as in neurons in the brain that
                tightly cluster with the PDF-positive LNv clock neurons and innervate the optic
                lobes. There is moderate expression detected in the olfactory and gustatory regions
                of the brain, and weak expression in other central complex structures like the fan
                shaped body. 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression appears to be post-synaptic both in
                larvae and adults. This is consistent with the observed post-synaptic expression for
                the 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor in vertebrate CNS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Neumaier1">[4]</xref>. In the ventral nerve cord,
                expression is detected in several sets of postsynaptic neurons and in all neuromeres
                of the fused ganglion. Importantly, there is a close apposition between
                receptor-expressing processes and those containing serotonin. Although a majority of
                GAL4 driver strains present relevant/accurate expression data of the intended gene
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Bellen1">[46]</xref>, It
                should be emphasized here that 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 enhancer expression may not
                represent the entire expression pattern of the native 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor,
                or may be even expressing in cells that do not express the native receptor. It
                should also be emphasized that the mCD8:GFP construct we used in this study to
                examine expression is a membrane-bound form of the GFP protein that highlights all
                cellular membranes. Whereas the GFP expression patterns observed here provide clues
                as to the cells and structures that express the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 element, it
                is unable to provide information regarding the subcellular localization of the GPCR
                on the cellular membrane. Unfortunately, our attempts to generate anti-sera to
                    5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro for further validation of native protein expression were
                unsuccessful.</p>
      <p>Treatment with the 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor antagonist SB258719 interferes with
                courtship and mating behaviors. Interestingly, the IC<sub>50</sub> values for
                inhibition of courtship behavior frequency decreases as the courtship and mating
                process progresses from hardly any disruptive effect with respect to early behaviors
                involving sensory cues (orient and wing vibration), to more pronounced effects for
                intermediate behaviors (licking, curling, attempts), to complete loss of successful
                copulation at higher levels of the drug. In corroboration with the pharmacological
                studies, knockdown of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro message within 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4
                expressing neurons produces behavioral changes consistent with our pharmacological
                results. The early behaviors of orientation and wing song are not affected much, the
                intermediate behaviors of licking and curling are significantly disrupted, and
                successful copulation is eliminated. There are some subtle differences between
                methods, however, like for curling latencies, which could be due to the nature of
                receptor inactivation (more acute pharmacological methods <italic>vs</italic>.
                constitutive nature of the RNAi knockdown).</p>
      <p>From our results, there appears to be little 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor involvement
                in the early stages, where we observed that antagonist treated males are receptive
                to females present in the mating chamber, and are able to initiate the first
                elements of the mating process. During the intermediate stages, involving licking
                and curling, there is likely more involvement of 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor
                signaling. A decrease in licking behavior may result in decreased curling, and
                decreased curling may result in decreased successful copulation attempts, with the
                effects compounding at each successive behavior leading to an overall failure at
                successful copulation. These effects could arise from alterations in physical
                performance and coordination, sensory perception, olfaction, or to decreases in
                receptivity or interest, or a lack of ‘motivation’ to perform the higher
                intensity physical behaviors. We believe these effects are not due to deficits in
                overt locomotor activity because the drug treated flies demonstrate normal levels of
                measured activity, or in coordination because at drug levels where mating frequency
                is decreased the flies that do perform, perform well with latencies not
                significantly different than control pairs. General alteration of sensory perception
                is also not a likely reason because males recognize females and readily perform
                behaviors related to visual and acoustic cues (orienting and wing vibration) despite
                administration of antagonist or knockdown of message. Whereas olfaction is necessary
                for receptivity, it is unlikely impeded following antagonist administration because
                flies fed 3 mM SB as well as the knockdown flies exhibit normal aversion and
                sensitivity to odors in olfactory tests. Nevertheless, there still may be an
                olfactory or pheromone component if the limited 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression
                detected in the olfactory lobes correlates with select neurons necessary for
                reception of specific courtship related pheromones, or the expression does not
                correlate appropriately with native 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro expression and localization
                in the olfactory lobes.</p>
      <p>A key gene known to be significantly involved in courtship behaviors is
                    <italic>fruitless</italic> (<italic>fru</italic>), where almost every stage of
                the mating process has been shown to be disrupted by certain alleles of the locus
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Villella1">[47]</xref>. With
                the exception of one <italic>fru</italic> allele, <italic>satori,</italic> where
                males exclusively courts males, <italic>fru</italic> mutants indiscriminately court
                both males and females <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Billeter2">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Ito1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Yamamoto2">[50]</xref>. In Drosophila, there are also several other known
                mutants that rarely court females or males. These include <italic>he's not
                    interested</italic> (<italic>hni</italic>), <italic>tapered</italic>
                    (<italic>ta</italic>), <italic>pale</italic>, <italic>cuckold</italic>
                    (<italic>cuc</italic>) and <italic>courtless</italic> (<italic>crl</italic>)
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Yamamoto3">[51]</xref>. Two of
                these genes have been characterized: <italic>courtless</italic> encodes a
                ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme that is also involved in spermatogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Orgad1">[52]</xref>, and
                    <italic>pale</italic> encodes a tyrosine hydroxylase that catalyzes the
                synthesis of dopamine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Buchner1">[53]</xref>. In our experiments with both the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>
                receptor antagonist and the RNAi knockdown, male flies displayed a general
                disinterest in mating with either females or other males, and females appeared
                non-responsive to male courtship attempts.</p>
      <p>Ectopic expression of the <italic>white</italic> gene, which encodes for the
                transporter for the biosynthetic precursor of serotonin, tryptophan, can induce
                inter-male courtship <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Zhang1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Hing1">[45]</xref>. These observations, along with others, suggested that
                serotonin may be involved in courtship in the fly (interestingly, alterations in
                5-HT levels have been shown to elicit homosexual behavior in mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Fratta1">[54]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Gessa1">[55]</xref>). In early
                studies examining co-expression of the male-specific Fru<sup>M</sup> protein and
                5-HT, it was found that in wild-type males there were no 5-HT CNS neurons that
                co-expressed Fru<sup>M</sup>, with the exception of a small cluster of serotonergic
                cells at the posterior tip of the ventral nerve cord <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Lee2">[37]</xref>. The possibility, however, still
                remained that perhaps Fru<sup>M</sup> expression was mediating the effects of
                serotonin postsynaptically. Our results have shown there is no overlap between
                    Fru<sup>M</sup> and 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression. Therefore, it would
                appear that 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro and Fru<sup>M</sup> do not directly interact in
                their modulation and control of courtship and mating behaviors.</p>
      <p>What then is the role that 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor signaling plays in reducing
                receptivity at each stage? One possibility is that pheromone release from the female
                may be disrupted, resulting in a decrease of courtship. We believe that this is
                unlikely, however, because control males paired with SB fed females continue to
                attempt copulation with SB fed females that are not receptive, and will continually
                chase these females in the mating chamber, which remain uninterested despite
                repeated attempts by the males. Furthermore, when males fed SB were paired with
                control females, we often observed females that seemed to seek out the male, which
                would then run away from the female. Therefore, it would appear that because the
                control fly of the pair seeks out and attempts to initiate courtship behaviors, SB
                treatment and manipulation of 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor function does not interfere
                with pheromone release, or potentially other sensory cues, related to receptivity.
                If the default behavior is to initiate courtship in the absence of pheromones,
                however, then it may still be possible that SB is interfering with pheromone
                reception at later stages if they are required for the maintenance and
                intensification of courtship. In the SB/control pairing experiments, the SB fed male
                + control female pairs were the least successful at courtship behavior. One
                interpretation of these results are that males are essential to initiating certain
                elements of mating that are regulated by 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptor function, and
                when these do not occur it may contribute to further lack of receptivity by females.
                Alternatively, males and females may be only responding to the SB drug
                differently.</p>
      <p>Because of the high level of expression of the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 driver in the
                large-field R field neurons that innervate the ellipsoid body, we hypothesize that
                receptor expression in these neurons is relevant for normal courtship and mating.
                Furthermore, that the 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptors expressed by these neurons regulate
                receptivity/interest of one fly for its partner. Little is known regarding the exact
                function of the ellipsoid body, and the neurons that feed into it. The overall
                structure is believed to be involved in mediating higher order behaviors, including
                aspects of learning and memory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Neuser1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Wang1">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Wu1">[58]</xref>, stress response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Neckameyer2">[59]</xref>, flight control <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Ilius1">[60]</xref>, and gravitaxis
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Baker1">[61]</xref>. It is
                comprised of many distinct cell types and individual circuits including 10 types of
                small field neurons, and 4 known major types of large-field R neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Renn1">[31]</xref>. Previous reports
                have indicated that there are about 40 large-field R neurons in each of two clusters
                in the central brain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Renn1">[31]</xref>, and based upon the number of large-field R neurons that
                we detect 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 GFP expression in, there may be nearly 50,
                suggesting that there are additional subtypes of this neuron beyond those already
                identified. Significantly, 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 may be the first GAL4 driver
                line reported that predominantly and strongly drives expression in the putative full
                set of large-field R neurons within the central brain, and as such may be a valuable
                strain to use to define the functional role of these cells and the development of
                ellipsoid body circuits. A subset, the R4m neurons, are cholinergic and express NMDA
                receptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Wu1">[58]</xref>. It
                remains to be seen which of the major subsets of large-field R neurons contribute to
                courtship and mating behaviors. Although we hypothesize that it is the ellipsoid
                body mediating courtship behaviors, it is entirely possible that other neurons that
                are weakly expressing 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4, or neurons perhaps not expressing
                the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 element in the brain, are contributing to or completely
                mediating these observed effect on courtship and mating.</p>
      <p>Courtship and mating has been shown by others to involve additional neurotransmitter
                systems including dopamine, which has been shown to play a role in both female
                receptivity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Neckameyer1">[24]</xref> as well as male-male courtship <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Liu1">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Liu2">[63]</xref>, and GABA, which also plays a role
                in female receptivity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Sakai1">[64]</xref>. Various brain structures including the mushroom bodies,
                protocerebrum, and optic lobes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Villella1">[47]</xref> have also been shown to be involved in courtship and
                mating in the fly. With regards to courtship and mating, the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro
                circuitry, the ellipsoid body, or both, may be essential to the integration and
                processing of information received from the various sensory stimuli to correctly
                initiate physical courtship behaviors. Significantly, proper function of
                Gαs-coupled 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor signaling within these neurons may also
                be essential to this process. Interestingly, 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptors have also
                been implicated in the regulation of mammalian sexual behavior, although the
                response is reverse to that in flies. Blockade of this receptor with antagonist in
                female rats increases lordosis activity, and the authors of the study hypothesize
                that in mammals 5-HT<sub>7</sub> receptors exert a tonic inhibitory effect on female
                sexual behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020800-Siddiqui1">[15]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In summary, we have generated a 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 reporter and have used it to
                characterize the putative expression of the 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro receptor, and find
                it highly expressed in the brain in large-field R neurons in the adult, as well as
                in small groups of cells that cluster with PDF-positive LNvs neurons. Functional
                studies utilizing pharmacological and genetic methods indicate that this receptor is
                necessary for normal courtship and mating.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0020800.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression in relation to
                            serotonin-immunoreactive neurons</bold>. Ai and Aii. The cell bodies
                        (cb) of the R-neurons express the reporter, but not serotonin (at arrow).
                        Bii and Bii. The large serotonergic neurons of the antennal lobes (arrows in
                        Bii) do not express the reporter. C. One neuron in each antennal lobe
                        displays 5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression (arrow). Di and Dii. This
                        neuron does not produce serotonin, as seen in this double labeling. AL,
                        antennal lobe.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0020800.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Distribution of male form of Fruitless (Fru<sup>M</sup>) and
                                5-HT<sub>7</sub>Dro-GAL4 expression in adult ventral nerve
                            cord</bold>. Gal4-expression is shown in green and Fru<sup>M</sup>
                        imunolabeling in magenta in these horizontal views of the ganglion (anterior
                        is up in all panels and the scale bar applies to all panels, except 5iv
                        which is a slight enlargement). Ai-iii) No colocalization of Fru<sup>M</sup>
                        and GFP in neurons of the pro- and mesothoracic neuromeres. Bi-iv) No
                        colocalization of markers in meso- and metathoracic neuromeres. Some neurons
                        appear white (in boxed area) due to superposition in this projection of
                        about 12 sections. In panel Biv we show two optical sections in the boxed
                        area to visualize that neurons do not coexpress markers. C) Also in
                        abdominal neuromeres the two labels are not coexpressed.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0020800.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020800.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>SB-treated male flies do not exhibit increased intermale
                            courtship.</bold> The Courtship Index (CI) was measured for untreated
                        male/female pairs (white), untreated male/male pairs (gray) and SB treated
                        males/male pairs (Black). The CI of male/female pairs was 0.75, consistent
                        with published reports. The CI for untreated male/male pairs was less than
                        0.1. Male pairs treated with 3 mM SB did not show a significant increase in
                        intermale courtship when compared to untreated male/male pairs. (Error bars
                         =  SEM; *p = &lt;0.01 vs m/f;
                        ANOVA with Tukey's Multiple Comparison Test).</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Dr. Stephen F. Goodwin (Oxford, UK) for supplying the Fru<sup>M</sup>
                antiserum.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Breier1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1995</year>
                    <article-title>Serotonin, schizophrenia and antipsychotic drug
                        action.</article-title>
                    <source>Schizophr Res</source>
                    <volume>14</volume>
                    <fpage>187</fpage>
                    <lpage>202</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Lucki1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>The spectrum of behaviors influenced by
                        serotonin.</article-title>
                    <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>
                    <volume>44</volume>
                    <fpage>151z162</fpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Nichols1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Serotonin receptors.</article-title>
                    <source>Chem Rev</source>
                    <volume>108</volume>
                    <fpage>1614</fpage>
                    <lpage>1641</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Neumaier1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumaier</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sexton</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yracheta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brownfield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Localization of 5-HT(7) receptors in rat brain by
                        immunocytochemistry, in situ hybridization, and agonist stimulated cFos
                        expression.</article-title>
                    <source>J Chem Neuroanat</source>
                    <volume>21</volume>
                    <fpage>63</fpage>
                    <lpage>73</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Belenky1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belenky</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Subcellular distribution of 5-HT(1B) and 5-HT(7) receptors in the
                        mouse suprachiasmatic nucleus.</article-title>
                    <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
                    <volume>432</volume>
                    <fpage>371</fpage>
                    <lpage>388</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Guscott1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guscott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bristow</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadingham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosahl</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Genetic knockout and pharmacological blockade studies of the
                        5-HT7 receptor suggest therapeutic potential in depression.</article-title>
                    <source>Neuropharmacology</source>
                    <volume>48</volume>
                    <fpage>492</fpage>
                    <lpage>502</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Guscott2">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guscott</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>The hypothermic effect of 5-CT in mice is mediated through the
                        5-HT7 receptor.</article-title>
                    <source>Neuropharmacology</source>
                    <volume>44</volume>
                    <fpage>1031</fpage>
                    <lpage>1037</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Hedlund1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedlund</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danielson</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slanina</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>No hypothermic response to serotonin in 5-HT7 receptor knockout
                        mice.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>100</volume>
                    <fpage>1375</fpage>
                    <lpage>1380</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Hedlund2">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedlund</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huitron-Resendiz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>5-HT7 receptor inhibition and inactivation induce
                        antidepressantlike behavior and sleep pattern.</article-title>
                    <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>
                    <volume>58</volume>
                    <fpage>831</fpage>
                    <lpage>837</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Janssen1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prins</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuideveld</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>5-HT7 receptor efficacy distribution throughout the canine
                        stomach.</article-title>
                    <source>Br J Pharmacol</source>
                    <volume>143</volume>
                    <fpage>331</fpage>
                    <lpage>342</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Monti1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jantos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Effects of the 5-HT(7) receptor antagonist SB-269970
                        microinjected into the dorsal raphe nucleus on REM sleep in the
                        rat.</article-title>
                    <source>Behav Brain Res</source>
                    <volume>167</volume>
                    <fpage>245</fpage>
                    <lpage>250</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Monti2">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leopoldo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jantos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>The serotonin 5-HT(7) receptor agonist LP-44 microinjected into
                        the dorsal raphe nucleus suppresses REM sleep in the rat.</article-title>
                    <source>Behav Brain Res</source>
                    <volume>191</volume>
                    <fpage>184</fpage>
                    <lpage>189</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Sprouse1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprouse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeish</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Circadian rhythm phenotype of 5-HT7 receptor knockout mice: 5-HT
                        and 8-OH-DPAT-induced phase advances of SCN neuronal firing.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Rhythms</source>
                    <volume>20</volume>
                    <fpage>122</fpage>
                    <lpage>131</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Thomas1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>5-HT7 receptors.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Drug Targets CNS Neurol Disord</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>81</fpage>
                    <lpage>90</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Siddiqui1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaharyar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>The 5HT(7) receptor subtype is involved in the regulation of
                        female sexual behaviour in the rat.</article-title>
                    <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source>
                    <volume>87</volume>
                    <fpage>386</fpage>
                    <lpage>392</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Pandey1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2011</year>
                    <article-title>Human Disease Models in Drosophila melanogaster and the Role of
                        the Fly in Therapeutic Drug Discovery.</article-title>
                    <publisher-name>Pharmacol Rev</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Bier1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Drosophila, the golden bug, emerges as a tool for human
                        genetics.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
                    <volume>6</volume>
                    <fpage>9</fpage>
                    <lpage>23</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Nichols2">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Drosophila melanogaster neurobiology, neuropharmacology, and how
                        the fly can inform central nervous system drug discovery.</article-title>
                    <source>Pharmacol Ther</source>
                    <volume>112</volume>
                    <fpage>677</fpage>
                    <lpage>700</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Yuan1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Serotonin modulates circadian entrainment in
                        Drosophila.</article-title>
                    <source>Neuron</source>
                    <volume>47</volume>
                    <fpage>115</fpage>
                    <lpage>127</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Johnson1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becnel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Serotonin 5-HT(2) and 5-HT(1A)-like receptors differentially
                        modulate aggressive behaviors in Drosophila melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <source>Neuroscience</source>
                    <volume>158</volume>
                    <fpage>1292</fpage>
                    <lpage>1300</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Nichols3">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>5-HT2 receptors in Drosophila are expressed in the brain and
                        modulate aspects of circadian behaviors.</article-title>
                    <source>Dev Neurobiol</source>
                    <volume>67</volume>
                    <fpage>752</fpage>
                    <lpage>763</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Ja1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ja</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Rosa</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Prandiology of Drosophila and the CAFE assay.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>104</volume>
                    <fpage>8253</fpage>
                    <lpage>8256</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Ejima1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ejima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Courtship initiation is stimulated by acoustic signals in
                        Drosophila melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS One</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>e3246</fpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Neckameyer1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neckameyer</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Dopamine modulates female sexual receptivity in Drosophila
                        melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurogenet</source>
                    <volume>12</volume>
                    <fpage>101</fpage>
                    <lpage>114</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Bastock1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1955</year>
                    <article-title>The Courtship of Drosophila Melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <publisher-name>Behaviour</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>85</fpage>
                    <lpage>111</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Greenspan1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenspan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferveur</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Courtship in Drosophila.</article-title>
                    <source>Annu Rev Genet</source>
                    <volume>34</volume>
                    <fpage>205</fpage>
                    <lpage>232</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Tully1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1985</year>
                    <article-title>Classical conditioning and retention in normal and mutant
                        Drosophila melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <source>J Comp Physiol [A]</source>
                    <volume>157</volume>
                    <fpage>263</fpage>
                    <lpage>277</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Giordano1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rendina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>RNAi triggered by symmetrically transcribed transgenes in
                            <italic>Drosophila nelanogaster</italic>.</article-title>
                    <source>Genetics</source>
                    <volume>160</volume>
                    <fpage>637</fpage>
                    <lpage>648</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Lee1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Spatial, temporal, and sexually dimorphic expression patterns of
                        the fruitless gene in the Drosophila central nervous system.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurobiol</source>
                    <volume>43</volume>
                    <fpage>404</fpage>
                    <lpage>426</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-HelfrichForster1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Helfrich-Forster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wulbeck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grieshaber</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rieger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Development and morphology of the clock-gene-expressing lateral
                        neurons of Drosophila melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
                    <volume>500</volume>
                    <fpage>47</fpage>
                    <lpage>70</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Renn1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Renn</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Genetic analysis of the Drosophila ellipsoid body neuropil:
                        organization and development of the central complex.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurobiol</source>
                    <volume>41</volume>
                    <fpage>189</fpage>
                    <lpage>207</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Young1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Structure of the adult central complex in Drosophila:
                        organization of distinct neuronal subsets.</article-title>
                    <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
                    <volume>518</volume>
                    <fpage>1500</fpage>
                    <lpage>1524</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Hanesch1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanesch</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischbach</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heisenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1989</year>
                    <article-title>Neuronal architecture of the central complex in
                            <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>.</article-title>
                    <source>Cell and Tissue Research</source>
                    <volume>257</volume>
                    <fpage>343</fpage>
                    <lpage>366</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Dacks1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dacks</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Phylogeny of a serotonin-immunoreactive neuron in the primary
                        olfactory center of the insect brain.</article-title>
                    <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
                    <volume>498</volume>
                    <fpage>727</fpage>
                    <lpage>746</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Roy1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>North</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Metamorphosis of an identified serotonergic neuron in the
                        Drosophila olfactory system.</article-title>
                    <source>Neural Dev</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>20</fpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Billeter1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Billeter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allendorfer</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dornan</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Isoform-specific control of male neuronal differentiation and
                        behavior in Drosophila by the fruitless gene.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Biol</source>
                    <volume>16</volume>
                    <fpage>1063</fpage>
                    <lpage>1076</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Lee2">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Abnormalities of male-specific FRU protein and serotonin
                        expression in the CNS of fruitless mutants in Drosophila.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurosci</source>
                    <volume>21</volume>
                    <fpage>513</fpage>
                    <lpage>526</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-HelfrichForster2">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Helfrich-Forster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wulf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Belle</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Mushroom body influence on locomotor activity and circadian
                        rhythms in Drosophila melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurogenet</source>
                    <volume>16</volume>
                    <fpage>73</fpage>
                    <lpage>109</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Rollmann1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rollmann</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwarts</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callaerts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Pleiotropic effects of Drosophila neuralized on complex behaviors
                        and brain structure.</article-title>
                    <source>Genetics</source>
                    <volume>179</volume>
                    <fpage>1327</fpage>
                    <lpage>1336</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Fleischmann1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleischmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choffat</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spengler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Mushroom bodies and post-mating behaviors of Drosophila
                        melanogaster females.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurogenet</source>
                    <volume>15</volume>
                    <fpage>117</fpage>
                    <lpage>144</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Popov1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitnik</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savvateeva-Popova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heisenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>[Brain central regions in courtship sound production in
                        Drosophila melanogaster].</article-title>
                    <source>Ross Fiziol Zh Im I M Sechenova</source>
                    <volume>87</volume>
                    <fpage>779</fpage>
                    <lpage>794</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Yamamoto1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Sexual behavior mutants revisited: molecular and cellular basis
                        of Drosophila mating.</article-title>
                    <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>
                    <volume>56</volume>
                    <fpage>634</fpage>
                    <lpage>646</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Thomas2">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gittins</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Middlemiss</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Functional characterisation of the human cloned 5-HT7 receptor
                        (long form); antagonist profile of SB-258719.</article-title>
                    <source>Br J Pharmacol</source>
                    <volume>124</volume>
                    <fpage>1300</fpage>
                    <lpage>1306</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Zhang1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Odenwald</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1995</year>
                    <article-title>Misexpression of the white (w) gene triggers male-male courtship
                        in Drosophila.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>92</volume>
                    <fpage>5525</fpage>
                    <lpage>5529</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Hing1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hing</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Male-male courtship behavior induced by ectopic expression of the
                        Drosophila white gene: role of sensory function and age.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurobiol</source>
                    <volume>30</volume>
                    <fpage>454</fpage>
                    <lpage>464</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Bellen1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Ten years of enhancer detection: lessons from the
                        fly.</article-title>
                    <source>Plant Cell</source>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                    <fpage>2271</fpage>
                    <lpage>2281</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Villella1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Neurogenetics of courtship and mating in
                        Drosophila.</article-title>
                    <source>Adv Genet</source>
                    <volume>62</volume>
                    <fpage>67</fpage>
                    <lpage>184</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Billeter2">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Billeter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Dell</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Genes mediating sex-specific behaviors in
                        Drosophila.</article-title>
                    <source>Adv Genet</source>
                    <volume>47</volume>
                    <fpage>87</fpage>
                    <lpage>116</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Ito1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujitani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Usui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu-Nishikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Sexual orientation in Drosophila is altered by the satori
                        mutation in the sex-determination gene fruitless that encodes a zinc finger
                        protein with a BTB domain.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>93</volume>
                    <fpage>9687</fpage>
                    <lpage>9692</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Yamamoto2">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujitani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Genetic dissection of sexual orientation: behavioral, cellular,
                        and molecular approaches in Drosophila melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <source>Neurosci Res</source>
                    <volume>26</volume>
                    <fpage>95</fpage>
                    <lpage>107</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Yamamoto3">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Genes for sexual behavior.</article-title>
                    <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
                    <volume>246</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>6</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Orgad1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orgad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenspan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>courtless, the Drosophila UBC7 homolog, is involved in male
                        courtship behavior and spermatogenesis.</article-title>
                    <source>Genetics</source>
                    <volume>155</volume>
                    <fpage>1267</fpage>
                    <lpage>1280</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Buchner1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1991</year>
                    <article-title>Genes expressed in the adult brain of Drosophila and effects of
                        their mutations on behavior: a survey of transmitter- and second
                        messenger-related genes.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurogenet</source>
                    <volume>7</volume>
                    <fpage>153</fpage>
                    <lpage>192</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Fratta1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fratta</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biggio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gessa</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1977</year>
                    <article-title>Homosexual mounting behavior induced in male rats and rabbits by
                        a tryptophan-free diet.</article-title>
                    <source>Life Sci</source>
                    <volume>21</volume>
                    <fpage>379</fpage>
                    <lpage>383</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Gessa1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gessa</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tagliamonte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1974</year>
                    <article-title>Possible role of brain serotonin and dopamine in controlling male
                        sexual behavior.</article-title>
                    <source>Adv Biochem Psychopharmacol</source>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                    <fpage>217</fpage>
                    <lpage>228</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Neuser1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Triphan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mronz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poeck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Analysis of a spatial orientation memory in
                        Drosophila.</article-title>
                    <source>Nature</source>
                    <volume>453</volume>
                    <fpage>1244</fpage>
                    <lpage>1247</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Wang1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatzimanolis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Visual pattern memory requires foraging function in the central
                        complex of Drosophila.</article-title>
                    <source>Learn Mem</source>
                    <volume>15</volume>
                    <fpage>133</fpage>
                    <lpage>142</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Wu1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Specific requirement of NMDA receptors for long-term memory
                        consolidation in Drosophila ellipsoid body.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
                    <volume>10</volume>
                    <fpage>1578</fpage>
                    <lpage>1586</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Neckameyer2">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neckameyer</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Distinct neural circuits reflect sex, sexual maturity, and
                        reproductive status in response to stress in Drosophila
                        melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <source>Neuroscience</source>
                    <volume>156</volume>
                    <fpage>841</fpage>
                    <lpage>856</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Ilius1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilius</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heisenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>The central complex of Drosophila melanogaster is involved in
                        flight control: studies on mutants and mosaics of the gene ellipsoid body
                        open.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurogenet</source>
                    <volume>21</volume>
                    <fpage>321</fpage>
                    <lpage>338</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Baker1">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckingham</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Functional dissection of the neural substrates for gravitaxic
                        maze behavior in Drosophila melanogaster.</article-title>
                    <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
                    <volume>501</volume>
                    <fpage>756</fpage>
                    <lpage>764</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Liu1">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dartevelle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Increased dopamine level enhances male-male courtship in
                        Drosophila.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurosci</source>
                    <volume>28</volume>
                    <fpage>5539</fpage>
                    <lpage>5546</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Liu2">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dartevelle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Reduction of dopamine level enhances the attractiveness of male
                        Drosophila to other males.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS One</source>
                    <volume>4</volume>
                    <fpage>e4574</fpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020800-Sakai1">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasuya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aigaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>The Drosophila TRPA channel, Painless, regulates sexual
                        receptivity in virgin females.</article-title>
                    <source>Genes Brain Behav</source>
                    <volume>8</volume>
                    <fpage>546</fpage>
                    <lpage>557</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>