<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-18752</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038267</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Immune physiology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Marine ecology</subject>
              <subject>Microbial ecology</subject>
              <subject>Physiological ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary immunology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genomics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Functional genomics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Immunology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Immunity</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Innate immunity</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Immune response</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Marine biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Marine ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Immunity</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Innate immunity</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Microbial ecology</subject>
              <subject>Microbial growth and development</subject>
              <subject>Microbial physiology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Model organisms</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal models</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Molecular cell biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Gene expression</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Earth sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Marine and aquatic sciences</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Marine biology</subject>
              <subject>Marine ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Immunology</subject>
          <subject>Microbiology</subject>
          <subject>Molecular Biology</subject>
          <subject>Marine and Aquatic Sciences</subject>
          <subject>Physiology</subject>
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Expression and Putative Function of Innate Immunity Genes under <italic>in situ</italic> Conditions in the Symbiotic Hydrothermal Vent Tubeworm <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Innate Immunity in a Hydrothermal Vent Tubeworm</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nyholm</surname>
            <given-names>Spencer V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>Pengfei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
            <sup>¤</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Dang</surname>
            <given-names>Jeanne</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bunce</surname>
            <given-names>Corey</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Girguis</surname>
            <given-names>Peter R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Molecular and Cell Biology, University of Connecticut, Storrs, Connecticut, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Organismic and Evolutionary Biology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Leulier</surname>
            <given-names>François</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">French National Centre for Scientific Research - Université Aix-Marseille, France</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">spencer.nyholm@uconn.edu</email> (SVN); <email xlink:type="simple">pgirguis@oeb.harvard.edu</email> (PRG)</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SVN PS PRG. Performed the experiments: SVN PS JD CB PRG. Analyzed the data: SVN PS JD CB PRG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SVN PRG. Wrote the paper: SVN PS JD CB PRG.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn1">
          <label>¤</label>
          <p>Current address: Institute for Core Studies, St. John’s University, Queens, New York, United States of America</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e38267</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Nyholm et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>The relationships between hydrothermal vent tubeworms and sulfide-oxidizing bacteria have served as model associations for understanding chemoautotrophy and endosymbiosis. Numerous studies have focused on the physiological and biochemical adaptations that enable these symbioses to sustain some of the highest recorded carbon fixation rates ever measured. However, far fewer studies have explored the molecular mechanisms underlying the regulation of host and symbiont interactions, specifically those mediated by the innate immune system of the host. To that end, we conducted a series of studies where we maintained the tubeworm, <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic>, in high-pressure aquaria and examined global and quantitative changes in gene expression via high-throughput transcriptomics and quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR). We analyzed over 32,000 full-length expressed sequence tags as well as 26 Mb of transcript sequences from the trophosome (the organ that houses the endosymbiotic bacteria) and the plume (the gas exchange organ in contact with the free-living microbial community). <italic>R. piscesae</italic> maintained under conditions that promote chemoautotrophy expressed a number of putative cell signaling and innate immunity genes, including pattern recognition receptors (PRRs), often associated with recognizing microbe-associated molecular patterns (MAMPs). Eighteen genes involved with innate immunity, cell signaling, cell stress and metabolite exchange were further analyzed using qPCR. PRRs, including five peptidoglycan recognition proteins and a Toll-like receptor, were expressed significantly higher in the trophosome compared to the plume. Although PRRs are often associated with mediating host responses to infection by pathogens, the differences in expression between the plume and trophosome also implicate similar mechanisms of microbial recognition in interactions between the host and symbiont. We posit that regulation of this association involves a molecular “dialogue” between the partners that includes interactions between the host’s innate immune system and the symbiont.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The sequence data were obtained by the United States Department of Energy Joint Genome Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jgi.doe.gov" xlink:type="simple">http://www.jgi.doe.gov</ext-link>) in collaboration with the user community. This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation (NSF) under Grant Nos. NSF OCE-0732369 and NSF OCE-0426109 (nsf.gov) to PRG and the University of Connecticut Research Foundation (research.uconn.edu) to SVN. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Deep-sea hydrothermal vents host highly productive ecosystems based on microbial chemoautotrophy (for review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Dubilier1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Stewart1">[2]</xref>). Many of these vent communities are dominated by siboglinid annelid tubeworms that are mouthless and gutless, and symbiotic with sulfide-oxidizing, chemoautotrophic bacteria. These intracellular gammaproteobacterial symbionts are found within specialized host cells (bacteriocytes) in an organ called the trophosome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Cavanaugh1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Felbeck1">[4]</xref>. The symbionts fix inorganic carbon using energy derived from oxidizing sulfide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Childress1">[5]</xref> using oxygen or nitrate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Fisher1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Hentschel1">[8]</xref>. They receive all metabolites necessary for chemoautotrophy from the host, which acquires the majority of these substrates through the branchial plume, the respiratory organ that extends outside the host’s chitinous tube directly into vent fluid-enriched seawater. The host appears to be largely, if not entirely, dependent upon the symbionts for their nutritional needs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Childress1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Fisher1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Childress2">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Fisher2">[10]</xref>. To our knowledge, the symbionts of an adult worm are never in contact with the external milieu, even though the bacteria are likely environmentally transmitted with each host generation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nussbaumer1">[11]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Siboglinid tubeworm symbioses have been extensively studied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright1">[12]</xref> though research has focused primarily on biochemistry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Arp1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Sanchez1">[20]</xref>, metabolism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Childress1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Girguis1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Childress2">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Fisher2">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Felbeck2">[21]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Robidart2">[26]</xref>, ecology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Cooper1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Shank1">[30]</xref> and to a lesser extent, development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Hurtado1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Marsh1">[32]</xref>. In particular, much of this research has focused on better understanding host adaptations to the geochemical conditions at vents and symbiont primary productivity, as sustained carbon fixation and nitrogen metabolism is necessary to support the growth and reproduction of this obligate host and symbiont pair. Despite the breadth of physiological and biochemical data on these symbioses, the underlying molecular mechanisms that govern chemautotrophic symbiostasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Reid1">[33]</xref> (the balance of host and symbiont metabolism and growth) are largely unknown. Specifically, the nature and extent to which siboglinid hosts and symbionts interact, and how the association is regulated at the cellular and/or molecular level has not been as thoroughly explored. To date, only a few studies have examined related questions through microscopic and morphological investigations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bosch1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Pflugfelder1">[37]</xref>, as well as gene expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Sanchez1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-DeCian2">[38]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>. Taken together, these studies suggest that host bacteriocyte and symbiont cell growth and turnover are likely highly regulated.</p>
      <p>As in other symbioses, tubeworms may regulate symbiont activity to maintain symbiostasis through pathways involved with substrate availability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Fitt1">[41]</xref>, and/or by regulating pathways that govern host/symbiont population dynamics, e.g. programmed cell death or immune system responses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright2">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Pflugfelder1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Benson1">[42]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-McFallNgai1">[46]</xref>. Notably, these mechanisms would require that the host be able to A) recognize its symbiont, B) differentiate the symbiont from other bacteria, and C) directly or indirectly influence the growth of the population.</p>
      <p>To further our understanding of the biomolecular mechanisms used by siboglinid tubeworms to maintain symbiostasis, we conducted a series of studies of <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic> to examine host gene expression at <italic>in situ</italic> conditions that stimulate high productivity to ensure that energy limitation, such as the availability of sulfide and oxygen to the symbionts, does not limit symbiont activity or growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>. We chose <italic>R. piscesae</italic> (hereafter referred to as <italic>Ridgeia</italic>) as our study organism because it shares many of the attributes of the better-studied <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>, including gross morphology and symbiont type <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-deBurgh1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Laue1">[48]</xref>. Far fewer studies have examined aspects of <italic>Ridgeia</italic> physiology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Ruan1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Carney1">[49]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Young1">[51]</xref> though <italic>Ridgeia’s</italic> “short” morphotype exhibits sulfide uptake rates comparable to those of <italic>R. pachyptila</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>. These experiments were enabled by ready access to <italic>Ridgeia</italic> during numerous expeditions to the Juan de Fuca ridge system. We examined gene expression in two different tissues to understand how the plume, which serves as the direct interface between the host and free-living microorganisms in the environment, and the trophosome, which maintains the highly specific intracellular symbiont population, respond under <italic>in situ</italic> conditions. We present gene expression data from these tissues to identify host biochemical and biomolecular mechanisms that are involved in cell cycle, signaling, stress response and innate immunity. We observed expression of a number of putative pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) involved with recognition of microbe-associated molecular patterns (MAMPs). Via quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR), we quantified and characterized the abundance and pattern of eighteen genes involved with innate immunity, cell signaling, and metabolite uptake. Although studies of the innate immune systems of polychaete worms are limited, there is evidence that this group has an immune response similar to those described for other invertebrates, such as the use of PRRs, reactive oxygen species and the production of antimicrobial compounds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Altincicek1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Davidson1">[53]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Gagniere1">[54]</xref>. Our data show that many PRRs, including five peptidoglycan recognition proteins (PGRPs) and a Toll-like receptor are expressed in the trophosome at significantly higher levels compared to the plume, suggesting that the host’s innate immune system may interact directly with the symbionts to govern cell growth during conditions that promote high primary productivity. The presence and expression of PRRs, such as the PGRPs underscore the likely role that host innate immunity plays in governing host/symbiont interactions. These data further suggest that the host may utilize different components of the innate immune system in interactions with free-living microorganisms. From these findings, we present a model of the mechanisms by which the host and the symbiont may interact to maintain symbiostasis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Ethics Statement</title>
        <p>No specific permits were required for the described field studies. <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic> is not an endangered or protected species.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Animal Collection</title>
        <p><italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic> tubeworms were collected during a research expedition to the Mothra (47°55.4′N by 129°06.4′W) and Main Endeavour (47°57.0′N by 129°5.82′W) vent fields along the Juan de Fuca ridge from August to September 2006 and 2007 as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>. Briefly, <italic>Ridgeia</italic> tubeworms were collected <italic>via</italic> the DSV <italic>Alvin</italic> from approximately 2300 m, and placed in thermally insulated boxes prior to returning to the surface. On the surface, tubeworms were assessed for health and select worms were immediately placed in flow-through, high-pressure respirometry aquaria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Girguis3">[23]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Experimental Apparatus and Design</title>
        <p>During all respirometry experiments, tubeworms were maintained in the high-pressure respirometry system (HPRS; as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Girguis1">[7]</xref>) between 50 h and 6 days. <italic>Ridgeia</italic> were maintained at conditions previously shown to support high primary productivity by <italic>R. pachyptila</italic> (5.5 mM dissolved inorganic carbon; 215–230 µM H<sub>2</sub>S; 150 µM O<sub>2</sub>; 40 µM NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>; pH 5.9; 15°C; and 27.5 MPa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Girguis3">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>. As a control, a subset of worms (n = 3) was also maintained in the same conditions as described above, but with a limiting concentration of 50 µM H<sub>2</sub>S. Oxygen and total inorganic carbon uptake rates presented here were collected as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Girguis3">[23]</xref>. At the end of the experiments, the worms were quickly removed from the vessels and dissected into plume, vestimentum, body wall, and trophosome sections. Great care was taken to selectively harvest the trophosome lobules containing the bacteriocytes, and avoid contamination with reproductive tissues. Samples were then flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C for RNA extraction in the laboratory.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>RNA Extractions for EST and cDNA Construction</title>
        <p>RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis for EST library construction and massively parallel sequencing were as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>. In conjunction with the Department of Energy’s Joint Genome Institute (Department of Energy, Walnut Creek, CA), cDNA was generated from RNA of <italic>R. piscesae</italic> maintained under <italic>in situ</italic> conditions and analyzed by either traditional Sanger sequencing of ESTs or massively parallel pyrosequencing of cDNA (hereafter referred to as 454 sequencing; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t001">Table 1</xref>). For Sanger sequencing, we submitted a 500-µg sample of total RNA pooled from the trophosomes of ten individuals to the Joint Genome Institute for cDNA synthesis, library construction, and sequencing as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>. For 454 sequencing, total RNA pooled from the plume tissues of seven of the individuals sampled for the trophosome was used to construct a cDNA library using standard protocols described below. Reverse transcribed cDNA greater than 100 bp was gel purified and cDNA concentration was estimated using an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, Inc.). cDNA was then fragmented and nebulized, and adaptors were ligated to both the 5′and 3′ in preparation for emulsion PCR. cDNA was clonally amplified in a bead-immobilized form by using the GS20 emPCR kit (Roche-454 Life Sciences Inc.) following the manufacturer's recommendations. After emulsion PCR, sequencing was conducted using a Roche/454 Titanium FLX system (Roche-454 Life Sciences). Data assembly was performed using MIRA 3 assembler and Roche GS Reference Mapper.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0038267-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Summary of transcriptome sequencing of the trophosome (EST) and the plume (454 pyrosequencing) from <italic>Ridgeia piscesae.</italic></title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038267-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">TROPHOSOME</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Number of Unique ESTs</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32, 256</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average EST length</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">582 bp</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Trimmed Unique ESTs</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26, 355</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Megablast Analysis</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESTs with no hits</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21, 327</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESTs with hits</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5, 028</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic> non-cellular</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic> Archaea/Bacteria</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic> Eukaryota</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,971</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Number of Consensus Sequences</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,824</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total bases</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9 Mb</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average sequence length</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">672 bp</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average percent GC</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46 (+/−0.08)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PLUME</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Number of Reads</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">918, 215</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total bases</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">363.6 Mb</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average read length</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">396 bp</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Number of Contigs</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20, 757</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total bases</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.5 Mb</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average length</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,279 bp</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range of contig length</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50–12,251 bp</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average percent GC</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>analysis of Trimmed Unique ESTs.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>RNA Extractions and cDNA Synthesis for Quantitative PCR</title>
        <p>One cm pieces of flash-frozen tissues of trophosome and plume were excised on a dry-ice-cooled stainless steel dissecting tray and immediately placed into pre-chilled (−20°C) RNA<italic>later</italic> ICE (Ambion Inc.). Between 50–100 mg each of both trophosome and plume from six separate worms maintained in the HPRS system between 50–72 h were used to isolate total RNA according to manufacturer’s guidelines (MaxiPrep total RNA extraction kit, Qiagen Inc.). After extraction, total RNA was quantified on a microscale UV spectrophotometer (Nanodrop Inc.), quality checked by gel electrophoresis or a Bioanalyzer RNA Nano chip (Agilent Technologies, Inc.), and stored at −80°C.</p>
        <p>First-strand cDNA was synthesized using the SuperScript II Reverse Transcription kit (Invitrogen, Inc.) according to manufacturer’s guidelines. A mixture of 5 ml of total RNA, 1 ml of 250 ng random hexamer primers, 1 ml of dNTP mix (10 mM each), and sterile distilled water to a total volume of 12 ml were incubated for 5 min at 65°C and quick-chilled on ice. After adding 4 ml of 5x First-Strand Buffer and 2 ml of DTT (0.1 M), the mixture was incubated for 2 min at 25°C. One ml (200 units) of SuperScript II RT was then added to the reaction, then incubated for another 10 min at 25°C before 50 min at 42°C, and finally inactivated by heating at 70°C for 10 min. Storage of cDNA was maintained at −80°C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Quantitative Real-Time PCR</title>
        <p>Quantitative Real-Time PCR (qPCR) was performed on Stratagene Mx3005P Real-Time PCR System (Agilent Technologies, Inc.) using SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems Inc.). The PCR reaction consisted of 10 µl of SYBR Green PCR Master Mix, 0.75 µl each of forward and reverse primers (10 mM), and 5 µl of template cDNA in a final volume of 20 µl. The thermal cycle profile was 15 min at 95°C, followed by 40 cycles of 94°C for 15 sec, 58°C (or 55°C if annealing temperature of primer is less than 58°C) for 30 sec, and 72°C for 30 sec, and a final segment of 95°C for 15 sec, 58°C (or 55°C) for 20 sec, and 95°C for 15 sec. A dissociation curve and subsequent capillary sequencing (Applied Biosystems Inc.) verified that the used primer pair produced only a single product. The assay included a no-template control and each of the test cDNAs from twelve tissues (6 plumes, 6 trophosomes) for each target gene. Each reaction was run in technical duplicates.</p>
        <p>Threshold cycle (C<sub>T</sub>) measured at fluorescence dRn  = 0.05 was utilized to calculate the fold expression using the 2<sup>–ΔΔCT</sup> method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Livak1">[55]</xref>. All target genes were normalized to actin (ΔC<sub>T</sub>  =  C<sub>T:target</sub> – C<sub>T: actin</sub>) and the relative quantification was obtained by comparing the expression of the same RNA in the target organ with the reference organ, plume (ΔΔC<sub>T</sub>  =  [C<sub>T:target</sub> – C<sub>T: actin</sub>]<sub>sample</sub> – [C<sub>T:target</sub> – C<sub>T:actin</sub>]<sub>reference</sub>). The mean and standard deviations of the 2<sup>–ΔΔCT</sup> equation were then calculated from the duplicate samples, with the mean value of the plume samples equating to approximately one (2<sup>0</sup> = 1).</p>
        <p>Box plots of target gene expression in trophosome were drawn in R (R Foundation for Statistical Computing) using the 1st and 3rd quartiles (Q1 and Q3) of each gene for the upper and lower bounds of the box, respectively. Thus, 50% of the values (interquartile range, or IQR) are within the box, with the median drawn as a solid black line. Whiskers are depicted at the maximum and minimum values or 1.5*IQR (Q1–1.5*IQR, and Q3+1.5*IQR), whichever value is smaller. A dotted line indicates the fold expression of plume samples (y = 1). Outliers were those values lying more than the IQR beyond those quartiles and are not represented in the analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Selection of Normalization Gene Candidates</title>
        <p>We examined three potential housekeeping genes, actin, elongation factor-1 alpha (Ef1α), and 18S ribosomal RNA, by qPCR. These data were also analyzed using the 2<sup>–ΔΔCt</sup> method to determine whether they yielded similar results with respect to consistency within a single organism, consistency between the two tissues, and consistency among technical replicates. The program NormFinder was used to assess the stability values of actin and Ef1α from six plume and trophosome samples <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Andersen1">[56]</xref>. The average stability value for actin was determined to be 0.0735 compared to the average stability value of 0.102 for Ef1α. Because actin expression was determined to be the most constant in both tissues, and, to allow comparison with previous studies, actin was selected as the housekeeping gene for these analyses.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Physiological Responses of Host and Symbiont to Experimental Conditions Demonstrate Active Chemoautotrophy</title>
        <p>To enable appropriate examination of genes involved with bacteriocyte cell cycle and growth, it was our intention to insure that metabolic substrates such as sulfide and oxygen were sufficiently replete as not to limit symbiont activity and confound these data. Specifically, <italic>Ridgeia</italic> tubeworms used in our studies had to exhibit sulfide and oxygen uptake rates that were indicative of high chemoautotrophic activity. While sulfide uptake for these individuals has been previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>, here we present ΣCO<sub>2</sub> uptake rates (where ΣCO<sub>2</sub> represents the total change in concentration of all dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC), including carbon dioxide, bicarbonate and carbonate) that are a direct indicator of chemoautotrophy (net chemoautotrophy occurs when there is a net ΣCO<sub>2</sub> uptake). Both the DIC and O<sub>2</sub> uptake rates indicate that <italic>Ridgeia</italic> sustained very high carbon fixation rates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038267.s001">Fig. S1</xref>), comparable to those previously observed for <italic>Riftia</italic>, <italic>Alviniconcha</italic> and other highly productive symbioses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Girguis3">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Henry1">[57]</xref>. For comparison, data on DIC and oxygen uptake by <italic>Ridgeia</italic> maintained with limiting amounts of hydrogen sulfide (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>) are shown to illustrate the differences in rate. Together these data provide physiological context for the gene expression analyses described herein.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Characterization of Trophosome and Plume Gene Expression</title>
        <p>To better understand how gene expression might regulate this symbiotic association, we analyzed the plume (site of metabolic exchange and primary interface with the external environment) and the trophosome (the tissue housing symbiont-containing bacteriocytes, site of primary sulfide oxidation and the point of physical contact between the host and symbiont) under <italic>in situ</italic> conditions.</p>
        <p>From the trophosome, 16,128 unique clones, sequenced bidirectionally, yielded a total of 32,040 ESTs, of which 26,355 contained an insert and were of sufficient quality for subsequent analyses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t001">Table 1</xref>). Of these expressed sequence tags (or ESTs), 19.08% (5,028) yielded BLAST hits with <italic>E</italic>-values &lt;10<sup>–06</sup> when analyzed using the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" xlink:type="simple">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>). From the plume, 454 pyrosequencing generated ∼26 Mb of sequence data. 108,717 single sequences were used to assemble 20,757 isotigs, which again were analyzed using the NCBI databases with the aforementioned <italic>E</italic>-value (as in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>Gene expression data between the two tissues were analyzed using cluster of orthologous group analysis (KOG) for eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038267.s002">Fig. S2</xref>). Comparison of expressed genes from each tissue revealed that, in the trophosome, there was typically greater representation of genes involved with energy production and metabolism, as well as those involved with translation, post-translational modification and protein turnover, suggesting that the trophosome is highly active. The plume showed more representation of genes involved in signal transduction, which in turn may be a reflection of its proximity to the environment and a need to respond quickly to external stimuli (though this supposition remains to be properly examined).</p>
        <p>Closer examination of expression in each tissue revealed a number of putative genes involved with host cell cycle, innate immunity, signal transduction, cell stress response and apoptosis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t002">Table 2</xref>). We identified PRRs involved with recognition of MAMPs, including peptidoglycan recognition proteins, PGRPs, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Dziarski1">[58]</xref> a Toll-like receptor, TLR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Leulier1">[59]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Rosenstiel1">[60]</xref> and a lipoprotein receptor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Miyake1">[61]</xref>. Also represented were those genes involved with down-stream cell signaling cascades in response to MAMPs, including members of the NF-κB signaling pathway. Genes involved with cell cycle and apoptosis, as well as putative cell stress mediators (i.e., heat shock proteins), were also identified (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t002">Table 2</xref>). Of the five PGRPs identified (Rpi1–5), protein domain analysis indicated three of the five may be secreted, as Rpi1, 2 and 4 all have signal peptides while Rpi 1, 4 and 5 also contain transmembrane domains (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t003">Table 3</xref>). PGRP Rpi 3 and 5 are predicted to be expressed either in the cytoplasm, nucleus or plasma membrane. Taken together, these data suggest that the trophosome is well poised to respond to peptidoglycan both intra and extracellularly. PGRP Rpi2 also had predicted amidase activity, suggesting that it may be capable of degrading peptidoglycan.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0038267-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>Trophosome and plume sequences from <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic>.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038267-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Category</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Putative Identification</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E-Value</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Organism</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GenBank Accession Number</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tissue Database</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAMP recognition</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peptidoglycan recognition protein 3 precursor (RpiPGRP1)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-30</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Euprymna scolopes</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AY956813</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PGRP SC3 precursor (RpiPGRP2)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.00E-15</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Branchiomonas manjavacas</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FJ829250</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PGRP 2 (RpiPGRP3)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.00E-10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q8VCS0</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PGRP S1S (RpiPGRP4)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.00E-12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AB425335</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PGRP-LE (RpiPGRP5)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-26</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AF313391</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Macrophage mannose receptor 1-like protein 1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.00E-11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q5VSK2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lipoprotein receptor-related protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.00E-22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q9NZR2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Toll-like receptor 2 precursor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.00E-07</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Cricetulus griseus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q9R1F8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Galectin</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00E-38</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Saccoglossus kowalevskii</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">XM_002731539</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Immune Signaling</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NF-κB inhibitor (cactus)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.00E-14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q03017</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NF-κB inhibitor (I kappa-B alpha)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.00E-13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Gallus gallus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q91974</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NF-κB inhibitor epsilon (I kappa-B-epsilon)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00E-13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q54910</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NF-κB repressing factor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.00E-12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q8BY02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B-cell receptor associated protein (Bap31)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.00E-46</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Pongo abelii</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q5R8H3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lipopolysaccharide-induced tumor necrosis factor-alpha</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00E-15</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Gallus gallus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q8QGW7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Notch 1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-71</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q5BJL5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Macrophage migration inhibitory factor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Xenopus tropicalis</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A9JSE7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell cycling/Apoptosis</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ubiquitin<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-19</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P14792</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dnaJ (apoptosis)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-108</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P59910</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">skpA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.00E-29</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NM166861</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MADS-box<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00E-12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DQ512346.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T-complex protein 1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.00E-25</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q5XIM9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zonadehsin precursor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O88799</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GRIM 19 cell death regulatory protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Bos taurus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q95KV7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DAD-1 defender against cell death</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-41</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Drosophila melanoga</italic>ster</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q9VLM5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LITAF-like cell death inducing protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.00E-15</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q9H305</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Apoptosis-inducing factor 1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-136</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O95831</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Programmed cell death 6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.00E-61</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P12815</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cytokine induced apoptosis inhibitor 1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.00E-69</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Bos taurus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q5EAC7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BCL2-antagonist/killer</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-30</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O08734</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BIRC4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.00E-50</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q9R0I6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tumor response</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tumor suppressor candidate 3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-120</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q13454</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Translationally-controlled tumor protein homolog (TCTP)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-61</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Lumbricus rubellus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O18477</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell stress mediators</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BAT1 ATP-dependent helicase (inflammation)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.00E-29</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AF075691.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heat shock protein 10(mitochondrial)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00E-30</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P26772</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heat shock protein 70<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-138</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P27420</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heat shock protein 75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q9CQN1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heat shock protein 90</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-176</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P14625</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heat shock protein betat1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Gallus gallus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q00649</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stress-induced protein SAM-22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Glycine max</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P26987</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zinc finger stress associated protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.00E-14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q7Y1W9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Immunoglobulin superfamily</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alpha-2 macroglobulin receptor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.00E-13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q91ZX7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alpha-2 macroglobulin receptor associated protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00E-28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P30533</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plasminogen precursor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.00E-52</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Macropus eugenii</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O18783</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Growth and differentiation factor-associated serum protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.00E-10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q7TQN3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Leucine-rich repeat and IG-like nogo receptor</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q3URE9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Miscellaneous immune/defense-related domains</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sushi EGF domain-containing protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00E-51</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q70E20</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DC-Sign C-type lectin</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00E-09</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q8CJ91</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lipopolysaccharide-induced TNF alpha</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00E-15</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Gallus gallus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q8QGW7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease-resistance protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.00E-14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Pisum sativum</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P14710</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bactericidal permeability increasing protein</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-37</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P17213</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autophagy related 5 homolog</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.00E-75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q3MQ04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reactive oxygen species modulator 1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-24</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q4V7T9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>Genes previously reported as being expressed in the trophosome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label/>
              <p>ESTs contigs and 454 isotigs were identified using the BLAST-based analysis program BLASTX (National Center for Bioinformatics Information; NCBI; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Altschul1">[85]</xref>, which compared our sequence to six non-redundant peptide sequence databases (GenBank CDS translations, RefSeq Proteins, PDB, SwissProt, PIR, and PRF). Sequences with <italic>E</italic> values of &lt;10<sup>–6</sup> were categorized and quantified according to the functional category of the homologous gene. Source sequence tissue databases are: T, Trophosome; P, Plume; B, Both.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0038267-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
            <title>Characteristics of putative <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic> PGRP peptides.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038267-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PGRP</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Organism</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E-Value</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Domains</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Predicted Localization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SP</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TM</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PGRP</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rpi1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Euprymna scolopes</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1e-30</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Extracellular (secreted)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rpi2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Brachionus manjavacas</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1e-53</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Extracellular (secreted)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rpi3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Sebastes schlegelii</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7e-10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cytoplasmic and Nuclear</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rpi4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Euprymna scolopes</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6e-11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Extracellular (secreted)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rpi5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Saccoglossus kowalevskii</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3e-31</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cytoplasmic and Plasma Membrane</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label/>
              <p>Peptide sequences were predicted for the 5 putative PGRP ESTs using NCBI’s ORF Finder analysis tool. The sequences were then analyzed using BLASTP, against the non-redundant (nr) protein database to find top hits. The organism and <italic>E</italic>-value of the top PGRP homolog found for each is presented. Protein domains were predicted for the peptides using InterProScan (EMBL-EBI), and are as follows: SP  =  signal peptide, TM  =  transmembrane, and PGRP  =  peptidoglycan recognition protein domain. An X means the domain was found in the protein sequence. Cellular localization for each peptide was predicted using the WoLF PSORT prediction server <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Horton1">[86]</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Quantification of Select Innate Immunity, Cell Signaling, and Metabolic Genes</title>
        <p>qPCR primers were designed to target a total of eighteen genes, including seven genes involved with MAMP recognition (five PGRPs, a TLR and a macrophage mannose receptor); other humoral-associated genes, including an alpha-2-macroglobulin receptor-associated protein and a bacteriocidal lipobinding protein; immune signaling genes, including a NF-κB inhibitor, a macrophage inhibitor factor and a LPS-induced TNFα transcription factor (LITAF); and cell stress mediators, including heat shock protein 70 and a reactive oxygen species modulator (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g001">Fig 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t004">Table 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038267.s003">Tables S1</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038267.s004">S2</xref>). For reference, we also examined three genes involved with metabolite uptake: two carbonic anhydrases predicted to be specific to the plume and trophosome and a hemoglobin involved with sulfide and oxygen binding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Arp1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Arp2">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Flores1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Kochevar1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-DeCian2">[38]</xref>. These have been well characterized in these tissues, and their representation in each tissue provided a means of assessing whether there was any cross-contamination during sampling.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0038267-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Box plot showing expression of target genes in the trophosome compared to the plume as determined by qPCR.</title>
            <p>The fold expression level differences, of 18 target genes, in the trophosome were compared to those of the plume. The upper and lower ends of the boxes indicate the 25th and 75th percentiles, respectively. The length of the box depicts the interquartile range within which 50% of the values are located. The solid black lines denote the median. Capped error bars represent the minimum and maximum values, excluding outliers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t004">Table 4</xref>). The dotted black line represents expression levels in the plume (y = 1), thus genes with medians &gt;1 exhibit higher expression levels in the trophosome compared to the plume, and inversely genes with medians &lt;1 show higher expression levels in the plume. All expression levels are normalized to the expression of actin. The gene abbreviations are as follows: hbB1, hemoglobin B1; HSP70, heat shock protein 70; LITAF, lipopolysaccharide-induced tumor necrosis factor-alpha; PGRPrpi1–5, peptidoglycan recognition protein 1–5; TLR2p, toll-like receptor 2 precursor; A2MRAP, alpha-2 macroglobulin receptor associated protein; CAbr, carbonic anhydrase (branchial plume); CAtr, carbonic anhydrase (trophosome); EF1α, elongation factor 1-alpha; LBPIP, LPS induced bactericidal permeability increasing protein; MMIF, macrophage migration inhibitory factor; MR, macrophage mannose receptor 1-like protein; NF-κBic, NF-κB inhibitor (cactus); ROSm, reactive oxygen species modulator.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0038267-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
            <title>Targeted gene expression for individual worms.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038267-t004-4" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.t004" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Target Gene</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Individual</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>hbB1</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">206.52</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.05</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.66</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.37</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.36</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>643.98</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>HSP70</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>541.21</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.19</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.47</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.45</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>LITAF</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.49</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.89</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.87</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>90.52</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PGRP(Rpi1)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.75</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>237.29</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.09</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.68</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PGRP(Rpi2)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.45</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>3344.49</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.78</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.77</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PGRP(Rpi3)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.61</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.98</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.09</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>747.56</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PGRP(Rpi5)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.41</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.63</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.66</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>TLR2p</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.66</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.71</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.83</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.50</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>A2MRAP</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.16</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.03</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>13.74</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>CAbr</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>CAtr</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.55</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.70</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.34</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.30</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Ef1α</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>1.83</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>LBPIP</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.33</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.18</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>5.80</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>MMIF</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.46</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>105.6</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>MR</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>0.67</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>NF</bold>κ<bold>Bic</bold></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.93</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.27</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.95</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.92</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>83.36</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>PGRP (Rpi4)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.09</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.64</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.80</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.58</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>29.39</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>ROSM</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>2.58</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label/>
              <p>Values are fold change calculated with the 2<sup>–ΔΔCt</sup> method and normalized to actin in trophosome compared to plume. <italic>Outliers are shown in italics (</italic>see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref><italic>).</italic></p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>The majority of the PRRs analyzed, including all five of the PGRPs and a Toll-like receptor (TLR) showed between five and one hundred-fold higher expression in the trophosome compared to the plume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The NF-κB inhibitory protein was up-regulated in the trophosome along with the alpha-2 macroglobulin receptor and LITAF. Immune and stress-associated genes that were expressed similarly between the tissues included the lipobinding protein, macrophage inhibitory factor, and the reactive oxygen species-associated gene. The mannose receptor was found to have lower expression in the trophosome. As predicted, tissue-specific carbonic anhydrases showed expression levels indicating differential expression between the trophosome and plume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g001">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The main objective of this study was to examine gene expression in the trophosome (the organ where symbionts are housed in bacteriocytes), and the plume (the site of metabolite exchange and where the host encounters free-living microorganisms), in order to better understand how this association remains stable and highly productive. Our results indicate that, during high chemoautotrophic productivity, <italic>R. piscesae</italic> differentially expresses a suite of genes in the trophosome and the plume that are involved with detecting and responding to bacteria, cell stress and the regulation of cell cycle. The substantial expression of putative receptors in the trophosome that are involved with recognizing bacterial MAMPs suggests that elements of the host’s innate immune system are involved with mediating interactions with the endosymbiont population. A suite of other genes associated with innate immunity, as well as cell signaling and stress, were differentially expressed in the trophosome. When considered in the context of previous research on the structural morphology within the trophosomes of siboglinid tubeworms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bosch1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Pflugfelder1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-deBurgh1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright3">[62]</xref>, the data presented herein support the hypothesis that an orderly but complex host and symbiont cell cycle is important in maintaining symbiostasis. Furthermore, these results demonstrate differential expression of innate immunity genes between the trophosome and the plume, suggesting that different strategies are adopted by the host in response to regulation of the intracellular symbionts contained within the trophosome and free-living microorganisms found in the external environment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). The paragraphs below address these observations and discuss the implications in greater detail.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0038267-g002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Model of host-symbiont interactions between pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) and microbe-associated molecular patterns (MAMPs) in <italic>R. piscesae</italic>.</title>
          <p>The branchial plume (p) of <italic>Ridgeia</italic> exchanges metabolites with the environment. The plume lacks symbionts but may still use PRRs to interact with microorganisms found in the surrounding vent fluid and seawater. The center of the worm is comprised mainly of one organ, the trophosome (t) made up of lobules that contain bacteriocytes housing the intracellular bacterial symbionts (endosymbionts) as well as blood vessels (bv) that transfer metabolites. Central bacteriocytes (c) harbor healthy and actively dividing endosymbionts. Towards the periphery of the lobules, bacteriocytes and symbionts appear to undergo terminal differentiation and apoptosis with many of the degenerative symbionts undergoing autophagy. We suggest a significantly greater response of the trophosome to MAMPs via PRRs that may trigger signal transduction cascades, ultimately helping to regulate symbiostasis. PRR expression in the trophosome may occur in the bacteriocytes and/or in the surrounding vasculature. Given the densities of endosymbionts, bacteriocytes encounter high concentrations of MAMPs. A constant turnover of bacteriocytes may also release extracellular MAMPs into the trophosome periphery.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Many of the genes identified from the trophosome and plume transcriptomes, including those with predicted immune function, were expressed in both tissues (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t002">Table 2</xref>). This is not surprising considering that both tissues are in direct contact with microorganisms. The trophosome of <italic>R. pachyptila</italic> hosts a tremendous density (ca. 10<sup>9</sup> bacteria per cm<sup>−3</sup>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Cavanaugh1">[3]</xref>) of a nearly monospecific population of gammaproteobacterial symbionts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Laue1">[48]</xref>. <italic>Ridgeia</italic> also has a similar density and composition of symbionts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-deBurgh1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Laue1">[48]</xref>. The plume sits at the interface between the host and the environment and will invariably encounter non-symbiotic, and potentially pathogenic, microorganisms that reside in the surrounding seawater. Unlike other chemoautotrophic associations (discussed below), <italic>R. piscesae</italic> and all siboglinid tubeworms provide a unique opportunity to examine differential gene expression in these two distinct tissues that interact with different microbial populations, since –to our knowledge– the trophosome does not encounter a substantial number of exogenous bacteria and the plume does not interact with the symbionts.</p>
      <p>Among host/bacterial associations, MAMPs such as lipopolysaccharide (LPS), bacterial lipoproteins, and peptidoglycan and its derivatives, lead to the activation of innate immunity effectors through interactions with specific host PRRs. This activation involves well-regulated signaling cascades and the induction of host functions such as innate immunity activation, apoptosis, mucus secretion, and cell regression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Koropatnick1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Dziarski1">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bittel1">[63]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm2">[65]</xref>. Indeed, hosts often exhibit phenotypes that appear to be induced by the detection of MAMPs associated with their symbionts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Dethlefsen1">[43]</xref>. In many symbioses, fine-tuned molecular communication between symbionts and hosts via PRR interactions with MAMPs appears to help maintain specificity and stability of the associations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Dethlefsen1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-McFallNgai1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Kvennefors1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Wells1">[67]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Examination of genes expressed by both the trophosome and the plume revealed five putative homologues of peptidoglycan recognition proteins (PGRPs) in <italic>Ridgeia</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t002">Table 2</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t003">3</xref>). Evidence is growing that PGRPs are common among a diversity of metazoans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Chaput1">[68]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Royet1">[69]</xref>. One of the <italic>Ridgeia</italic> PGRPs (Rpi1) has homology (42% at the amino acid level) to a putative PGRP (EsPGRP3) from the Hawaiian bobtail squid <italic>Euprymna scolopes</italic>. In that system, four homologues of the PGRP family have been implicated in playing a role in the development of the association between the host and its bioluminescent bacterial symbiont <italic>Vibrio fischeri</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Goodson1">[70]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Troll2">[72]</xref>. Two other PGRPs detected in <italic>Ridgeia</italic>, Rpi2 and Rpi5, have homology to PGRP-SC3 and PGRP-LE. In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, these PGRPs have been implicated in regulating gut homeostasis of ingested bacteria and the mediation of host response to intracellular pathogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bischoff1">[73]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Kurata1">[74]</xref>. Protein domain predictions of the five PGRPs from <italic>Ridgeia</italic> suggest that they are found both intracellular and at the membrane surface, with three of the five (Rpi1, Rpi2 and Rpi4) also having the potential of being secreted (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t003">Table 3</xref>), suggesting that the host can respond to peptidoglycan in multiple locations in the trophosome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). At least one of these PGRPs, Rpi2, has predicted amidase activity suggesting that it may also degrade peptidoglycan, a phenomenon that has been shown to be important in regulating symbionts of other invertebrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Troll2">[72]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bischoff1">[73]</xref>. Although a putative PGRP was found in a cDNA library from the hydrothermal vent polychaete <italic>Alvinella pompejana</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Gagniere1">[54]</xref>, to our knowledge this is the first description of multiple PGRPs from a member of the annelids.</p>
      <p>To quantify differences in gene expression between the two tissues in each of the six individual tubeworms, we employed qPCR that targeted key PRRs, and other innate immunity and cell stress response genes. All of the <italic>Ridgeia</italic> PGRPs showed markedly higher expression in the trophosome relative to the plume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The relative abundance of these PRRs in the trophosome suggests that the host may employ mechanisms to detect symbiont MAMPs. Notably, the bacterial “load” of the trophosome is significantly greater than the environment, with the symbionts comprising as much as 25% of the biomass of the trophosome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Pflugfelder1">[37]</xref>. As such, the bacterial cell numbers that the host is exposed to in this tissue will be orders of magnitude greater than what the plume experiences (the microbial load in seawater/vent fluid is typically 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Jeanthon1">[75]</xref>, and the substantial difference in gene expression may be a manifestation of this higher microbial density (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g002">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>MAMPs are also known to stimulate host signaling and gene expression via the evolutionarily conserved Toll/NF-κB signaling pathway that leads to expression of immunity effectors in both pathogenic and mutualistic associations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Chaput1">[68]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Pal1">[76]</xref>. Toll-like receptors have been described in a number of invertebrate phyla, including among annelids such as the leech, <italic>Hirudo medicinalis</italic> and the polychaete, <italic>Capitella capitata</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Davidson1">[53]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Macagno1">[77]</xref>. Five putative members of the Toll/NF-κB signaling family were identified in <italic>Ridgeia</italic>, including homologues to a Toll-like receptor, cactus, Iκ-B alpha, Iκ-B-epsilon, and NF-κB repressing factor (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t002">Table 2</xref>). qPCR showed that the putative NF-κB inhibitor was expressed, on average, greater than two fold in the trophosome compared to the plume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Future studies should determine whether other members of the NF-κB signaling pathway are differentially regulated in these tissues and, ideally, their presence in differentiated bacteriocytes under various environmental conditions.</p>
      <p>Other expressed innate immunity genes included members of the immunoglobulin super family; an alpha-2 macroglobulin receptor, a plasminogen precursor, a leucine-rich repeat (LRR) receptor and a serum protein (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t002">Table 2</xref>). Homologues for the putative proteins encoded by these genes, and/or their binding partners, such as alpha-2 macroglobulins, have been shown to function as broad-spectrum protease-binding proteins as well as mediators of lectin-dependent cytolytic pathways in arthropod defense <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Armstrong1">[78]</xref>, yet need to be further explored in this association.</p>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Emerging Hypotheses from the Plume and Trophosome Transcriptomes</title>
        <p>The trophosome and plume transcriptomes of <italic>Ridgeia</italic> also revealed a number of genes known to be involved with regulating cell cycle, apoptosis, and cell growth, including known mediators of cell cycle and apoptosis in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t002">Table 2</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Murphy1">[79]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Tsuchiya1">[80]</xref>. Genes were also expressed that both help induce (GRIM-19 and LITAF) and inhibit apoptosis (DAD-1) in other systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Moharikar1">[81]</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038267-t002">Table 2</xref>). Development and cell patterning and signaling genes, along with a number of transcription factors implicated in development and differentiation in other associations, were also identified <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Heard1">[82]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Messenguy1">[83]</xref>. Apoptosis is a common mechanism for maintaining tissue homeostasis. Whether these factors may regulate cell division in the trophosome remains to be determined. However, morphological and immunohistological observations of tubeworm bacteriocytes suggest that both the host cells and the symbionts transition from a healthy state with intact membranes to one of cell degradation and apoptosis during normal cell turnover <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Pflugfelder1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright3">[62]</xref>.</p>
        <p>The molecular regulation of bacteriocyte development has not been described for <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic> or any siboglinid tubeworm in great detail. Although this study did not attempt to characterize bacteriocyte gene expression specifically, the trophosome is highly enriched in bacteriocytes, making up 70% of the trophosome volume in <italic>R. pachyptila</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright3">[62]</xref>. Based on the results of this study and prior observations, we posit that a well-regulated dialogue occurs between both host and symbiont to ensure symbiostasis in the trophosome during conditions that promote high productivity. In previous studies, Bosch and Grasse first proposed and Bright and colleagues developed the “cell cycle with terminal differentiation” hypothesis, which states that the bacteriocytes of <italic>R. pachyptila</italic> exhibit a tractable, well-orchestrated cycle of growth and cell death, allowing for a well-regulated density of bacteria and bacteriocytes within the trophosome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bosch1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bosch2">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright3">[62]</xref>. These studies also showed that the bacteriocytes contain high densities of bacteria (the symbionts comprise 24.1% of the trophosome volume). Given that the vast majority of Gram-negative bacteria have an outer membrane containing LPS and a cell wall with peptidoglycan, and these compounds are often shed during cell division and lysis, host bacteriocytes are likely exposed to high concentrations of bacterial MAMPs. In addition it has been shown that the trophosome of <italic>R. pachyptila</italic> is enriched in LPS, containing 0.8 µg per milligram of tissue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Cavanaugh1">[3]</xref>. These observations are consistent with, if not indicative of, a suite and abundance of innate immunity and cell signaling genes expressed by <italic>Ridgeia</italic>, perhaps in response to symbiont MAMPs. Based on the data from this and previous studies, we extend a hypothetical model to <italic>Ridgeia</italic>, that the innate immune system of the host plays a critical role in maintaining symbiostasis within the trophosome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). We hypothesize that pattern recognition receptors expressed in the trophosome mediate bacterial cell signaling triggered by symbiont MAMPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). These genes are candidates for regulating the complicated bacteriocyte and symbiont cell cycles that have been observed in these associations. In <italic>Riftia</italic>, for example, there is both morphological and molecular evidence that the host bacteriocytes, along with the symbionts, undergo increasing cell death towards the periphery of the trophosome lobules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Pflugfelder1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright3">[62]</xref>. Consistent morphological observations have also been made in <italic>R. piscesae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-deBurgh1">[47]</xref>. It has been suggested that a significant fraction of the symbiont population may also be digested at any given time by the host <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright3">[62]</xref>. Although the PRRs of <italic>R. piscesae</italic> have yet to be localized at the cellular level, PGRPs and TLRs can be expressed in a variety of cellular locations (e.g., at the membrane surface, in the cytoplasm, in the nucleus or even secreted) in a number of different systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Dziarski1">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Goodson1">[70]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Troll2">[72]</xref>. Given these findings, we further hypothesize that PRR interactions with MAMPs in the trophosome of <italic>Ridgeia</italic> are likely occurring within bacteriocytes and/or with the surrounding vasculature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). We also suggest that the host’s innate immune system interacts with the dense population of endosymbionts in the trophosome via different mechanisms than with the free-living non-symbiotic microorganisms that undoubtedly come into contact with the plume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038267-g002">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>The data presented here represent one of a few studies to analyze gene expression of a hydrothermal vent association under <italic>in situ</italic> conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bettencourt1">[84]</xref>. However, these data are the only to date that examine gene expression at environmentally relevant conditions, during high productivity, when the opportunity for symbiont growth is arguably the highest. Moreover, a recent study of <italic>Bathymodiolus azoricus,</italic> a hydrothermal vent mussel, identified a number of innate immunity genes in this host <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bettencourt1">[84]</xref>. Many of the PRRs described in our study, including the PGRPs and TLR, appear to have homology to those described for this symbiotic bivalve (data not shown). However, the gills of vent mussels, which house endosymbiotic bacteria, are also in direct contact with seawater. This may confound the ability to examine which molecular mechanism(s) are associated with host-endosymbiont interactions versus those responsible for combating pathogens or interacting with environmental microorganisms.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p>In such a closed and intimate association as that which occurs between hydrothermal vent tubeworms and their bacterial symbionts (which, in the adult host, are never in contact with the external milieu), regulation of bacteriocyte and symbiont cell density and division is likely required to maintain a stable association. Previous studies suggest that symbiont digestion, as well as carbon translocation, may be the primary modes of regulating symbiont numbers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Felbeck2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright2">[36]</xref>. However, the complexity of the host bacteriocyte and symbiont cell cycles implies a high degree of regulation that is sustained through multiple mechanisms. Via cell-cell signaling between the partners, the host may be better poised to promote optimal carbon fixation while preventing symbiont overgrowth to its detriment. Although the trophosome is enriched in bacteriocytes (70% by volume <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Bright3">[62]</xref>), we recognize there are other cells that compose this tissue, e.g., the vasculature and peritoneum. As such, we cannot yet assign specific gene functions to specific host cell types. Nevertheless, the trophosome is indeed the sole location of the symbionts, and the organ is the primary site of interaction between the partners. Therefore, we hypothesize that our current gene expression analyses reflect gross yet biologically relevant differences between the bacteria-enriched trophosome and the plume. Future studies should focus on analyzing MAMP/PRR interactions within bacteriocytes and in different regions within the trophosome.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0038267.s001" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) and oxygen uptake by </bold><bold><italic>R. piscesae</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> ∑CO<sub>2</sub> (i.e., the uptake of dissolved inorganic carbon) and O<sub>2</sub> uptake rates (µmol·g<sup>–1</sup>·h<sup>–1</sup>) by <italic>Ridgeia</italic> were recorded over 70 hours under either quasi-<italic>in situ</italic> conditions (described as “optimal” conditions) or sulfide limiting conditions. All rates are expressed in terms of wet mass. During all respirometry experiments, tubeworms were maintained in the high-pressure respirometry system (HPRS; as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Girguis3">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">[40]</xref>. <italic>Ridgeia</italic> optimal conditions were 5.5 mmol l<sup>−1</sup> ∑CO<sub>2</sub>; 215–230 µmol l<sup>−1</sup> H<sub>2</sub>S; 150 µmol l<sup>−1</sup> O<sub>2</sub>; 40 µmol l<sup>−1</sup> NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>; pH 5.9; 15°C; and 27.5 MPa. Limiting conditions were the same, except the H<sub>2</sub>S concentration was 50 µmol l<sup>−1</sup>. To determine substrate uptake rates, seawater was collected pre- and post-aquarium for chemical analyses. For total CO<sub>2</sub> (∑CO<sub>2</sub>) and O<sub>2</sub> concentrations, 30 ml of effluent was added to N<sub>2</sub>-purged 50-ml serum vials containing 3 ml of concentrated NaOH. ∑CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations were measured by adjusting the pH to 3 using degassed HCl, and measuring <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> in the headspace using a blood gas analyzer (Capni-Con II, Cameron Instruments). O<sub>2</sub> concentrations were measured using a gas chromatograph with a thermal conductivity detector (Agilent 6890N, as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0038267-Childress2">[9]</xref>).</p>
          <p>(EPS)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0038267.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>KOG analysis and comparison of </bold><bold><italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic></bold><bold> trophosome and plume ESTs and 454-generated contigs.</bold> Significant matches to sequences in the KOG database were determined using the tblastx BLAST program (NCBI), and KOG categories were accordingly assigned. Percentages are based on the number of sequences successfully assigned to categories for each database.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0038267.s003" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Quantitative RT-PCR primer sequences for target genes.</bold> F  =  Forward primer, R  =  Reverse primer, T<sub>A</sub>  =  Temperature used for annealing step of qPCR reaction. The gene abbreviations are as follows: Actin; β-actin: EF1α; elongation factor 1-alpha: TLR2p; toll-like receptor 2 precursor: NFκBic; NF-kappa-B inhibitor (cactus): A2MRAP; alpha-2 macroglobulin receptor associated protein: HSP70; heat shock protein 70: LBPIP; LPS induced bactericidal permeability increasing protein: LITAF; lipopolysaccharide-induced tumor necrosis factor-alpha: MMIF; macrophage migration inhibitory factor: MR; macrophage mannose receptor 1-like protein: CAtr; carbonic anhydrase (trophosome): CAbr; carbonic anhydrase (brachial plume): ROSm; reactive oxygen species modulator: PGRPrpi1–5; peptidoglycan recognition protein 1–5: hbB1; hemoglobin B1.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0038267.s004" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0038267.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Putative identities of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Ridgeia</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> genes found in ESTs and used in quantitative RT-PCR.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We are grateful for the hard work and efforts of the crew of the <italic>RV Atlantis</italic> and <italic>DSV Alvin</italic>. We would like to thank Dr. Deborah Kelley for being Chief Scientist and members of the Girguis lab for their assistance during the expedition, especially Dr. Helen White. We thank Dr. Pascal LaPierre and the University of Connecticut Bioinformatics Facility for computing resources and assistance with the KOG analysis. Thank you to Virge Kask for assistance with illustrations and Dr. Bethany Rader for helpful comments about the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Dubilier1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubilier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Symbiotic diversity in marine animals: the art of harnessing chemosynthesis.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>725</fpage>             <page-range>740</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Stewart1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavanaugh</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Symbiosis of thioautotrophic bacteria with <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Basis of Symbiosis</source>             <fpage>197</fpage>             <page-range>225</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Cavanaugh1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavanaugh</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jannasch</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waterbury</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Prokaryotic Cells in the Hydrothermal Vent Tube Worm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> Jones: Possible Chemoautotrophic Symbionts.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>213</volume>             <fpage>340</fpage>             <page-range>342</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Felbeck1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Felbeck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Chemoautotrophic Potential of the Hydrothermal Vent Tube Worm, <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> Jones (Vestimentifera).</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>213</volume>             <fpage>336</fpage>             <page-range>338</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Childress1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Favuzzi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kochevar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Sulfide-driven autotrophic balance in the bacterial symbiont-containing hydrothermal vent tubeworm, <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> Jones.</article-title>             <source>The Biological Bulletin</source>             <volume>180</volume>             <fpage>135</fpage>             <page-range>153</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Fisher1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minnich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Autotrophic carbon fixation by the chemoautotrophic symbionts of <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>The Biological Bulletin</source>             <volume>177</volume>             <fpage>372</fpage>             <page-range>385</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Girguis1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girguis</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desaulniers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pospesel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Fate of Nitrate Acquired by the Tubeworm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Applied and environmental microbiology</source>             <volume>66</volume>             <fpage>2783</fpage>             <page-range>2790</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Hentschel1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hentschel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felbeck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Nitrate respiration in the hydrothermal vent tubeworm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>366</volume>             <fpage>388</fpage>             <page-range>340</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Childress2">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>Metabolic and blood characteristics of the hydrothermal vent tube-worm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Marine Biology</source>             <volume>83</volume>             <fpage>109</fpage>             <page-range>124</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Fisher2">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Distel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Physiology, morphology, and biochemical composition of <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> at Rose Garden in 1985.</article-title>             <source>Deep Sea Research Part A Oceanographic Research Papers</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>1745</fpage>             <page-range>1758</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Nussbaumer1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nussbaumer</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Horizontal endosymbiont transmission in hydrothermal vent tubeworms.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>441</volume>             <fpage>345</fpage>             <page-range>348</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Bright1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lallier</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The biology of vestimentiferan tubeworms.</article-title>             <source>Oceanography and Marine Biology</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>213</fpage>             <page-range>265</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Arp1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arp</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Blood function in the hydrothermal vent vestimentiferan tube worm.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>213</volume>             <fpage>342</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Arp2">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arp</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1983</year>             <article-title>Sulfide binding by the blood of the hydrothermal vent tube worm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>219</volume>             <fpage>295</fpage>             <page-range>297</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-DeCian1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Cian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regnault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lallier</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Nitrogen metabolites and related enzymatic activities in the body fluids and tissues of the hydrothermal vent tubeworm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Journal of experimental biology</source>             <volume>203</volume>             <fpage>2907</fpage>             <page-range>2920</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Flores1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freytag</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Sulfide binding is mediated by zinc ions discovered in the crystal structure of a hydrothermal vent tubeworm hemoglobin.</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>             <volume>102</volume>             <fpage>2713</fpage>             <page-range>2718</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Goffredi1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goffredi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lallier</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desaulniers</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>The Ionic Composition of the Hydrothermal Vent Tube Worm Riftia pachyptila: Evidence for the Elimination of SO2–4SO and H+ for a Cl−/HCO-3HCO shift.</article-title>             <source>Physiological and biochemical zoology</source>             <volume>72</volume>             <fpage>296</fpage>             <page-range>306</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Goffredi2">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goffredi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girguis</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desaulniers</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Physiological functioning of carbonic anhydrase in the hydrothermal vent tubeworm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>The Biological Bulletin</source>             <volume>196</volume>             <fpage>257</fpage>             <page-range>264</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Kochevar1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kochevar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Carbonic anhydrase in deep-sea chemoautotrophic symbioses.</article-title>             <source>Marine Biology</source>             <volume>125</volume>             <fpage>375</fpage>             <page-range>383</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Sanchez1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hourdez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lallier</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Identification, sequencing, and localization of a new carbonic anhydrase transcript from the hydrothermal vent tubeworm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>FEBS Journal</source>             <volume>274</volume>             <fpage>5311</fpage>             <page-range>5324</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Felbeck2">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Felbeck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarchow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Carbon Release from Purified Chemoautotrophic Bacterial Symbionts of the Hydrothermal Vent Tubeworm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Physiological Zoology</source>             <volume>71</volume>             <fpage>294</fpage>             <page-range>302</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Girguis2">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girguis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freytag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Effects of metabolite uptake on proton-equivalent elimination by two species of deep-sea vestimentiferan tubeworm, <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> and <italic>Lamellibrachia cf luymesi</italic>: proton elimination is a necessary adaptation to sulfide-oxidizing chemoautotrophic symbionts.</article-title>             <source>Journal of experimental biology</source>             <volume>205</volume>             <fpage>3055</fpage>             <page-range>3066</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Girguis3">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girguis</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Metabolite uptake, stoichiometry and chemoautotrophic function of the hydrothermal vent tubeworm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>: responses to environmental variations in substrate concentrations and temperature.</article-title>             <source>Journal of experimental biology</source>             <volume>209</volume>             <fpage>3516</fpage>             <page-range>3528</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Markert1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felbeck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sievert</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Physiological proteomics of the uncultured endosymbiont of <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>315</volume>             <fpage>247</fpage>             <page-range>250</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Robidart1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robidart</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girguis</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Linking hydrothermal geochemistry to organismal physiology: physiological versatility in <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> from sedimented and basalt-hosted vents.</article-title>             <source>PLoS One</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>e21692</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Robidart2">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robidart</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bench</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novoradovsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Podell</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Metabolic versatility of the <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> endosymbiont revealed through metagenomics.</article-title>             <source>Environ Microbiol</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>727</fpage>             <page-range>737</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Cooper1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kauschke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cossarizza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Annelid humoral immunity: cell lysis in earthworms.</article-title>             <source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source>             <volume>484</volume>             <fpage>169</fpage>             <page-range>183</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Govenar1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Govenar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Bris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gollner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glanville</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aperghis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Epifaunal community structure associated with <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> aggregations in chemically different hydrothermal vent habitats.</article-title>             <source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source>             <volume>305</volume>             <fpage>67</fpage>             <page-range>77</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Hessler1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hessler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smithey Jr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1983</year>             <article-title>The distribution and community structure of megafauna at the Galapagos Rift hydrothermal vents.</article-title>             <source>Hydrothermal processes at seafloor spreading centers</source>             <fpage>735</fpage>             <page-range>770</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Shank1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shank</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fornari</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Von Damm</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haymon</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Temporal and spatial patterns of biological community development at nascent deep-sea hydrothermal vents (9 50′ N, East Pacific Rise).</article-title>             <source>Deep-Sea Research Part II</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>465</fpage>             <page-range>515</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Hurtado1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurtado</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Distinct patterns of genetic differentiation among annelids of eastern Pacific hydrothermal vents.</article-title>             <source>Molecular ecology</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>2603</fpage>             <page-range>2615</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Marsh1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullineaux</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manahan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Larval dispersal potential of the tubeworm Riftia pachyptila at deep-sea hydrothermal vents.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>411</volume>             <fpage>77</fpage>             <page-range>80</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Reid1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>RGB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Biological emergences: Evolution by natural experiment: The MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.</article-title>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Bosch1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grasse</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984a</year>             <article-title>Cycle partiel des bacteries chimioautotrophes symbiotiques et leurs rapport avec les bactericoytes chez <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> Jones (Pogonophora Vestimentifere). I. Le trophosome et les bacteriocytes.</article-title>             <source>Cr hebd Seanc Acad Sci, Paris</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>371</fpage>             <page-range>376</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Bosch2">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grasse</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984b</year>             <article-title>Cycle partiel des bacteries chimiautotrophes symbiotiques et leurs rapport avec les bacteriocytes chez <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> Jones (Pogonophora Vestimintifere) II. L'evolution des bacteries symbiotiques et des bacteriocytes.</article-title>             <source>CR Hebd Seanc Acad Sci, Paris</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>413</fpage>             <page-range>419</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Bright2">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keckeis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>An autoradiographic examination of carbon fixation, transfer and utilization in the <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> symbiosis.</article-title>             <source>Marine Biology</source>             <volume>136</volume>             <fpage>621</fpage>             <page-range>632</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Pflugfelder1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pflugfelder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cary</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Dynamics of cell proliferation and apoptosis reflect different life strategies in hydrothermal vent and cold seep vestimentiferan tubeworms.</article-title>             <source>Cell and tissue research</source>             <volume>337</volume>             <fpage>149</fpage>             <page-range>165</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-DeCian2">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Cian</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailly</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lallier</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Expression and localization of carbonic anhydrase and ATPases in the symbiotic tubeworm <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Journal of experimental biology</source>             <volume>206</volume>             <fpage>399</fpage>             <page-range>409</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Ruan1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Molecular characteristics of the tubeworm, <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic>, from the deep-sea hydrothermal vent.</article-title>             <source>Extremophiles</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>735</fpage>             <page-range>739</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Nyholm1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyholm</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robidart</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girguis</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Coupling metabolite flux to transcriptomics: insights into the molecular mechanisms underlying primary productivity by the hydrothermal vent tubeworm <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>The Biological Bulletin</source>             <volume>214</volume>             <fpage>255</fpage>             <page-range>265</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Fitt1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Cellular growth of host and symbiont in a cnidarian-zooxanthellar symbiosis.</article-title>             <source>The Biological Bulletin</source>             <volume>198</volume>             <fpage>110</fpage>             <page-range>120</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Benson1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pifer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrendt</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yarovinsky</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Gut commensal bacteria direct a protective immune response against Toxoplasma gondii.</article-title>             <source>Cell Host &amp; Microbe</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>187</fpage>             <page-range>196</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Dethlefsen1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dethlefsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McFall-Ngai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>An ecological and evolutionary perspective on human-microbe mutualism and disease.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>449</volume>             <fpage>811</fpage>             <page-range>818</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Dunn1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Apoptosis as a post-phagocytic winnowing mechanism in a coral–dinoflagellate mutualism.</article-title>             <source>Environ Microbiol</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>268</fpage>             <page-range>276</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Koropatnick1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koropatnick</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engle</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apicella</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stabb</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Microbial factor-mediated development in a host-bacterial mutualism.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>306</volume>             <fpage>1186</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-McFallNgai1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <article-title>McFall-Ngai M, Nyholm SV, Castillo MG. The role of the immune system in the initiation and persistence of the <italic>Euprymna scolopes-Vibrio fischeri</italic> symbiosis; 2010. Semin. Immunol.</article-title>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>48</fpage>             <page-range>53</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-deBurgh1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>deBurgh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juniper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Bacterial symbiosis in Northeast Pacific Vestimentifera: a TEM study.</article-title>             <source>Marine Biology</source>             <volume>101</volume>             <fpage>97</fpage>             <page-range>105</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Laue1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laue</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Sulfur-oxidizing symbionts have not co-evolved with their hydrothermal vent tube worm hosts: an RFLP analysis.</article-title>             <source>Mol Mar Biol Biotechnol</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>180</fpage>             <page-range>188</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Carney1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orobona</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butterfield</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Environmental differences in hemoglobin gene expression in the hydrothermal vent tubeworm, <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part B: Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</source>             <volume>146</volume>             <fpage>326</fpage>             <page-range>337</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Peng1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Ultrastructural evidence for iron accumulation within the tube of Vestimentiferan <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Biometals</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>723</fpage>             <page-range>732</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Young1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Directional dispersal between mid-ocean ridges: deep-ocean circulation and gene flow in <italic>Ridgeia piscesae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Molecular ecology</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>1718</fpage>             <page-range>1731</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Altincicek1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altincicek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilcinskas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Analysis of the immune-related transcriptome of a lophotrochozoan model, the marine annelid <italic>Platynereis dumerilii</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Front Zool</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>18</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Davidson1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Best</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Toll-like receptor genes (TLRs) from <italic>Capitella capitata</italic> and <italic>Helobdella robusta</italic> (Annelida).</article-title>             <source>Dev Comp Immunol</source>             <volume>32</volume>             <fpage>608</fpage>             <page-range>612</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Gagniere1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagniere</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jollivet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutet</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brelivet</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Busso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Insights into metazoan evolution from <italic>Alvinella pompejana</italic> cDNAs.</article-title>             <source>BMC genomics</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>634</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Livak1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2-[Delta][Delta] CT method.</article-title>             <source>Methods</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>402</fpage>             <page-range>408</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Andersen1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orntoft</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Normalization of real-time quantitative reverse transcription-PCR data: a model-based variance estimation approach to identify genes suited for normalization, applied to bladder and colon cancer data sets.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>64</volume>             <fpage>5245</fpage>             <page-range>5250</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Henry1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Metabolic rates and thermal tolerances of chemoautotrophic symbioses from Lau Basin hydrothermal vents and their implications for species distributions.</article-title>             <source>Deep Sea Research Part I: Oceanographic Research Papers</source>             <volume>55</volume>             <fpage>679</fpage>             <page-range>695</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Dziarski1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dziarski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Review: Mammalian peptidoglycan recognition proteins (PGRPs) in innate immunity.</article-title>             <source>Innate Immunity</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>168</fpage>             <page-range>174</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Leulier1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leulier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemaitre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Toll-like receptors–taking an evolutionary approach.</article-title>             <source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>165</fpage>             <page-range>178</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Rosenstiel1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenstiel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philipp</surname><given-names>EER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Evolution and function of innate immune receptors–insights from marine invertebrates.</article-title>             <source>Innate Immun</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>291</fpage>             <page-range>300</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Miyake1">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Invited review: Roles for accessory molecules in microbial recognition by Toll-like receptors.</article-title>             <source>Journal of endotoxin research</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>195</fpage>             <page-range>204</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Bright3">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorgo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Ultrastructural reinvestigation of the trophosome in adults of <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> (Annelida, Siboglinidae).</article-title>             <source>Invertebrate Biology</source>             <volume>122</volume>             <fpage>347</fpage>             <page-range>368</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Bittel1">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bittel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robatzek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Microbe-associated molecular patterns (MAMPs) probe plant immunity.</article-title>             <source>Current opinion in plant biology</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>335</fpage>             <page-range>341</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Nrnberger1">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nürnberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemmerling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Innate immunity in plants and animals: striking similarities and obvious differences.</article-title>             <source>Immunological reviews</source>             <volume>198</volume>             <fpage>249</fpage>             <page-range>266</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Nyholm2">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyholm</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McFall-Ngai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>The winnowing: establishing the squid–<italic>Vibrio</italic> symbiosis.</article-title>             <source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>632</fpage>             <page-range>642</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Kvennefors1">
        <label>66</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kvennefors</surname><given-names>ECE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leggat</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoegh-Guldberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Analysis of evolutionarily conserved innate immune components in coral links immunity and symbiosis.</article-title>             <source>Developmental &amp; Comparative Immunology</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>1219</fpage>             <page-range>1229</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Wells1">
        <label>67</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijerink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Baarlen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Epithelial crosstalk at the microbiota–mucosal interface.</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>             <volume>108</volume>             <fpage>4607</fpage>             <page-range>4614</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Chaput1">
        <label>68</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaput</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boneca</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Peptidoglycan detection by mammals and flies.</article-title>             <source>Microbes and Infection</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>637</fpage>             <page-range>647</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Royet1">
        <label>69</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Royet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dziarski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Peptidoglycan recognition proteins: modulators of the microbiome and inflammation.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>837</fpage>             <page-range>851</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Goodson1">
        <label>70</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kojadinovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troll</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheetz</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casavant</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Identifying components of the NF-kappaB pathway in the beneficial <italic>Euprymna scolopes-Vibrio fischeri</italic> light organ symbiosis.</article-title>             <source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source>             <volume>71</volume>             <fpage>6934</fpage>             <page-range>6946</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Troll1">
        <label>71</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Troll</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wier</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paquette</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Peptidoglycan induces loss of a nuclear peptidoglycan recognition protein during host tissue development in a beneficial animal-bacterial symbiosis.</article-title>             <source>Cellular Microbiology</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>1114</fpage>             <page-range>1127</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Troll2">
        <label>72</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Troll</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacquette</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wier</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Taming the symbiont for coexistence: a host PGRP neutralizes a bacterial symbiont toxin.</article-title>             <source>Environ Microbiol</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>2190</fpage>             <page-range>2203</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Bischoff1">
        <label>73</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bischoff</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vignal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duvic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boneca</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Downregulation of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> immune response by peptidoglycan-recognition proteins SC1 and SC2.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Pathogens</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>e14</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Kurata1">
        <label>74</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Extracellular and intracellular pathogen recognition by <italic>Drosophila</italic> PGRP-LE and PGRP-LC.</article-title>             <source>International immunology</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>143</fpage>             <page-range>148</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Jeanthon1">
        <label>75</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeanthon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Molecular ecology of hydrothermal vent microbial communities.</article-title>             <source>Antonie van Leeuwenhoek</source>             <volume>77</volume>             <fpage>117</fpage>             <page-range>133</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Pal1">
        <label>76</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Lessons from the fly: pattern recognition in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>. Target Pattern Recognition in Innate Immunity.</article-title>             <source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source>             <volume>653</volume>             <fpage>162</fpage>             <page-range>174</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Macagno1">
        <label>77</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macagno</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaasterland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edsall</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bafna</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Construction of a medicinal leech transcriptome database and its application to the identification of leech homologs of neural and innate immune genes.</article-title>             <source>BMC Genomics</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>407</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Armstrong1">
        <label>78</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Alpha2-macroglobulin: an evolutionarily conserved arm of the innate immune system.</article-title>             <source>Developmental &amp; Comparative Immunology</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>375</fpage>             <page-range>390</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Murphy1">
        <label>79</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Drosophila skpA, a component of SCF ubiquitin ligases, regulates centrosome duplication independently of cyclin E accumulation.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Cell Science</source>             <volume>116</volume>             <fpage>2321</fpage>             <page-range>2332</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Tsuchiya1">
        <label>80</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawase</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okudaira</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> rfc1 gene by the DRE–DREF pathway.</article-title>             <source>FEBS Journal</source>             <volume>274</volume>             <fpage>1818</fpage>             <page-range>1832</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Moharikar1">
        <label>81</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moharikar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D’souza</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A homologue of the defender against the apoptotic death gene (dad1) in UV-exposed <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> cells is downregulated with the onset of programmed cell death.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Biosciences</source>             <volume>32</volume>             <fpage>261</fpage>             <page-range>270</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Heard1">
        <label>82</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Symbiotic induction of a MADS-box gene during development of alfalfa root nodules.</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>             <volume>92</volume>             <fpage>5273</fpage>             <page-range>5277</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Messenguy1">
        <label>83</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Messenguy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Role of MADS box proteins and their cofactors in combinatorial control of gene expression and cell development.</article-title>             <source>Gene</source>             <volume>316</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <page-range>21</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Bettencourt1">
        <label>84</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bettencourt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>High-throughput sequencing and analysis of the gill tissue transcriptome from the deep-sea hydrothermal vent mussel <italic>Bathymodiolus azoricus</italic>.</article-title>             <source>BMC Genomics</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>559</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Altschul1">
        <label>85</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>3389</fpage>             <page-range>3402</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0038267-Horton1">
        <label>86</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>WoLF PSORT: protein localization predictor.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>W585</fpage>             <page-range>W587</page-range>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>