<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-23237</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110094</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Ion channels</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell death</subject><subj-group><subject>Apoptosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Transcriptome analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Serial analysis of gene expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Electrophysiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Basic cancer research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Bioassays and physiological analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Microarrays</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Database and informatics methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Bioinformatics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Expression Profiling of Mitochondrial Voltage-Dependent Anion Channel-1 Associated Genes Predicts Recurrence-Free Survival in Human Carcinomas</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Mitochondrial Voltage-Dependent Anion Channel 1 and Human Cancers</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>Jae-Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Wanjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Inja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Tong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>Hyoweon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Physiology, College of Medicine, Chung-Ang University, Seoul, South Korea</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Research Center for Learning Sciences, Southeast University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Medicine, University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Aamir</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University College London, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">tongzhou@email.arizona.edu</email> (TZ); <email xlink:type="simple">haena@cau.ac.kr</email> (HB)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JHK WG IL TZ HB. Performed the experiments: JHK WG IL TZ HB. Analyzed the data: JHK WG TZ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JHK WG TZ. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: JHK WG IL TZ HB.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<elocation-id>e110094</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Ko et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>Mitochondrial voltage-dependent anion channels (VDACs) play a key role in mitochondria-mediated apoptosis. Both <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> evidences indicate that VDACs are actively involved in tumor progression. Specifically, VDAC-1, one member of the VDAC family, was thought to be a potential anti-cancer therapeutic target. Our previous study demonstrated that the human gene <italic>VDAC1</italic> (encoding the VDAC-1 isoform) was significantly up-regulated in lung tumor tissue compared with normal tissue. Also, we found a significant positive correlation between the gene expression of <italic>VDAC1</italic> and histological grade in breast cancer. However, the prognostic power of <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its associated genes in human cancers is largely unknown.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>We systematically analyzed the expression pattern of <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes in breast, colon, liver, lung, pancreatic, and thyroid cancers. The genes differentially expressed between normal and tumor tissues in human carcinomas were identified.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>The expression level of <italic>VDAC1</italic> was uniformly up-regulated in tumor tissue compared with normal tissue in breast, colon, liver, lung, pancreatic, and thyroid cancers. Forty-four <italic>VDAC1</italic> interacting genes were identified as being commonly differentially expressed between normal and tumor tissues in human carcinomas. We designated <italic>VDAC1</italic> and the 44 dysregulated interacting genes as the <italic>VDAC1</italic> associated gene signature (VAG). We demonstrate that the VAG signature is a robust prognostic biomarker to predict recurrence-free survival in breast, colon, and lung cancers, and is independent of standard clinical and pathological prognostic factors.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>VAG represents a promising prognostic biomarker in human cancers, which may enhance prediction accuracy in identifying patients at higher risk for recurrence. Future therapies aimed specifically at <italic>VDAC1</italic> associated genes may lead to novel agents in the treatment of cancer.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Korea Research Foundation Grant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.krf.or.kr/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.krf.or.kr/</ext-link>) funded by the Korean Government (MOEHRD, Basic Research Promotion Fund) (KRF-2011-0016587 to JHK). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All microarray data are available from the Gene Expression Omnibus (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) database (GSE15852, GSE23878, GSE14520, GSE18842, GSE15471, GSE33630, GSE21653, GSE25066, GSE17536, GSE39582, GSE8894, and GSE31210).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Mitochondrial voltage-dependent anion channels (VDACs) are a class of porin ion channels located on the outer membrane of mitochondria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Hoogenboom1">[1]</xref>. VDACs allow diffusion of small hydrophilic molecules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Benz1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Dihanich1">[3]</xref>, which play an important role in regulating metabolic and energetic flux across the outer mitochondrial membrane by transporting ions and molecules such as ATP, ADP, pyruvate, malate, and other metabolites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-BlachlyDyson1">[4]</xref>. Also, VDACs are known to form channels through the plasma membrane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-DePinto1">[5]</xref>, which are involved in cell volume regulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-DePinto1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Okada1">[6]</xref>. In addition, VDACs have been reported to play a key role in mitochondria-mediated apoptosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Lemasters1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-ShoshanBarmatz1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Tan1">[9]</xref>. VDACs are the major permeability pathways through the outer mitochondrial membrane. During apoptosis, increased permeability of VDACs allows for the release of apoptogenic proteins to the cytosol, which is strongly associated with cell death <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Tsujimoto1">[10]</xref>.</p>
<p>Given their key role in apoptosis, VDACs are being studied as cancer-specific targets <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Leanza1">[11]</xref>. Both <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> evidences indicate that VDACs are actively involved in tumor progression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Lemasters1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Leanza1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Krasnov1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Simamura1">[13]</xref>. Specifically, voltage dependent anion channel-1 (VDAC-1), one member of the VDAC family, is thought to be a potential anti-cancer therapeutic target <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Simamura1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Mathupala1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Koren1">[15]</xref>. Currently, there are three isoforms of VDACs that have been characterized in mammalian tissues, including VDAC-1, voltage dependent anion channel-2 (VDAC-2), and voltage dependent anion channel-3 (VDAC-3). VDAC-1 is the most abundant in comparison to VDAC-2 and VDAC-3. More importantly, VDAC-1 is ubiquitously expressed across all other tissues types <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Mathupala1">[14]</xref>. The complex of VDAC-1 and glycolytic enzyme hexokinase regulates metabolite trafficking through the outer membrane channels and provides cancer cells with metabolic advantages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Lemasters1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Perevoshchikova1">[16]</xref>, which protects against mitochondria-mediated apoptosis. Knockdown of VDAC-1 can lead to a block in cancer cell proliferation in nude mice subcutaneously injected with HeLa cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Koren1">[15]</xref>. Overall, VDAC-1 is the most physiologically and metabolically important isoform among the VDAC family.</p>
<p>In our previous study, we demonstrated that the human gene of the VDAC-1 isoform (<italic>VDAC1</italic>) is significantly up-regulated in lung tumor tissue compared with normal tissue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Ko1">[17]</xref>. Also, we found a significant positive correlation between the gene expression of <italic>VDAC1</italic> and histological grade in breast cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Ko2">[18]</xref>, which suggests that the expression pattern of <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes may serve as indicators for cancer prognosis. In fact, gene expression profiling of clinical tumors has led to the discovery of numerous molecular biomarkers for prognosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Pitroda1">[19]</xref>. For example, meta-analysis on gene expression by Grills <italic>et al.</italic> suggested <italic>VDAC1</italic> as a potential predictor of poor outcome in early stage non-small cell lung cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Grills1">[20]</xref>. However, the prognostic power of <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its associated genes in human cancers is still largely unknown.</p>
<p>In this study, we systematically analyzed the expression pattern of <italic>VDAC1</italic> associated genes in cancers. We looked to identify a molecular signature consisting of multiple genes including <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes that are implicated in the pathology of human carcinomas. We first compared the expression of <italic>VDAC1</italic> associated genes between normal and tumor tissues in six different carcinomas. Forty-four genes were identified as being commonly differentially expressed between normal and tumor tissues. Next, we investigated the prognostic power of the <italic>VDAC1</italic> associated genes in breast, colon, and lung cancers. We demonstrate that the <italic>VDAC1</italic> associated gene signature is a robust prognostic biomarker to predict recurrence-free survival in breast, colon, and lung cancers, and is independent of standard clinical and pathological prognostic factors. Notably, we derived a novel gene signature associated with mitochondria-mediated apoptosis that predicts clinical outcome in human cancers.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Gene expression data of paired normal and tumor tissues</title>
<p>We collected gene expression data of paired normal and tumor tissues for breast (GSE15852) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-PauNi1">[21]</xref>, colon (GSE23878) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Uddin1">[22]</xref>, liver (GSE14520) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Roessler1">[23]</xref>, lung (GSE18842) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-SanchezPalencia1">[24]</xref>, pancreatic (GSE15471) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Badea1">[25]</xref>, and thyroid (GSE33630) cancers from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database. We used these datasets to identify differentially expressed genes between normal and tumor tissues for each type of cancer. The platform information for each dataset is listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s004">Table S1</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Gene expression data for cancer survival analysis</title>
<p>Training and validation cohorts were constructed for breast, colon, and lung cancers. From the GEO database, we collected the expression datasets with available information on recurrence-free survival for breast (GSE21653 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Sabatier1">[26]</xref> for training and GSE25066 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Hatzis1">[27]</xref> for validation), colon (GSE17536 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Smith1">[28]</xref> for training and GSE39582 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Marisa1">[29]</xref> for validation), and lung (GSE8894 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Lee1">[30]</xref> for training and GSE31210 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Okayama1">[31]</xref> for validation) cancers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s004">Table S1</xref>). These datasets were chosen based on the large number of samples and the availability of clinical outcome data.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Microarray data preprocessing</title>
<p>The GC robust multichip average algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Wu1">[32]</xref> was used to summarize the expression level of each probe set for the microarray data of paired normal and tumor tissues. Only the probe sets present (determined by function “mas5calls” in the Bioconductor “affy” package) in at least two thirds of the samples were retained. We further limited our analysis to the probe sets with unique annotations and removed genes on chromosomes X and Y to avoid potential confounding factors. For the gene with multiple probe sets, we use the average expression value of all probe sets that map to the gene. The preprocessed training and validation datasets are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s009">Data S1</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Identification of genes interacting with VDAC1</title>
<p>Information on genes interacting with <italic>VDAC1</italic> was obtained from GeneCards <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Rebhan1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Rebhan2">[34]</xref> and BioGRID <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-ChatrAryamontri1">[35]</xref>. We also included several genes known to interact with <italic>VDAC1</italic>, including <italic>HK2</italic>, <italic>MMP2</italic>, and <italic>MMP9</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Kroemer1">[36]</xref>. In total, we collected 342 well-annotated genes which interact with <italic>VDAC1</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s005">Table S2</xref>), according to the definition provided by BioGRID <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-ChatrAryamontri1">[35]</xref>, UniProtKB <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-UniProt1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Magrane1">[38]</xref>, MINT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Licata1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Chatraryamontri1">[40]</xref>, I2D <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Brown1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Brown2">[42]</xref>, STRING <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-vonMering1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Franceschini1">[44]</xref>, and published literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Kroemer1">[36]</xref>. We also inferred the expression-based regulatory network of these interacting genes by GENIE3 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-HuynhThu1">[45]</xref>, which is a gene regulatory network inference algorithm based on variable selection with ensembles of regression trees. The R script provided by the authors of GENIE3 was applied in this study.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Patient risk score</title>
<p>For each cancer training dataset, univariate Cox proportional hazards regression was used to evaluate the association between recurrence-free survival and expression of commonly differentially expressed genes between normal and tumor tissues across breast, colon, liver, lung, pancreatic, and thyroid cancers. A risk score was then calculated for each patient using a linear combination of gene expression weighted by the Wald statistic (ratio of regression coefficient to its standard error) as shown below:<disp-formula id="pone.0110094.e001"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>Here, <italic>S</italic> is the risk score of the patient; <italic>n</italic> is the number of differentially expressed genes; <italic>Z<sub>i</sub></italic> denotes the Wald statistic of gene <italic>i</italic>; <italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic> denotes the expression level of gene <italic>i</italic>; and <italic>μ<sub>i</sub></italic> and <italic>τ<sub>i</sub></italic> are the mean and standard deviation of the gene expression values for gene <italic>i</italic> across all samples, respectively. Patients were then divided into high- and low-score groups with the median of the risk score as the threshold value. A higher risk score implies a poor outcome. The scoring system and the associated scaling coefficients were fixed based on the training cohorts and then evaluated in the validation cohorts. All the statistical analyses were conducted by the R platform.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Expression of VDAC1 and its interacting genes in human carcinomas</title>
<p>We first explored the difference in expression level of <italic>VDAC1</italic> between normal and tumor tissues in several human carcinomas. Paired normal and tumor tissues from 43 breast, 19 colon, 214 liver, 44 lung, 36 pancreatic, and 44 thyroid cancer patients were included. Paired t-tests indicated that <italic>VDAC1</italic> was uniformly up-regulated in tumor tissues across all six cancer types, with a fold change of 1.25 in breast, 1.32 in colon, 1.64 in liver, 1.67 in lung, 1.91 in pancreatic, and 1.14 in thyroid cancers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110094-g001">Figure 1A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0110094-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title><italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes.</title>
<p>(A) <italic>VDAC1</italic> is up-regulated in tumor tissues in breast, colon, liver, lung, pancreatic, and thyroid cancers. Paired normal and tumor tissues were included in the comparison. Y-axis: log<sub>2</sub>-transformed expression values. (B) The top 10 GO biological process terms associated with dysregulated <italic>VDAC1</italic> interacting genes. Forty-four <italic>VDAC1</italic> interacting genes were identified as being commonly differentially expressed between normal and tumor tissues in human carcinomas. The <italic>P</italic>-values were calculated by Fisher’s exact test. The red dash line denotes the significance level of 0.05. (C) The top ten PANTHER pathway terms associated with dysregulated <italic>VDAC1</italic> interacting genes. The <italic>P</italic>-values were calculated by Fisher’s exact test. The red dash line denotes the significance level of 0.05.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We next checked the difference in expression levels of genes interacting with <italic>VDAC1</italic> between normal and tumor tissues. We collected 342 <italic>VDAC1</italic> interacting genes, by which the proteins encoded have been reported to interact with VDAC-1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s005">Table S2</xref>). Paired t-test was used to detect the differentially expressed genes between normal and tumor tissues. In total, 44 <italic>VDAC1</italic> interacting genes were identified as being differentially expressed in the accordant direction between the two groups (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05 after Benjamini-Hochberg adjustment) in at least four cancer types (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s006">Table S3</xref>). As expected, these genes were significantly enriched by Gene Ontology (GO) biological process terms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Ashburner1">[46]</xref> involved in apoptosis, such as “Apoptosis”, “Programmed cell death”, and “Generation of precursor metabolites and energy” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110094-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). Also, pathway analysis in the PANTHER database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Mi1">[47]</xref> confirmed that the top term associated with the 44 <italic>VDAC1</italic> interacting genes is “Apoptosis signaling pathway” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110094-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). We designated <italic>VDAC1</italic> and the 44 dysregulated interacting genes as the <italic><underline>V</underline>DAC1</italic> <underline>a</underline>ssociated <underline>g</underline>ene signature (VAG) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0110094-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0110094-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title><italic>VDAC1</italic> associated gene signature (VAG).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0110094-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene symbol</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene title</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>VDAC1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">voltage-dependent anion channel 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ACADVL</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">acyl-CoA dehydrogenase, very long chain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AGK</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">acylglycerol kinase</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AP2M1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adaptor-related protein complex 2, mu 1 subunit</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ATP6V1A</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATPase, H+ transporting, lysosomal 70 kDa, V1 subunit A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>BCL2L1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCL2-like 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CDK2</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cyclin-dependent kinase 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>COX4I1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome c oxidase subunit IV isoform 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CYCS</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome c, somatic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>DAP3</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">death associated protein 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>DBT</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dihydrolipoamide branched chain transacylase E2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>DENR</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">density-regulated protein</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>DHX30</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DEAH (Asp-Glu-Ala-His) box polypeptide 30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ECI1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">enoyl-CoA delta isomerase 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>EIF6</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>FLAD1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavin Adenine Dinucleotide Synthetase 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GAPDH</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GSN</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gelsolin</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GSTK1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glutathione S-transferase kappa 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>HADHA</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hydroxyacyl-CoA dehydrogenase/3-ketoacyl-CoA thiolase/enoyl-CoA hydratase (trifunctional protein), alpha subunit</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>HAUS3</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAUS augmin-like complex, subunit 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>IGF2BP2</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">insulin-like growth factor 2 mRNA binding protein 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>KIAA0391</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KIAA0391</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>KIF5B</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">kinesin family member 5B</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>LONP1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lon peptidase 1, mitochondrial</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MAPK1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitogen-activated protein kinase 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MCAT</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">malonyl CoA:ACP acyltransferase (mitochondrial)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MCL1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">myeloid cell leukemia sequence 1 (BCL2-related)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MDC1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mediator of DNA-damage checkpoint 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MRPL3</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitochondrial ribosomal protein L3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MRPL9</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitochondrial ribosomal protein L9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MRPS10</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitochondrial ribosomal protein S10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MRPS17</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitochondrial ribosomal protein S17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MTERFD1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MTERF domain containing 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MTPAP</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrial poly(A) polymerase</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MUT</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">methylmalonyl CoA mutase</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PANK2</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pantothenate kinase 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PPID</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidylprolyl isomerase D</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RNGTT</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA guanylyltransferase and 5′-phosphatase</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TFB1M</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transcription factor B1, mitochondrial</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TIAL1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIA1 cytotoxic granule-associated RNA binding protein-like 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TMX1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">thioredoxin-related transmembrane protein 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TOMM20</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">translocase of outer mitochondrial membrane 20 homolog (yeast)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TUBA4A</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tubulin, alpha 4a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>YWHAB</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tyrosine 3-monooxygenase/tryptophan 5-monooxygenase activation protein, beta polypeptide</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>To investigate the inherent relationship in gene expression among <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes, we computed the gene regulatory network for VAG using GENIE3 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-HuynhThu1">[45]</xref>, a state-of-the-art per-gene network inference algorithm. The weighted adjacency matrix was computed for breast, colon, liver, lung, pancreatic, and thyroid cancers. The element <italic>w<sub>ij</sub></italic> in the weighted adjacency matrix gives the importance of the link from regulatory gene <italic>i</italic> to target gene <italic>j</italic>. We used the sum of the weighted adjacency matrix to measure the inherent relationship in gene expression among <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes. We assumed that the linkage in VAG expression is stronger than random pattern. Therefore, we performed a resampling test to check whether the association in expression among VAG was by chance or not. We generated 1,000 random gene signatures with identical size as VAG. The weighted adjacency matrix was computed for each resampled gene set using GENIE3. We found that the sum of the weighted adjacency matrix of VAG was significantly larger than that of the randomized signature (<italic>P</italic> = 0.003 for breast cancer and <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001 for colon, liver, lung, pancreatic, and thyroid cancers) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s001">Figure S1</xref>), which confirmed the inherent relationship in gene expression among <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>VAG predicts recurrence-free survival in breast, colon, and lung cancers</title>
<p>We hypothesized that the apoptosis associated gene signature, VAG, is predictive of tumor outcome in cancer patients. We constructed a risk scoring system that combined gene expression of VAG with risk for recurrence in the training dataset (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref> for details). VAG-positive patients were defined as those having risk score greater than the group median. As expected, there was a significantly reduced recurrence-free survival for VAG-positive patients in the training cohorts (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s002">Figure S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0110094-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0110094-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Cox proportional hazards regression of survival by VAG status in breast, colon, and lung cancers.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0110094-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Training cohort</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Validation cohort</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hazardratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidenceinterval</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hazardratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidenceinterval</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.13, 2.71)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.48, 3.24)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0×10<sup>−5</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colon</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.37, 13.71)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0×10<sup>−4</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.10, 2.00)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4×10<sup>−3</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.10, 2.88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.40, 7.88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3×10<sup>−6</sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>We next tested the ability of the VAG based risk score to classify patients into prognostic groups in the independent validation cohorts. Kaplan-Meier survival curves demonstrated a significantly reduced recurrence-free survival for VAG-positive patients in the validation cohorts for breast (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001), colon (<italic>P</italic> = 0.009), and lung (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) cancers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110094-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Univariate Cox proportional hazards regression indicated that VAG-positive patients had an increased risk for recurrence of 2.19-fold in breast, 1.48-fold in colon, and 4.35-fold in lung cancers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0110094-t002">Table 2</xref>). These findings collectively indicated that VAG is predictive of recurrence-free survival in multiple human cancers. However, we found that <italic>VDAC1</italic> expression itself is not predictive of recurrence-free survival in both training and validation datasests (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s007">Table S4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0110094-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Kaplan-Meier curves for patients in the validation cohorts.</title>
<p>The expression of VAG predicts poor recurrence-free survival in breast, colon, and lung cancers. Red curves are for VAG-positive patients while blue curves are for VAG-negative patients. VAG-positive patients were defined as those having a risk score greater than the group median. <italic>P</italic>-values were calculated by log-rank tests for the differences in survival between VAG-positive and -negative groups.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Non-random prognostic power of VAG</title>
<p>A computational study by Venet <italic>et al.</italic> pointed out that most random gene expression signatures are significantly associated with breast cancer outcome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Venet1">[48]</xref>. They compared 47 published breast cancer outcome signatures to signatures made of random genes. Roughly 60% of the published signature were not significantly better than random signatures of identical size.</p>
<p>Here, we performed a resampling test to check whether the prognostic power of VAG was significantly better than random gene signatures. We constructed 1,000 random gene signatures with identical size as VAG. Cox proportional hazards regression of survival was conducted for each resampled gene signature. The association between each random gene signature and recurrence-free survival was measured by the Wald statistic, the ratio of Cox regression coefficient to its standard error. Our alternative hypothesis was that the Wald statistic of VAG should be more positive than expected by chance if the prognostic power of VAG was significantly better than random gene signatures. We found that, in the validation cohorts, we could reject the null hypothesis that the association between VAG and recurrence-free survival is by chance. The Wald statistic of VAG was significantly larger than that of randomized gene signatures (<italic>P</italic> = 0.038 for breast cancer, <italic>P</italic> = 0.035 for colon cancer, and <italic>P</italic> = 0.001 for lung cancer) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110094-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0110094-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Non-random prognostic power of VAG in breast, colon, and lung cancers.</title>
<p><italic>Z</italic> denotes the Wald statistic, the ratio of Cox regression coefficient to its standard error. The black triangles stand for the <italic>Z</italic> values of VAG. The grey areas show the distribution of <italic>Z</italic> values for the 1,000 resampled gene signatures with identical size as VAG under the null hypothesis of no association between VAG and recurrence-free survival. One-tailed <italic>P</italic>-values for the right tail of the sampling distribution were calculated.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Next, we compared the prognostic power of VAG with the other cancer-related genes. The cancer-related genes were identified as being differentially expressed in the accordant direction between normal and tumor tissues (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05 after Benjamini-Hochberg adjustment) in at least four cancer types. In total, we collected 1,357 cancer-related genes that don’t interact with <italic>VDAC1</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s008">Table S5</xref>). We performed a resampling test to check whether the predictive power of VAG was statistically better than the other cancer-related genes. We randomly picked up 45 genes from the pool of cancer-related genes. The performance of the random gene set was quantified by the sum of the Wald statistic of the validation cohorts. By 1,000 times of randomization, we found that the prognostic power of VAG was significantly better than that of the random gene signatures that were composed of cancer-related genes (<italic>P</italic> = 0.014) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110094.s003">Figure S3</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Multivariate analysis with clinical and pathological factors</title>
<p>To investigate the performance of VAG in comparison with standard clinical and pathological factors associated with prognosis in human carcinomas, multivariate analyses were conducted for breast, colon, and lung cancers. For breast cancer, we considered factors including patient age, lymph node status, histological grade, tumor size, estrogen receptor (ER) status, and progesterone receptor (PR) status. For colon cancer, we took age, gender, stage, and <italic>TP53</italic>, <italic>BRAF</italic>, and <italic>KRAS</italic> mutation status into account. For lung cancer, factors, such as age, gender, stage, smoking history, Myc protein level, and <italic>EGFR</italic>/<italic>KRAS</italic>/<italic>ALK</italic> alteration status were included in the multivariate model. Multivariate Cox proportional hazards regression of survival indicated that, in the validation cohorts, VAG dichotomized status remained a significant covariate in relation to the clinical and pathological factors for breast (<italic>P</italic> = 0.030), colon (<italic>P</italic> = 0.018), and lung (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) cancers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0110094-t003">Table 3</xref>). VAG was the most significant covariate in lung cancer. However, lymph node status and stage appeared to be the most significant covariate in breast and colon cancers, respectively. Accordingly, for breast cancer, we further stratified the patients by lymph node status. For breast cancer patients without or with lymph node involvement, VAG-positive patients had a 3.41-fold (<italic>P</italic> = 0.032) and 2.00-fold (<italic>P</italic> = 0.001) increased risk for recurrence, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110094-g004">Figure 4</xref>). For colon cancer patients with stage &lt;3 or ≥3, VAG-positive patients had a 1.89-fold (<italic>P</italic> = 0.018) and 1.40-fold (<italic>P</italic> = 0.069) increased risk for recurrence, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110094-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that VAG enhances the identification of cancer patients at greater risk for recurrence.</p>
<fig id="pone-0110094-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Kaplan-Meier curves for breast cancer patients from validation cohort grouped by lymph node status.</title>
<p>Red curves are for VAG-positive patients while blue curves are for VAG-negative patients. VAG-positive patients were defined as those having a risk score greater than the group median. <italic>P</italic>-values were calculated by log-rank tests for the differences in survival between VAG-positive and -negative groups.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0110094-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Kaplan-Meier curves for colon cancer patients from the validation cohort stratified by stage.</title>
<p>Red curves are for VAG-positive patients while blue curves are for VAG-negative patients. VAG-positive patients were defined as those having a risk score greater than the group median. <italic>P</italic>-values were calculated by log-rank tests for the differences in survival between VAG-positive and -negative groups.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0110094-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Multivariate Cox proportional hazards regression of survival in the validation cohorts.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0110094-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Covariate</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hazard ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidence interval</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAG + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.05, 2.68)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (per year)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.98, 1.02)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymph node + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.60, 4.82)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0×10<sup>−4</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 3 vs. 1,2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.43, 1.17)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor size ≥T3 vs. &lt;T3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.19, 2.64)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5×10<sup>−3</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ER + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.30, 0.89)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PR + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.41, 1.16)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colon</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAG + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.08, 2.33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (per year)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.98, 1.01)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender male vs. female</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.88, 1.93)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage III, IV vs. I, II</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.49, 3.34)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4×10<sup>−5</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TP53</italic> mutation + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.87, 1.90)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>BRAF</italic> mutation + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.64, 2.80)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>KRAS</italic> mutation + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.03, 2.30)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAG + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.28, 8.12)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5×10<sup>−6</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (per year)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.01, 1.09)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender male vs. female</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.47, 1.91)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.45, 1.88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage II vs. I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.57, 4.47)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8×10<sup>−4</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>EGFR</italic>/<italic>KRAS</italic>/<italic>ALK</italic> alteration + vs. −</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.29, 0.83)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4×10<sup>−3</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myc level high vs. low</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.28, 1.84)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Mitochondria are membrane-bound organelles found in most eukaryotic cells, which have been recognized for their multiple functions in metabolism, energy transduction, ion transport, inheritance, signaling, and cell death <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-ORourke1">[49]</xref>. The outer membrane of mitochondria encloses a periplasmic space where proteins associated with cell death are stored <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Leanza2">[50]</xref>. VDAC-1 is one of the major proteins located on the outer mitochondrial membrane, which may inhibit apoptosis and promote tumorigenesis through specific interactions with enzymes favoring glycolysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Leanza2">[50]</xref>. The complex of VDAC-1 and hexokinase regulates metabolite transportation through the outer membrane channels and provides cancer cells with metabolic advantages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Leanza1">[11]</xref>. Therefore, any change in VDAC-1 expression may lead to alteration in cancer cell metabolism, ultimately promoting or inhibiting cell death <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Leanza1">[11]</xref>.</p>
<p>Because VDAC-1 plays a key role in cancer cell fate through different signaling mechanisms, we investigated the expression pattern of <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes. Firstly, we found that <italic>VDAC1</italic> is uniformly up-regulated in tumor tissues compared with normal tissues in breast, colon, liver, lung, pancreatic, and thyroid cancers. Secondly, we found that the gene signature, VAG, which is associated with apoptosis and composed of <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes, is capable of predicting recurrence-free survival in breast, colon, and lung cancers. Finally, we confirmed that VAG is independent of standard clinical and pathological prognostic factors, which enhances the identification of cancer patients at greater risk for recurrence.</p>
<p>Among the gene list for VAG, <italic>BCL2L1</italic> and <italic>CYCS</italic> are among the top genes that have been heavily documented for their active roles in mitochondria-mediated apoptosis. <italic>BCL2L1</italic> encodes Bcl-2-like protein 1 in humans. This protein is located on the outer mitochondrial membrane and has been shown to regulate the opening of VDAC-1; thus, acting as an anti- or pro-apoptotic regulator. <italic>BCL2L1</italic> was found to play a functional role in colon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-SillarsHardebol1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Zhu1">[52]</xref>, prostate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Vilenchik1">[53]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Castilla1">[54]</xref>, and pancreatic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Mohammad1">[55]</xref> cancers. <italic>CYCS</italic> encodes a small heme protein (cytochrome c) that functions as a central component of the electron transport chain in mitochondria. This protein is involved in the initiation of apoptosis. <italic>CYCS</italic> has been reported to be related to breast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Ehrlichova1">[56]</xref> and colon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Schmitt1">[57]</xref> cancers.</p>
<p>In contrast to many published prognostic gene signatures derived from whole genome screening, the VAG signature was developed based on one gene and pre-identified gene-gene interactions. Statistically-derived clinical signatures by whole genome screening are often highly accurate in the patient data sets from which they were identified, yet most of them have not been validated as useful clinical tools <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Koscielny1">[58]</xref>. Moreover, a recent study suggests that random gene signatures have a high probability of being associated with survival outcome in cancer and most published signatures are not significantly more associated with outcome than random predictors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Venet1">[48]</xref>. In our study, the resampling test proved that the prognostic power of the VAG signature is significantly better than random gene signatures. More importantly, the genes discovered through our “bottom-up” approach have allowed the discovery of specific pathways relevant to human cancers and may yield new insights into disease pathology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Chang1">[59]</xref>. Our results identified that apoptosis associated genes are commonly differentially expressed between normal and tumor tissues in human carcinomas. The relationship between apoptosis and human cancers has been heavily documented in the past decade <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Lowe1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Kasibhatla1">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Fernald1">[62]</xref>. Thus, it is not surprising that the apoptosis associated gene signature is related to the aggressiveness of cancer across different tumor types. However, our results support the concept that mitochondria can serve as promising pharmacological targets in oncology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Leanza1">[11]</xref>. More specifically, the emerging data on <italic>VDAC1</italic> associated genes will help to not only predict clinical outcome in diversified human cancers, but also identify specific drugs that can be used to obtain maximal cancer-killing efficacy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0110094-Leanza1">[11]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The expression level of <italic>VDAC1</italic> is uniformly up-regulated in tumor tissue compared with normal tissue in breast, colon, liver, lung, pancreatic, and thyroid cancers. The apoptosis associated molecular signature VAG, which is composed of <italic>VDAC1</italic> and some of its interacting genes, represents a promising prognostic biomarker in human cancers. When working cooperatively with standard clinical and pathological prognostic factors, VAG may enhance prediction accuracy in identifying patients at higher risk for recurrence. Future therapies aimed specifically at <italic>VDAC1</italic> associated genes may lead to novel agents in the treatment of cancer.</p>
</sec><sec id="s6">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0110094.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Non-random inherent relationship in gene expression among </bold><bold><italic>VDAC1</italic></bold><bold> and its interacting genes.</bold> We computed the gene regulatory network for VAG using GENIE3. Weighted adjacency matrix was computed for breast, colon, liver, lung, pancreatic, and thyroid cancers, respectively. We used the sum of weighted adjacency matrix to measure the inherent relationship in gene expression among <italic>VDAC1</italic> and its interacting genes. We also generated 1,000 random gene signatures with identical size as VAG. Weighted adjacency matrix was computed for each resampled gene set using GENIE3. The sum of weighted adjacency matrix of VAG is significantly larger than that of randomized signature.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0110094.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Kaplan-Meier curves for the patients in the training cohorts.</bold> The expression of VAG predicts poor recurrence-free survival in breast, colon, and lung cancers. Red curves are for the VAG-positive patients while blue curves are for the VAG-negative patients. VAG-positive patients were defined as those having a risk score greater than the group median. <italic>P</italic>-values were calculated by log-rank tests for the differences in survival between the VAG-positive and -negative groups.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0110094.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Better prognostic power of VAG compared with other cancer-related genes.</bold> <italic>Z</italic> denotes the Wald statistic. The black triangle stands for the sum of the <italic>Z</italic> values of VAG in the three validation cohorts. The grey area shows the distribution of the sum of the <italic>Z</italic> values for the 1,000 resampled gene signatures that are composed of the cancer-related genes. One-tailed <italic>P</italic>-value for the right tail of the sampling distribution was calculated.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0110094.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Gene expression datasets used in this study.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0110094.s005" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Interacting genes for </bold><bold><italic>VDAC1</italic></bold><bold>.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0110094.s006" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p><bold><italic>VDAC1</italic></bold><bold> interacting genes that are differentially expressed between normal and tumor tissues.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0110094.s007" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Cox proportional hazards regression of survival against </bold><bold><italic>VDAC1</italic></bold><bold> expression in breast, colon, and lung cancers.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0110094.s008" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.s008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S5</label><caption>
<p><bold>Cancer-related genes that don’t interact with </bold><bold><italic>VDAC1</italic></bold><bold>.</bold></p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0110094.s009" mimetype="application/zip" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0110094.s009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Data S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>The preprocessed training and validation datasets.</bold></p>
<p>(ZIP)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Hoogenboom1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoogenboom</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fotiadis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The supramolecular assemblies of voltage-dependent anion channels in the native membrane</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>370</volume>: <fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Benz1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Permeation of hydrophilic solutes through mitochondrial outer membranes: review on mitochondrial porins</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1197</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Dihanich1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dihanich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>The biogenesis and function of eukaryotic porins</article-title>. <source>Experientia</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-BlachlyDyson1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blachly-Dyson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>VDAC channels</article-title>. <source>IUBMB Life</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-DePinto1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Pinto</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Voltage-dependent anion-selective channel (VDAC) in the plasma membrane</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>584</volume>: <fpage>1793</fpage>–<lpage>1799</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Okada1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Neal</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostrowski</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Voltage-dependent anion channel-1 (VDAC-1) contributes to ATP release and cell volume regulation in murine cells</article-title>. <source>J Gen Physiol</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Lemasters1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemasters</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmuhamedov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Voltage-dependent anion channel (VDAC) as mitochondrial governator–thinking outside the box</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1762</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-ShoshanBarmatz1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoshan-Barmatz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keinan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abu-Hamad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyomkin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aram</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Apoptosis is regulated by the VDAC1 N-terminal region and by VDAC oligomerization: release of cytochrome c, AIF and Smac/Diablo</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1797</volume>: <fpage>1281</fpage>–<lpage>1291</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Tan1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>VDAC blockage by phosphorothioate oligonucleotides and its implication in apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1818</volume>: <fpage>1555</fpage>–<lpage>1561</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Tsujimoto1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsujimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The voltage-dependent anion channel: an essential player in apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Biochimie</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Leanza1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Leanza L, Zoratti M, Gulbins E, Szabo I (2014) Mitochondrial ion channels as oncological targets. Oncogene.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Krasnov1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krasnov</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dmitriev</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lakunina</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirpiy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kudryavtseva</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Targeting VDAC-bound hexokinase II: a promising approach for concomitant anti-cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Ther Targets</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1221</fpage>–<lpage>1233</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Simamura1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simamura</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial voltage-dependent anion channels (VDACs) as novel pharmacological targets for anti-cancer agents</article-title>. <source>J Bioenerg Biomembr</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Mathupala1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathupala</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Voltage dependent anion channel-1 (VDAC-1) as an anti-cancer target</article-title>. <source>Cancer Biol Ther</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1053</fpage>–<lpage>1056</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Koren1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raviv</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shoshan-Barmatz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Downregulation of voltage-dependent anion channel-1 expression by RNA interference prevents cancer cell growth in vivo</article-title>. <source>Cancer Biol Ther</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1046</fpage>–<lpage>1052</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Perevoshchikova1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perevoshchikova</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zorov</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotova</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zorov</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antonenko</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Hexokinase inhibits flux of fluorescently labeled ATP through mitochondrial outer membrane porin</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>584</volume>: <fpage>2397</fpage>–<lpage>2402</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Ko1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Ion channel gene expression in lung adenocarcinoma: potential role in prognosis and diagnosis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e86569</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Ko2"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Expression profiling of ion channel genes predicts clinical outcome in breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Pitroda1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitroda</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sweis</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Filippo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labay</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Tumor endothelial inflammation predicts clinical outcome in diverse human cancers</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e46104</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Grills1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grills</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jithesh</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blayney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Gene expression meta-analysis identifies VDAC1 as a predictor of poor outcome in early stage non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e14635</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-PauNi1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pau Ni</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zakaria</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Gene expression patterns distinguish breast carcinomas from normal breast tissues: the Malaysian context</article-title>. <source>Pathol Res Pract</source> <volume>206</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Uddin1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abubaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Sanea</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide expression analysis of Middle Eastern colorectal cancer reveals FOXM1 as a novel target for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source> <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Roessler1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roessler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budhu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forgues</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A unique metastasis gene signature enables prediction of tumor relapse in early-stage hepatocellular carcinoma patients</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>10202</fpage>–<lpage>10212</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-SanchezPalencia1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Palencia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Morales</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Capilla</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedraza</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Gene expression profiling reveals novel biomarkers in nonsmall cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Badea1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badea</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herlea</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dima</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dumitrascu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Combined gene expression analysis of whole-tissue and microdissected pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma identifies genes specifically overexpressed in tumor epithelia</article-title>. <source>Hepatogastroenterology</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>2016</fpage>–<lpage>2027</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Sabatier1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabatier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cervera</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambaudie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esterni</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A gene expression signature identifies two prognostic subgroups of basal breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Hatzis1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatzis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pusztai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valero</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Booser</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esserman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A genomic predictor of response and survival following taxane-anthracycline chemotherapy for invasive breast cancer</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>305</volume>: <fpage>1873</fpage>–<lpage>1881</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Smith1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Experimentally derived metastasis gene expression profile predicts recurrence and death in patients with colon cancer</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>958</fpage>–<lpage>968</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Marisa1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marisa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Reynies</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selves</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaub</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Gene expression classification of colon cancer into molecular subtypes: characterization, validation, and prognostic value</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e1001453</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Lee1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Prediction of recurrence-free survival in postoperative non-small cell lung cancer patients by using an integrated model of clinical information and gene expression</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>7397</fpage>–<lpage>7404</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Okayama1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shiraishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Identification of genes upregulated in ALK-positive and EGFR/KRAS/ALK-negative lung adenocarcinomas</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Wu1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Murillo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A model-based background adjustment for oligonucleotide expression arrays</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>909</fpage>–<lpage>917</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Rebhan1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebhan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalifa-Caspi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prilusky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lancet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>GeneCards: a novel functional genomics compendium with automated data mining and query reformulation support</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>656</fpage>–<lpage>664</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Rebhan2"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebhan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalifa-Caspi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prilusky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lancet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>GeneCards: integrating information about genes, proteins and diseases</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-ChatrAryamontri1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatr-Aryamontri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breitkreutz</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinicke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The BioGRID interaction database: 2013 update</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>D816</fpage>–<lpage>823</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Kroemer1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galluzzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial membrane permeabilization in cell death</article-title>. <source>Physiol Rev</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-UniProt1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>UniProt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Activities at the Universal Protein Resource (UniProt)</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>D191</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Magrane1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Magrane M, Consortium U (2011) UniProt Knowledgebase: a hub of integrated protein data. Database-the Journal of Biological Databases and Curation.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Licata1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Licata</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briganti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perfetto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iannuccelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>MINT, the molecular interaction database: 2012 update</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>D857</fpage>–<lpage>861</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Chatraryamontri1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatr-aryamontri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ceol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palazzi</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nardelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>MINT: the Molecular INTeraction database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>D572</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Brown1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jurisica</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Unequal evolutionary conservation of human protein interactions in interologous networks</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>R95</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Brown2"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jurisica</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Online predicted human interaction database</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>2076</fpage>–<lpage>2082</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-vonMering1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Mering</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huynen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeggi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>STRING: a database of predicted functional associations between proteins</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Franceschini1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franceschini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szklarczyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frankild</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simonovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>STRING v9.1: protein-protein interaction networks, with increased coverage and integration</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>D808</fpage>–<lpage>815</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-HuynhThu1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Huynh-Thu VA, Irrthum A, Wehenkel L, Geurts P (2010) Inferring regulatory networks from expression data using tree-based methods. PLoS One 5.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Ashburner1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Mi1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muruganujan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>PANTHER in 2013: modeling the evolution of gene function, and other gene attributes, in the context of phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>D377</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Venet1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dumont</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Detours</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Most random gene expression signatures are significantly associated with breast cancer outcome</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002240</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-ORourke1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Rourke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial ion channels</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Physiol</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Leanza2"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leanza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biasutto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manago</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gulbins</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zoratti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Intracellular ion channels and cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-SillarsHardebol1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sillars-Hardebol</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belien</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delis-van Diemen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>BCL2L1 has a functional role in colorectal cancer and its protein expression is associated with chromosome 20q gain</article-title>. <source>J Pathol</source> <volume>226</volume>: <fpage>442</fpage>–<lpage>450</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Zhu1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Adenovirus-mediated small hairpin RNA targeting Bcl-XL as therapy for colon cancer</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>1366</fpage>–<lpage>1372</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Vilenchik1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilenchik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raffo</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benimetskaya</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shames</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Antisense RNA down-regulation of bcl-xL Expression in prostate cancer cells leads to diminished rates of cellular proliferation and resistance to cytotoxic chemotherapeutic agents</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>2175</fpage>–<lpage>2183</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Castilla1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castilla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Congregado</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chinchon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torrubia</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Japon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Bcl-xL is overexpressed in hormone-resistant prostate cancer and promotes survival of LNCaP cells via interaction with proapoptotic Bak</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>4960</fpage>–<lpage>4967</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Mohammad1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Nonpeptidic small-molecule inhibitor of Bcl-2 and Bcl-XL, (–)-Gossypol, enhances biological effect of genistein against BxPC-3 human pancreatic cancer cell line</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Ehrlichova1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrlichova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Truksa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naldova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaclavikova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cell death induced by taxanes in breast cancer cells: cytochrome C is released in resistant but not in sensitive cells</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>4215</fpage>–<lpage>4224</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Schmitt1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parcellier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghiringhelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casares</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gurbuxani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Increased immunogenicity of colon cancer cells by selective depletion of cytochrome C. Cancer Res</article-title>. <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>2705</fpage>–<lpage>2711</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Koscielny1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koscielny</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Why most gene expression signatures of tumors have not been useful in the clinic</article-title>. <source>Sci Transl Med</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>14ps12</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Chang1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nuyten</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sneddon</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Robustness, scalability, and integration of a wound-response gene expression signature in predicting breast cancer survival</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>3738</fpage>–<lpage>3743</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Lowe1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Apoptosis in cancer</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Kasibhatla1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasibhatla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Why target apoptosis in cancer treatment?</article-title> <source>Mol Cancer Ther</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0110094-Fernald1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurokawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Evading apoptosis in cancer</article-title>. <source>Trends Cell Biol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>620</fpage>–<lpage>633</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>