<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PONE-RA-15679R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subject>Molecular Biology</subject><subject>Radiology and Medical Imaging</subject><subject>Microbiology/Medical Microbiology</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Bacterial Infections</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Respiratory Infections</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Optimisation of Bioluminescent Reporters for Use with Mycobacteria</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Bioluminescent Mycobacteria</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreu</surname><given-names>Nuria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zelmer</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>Taryn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkington</surname><given-names>Paul T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>Theresa H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>Jorge</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parish</surname><given-names>Tanya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>Gregory J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaible</surname><given-names>Ulrich</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>Brian D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiles</surname><given-names>Siouxsie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Medicine, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Infectious and Tropical Diseases, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Institute of Electronic Structure and Laser, Foundation for Research and Technology-Hellas, Heraklion, Crete, Greece</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Barts and the London School of Medicine and Dentistry, Queen Mary University of London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Infectious Diseases Research Institute, Seattle, Washington, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Department of Molecular Infection Research, Research Center Borstel, Borstel, Germany</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><addr-line>Department of Molecular Medicine and Pathology, University of Auckland, Auckland, New Zealand</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>T. Mark</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Statens Serum Institute, Denmark</aff><author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">s.wiles@auckland.ac.nz</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: NA THW JR TP GJB UES BDR SW. Performed the experiments: NA AZ TF PE SW. Analyzed the data: NA SW. Wrote the paper: NA BDR SW.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e10777</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2010</year></date>
</history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Andreu et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>, the causative agent of tuberculosis, still represents a major public health threat in many countries. Bioluminescence, the production of light by luciferase-catalyzed reactions, is a versatile reporter technology with multiple applications both in vitro and in vivo. In vivo bioluminescence imaging (BLI) represents one of its most outstanding uses by allowing the non-invasive localization of luciferase-expressing cells within a live animal. Despite the extensive use of luminescent reporters in mycobacteria, the resultant luminescent strains have not been fully applied to BLI.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title>
<p>One of the main obstacles to the use of bioluminescence for <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging is the achievement of reporter protein expression levels high enough to obtain a signal that can be detected externally. Therefore, as a first step in the application of this technology to the study of mycobacterial infection <italic>in vivo</italic>, we have optimised the use of firefly, <italic>Gaussia</italic> and bacterial luciferases in mycobacteria using a combination of vectors, promoters, and codon-optimised genes. We report for the first time the functional expression of the whole bacterial <italic>lux</italic> operon in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> and <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> thus allowing the development of auto-luminescent mycobacteria. We demonstrate that the <italic>Gaussia</italic> luciferase is secreted from bacterial cells and that this secretion does not require a signal sequence. Finally we prove that the signal produced by recombinant mycobacteria expressing either the firefly or bacterial luciferases can be non-invasively detected in the lungs of infected mice by bioluminescence imaging.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions/Significance</title>
<p>While much work remains to be done, the finding that both firefly and bacterial luciferases can be detected non-invasively in live mice is an important first step to using these reporters to study the pathogenesis of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> and other mycobacterial species <italic>in vivo</italic>. Furthermore, the development of auto-luminescent mycobacteria has enormous ramifications for high throughput mycobacterial drug screening assays which are currently carried out either in a destructive manner using LuxAB or the firefly luciferase.</p>
</sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work is funded by an award (42786) to the Imaging TB Consortium from the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gatesfoundation.org" xlink:type="simple">www.gatesfoundation.org</ext-link>) TB Drug Accelerator program. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> was first isolated more than 125 years ago. Although a huge amount of research has been devoted to it over this time, tuberculosis still represents a major public health threat in many countries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-WHO1">[1]</xref>. The main hindrances in fighting this disease include a lack of understanding of the human infection, its establishment and progression, as well as the host-pathogen interactions that determine the different outcomes. Furthermore, the treatment regimen of six months administration of up to four drugs has not evolved in more than four decades, and recent years have seen an alarming increase in multi-drug resistant (MDR) and extensively drug-resistant (XDR) strains. It is clear then that novel and imaginative approaches are needed to speed up both basic and translational research in tuberculosis, especially in the areas of vaccine and drug development.</p>
<p>Bioluminescence, the production of light by luciferase-catalysed reactions, is a versatile reporter technology with multiple applications both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. <italic>In vivo</italic> bioluminescence imaging (BLI) represents one of its most outstanding uses by allowing the non-invasive localisation of luciferase-expressing cells within an animal. Applied to the study of infectious diseases, BLI permits the detection of microorganisms from within living animals thus allowing the spatiotemporal study of infection in real-time in the same host <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Hutchens1">[2]</xref>. Moreover, using luciferase as a reporter of gene expression, it is possible to establish when and where a gene function is needed, shedding light on bacterial pathogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Wright1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Lane1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Steinhuber1">[5]</xref>. Finally, BLI constitutes an easy and rapid method to test novel antimicrobial compounds <italic>in vivo</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Xiong1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Kadurugamuwa1">[7]</xref>.</p>
<p>Luciferases are a large family of enzymes that catalyse the oxidation of a substrate, generically called luciferin, to yield oxyluciferin with the concomitant production of light. Three main luciferin-luciferase systems have been utilised for BLI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Gheysens1">[8]</xref>. The first system is represented by the firefly luciferase (FFluc) from <italic>Photinus pyralis</italic> which uses D-luciferin (a benzothiazole) as substrate, is dependent on ATP and results in the production of yellow-green light (557 nm). The second system includes the luciferases from the marine organisms <italic>Renilla reniformis</italic> (a cnidarian) and <italic>Gaussia princeps</italic> (a copepod) and the substrate coelenterazine. The signal produced by the <italic>G. princeps</italic> luciferase (Gluc) has been reported to be stronger than that of FFluc <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Tannous1">[9]</xref>, even though the light emitted is in the blue range (480 nm) and is therefore more susceptible to tissue absorption and scattering. The fact that Gluc is strongly resistant to heat and extreme pH <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Tannous1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Wiles1">[10]</xref>, and that it is secreted by eukaryotic cells also make this system very attractive. Bacterial luciferases, found in the terrestrial bacterium <italic>Photorhabdus luminescens</italic> and marine bacteria from the genera <italic>Vibrio</italic> and <italic>Photobacterium</italic>, constitute the third luciferin-luciferase system. These luciferases are heterodimeric enzymes that use FMNH<sub>2</sub> and a long-chain aldehyde as substrates. Bacterial luciferases are encoded by the genes <italic>luxAB</italic> that form an operon (<italic>luxCDABE</italic>) together with three additional genes (<italic>luxCDE</italic>) whose products synthesise the long-chain aldehyde. The main advantage of this system is that it does not need exogenously added substrate, but again the light produced is in the blue range (490 nm).</p>
<p>Bioluminescence has been used in mycobacterial research for more than 20 years. Initially, FFluc was used to measure ATP as an indirect method of assessing cell viability and cell numbers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Prioli1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Janaszek1">[12]</xref>. Considering the long duplication times of mycobacteria, the advantages of using bioluminescence as a reporter to assay anti-mycobacterial agents soon became evident when compared to the more traditional colony count methods. To this end LuxAB (requiring the addition of exogenous substrate) and FFluc have been used in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>, <italic>M. bovis</italic> BCG, and even <italic>M. avium</italic>, <italic>M. intracellulare</italic> and <italic>M. aurum</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Andrew1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Cooksey1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Cooksey2">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Arain1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Gordon1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Deb1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Shawar1">[19]</xref>. The development of luciferase reporter phages represented a further improvement as it enabled testing of the drug susceptibility of clinical strains and has subsequently been applied to tuberculosis diagnostics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Jacobs1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Carriere1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Riska1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Riska2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Banaiee1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Bardarov1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Pai1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Banaiee2">[27]</xref>. Finally, luminescent reporter strains have also been used for antibiotic testing and immunity assessment in cell cultures and <italic>ex vivo</italic> in organ homogenates of infected mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Arain2">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Hickey1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Bonay1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Snewin1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Bouchonnet1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Turner1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Kampmann1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-AlAttiyah1">[35]</xref>.</p>
<p>Despite the extensive use of luminescent reporters in mycobacteria, these have only recently been applied to the imaging of mycobacteria <italic>in vivo</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Heuts1">[36]</xref>. In the single published paper on BLI of mycobacteria, Heus and collaborators utilised a recombinant <italic>M. bovis</italic> BCG strain expressing <italic>luxAB</italic> to monitor mycobacteria infection <italic>in vivo</italic>. While the authors prove that BLI can be used to study bacterial dissemination, drug efficacy and the role of the immune response, their approach has some limitations. In fact, the authors failed to detect BCG in the lungs of infected mice despite being able to detect bacteria in these organs by colony counting and <italic>ex vivo</italic> imaging. Because their luminescent strain of BCG did not express the <italic>luxCDE</italic> genes for substrate synthesis, Heus and collaborators had to administer decanal to the mice in order to image the bacteria. This substrate is highly toxic and, although they were able to deliver it by injection into the murine peritoneum dissolved in a mixture of olive oil and ethanol, this delivery method would appear to have limited distribution to the lungs, which are of major importance for tuberculosis research.</p>
<p>In the work reported here, we have improved the signal obtained from FFluc and Gluc (both of which use non-toxic substrates), and Lux in mycobacteria using a combination of vectors, promoters, and codon-optimised genes. We report for the first time the functional expression of the whole Lux operon in <italic>M. tuberculosis and M. smegmatis</italic> thus allowing the development of auto-luminescent mycobacteria. Moreover, we demonstrate that FFluc and Lux are both useful for the non-invasive detection of mycobacteria in the lungs of infected mice.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Maximising luminescent reporter gene expression</title>
<p>As a first step towards the generation of highly-luminescent mycobacteria, each of the three luciferases was cloned into three different expression vectors that contained the same promoter (P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic>) but which differ in copy number: (i) pSMT3, which has a pAL5000 replicon and is maintained at 2–5 copies per cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Ranes1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Stover1">[38]</xref>; (ii) pSMT3M <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Carroll1">[39]</xref>, which has a mutation in the <italic>repA</italic> gene that increases the copy number to 32–64 copies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Bourn1">[40]</xref>; and (iii) pMV306hsp which integrates into the chromosomal <italic>attB</italic> site and hence results in single copy number <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Stover1">[38]</xref>. For the Lux reporter we used a <italic>luxABCDE</italic> operon that had been previously modified for expression in Gram positive bacteria by replacement of the ribosome binding sites and reorganisation of the genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Qazi1">[41]</xref>. All the constructs were electroporated into <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, and the luminescence of 10 randomly selected clones was analysed for each type of construct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). For the three reporters, a high luminescent signal was produced by colonies expressing the integrated constructs derived from pMV306hsp with median values of 1.1×10<sup>7</sup> RLUs for FFluc, 8.9×10<sup>6</sup> RLUs for Gluc, and 3.6×10<sup>4</sup> RLUs for Lux. The pSMT3 derivatives also yielded good signal levels with Gluc (median value, 1.5×10<sup>7</sup> RLUs) and in three out of ten FFluc clones (4.5×10<sup>5</sup>, 5.8×10<sup>6</sup> and 1.5×10<sup>7</sup> RLUs). Remarkably, a high variation was detected among the pSMT3+FFluc clones (signal range of 3.7×10<sup>2</sup>–1.5×10<sup>7</sup> RLUs), with light production only slightly over the background in three of them (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>); this is likely related to the fact that many of these clones carried deletions affecting the reporter gene (data not shown). For all three reporters, the lowest luminescence was obtained with pSMT3M, the high copy number vector. In particular, seven out of ten transformants carrying pSMT3M+FFluc and all the pSMT3M+Lux clones analysed produced only background levels of bioluminescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g001">Fig. 1A, C</xref>). Further screening of 96 pSMT3M+Lux transformants imaged with the IVIS® Spectrum failed to detect any bioluminescent clones. Similarly, out of 387 pSMT3+Lux transformants obtained, only 12 were glowing when imaged with the IVIS® Spectrum. However, these positive clones lost their luminescence after subculturing. Deletions of 5–6 kb, comprising almost the whole <italic>lux</italic> operon, were detected in these and the pSMT3M+Lux transformants (data not shown). Therefore the highest expression and stability was achieved with the pMV306hsp integrating vector, which was selected for further studies.</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Expression from an integrating vector results in the highest and most stable bioluminescent signal.</title>
<p>To study the effect of copy number on light production each reporter was cloned into standard (pSMT3), high (pSMT3M), and single copy number (pMV306hsp) vectors. Luminescence was measured for 10 independent <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> transformants each carrying the FFluc (<bold>a</bold>), Gluc (<bold>b</bold>) and Lux (<bold>c</bold>) constructs. Results are given as relative light units (RLUs) and are corrected for the background. Overall differences between groups were assessed using the Kruskal–Wallis non-parametric test with differences between subgroups assessed by Dunn's multiple comparisons test and those found to be significant (p&lt;0.01) are indicated with *.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Next, we tested different promoters to drive expression of the luciferase genes. Using the integrating vector pMV306, each reporter gene was cloned in front of previously described strong promoters: P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic>, P<italic><sub>myc</sub></italic>tetO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Ehrt1">[42]</xref>, and P<sub>G13</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Barker1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Barker2">[44]</xref>. These constructs were introduced into <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, and the luminescence of 10 randomly selected transformants analysed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). Similar luminescence values were obtained among strains expressing either FFluc or Gluc under the control of either P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> or P<sub>G13</sub> (median values of 1.5×10<sup>7</sup> and 2.3×10<sup>7</sup> RLUs respectively for FFluc, 8.9×10<sup>6</sup> and 5.05×10<sup>6</sup> RLUs for Gluc), while production of light from P<italic><sub>myc</sub></italic>tetO clones was 3–13 times lower. In the case of Lux, the highest luminescence was achieved using P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> (3.6×10<sup>4</sup> RLUs), followed by P<sub>G13</sub> (9 times lower), and P<italic><sub>myc</sub></italic>tetO (180 times lower than that of P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic>). Consequently P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> was the promoter chosen for expression of the luminescent reporters. Additionally, in order to increase the amount of substrate synthesised by the Lux operon and in this way the amount of luminescence, P<sub>G13</sub> was cloned in front of <italic>luxC</italic> in pMV306hsp+Lux. This resulted in a 6-fold increase in the luminescence activity compared to the original pMV306hsp+Lux, from 3.6×10<sup>4</sup> to 2.25×10<sup>5</sup> RLUs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Expression of luciferases using promoters P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> and P<sub>G13</sub> leads to greater light production.</title>
<p>Luminescence of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> expressing <italic>ffluc</italic> (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>gluc</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic>lux</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) was assayed using P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic>, P<italic><sub>myc</sub></italic>tetO, and P<sub>G13</sub> in the integrating vector pMV306. Each dot represents a randomly selected transformant. Results are given as relative light units (RLUs) and are corrected for the background. Statistical significance was evaluated by the Kruskal–Wallis test with subgroup analysis performed by Dunn's multiple comparison test and those found to be significant (p&lt;0.05) are indicated with *.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Lastly, as a potential way of enhancing the expression of reporter genes at the translational level, we utilised versions of <italic>ffluc</italic> and <italic>gluc</italic> whose codon usage had been optimised for use in mycobacteria, together with an improved Shine Dalgarno sequence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-LeDantec1">[45]</xref>. We also tested a <italic>lux</italic> operon with codon usage optimised for mycobacteria, but no luminescence was produced by this strain, even if the substrate for the bacterial luciferase was added exogenously (data not shown). Alternatively, we used a <italic>luxCDABE</italic> operon (LuxStm) codon-optimised for <italic>Streptomyces coelicolor</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Craney1">[46]</xref>. Using pMV306hsp as the expression vector the luminescence of the optimised reporters was compared to that of the wild-type genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). Codon optimisation resulted in a 30-fold, 2.5-fold and 4-fold improvement in the signal for FFluc, Gluc and Lux respectively. Accordingly, the optimised <italic>gluc</italic> and <italic>ffluc</italic> genes were selected for further study. However, since the luminescence of LuxStm was lower than that of the reorganised <italic>lux</italic> operon with P<sub>G13</sub> cloned in front of <italic>luxC,</italic> the latter was chosen for further study.</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Codon optimisation increases bioluminescence <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title>
<p>Relative light units (RLUs) were measured in 10 <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> clones transformed with a wild-type or a <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> optimised FFluc (<bold>a</bold>) or Gluc (<bold>b</bold>), or with a Gram positive or <italic>Streptomyces</italic> optimised Lux (<bold>c</bold>). In all cases pMV306hsp was used as backbone. Results are corrected for the background. Statistical significance was evaluated by the Mann-Whitney non-parametric test for FFluc and Lux, and by unpaired t test for Gluc (data normality passed) and those found to be significant (p&lt;0.05) are indicated with *.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The three reporters were also tested in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> by electroporating pMV306hsp+FFluc, pMV306hsp+Gluc and pMV306hsp+Lux and measuring the bioluminescence of 10 randomly selected clones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). The signal obtained in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> was slightly lower than that of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> for FFluc (1.1×10<sup>7</sup> and 1.5×10<sup>7</sup> RLUs, respectively), whereas no significant differences were detected for Gluc and Lux (5.8×10<sup>5</sup> vs. 8.4×10<sup>5</sup> RLUs, and 3.6×10<sup>4</sup> vs. 4.6×10<sup>4</sup> RLUs, correspondingly).</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Bioluminescence levels in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> and <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> are comparable <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title>
<p>Relative light units (RLUs) were measured in 10 <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> and 10 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> clones transformed with pMV306hsp+FFluc (<bold>a</bold>), pMV306hsp+Gluc (<bold>b</bold>) or pMV306hsp+Lux (<bold>c</bold>). Results are corrected for the background. Statistical significance was evaluated by the Mann-Whitney non-parametric test for Lux, and by unpaired t test for FFluc and Gluc (data normality passed) and those found to be significant (p&lt;0.05) are indicated with *.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g004" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Optimisation of the <italic>in vitro</italic> bioluminescence reaction</title>
<p>To achieve the highest signal to background ratio we tested different integration times (0.1–10 s) for the three reporters, at four different substrate concentrations for Gluc and FFluc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>, increasing the integration time yielded an increased ratio for FFluc, reaching a maximal ratio at integration times between 5 and 10 s, depending on substrate concentration. This was also the case for Lux, with 10 s yielding the best result (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>). In contrast, increasing the integration time resulted in a decreased signal to noise ratio for Gluc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). This was likely due to the high background produced by auto-oxidation of its substrate coelenterazine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Zhao1">[47]</xref>. Therefore, for further studies the integration times selected were 5 s, 0.1 s and 10 s for FFluc, Gluc and Lux respectively.</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Signal:noise for FFluc and Lux increases with integration time, and decreases for Gluc.</title>
<p>Luminescence was measured using six different integration times and four different substrate concentrations for <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> producing FFluc (<bold>a</bold>) and Gluc (<bold>b</bold>), or without substrate for Lux (<bold>c</bold>). The background luminescence was obtained from cultures of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> with the empty pMV306hsp. Assays were performed with three independent mid-log cultures and each culture was measured in duplicate. As the data was not normally distributed, median values are displayed (bar) with inter-quartile ranges (box), and highest and lowest values (whiskers).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g005" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We then studied the effect of substrate concentration on light production by FFluc and Gluc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). In both cases the luminescence increased with increasing substrate concentration in an exponential manner until a plateau was reached at 40 µM coelenterazine for Gluc and 1570 µM luciferin for FFluc, with 40 µM and 470 µm chosen as working concentrations.</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Bioluminescence correlates with substrate concentration at low concentrations.</title>
<p>Luminescence (given as relative light units [RLUs]) of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMVhsp+FFluc (<bold>a</bold>) and <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMVhsp+Gluc (<bold>b</bold>) was measured with integration times of 5 s and 0.1 s respectively. The substrate concentrations assayed ranged from 20 to 4710 µM luciferin for FFluc, and from 0.05 to 400 µM coelenterazine for Gluc. Means and standard deviations (smaller than symbols) of six replicates are shown.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g006" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Luminescence reaction kinetics</title>
<p>The kinetics of light output for each luciferase was measured for <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMVhsp+FFluc, pMVhsp+Gluc and pMVhsp+LuxAB+G13+CDE over 30 min, following the addition of substrate as appropriate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). For both Gluc and FFluc, the maximum signal was obtained immediately after substrate addition with median values of 2.9×10<sup>5</sup>±8.9×10<sup>3</sup> RLUs for Gluc and 2.2×10<sup>7</sup>±7.1×10<sup>5</sup> RLUs for FFluc. Then, Gluc luminescence decreased dramatically with a 90% loss in just 1 min, whereas the FFluc signal dropped slowly, still retaining 50% of the initial signal after 17 min. In contrast, the light output for Lux remained stable between 1.1×10<sup>6</sup> and 2.2×10<sup>6</sup> RLUs during the whole experiment, most likely reflecting a continuous production of substrate by the cells.</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Light production from FFluc and Lux is stable, whereas the signal from Gluc rapidly dissipates.</title>
<p>Luminescence (given as relative light units [RLUs]) was measured every 10 s for <italic>gluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> and every 30 s for <italic>ffluc</italic>- or <italic>lux</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, over a 30 min period. The integration times used were 0.1 s, 5 s and 10 s for Gluc, FFluc and Lux respectively. At time point 0 min, 470 µM luciferin or 40 µM coelenterazine were added to FFluc- and Gluc-producing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> respectively. Two independent cultures were used for FFluc and Lux, and three for Gluc. Each culture was measured in duplicate and the means and standard deviations (smaller than symbols) are plotted.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g007" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We then analysed luminescence production during the growth of the same luciferase-producing strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g008">Fig. 8</xref>). The level of luminescence correlated well with cell density during the exponential growth phase for all the three reporters. However, the signal dropped when the cultures of <italic>lux</italic>- and <italic>ffluc</italic>-expressing cells entered stationary phase with a total loss of 83% and 77% respectively between the time points 12 and 28 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g008">Fig. 8A, C</xref>). This is most likely related to a decrease in the metabolic activity of the bacteria, and therefore in the availability of the FMNH<sub>2</sub> and ATP needed by Lux and FFluc, respectively. In contrast, luminescence from cells expressing the <italic>Gaussia</italic> luciferase, which does not require any bacterial cofactors to catalyse the luminescence reaction, remained related to cell numbers until the end of the growth curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g008">Fig. 8B</xref>). Moreover, using mid-log cultures a good correlation (Spearman r = 1) was found between colony forming units (CFU) and luminescence (measured with the plate luminometer) over a range of cell numbers: 10<sup>4</sup> and 10<sup>8</sup> CFU for <italic>ffluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, 10<sup>3</sup> and 10<sup>8</sup> for <italic>lux</italic>-expressing cells, and 10<sup>4</sup>–10<sup>6</sup> for Gluc producing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g008">Fig. 8D–F</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Bioluminescence correlates with cell density during exponential growth <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title>
<p>Cultures of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMVhsp+FFluc (<bold>a</bold>), pMVhsp+Gluc (<bold>b</bold>) and pMVhsp+Lux (<bold>c</bold>) were inoculated to an optical density (OD) at 600 nm of 0.1 and the OD and the luminescence [given as relative light units (RLUs)] measured over 28 h. The luminescence was measured with integration times of 5, 0.1, and 10 s respectively, and substrate concentrations of 470 µM luciferin for FFluc and 40 µM coelenterazine for Gluc. The values represented correspond to the means of two independent cultures measured in triplicate. The error bars indicate standard deviations. A near linear relationship was found between bioluminescence [given as RLUs] and colony counts (given as colony forming units [CFU]) for mid-log cultures of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMVhsp+FFluc (<bold>d</bold>), pMVhsp+Gluc (<bold>e</bold>) and pMVhsp+Lux (<bold>f</bold>) using a plate luminometer.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g008" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Secretion of <italic>Gaussia</italic> luciferase</title>
<p>It has previously been stated that Gluc is secreted from eukaryotic cells because of a signal peptide situated at the N-terminal end of the protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Tannous1">[9]</xref>. To determine if Gluc was also secreted in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, we examined the luminescence produced by the whole culture, the cells or the culture supernatant. Moreover, as a way to assess the role of the signal peptide, experiments were also performed using strains expressing codon-optimised and wild-type forms of Gluc without the signal sequence. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g009">Fig. 9</xref>, almost 100% of the luminescence was detected in the supernatant of all <italic>gluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> regardless of the presence or absence of the signal peptide and the codon usage of the gene used. In contrast, only 2% of the total luminescence was found in the supernatant of FFluc-producing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> when analysed in a similar way. Surprisingly, the light output from Gluc was higher when the signal peptide was deleted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g009">Fig. 9</xref>), both for the <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> optimised (8.2×10<sup>5</sup>±5.6×10<sup>4</sup> RLUs compared to 1.75×10<sup>5</sup>±3.8×10<sup>4</sup> RLUs with signal peptide) and the wild-type genes (1.5×10<sup>5</sup>±1.36×10<sup>4</sup> RLUs compared to 2.1×10<sup>4</sup>±1.3×10<sup>3</sup> RLUs).</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption>
<title><italic>Gaussia</italic> luciferase is secreted from mycobacterial cells.</title>
<p>Luminescence (given as relative light units [RLUs]) was measured in culture, supernatant and cell samples of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> producing Gluc <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> optimised with (GlucSS) or without (Gluc) signal peptide, Gluc wild-type with (GlucWT+SS) or without (GlucWT-SS) signal peptide, and FFluc as control. Assays were performed with three independent cultures and each culture was measured in duplicate. As the data was not normally distributed, median values are displayed (bar) with inter-quartile ranges (box), and highest and lowest values (whiskers).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g009" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Bioluminescence <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging</title>
<p>To assess if the signal produced by each of the three reporters could be detected <italic>in vivo</italic>, three or four Balb/c mice were endotracheally inoculated with 10<sup>6</sup>–10<sup>7</sup> CFU of luminescent <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> and imaged 24 h later with the IVIS® Spectrum. The background level of luminescence was estimated by imaging two mice inoculated with the non-luminescent <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp.</p>
<p>Two substrate concentrations and two routes of administration were assessed for FFluc: (i) 300 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> body weight and 500 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> body weight for the intraperitoneal route, and (ii) 15 mg ml<sup>−1</sup> and 30 mg ml<sup>−1</sup> for the intranasal route. Images were acquired over a 3 h time period to determine the optimal time to image after luciferin administration. For luciferin administered via the intraperitoneal route, no signal could be detected until 5 min post-substrate administration at which point bioluminescence was evident in the lungs of all four positive mice and in the abdomen of one mouse injected with 500 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> luciferin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g010">Fig. 10</xref>). The signal in the abdomen most likely reflects the presence of <italic>ffluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> in the gastrointestinal tract, which could be due to the introduction of some bacteria into the oesophagus during the endotracheal inoculation. After the first 5 min, the bioluminescent signal increased exponentially, reaching a peak 25–30 min after substrate injection, with a level four to six times greater when using the higher concentration of luciferin (4.5×10<sup>7</sup>–7.5×10<sup>7</sup> photons s<sup>−1</sup> compared to 1.2×10<sup>7</sup>–1.4×10<sup>7</sup> photons s<sup>−1</sup>). After that the light level diminished approximately 50% in 30 min, followed by another 50% decrease every hour until the end of the experiment. No signal was detected in mice inoculated with <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g010">Fig. 10A</xref>), with stable background levels during the whole experiment (6×10<sup>4</sup>–8×10<sup>4</sup> photons s<sup>−1</sup> for 300 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> luciferin, and 5.9×10<sup>4</sup>–1.2×10<sup>5</sup> photons s<sup>−1</sup> for 500 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> luciferin, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g010">Fig. 10B</xref>). Therefore the best conditions for imaging of <italic>ffluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> given intraperitoneal substrate are using 500 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> luciferin and imaging 25–30 min post-substrate administration.</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g010" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption>
<title>Kinetics of FFluc activity in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> infected mice after intraperitoneal injection of luciferin.</title>
<p>Mice were endotracheally inoculated with 1.4×10<sup>7</sup> CFU of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp+FFlucWT [two representative mice (M1 and M2) out of four are shown] or with 6.8×10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp (control). 300 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> or 500 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> luciferin intraperitoneal was given 24 h post-inoculation and images were acquired at time points 0 (immediately after substrate administration), 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30, 60, 120 and 180 min. (<bold>a</bold>) Images were obtained using an IVIS Spectrum and are displayed as pseudocolour images of peak bioluminescence (given as photons s<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−2</sup> steridian [sr]<sup>−1</sup>), with variations in colour representing light intensity at a given location. Mice injected with 300 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> luciferin were imaged with an integration time of 1 min, whereas those that received 500 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> luciferin were imaged for 10 s to avoid saturation of the image. Three representative time points are shown. (<bold>b</bold>) Bioluminescence (given as photons s<sup>−1</sup>) in the thorax was quantified for each time point using the region of interest tool in the Living Image software program.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g010" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>For luciferin administered by the intranasal route, bioluminescence could be detected immediately after substrate introduction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g011">Fig. 11</xref>), and the maximum signal in the lungs was obtained in just 5–10 min (3.5×10<sup>6</sup>–4.6×10<sup>6</sup> photons s<sup>−1</sup> when 15 mg ml<sup>−1</sup> luciferin was administered, and 2.5×10<sup>6</sup>–4.6×10<sup>6</sup> photons s<sup>−1</sup> for 30 mg ml<sup>−1</sup> luciferin). In addition to the signal in the lungs a strong signal could be detected in the nose of the three positive mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g011">Fig. 11A</xref>) indicating the presence of FFluc-producing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> in that organ too. This signal was not observed when the luciferin was administered via the intraperitoneal route, most likely as a result of the increased systemic distribution of the substrate. After reaching a peak, the bioluminescence in the lung and nose decreased by 50–80% in 30 min falling close to background levels 2–3 h after substrate administration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g011">Fig. 11</xref>). The background levels remained constant during the whole experiment at approximately 1.2×10<sup>5</sup> photons s<sup>−1</sup>. Thus the best conditions for imaging of <italic>ffluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> given intranasal substrate are using 15 mg ml<sup>−1</sup> luciferin and imaging 5–10 min post-substrate administration.</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g011" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g011</object-id><label>Figure 11</label><caption>
<title>Kinetics of FFluc activity in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> infected mice after intranasal administration of luciferin.</title>
<p>Mice were endotracheally inoculated with 6.6×10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp+FFlucWT [two representative mice (M1 and M2) out of four are shown] or with 6.8×10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp as a control (one representative mouse out of two is shown). 20 µl of 15 mg ml<sup>−1</sup> or 30mg ml<sup>−1</sup> luciferin intranasal was administered 24 h post-inoculation and mice were imaged 0, 5, 10, 15, 30, 60, 120 and 180 min after. (<bold>a</bold>) Images were obtained using an IVIS Spectrum and are displayed as pseudocolour images of peak bioluminescence (given as photons s<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−2</sup> sr<sup>−1</sup>). Red represents the most intense light emission while blue correspond to the weakest signal. The colour bar indicates relative signal intensity. Mice were imaged with an integration time of 30 s. Three representative time points are shown. (<bold>b</bold>) Signal intensity (given as photons s<sup>−1</sup>) in the lungs was quantified for each time point using the region of interest tool in the Living Image software program.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g011" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>A similar assay was performed using Gluc. Two coelenterazine concentrations were administered intranasally (10 and 20 µg) and images were acquired at different time points over 3 h. A high background was detected in all cases and no differences were observed between mice inoculated with <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp+Gluc or <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g012">Fig. 12A, B</xref>). The same mice were then administered 10 µg coelenterazine by the intraperitoneal route 5 h after initial intranasal substrate administration. A high background signal was detected in the abdomen of both the positive and control mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g012">Fig. 12C</xref>), while the bioluminescence observed in the nose was due to the previous intranasal coelenterazine. Consequently, Gluc is not useful for <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g012" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g012</object-id><label>Figure 12</label><caption>
<title>BLI of <italic>gluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>.</title>
<p>Mice were endotracheally inoculated with 3.32×10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp+Gluc [two representative mice (M1 and M2) out of three are shown,) or with 1.58×10<sup>7</sup> CFU of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp as a control (one out of two mice is shown). 10 µg of coelenterazine intranasal was administered 24 h post-inoculation and mice were imaged at time points 0, 5, 10, 15, 30, 60, 120 and 180 min. (<bold>a</bold>) Images were obtained using an IVIS Spectrum and are displayed as pseudocolour images of peak bioluminescence (given as photons s<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−2</sup> sr<sup>−1</sup>), with variations in colour representing light intensity at a given location. Integration time was 5 min. (<bold>b</bold>) Bioluminescence (given as photons s<sup>−1</sup>) was quantified using the Living image software. (C) 10 µg of coelenterazine was given intraperitoneally to the same mice 5 h post-intranasal coelenterazine. Mice were imaged 0, 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min post-intraperitoneal coelenterazine with integration times of 3 min.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g012" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Mice infected with <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMVhsp+LuxAB+G13+CDE were also imaged. Bioluminescence could be detected in the lungs of the positive mice while no signal was observed in the control mouse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g013">Fig. 13</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g013" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g013</object-id><label>Figure 13</label><caption>
<title>BLI of <italic>lux</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>.</title>
<p>Mice were inoculated endotracheally with <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp+LuxAB+G13+CDE [7.9×10<sup>6</sup> CFU, two mice (M1 and M2) out of four are shown] or <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp (6.8×10<sup>6</sup> CFU, control) and imaged 24 h post-inoculation. Images were obtained using an IVIS Spectrum and are displayed as pseudocolour images of peak bioluminescence (given as photons s<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−2</sup> sr<sup>−1</sup>), with variations in colour representing light intensity at a given location. Mice were imaged with an integration time of 5 min.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g013" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Finally, we also imaged mice infected with <italic>ffluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> after administering intranasal luciferin. Bioluminescence was detected in the lungs of mice receiving <italic>ffluc</italic>-expressing bacteria, while no signal was observed in the control mouse infected with the wild-type <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0010777-g014">Fig. 14</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0010777-g014" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g014</object-id><label>Figure 14</label><caption>
<title>BLI of <italic>ffluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>.</title>
<p>Mice were inoculated endotracheally with 5×10<sup>6</sup> CFU of either wild-type <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> (control) or FFluc-producing <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>. 20 µl of 30 mg ml<sup>−1</sup> luciferin was administered intranasally and mice were imaged 5–10 min after. Mice were contained in a large air-tight box for safety considerations. The image was obtained using an IVIS Spectrum and is displayed as a pseudocolour image of peak bioluminescence (given as photons s<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−2</sup> sr<sup>−1</sup>). Red represents the most intense light emission while blue correspond to the weakest signal. The colour bar indicates relative signal intensity. Mice were imaged with an integration time of 1 min.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.g014" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Work with mycobacteria is hampered by their long duplication times meaning that, in the case of <italic>M. tuberculosis,</italic> results based on organ CFU counts are only available three to four weeks after the conclusion of the experiment. This handicap can, in part, be overcome by the use of non-invasive imaging techniques which allow infection dynamics to be studied in real-time. Moreover, such techniques allow for drastic reductions in the numbers of animals used in experiments. Recently an <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> recombinant strain expressing a bacterial thymidine kinase was visualised <italic>in vivo</italic> using [<sup>125</sup>I]FIAU-single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Davis1">[48]</xref>. While this technique is able to accurately measure the level of signal and has good spatial resolution, there are some issues with non-specific signals and the relatively high cost <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Davis1">[48]</xref>.</p>
<p>An alternative to this technique is the use of BLI which has proved very useful in the study of infectious diseases caused by a variety of bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Hardy1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Kadurugamuwa2">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Wiles2">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Glomski1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Lane2">[53]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Sjolinder1">[54]</xref>. In the only work on BLI of mycobacteria published so far, the <italic>luxAB</italic> genes were used, thus requiring the administration of the toxic substrate decanal. Although the infection could be detected in the abdomen of intravenously infected mice, the signal in the lungs was too low to be detected after intraperitoneal administration of aldehyde. To overcome these problems and thus further develop BLI imaging of mycobacteria, we have optimised the FFluc and Gluc luciferases for use in mycobacteria, both of which use non-toxic substrates, and the whole <italic>lux</italic> operon that does not require the external addition of substrate.</p>
<p>Approaches for imaging reporter gene expression mainly depend on robust levels of reporter protein. This, in turn, depends on the nature of the expression vector used, including the copy number, and the transcriptional and translational signals. With this in mind we compared the bioluminescent signal obtained with each reporter using three different vectors (two episomal vectors with 2–5 and 32–64 copies per cell, and one integrating vector), three different promoters (P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic>, P<italic><sub>myc</sub></italic>tetO, and P<sub>G13</sub>), and finally, with an optimised Shine-Dalgarno sequence, we also tested the effect of codon optimisation. Our results demonstrate that the best expression was achieved using the integrating vector, a finding most likely linked to a considerable instability of the replicating vectors when expressing <italic>ffluc</italic> and <italic>lux</italic>. In fact, the whole <italic>lux</italic> operon was only stably expressed in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> when it was cloned into the integrating vector, with no positive clones isolated using the episomal vectors. This would explain why this reporter operon had never been successfully expressed in mycobacteria until now. A similar situation has also been reported for the expression in mycobacteria of other recombinant genes like the HIV-1 gp120 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Stover1">[38]</xref> or the human interleukin 2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Kong1">[55]</xref>. The more stable expression of foreign antigens in mycobacteria using integrating vectors as opposed to episomal vectors has been extensively documented <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Mederle1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Kumar1">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Dennehy1">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Dennehy2">[59]</xref> and is mainly attributed to lower expression, and therefore a lower metabolic burden, associated with the reduction in the copy number.</p>
<p>In the case of the <italic>lux</italic> operon, we have previously found that plasmid-based expression of <italic>luxD</italic> is toxic in mycobacteria (S. Wiles, unpublished results). This gene encodes an acyl transferase which forms part of an enzyme complex (along with the products of <italic>luxC</italic> and <italic>luxE</italic>) responsible for recycling the fatty acid by-products of the luciferase reaction back into long chain aldehydes for use as further substrate. Given the importance of fatty acids in the cell wall structure of mycobacteria, it is not surprising that over-expression of fatty acid modifying enzymes would be detrimental.</p>
<p>Regarding promoter selection, we have found that the promoter P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> drove the highest luminescence for the three reporters, although the differences between the three promoters were only minor. P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> is known to be a strong promoter in mycobacteria and has been used extensively to over-express proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Stover1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Bastos1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-daCruz1">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Dellagostin1">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Wang1">[63]</xref>. However, P<italic><sub>myc</sub></italic>tetO, isolated from an <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>/<italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> library using GFP to assess gene expression <italic>in vitro</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Ehrt1">[42]</xref>; and P<sub>G13</sub>, isolated from an <italic>M. marinum</italic> library expressing GFP inside macrophages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Barker1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Barker2">[44]</xref>, have both been reported to be stronger than P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> (10 and 10–20 times, respectively). The discrepancy with our results could be related to the different reporters used to measure gene expression, and the toxicity and metabolic load associated with their over-expression. It may also be that the highest stable level of expression for our reporters had already been achieved with the P<italic><sub>hsp</sub></italic> and therefore the use of stronger promoters did not increase expression further. This would be in agreement with the instability observed using the episomal vectors for <italic>ffluc</italic> and <italic>lux</italic>, and when using the P<italic><sub>myc</sub></italic>tetO with <italic>lux</italic>.</p>
<p>Perhaps unsurprisingly, codon-optimisation was found to increase the signal obtained for FFluc (30-fold [76% homology]) and Gluc (2.5-fold [74% homology]). Unexpectedly, the <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> codon-optimised Lux was found to be non-functional, even after the addition of exogenous substrate. We have not explored the basis for this inactivity; however, there is a suggestion from the optimised sequence that after transcription the DNA may form secondary structures that impede translation (data not shown).</p>
<p>We also characterised the various bioluminescence reactions by varying the integration time and substrate concentration, and by measuring the kinetics of light output. The results obtained are similar to those previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Tannous1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Wiles1">[10]</xref> proving that Gluc catalyses a rapid ‘flash’ reaction, FFluc has glow kinetics, and the continuous synthesis of substrate by the <italic>lux</italic> operon allows for steady luminescence. In this work, we have found that FFluc produced the highest luminescence, 10 times brighter than that obtained with Lux, and 100 times that of Gluc. This is in contrast with the results of Snewin et al. who found LuxAB to be brighter than FFluc <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Snewin1">[31]</xref>, but this was done using an episomal reporter that required the addition of aldehyde substrate. Consequently, the substrate may have been in excess, which might be a limiting factor in our whole operon <italic>lux</italic> reporter. To test this hypothesis an extra promoter was cloned in front of <italic>luxCDE</italic> to boost substrate synthesis, and indeed a 6-fold higher signal was obtained. The alternative of adding exogenous substrate also increased the signal 5–10 times (data not shown). The availability of FMNH<sub>2</sub> could also be a limiting factor. In yeast, co-expression of <italic>luxAB</italic> together with the <italic>frp</italic> gene, encoding a NADPH-FMN oxidoreductase from <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic>, led to a 100-fold increase in the luminescence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Szittner1">[64]</xref>. However, we have found the same approach in mycobacteria to have no effect on the final signal (unpublished results).</p>
<p>Once the best conditions for reporter expression were selected, we proceeded to explore if the bioluminescence signal obtained was strong enough for the imaging of mycobacteria <italic>in vivo</italic>. Importantly, bioluminescence could be detected in the lungs of mice infected with either <italic>ffluc</italic> or <italic>lux</italic>-expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> or <italic>ffluc</italic>-expressing <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>. FFluc utilises a non-toxic, well tolerated substrate that can be repeatedly administered for repetitive imaging. The main route of luciferin administration is by intraperitoneal injection, however intranasal delivery has been recently described as a more efficient route for the monitoring of bioluminescence in the lungs, while using 30 times less luciferin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Buckley1">[65]</xref>. We have found that a good signal is obtained using intranasal luciferin, although a stronger signal can be achieved using intraperitoneal luciferin which would also have the advantage of allowing detection of signal in other locations besides the lungs.</p>
<p>Surprisingly, the signal from Gluc-producing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> in mice could not be distinguished from the strong background produced by the coelenterazine substrate alone. These results were unexpected considering that published work with eukaryotic cells states that the Gluc signal is 1000 times stronger than that of FFluc in cell culture, and as bright as FFluc <italic>in vivo</italic>, with no background detected <italic>in vivo</italic> even using a 20-fold higher concentration of coelenterazine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Tannous1">[9]</xref>. Gluc is naturally secreted from eukaryotic cells and this has been used to quantify the number of Gluc-producing cells in murine blood samples <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Wurdinger1">[66]</xref>. Although we have proved that Gluc is also secreted from <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>, we have been unable to detect it in blood samples taken from infected mice thus far (data not shown). Overall these results preclude Gluc as a reporter for either <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging of mycobacteria or <italic>ex vivo</italic> monitoring of infected organs.</p>
<p>The results presented here represent an important step towards the use of bioluminescence for the non-invasive study of mycobacteria infection <italic>in vivo</italic>. In fact, the use of FFluc, or the whole <italic>lux</italic> operon would represent a major advantage compared, for example, to the use of just <italic>luxAB</italic>. There are, however, some issues that should be considered and further investigated. First, the minimal number of bacteria capable of being detected within the lungs is expected to be quite high, especially when compared to the inocula that are normally used in experimental <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> infections. Although this could limit the use of BLI studies for the initial stages of the infection, it would not pose a problem in more advanced phases of the infection and would still represent an important improvement in drug or vaccine efficacy testing. Secondly, luciferin accessibility to the bacteria contained in granulomatous lesions could affect the signal obtained and has to be further investigated. To that end, preliminary results have shown that luminescence can be detected during infection of macrophage <italic>in vitro</italic> thus proving the permeability of macrophages to luciferin (unpublished data). Finally, the signal obtained is also affected by the metabolic state of the bacteria since the luciferase reaction relies on bacterial metabolites, mainly ATP and FMNH<sub>2</sub> for FFluc and Lux respectively. This is exemplified by the decrease in the luminescence observed when <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> enters the stationary phase and has also been previously described for other bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Loimaranta1">[67]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Francis1">[68]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Koga1">[69]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Galluzzi1">[70]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Morin1">[71]</xref>. Although this could represent a handicap for the study of, for example, dormant <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> it could be a powerful tool to gain insights into the metabolic state of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> during infection, to study entrance into dormancy, as well as for the rapid detection of drugs acting on bacterial metabolism.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title>
<p><italic>M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup>155 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Snapper1">[72]</xref>, <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> NEB-10β (New England Biolabs UK Ltd) were used in this work. <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> and <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> were grown on Middlebrook 7H11 agar medium (BD Diagnostics) supplemented with 0.5% glycerol and 10% oleic acid albumin-dextrose-catalase (OADC) (BD Diagnostics). When required, filter-sterilised luciferin was added at a final concentration of 0.157 mM. Liquid cultures of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> and <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> were grown either in Middlebrook 7H9 broth (BD Diagnostics) containing 0.05% Tween 80 (Sigma) and 10% albumin-dextrose-catalase (ADC) enrichment (BD Diagnostics), or (for <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> Gluc assays) in Luria-Bertani (LB) medium with 0.05% Tween. LB medium was preferred for the Gluc assays because the background of coelenterazine was 100 times lower in that medium than in 7H9 broth. LB medium was used for culturing <italic>E. coli</italic>. All the strains were grown at 37°C. The following antibiotics were added when appropriate: ampicillin [100 µg ml<sup>−1</sup> (Sigma)], hygromycin B [150 µg ml<sup>−1</sup> (Invitrogen)] and kanamycin [25 µg ml<sup>−1</sup>, for mycobacteria, 50 µg ml<sup>−1</sup> for <italic>E. coli</italic> (Sigma)].</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Construction of bioluminescent reporter plasmids and strains</title>
<p>The plasmids used in this study are described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0010777-t001">Tables 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0010777-t002"/><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0010777-t003"/><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0010777-t004">4</xref>. The integrating expression vectors pMV306hsp and pMV306myc were constructed by cloning into pMV306 the promoters P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> and P<italic><sub>myc1</sub>tetO</italic> obtained as NotI-HindIII and XbaI-SalI fragments from pSMT3 and pSE100 respectively. All reporter genes, except for the <italic>lux</italic> operon, were PCR amplified using the primers and templates listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0010777-t005">Table 5</xref>. These primers contained an optimised Shine-Dalgarno sequence (Mega SD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-LeDantec1">[45]</xref> and/or restriction sites as indicated. The sequence of the PCR products was confirmed by DNA sequencing. The <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> optimised <italic>gluc</italic> gene was cloned into pSMT3 and pSMT3M as a BamHI-HindIII fragment and into pMV306myc as an EcoRI-SalI fragment. For cloning the wild-type and optimised <italic>gluc</italic> genes into pMV306hsp the PCR products were digested with EcoRI-SalI. Plasmids containing the <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> optimised <italic>ffluc</italic> gene were made in a similar way but cloning the EcoRI-XbaI PCR product into pUC18 first to use the restriction sites of this vector's MCS. The wild-type <italic>ffluc</italic> was cloned into pMV306hsp as a HindIII-SalI insert. Plasmids pMV306hsp+Lux, pSMT3+Lux and pSMT3M+Lux were created by cloning a 5.7-kb EcoRI-PstI blunted fragment (containing the whole <italic>lux</italic> operon) from pSB2025 into the respective expression vector. Deletion of a 0.4 kb NotI-EcoRI fragment (containing P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic>) from pMV306hsp+Lux and insertion of P<italic><sub>myc1</sub>tetO</italic> from pMV306myc produced pMV306myc+Lux. In a similar way, the reporter plasmids containing the G13 promoter were made replacing the P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> of the corresponding reporter vector with P<italic><sub>G13</sub></italic> by digestion with NotI-EcoRI. pMVhsp+LuxAB+G13+CDE was obtained by cloning the KpnI P<italic><sub>G13</sub></italic> PCR fragment into pMVhsp+Lux in front of <italic>luxC</italic>. Finally, <italic>luxCDABE</italic> from pMU1* was cloned into pMV306hsp as a 5.7-kb EcoRI PCR fragment.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0010777-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Plasmids used in this study.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0010777-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plasmid</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference or source</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mycobacterial replicating expression vector containing P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic>, Hyg<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Garbe1">[75]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3M</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3 with a high copy number mutation</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Carroll1">[39]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSE100</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mycobacterial replicating expression vector containing P<italic><sub>myc1</sub>tetO</italic>, Hyg<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Guo1">[76]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mycobacterial integrating vector, Km<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Stover1">[38]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306 derivative containing P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306myc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306 derivative containing P<italic><sub>myc1</sub>tetO</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pUC18</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> cloning vector, Amp<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fermentas</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0010777-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Firefly luciferase encoding vectors used in this study.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0010777-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plasmid</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference or source</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pJ246:17659</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> cloning vector encoding the firefly luciferase (<italic>FFluc</italic>) codon optimized for <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>, Amp<sup>r</sup>, Km<sup>r</sup>, Cm<sup>r</sup>, Gen<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">J. Cirillo and K. Francis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3+FFluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3 encoding the codon optimized <italic>FFluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3M+FFluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3M encoding the codon optimized <italic>FFluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+FFluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp encoding the codon optimized <italic>FFluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306myc+FFluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306myc encoding the codon optimized <italic>FFluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306G13+FFluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+FFluc derivative in which P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> has been replaced with P<italic><sub>G13</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pGL2-Basic</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> vector encoding the wild-type <italic>FFluc</italic>, Amp<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Promega</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+FFlucWT</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp encoding the wild-type <italic>FFluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0010777-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title><italic>Gaussia</italic> luciferase encoding vectors used in this study.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0010777-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plasmid</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference or source</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pUC57+Gluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> vector encoding the <italic>Gaussia</italic> luciferase gene optimized for <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> codon and lacking the first 48 nt (corresponding to the secretion signal), Amp<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">D. Agranoff</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3+Gluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3 encoding the codon optimized <italic>Gluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3M+Gluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3M encoding the codon optimized <italic>Gluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+Gluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp encoding the codon optimized <italic>Gluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306myc+Gluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306myc encoding the codon optimized <italic>Gluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306G13+Gluc</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+Gluc derivative in which P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> has been replaced with P<italic><sub>G13</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pJ201:26462</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> cloning vector encoding the <italic>Gaussia</italic> luciferase gene including the secretion signal (<italic>GlucSS</italic>) codon optimized for <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>, Km<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DNA 2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+GlucSS</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp encoding <italic>GlucSS</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pUC18+GlucWT-SS</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> cloning vector encoding the wild-type <italic>Gluc</italic> without the secretion signal, Amp<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B. A. Tannous</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pUC18+GlucWT+SS</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> cloning vector encoding the wild-type <italic>Gluc</italic> with the secretion signal, Amp<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B. A. Tannous</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+GlucWT-SS</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp encoding the wild-type <italic>Gluc</italic> without the secretion signal</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+GlucWT+SS</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp encoding the wild-type <italic>Gluc</italic> with the secretion signal</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0010777-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Bacterial luciferase encoding vectors used in this study.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0010777-t004-4" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t004" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plasmid</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference or source</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSB2025</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> vector containing the <italic>LuxABCDE</italic> operon from <italic>P. luminescens</italic> modified for expression in Gram positive bacteria, Amp<sup>r</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Qazi1">[41]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3+Lux</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3 encoding LuxABCDE</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3M+Lux</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pSMT3M encoding LuxABCDE</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+Lux</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp encoding LuxABCDE</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306myc+Lux</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306myc encoding LuxABCDE</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306G13+Lux</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+LuxABCDE derivative in which P<italic><sub>hsp60</sub></italic> has been replaced with P<italic><sub>G13</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+LuxAB+G13+CDE</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMV306hsp+LuxABCDE derivative with P<italic><sub>G13</sub></italic> cloned in front of <italic>luxC</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMU1*</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Improved pMU1 (which has a promoterless <italic>luxCDABE</italic> optimized for high-GC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Craney1">[46]</xref>) with a corrected mutation in <italic>luxD</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A. Craney &amp; J. Nodwell</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0010777-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
<title>Primers used in this study.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0010777-t005-5" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0010777.t005" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Target</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primer<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Template</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>FFluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic>CCGAG<underline>GAATTCGGATCC</underline></italic><bold><italic>AGAAGGAGAAGTACCG</italic></bold>ATG GAAGATGCGAAGAAC-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pJ246:17659</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic>AGGCT<underline>TCTAGA</underline>G</italic>TCACTTGCCTCCTTTCTTCGC-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>FFlucWT</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic><underline>AAGCTT</underline></italic><bold><italic>AGAAGGAGAAGTACCG</italic></bold>ATGGAAGACGCCAA AAAC-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pGL2-Basic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic><underline>GTCGAC</underline></italic>TTACTTTCCGCCCTTCTTGGC-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Gluc</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic>CCGAG<underline>GAATTCGGATCC</underline></italic><bold><italic>AGAAGGAGAAGTACCG</italic></bold>ATG AAGCCGACCGAGAAC-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pUC57+Gluc</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic>TTATAT<underline>AAGCTT</underline>GTCGAC</italic>TCAGTCGCCGCCGGCGCC-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>GlucWT-SS</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic>CCGAG<underline>GAATTCGGATCC</underline></italic><bold><italic>AGAAGGAGAAGTACCG</italic></bold>ATG AAACCAACTGAAAAC-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pUC18+GlucWT-SS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic><underline>GTCGACAAGCTT</underline></italic>TTAATCACCACCGGCACCCTTTAT-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>GlucWT+SS</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic>CCGAG<underline>GAATTCGGATCC</underline></italic><bold><italic>AGAAGGAGAAGTACCG</italic></bold>AT GGGAGTGAAAGTTCTTTTTG-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pUC18+GlucWT+SS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic><underline>GTCGACAAGCTT</underline></italic>TTAATCACCACCGGCACCCTTTAT-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P<italic><sub>G13</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic><underline>GCGGCCGC</underline></italic>GATCGCCACTAGCGCCGCGGT-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>M. marinum</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic><underline>GAATTC</underline></italic>TCGGTTACCAAGCGTGCATTT-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic><underline>GGTACC</underline></italic>GATCGCCACTAGCGCCGCGGT-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic><underline>GGTACC</underline></italic>TCGGTTACCAAGCGTGCATTT-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>LuxStm</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic>CCGA<underline>GAATTC</underline></italic>CAGATCTGACTGAGTGACCAAAG-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pMU1*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-<italic>TGAC<underline>GAATTC</underline></italic>TCAGCTGTTGAACGCCTGGTT-3′</named-content></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>In italics, sequence added to include restriction sites (underlined) for cloning procedures, and optimized Shine-Dalgarno sequence (in bold) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-LeDantec1">[45]</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Reporter strains were obtained by electroporation of reporter plasmids into <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup>155 or <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-Parish1">[73]</xref>. Each strain was named according to the plasmid it contained. The strains transformed with an integrating vector were checked by PCR with primers amplifying the corresponding promoter and reporter gene; whereas recombinant strains with replicating vectors were confirmed by recovering the plasmid after transformation into <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Bioluminescence assays</title>
<sec id="s4c1">
<title>Luciferases substrates</title>
<p>Coelenterazine (Gold BioTechnology®, Inc., St. Louis, Mo., USA), the substrate for Gluc, was reconstituted in acid methanol to a concentration of 10 mM (4.238 mg ml<sup>−1</sup>). The substrate for FFluc, D-luciferin (Gold BioTechnology®), was prepared in distilled water at 94 mM (30 mg ml<sup>−1</sup>). All stocks were stored at −20°C and diluted in broth media or D-PBS (without calcium or magnesium) immediately before use. Working solutions were kept on ice in the dark during preparation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c2">
<title>Screening of transformants</title>
<p>After electroporation, 10 randomly selected transformants were grown in broth media. Luminescence was then measured at room temperature on a tube luminometer (Modulus™ Single Tube Multimode Reader, Turner Biosystems) by adding coelenterazine to a final concentration of 10 µM or luciferin to 470 µM, and integrating the signal over 1 s. The results are expressed as relative light units (RLU). The luminescence of Lux transformants was measured in a similar way but without adding any substrate. <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> Lux electroporation plates were imaged in the IVIS® Spectrum imaging system (Caliper Life Sciences, Alameda, CA) using the Living Image® software (Caliper Life Sciences) and acquiring the signal for 1 s to 30 s. <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> or <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> transformed with the corresponding empty vector were used to measure the background luminescence.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c3">
<title>Luciferase activity assays</title>
<p>For the integration time, substrate and kinetics assays, two or three independent cultures of each strain were grown to an optical density (OD) at 600 nm of 0.6 (mid-log phase) and each culture was measured in duplicate at 37°C with a microplate reader (Mithras LB 940, Berthold Technologies, Bad Wildbad, Germany) using MicroWin 2000 software (Berthold Technologies). When required 50 µl of substrate was injected into 50 µl of sample in a polystyrene 96-well plate and luminescence was measured for 0.1 s to 10 s after a delay of 0.1 s. For the kinetics assay luminescence was measured immediately after adding the substrate and then every 10 s or 30 s (Gluc and FFluc respectively) for 30 min. In the case of the bacterial luciferase the light output was also measured every 30 s for 30 min but without adding exogenous substrate. Cultures of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> pMV306hsp were processed in parallel to each experiment and the measurements were treated as the luminescence's background. The results are expressed as RLUs.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Study of <italic>Gaussia</italic> luciferase secretion</title>
<p>Three independent cultures of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> expressing <italic>gluc</italic> were grown in LB-Tween to mid-log phase (OD = 0.6). A sample of 0.5 ml of each culture was centrifuged, the supernatant filtered using a 0.22 µm Ultrafree-MC centrifugal filter unit (Millipore) and the cell pellet resuspended in 0.5 ml of fresh medium. The luminescence was then measured in duplicate in samples taken from the culture, supernatant and cells using the Mithras LB 940 microplate reader as above.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title><italic>In vivo</italic> studies</title>
<p>Experiments were performed in accordance with the Animals Scientific Procedures Act (1986) and were approved by the local Ethical Review Committee. Barrier-bred female 8–12 week old Balb/c mice (Charles River UK Ltd) were anaesthetised by intraperitoneal injection of 100 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> body weight ketamine (Ketaset; Fort Dodge Animal Health, Southampton, UK) and 10 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> body weight xylazine (Rompun; Bayer, Newbury, Berkshire, UK) and inoculated with <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> or <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> by endotracheal aerosol application of a total volume of 25 µl using a Microsprayer® (PennCentury, Philadelphia, PA, USA) as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0010777-BivasBenita1">[74]</xref>.</p>
<p>Assessment of bioluminescence (photons s<sup>−1</sup>cm<sup>−2</sup> steridian [sr]<sup>−1</sup>) from living animals was performed using an IVIS® Spectrum system (Caliper Life Sciences, Alameda, USA) which consists of a cooled charge-coupled device camera mounted on a light-tight specimen chamber. Prior to bioluminescent imaging, mice were anaesthetised with 4% isoflurane. Luciferin dissolved in sterile D-PBS was then administered to animals inoculated with FFluc expressing strains [20 µl of 15 mg ml<sup>−1</sup> (47 µM) or 30 mg ml<sup>−1</sup> (94 µM) luciferin via the intranasal route, or 300 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> or 500 mg kg<sup>−1</sup> body weight by intraperitoneal injection]. To image mice infected with Gluc expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> 50 µl of 0.48 mM or 0.96 mM coelenterazine (prepared by diluting the 10 mM stock in sterile D-PBS just before use) was intranasally administered (10 or 20 µg per mouse respectively), or 150 µl of 0.16 mM coelenterazine via the intraperitoneal route (10 µg). Mice were placed into the camera chamber of the IVIS® Spectrum imaging system where a controlled flow of 2.5% isoflurane in air was administered through a nose cone via the IXG8 gas anaesthesia system (Caliper Life Sciences). A grayscale reference image was taken under low illumination prior to quantification of emitted photons over 30 s to 5 min, depending on signal intensity, using the software program Living Image (Caliper Life Sciences) as an overlay on Igor (Wavemetrics, Seattle, WA). For anatomical localisation, a pseudocolour image representing light intensity (blue, least intense to red, most intense) was generated using the Living Image software and superimposed over the grayscale reference image. Bioluminescence within specific regions of individual mice was also quantified using the region of interest (ROI) tool in the Living Image software program (given as photons s<sup>−1</sup>). Animals were imaged immediately after inoculation, to assess the success of the delivery, and 24 h post-infection. Animals inoculated with <italic>ffluc</italic>- or <italic>gluc</italic>- expressing <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> were imaged at different time points after substrate administration for up to 3 h.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4f">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism 5.02 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, USA). Normality of data was tested by use of the D'Agostino &amp; Pearson omnibus normality test. According to this, differences in reporter constructs activity were assessed by use of the non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis test for comparisons of groups of three. If the Kruskal–Wallis test was statistically significant, then a Dunn's multiple comparison test was employed. For groups in pairs the non-parametric Mann-Whitney test, or the t test for normal data, were used.</p>
</sec></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank Phil Hill (University of Nottingham) for plasmid pSB2025; Bakhos A. Tannous (Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts) for plasmids pUC18 containing the wild-type <italic>gluc</italic> with and without secretion sequence; Jeff Cirillo (Texas A&amp;M) and Kevin Francis (Caliper Life Sciences) for plasmid pJ246:17659 containing <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> codon-optimised FFluc; Arryn Craney and Justin Nodwell (Biochemistry &amp; Biomedical Sciences, McMaster University, Ontario, Canada) for providing plasmid pMU1*; Paul Carroll (Queen Mary University of London, Barts and the London School of Medicine and Dentistry) for kindly supplying pSMT3M; and Dan Agranoff (Department of Infectious Diseases &amp; Immunity, Imperial College London) for plasmid pUC57+Gluc containing <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> codon-optimised Gluc. We would also like to thank Vivek Rao, Paul Carroll, Lise J. Schreuder and Dimitris Kioussis for helpful discussions. We especially thank César Sánchez for critically reviewing the manuscript and helpful suggestions.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0010777-WHO1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">WHO</collab>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Global tuberculosis control 2009.</article-title> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">303</size>              <comment>Epidemiology, strategy, financing: WHO Press.</comment>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Hutchens1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Luker</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Applications of bioluminescence imaging to the study of infectious diseases.</article-title>             <source>Cell Microbiol</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>2315</fpage>             <lpage>2322</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Wright1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JS</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Transient interference with staphylococcal quorum sensing blocks abscess formation.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>102</volume>             <fpage>1691</fpage>             <lpage>1696</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Lane1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alteri</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Expression of flagella is coincident with uropathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ascension to the upper urinary tract.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>16669</fpage>             <lpage>16674</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Steinhuber1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Steinhuber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Landmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goerke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wolz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fluckiger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Bioluminescence imaging to study the promoter activity of hla of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Int J Med Microbiol</source>             <volume>298</volume>             <fpage>599</fpage>             <lpage>605</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Xiong1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Willard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kadurugamuwa</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Real-time <italic>in vivo</italic> bioluminescent imaging for evaluating the efficacy of antibiotics in a rat <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> endocarditis model.</article-title>             <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>             <volume>49</volume>             <fpage>380</fpage>             <lpage>387</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Kadurugamuwa1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kadurugamuwa</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Modi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Orihuela</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Noninvasive monitoring of pneumococcal meningitis and evaluation of treatment efficacy in an experimental mouse model.</article-title>             <source>Mol Imaging</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>137</fpage>             <lpage>142</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Gheysens1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gheysens</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mottaghy</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Method of bioluminescence imaging for molecular imaging of physiological and pathological processes.</article-title>             <source>Methods</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>139</fpage>             <lpage>145</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Tannous1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tannous</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weissleder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Breakefield</surname><given-names>XO</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Codon-optimized <italic>Gaussia</italic> luciferase cDNA for mammalian gene expression in culture and <italic>in vivo</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Ther</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>435</fpage>             <lpage>443</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Wiles1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wiles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanidou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Alternative luciferase for monitoring bacterial cells under adverse conditions.</article-title>             <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>             <volume>71</volume>             <fpage>3427</fpage>             <lpage>3432</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Prioli1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prioli</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tanna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1985</year>             <article-title>Rapid methods for counting mycobacteria–comparison of methods for extraction of mycobacterial adenosine triphosphate (ATP) determined by firefly luciferase assay.</article-title>             <source>Tubercle</source>             <volume>66</volume>             <fpage>99</fpage>             <lpage>108</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Janaszek1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Janaszek</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aleksandrowicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sitkiewicz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>The use of the firefly bioluminescent reaction for the rapid detection and counting of mycobacterium BCG.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Stand</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>11</fpage>             <lpage>16</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Andrew1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Construction of a bioluminescent mycobacterium and its use for assay of antimycobacterial agents.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>31</volume>             <fpage>2251</fpage>             <lpage>2254</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Cooksey1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cooksey</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>WR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shinnick</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>A rapid method for screening antimicrobial agents for activities against a strain of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> expressing firefly luciferase.</article-title>             <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>1348</fpage>             <lpage>1352</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Cooksey2"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cooksey</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morlock</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beggs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Bioluminescence method to evaluate antimicrobial agents against <italic>Mycobacterium avium</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>754</fpage>             <lpage>756</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Arain1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arain</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Resconi</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Bioluminescence screening <italic>in vitro</italic> (Bio-Siv) assays for high-volume antimycobacterial drug discovery.</article-title>             <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>             <volume>40</volume>             <fpage>1536</fpage>             <lpage>1541</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Gordon1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>The application of bacterial luciferase as a reporter gene in mycobacteria.</article-title>             <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>             <volume>101</volume>             <fpage>235</fpage>             <lpage>243</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Deb1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Bioluminescent <italic>Mycobacterium aurum</italic> expressing firefly luciferase for rapid and high throughput screening of antimycobacterial drugs in vitro and in infected macrophages.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>             <volume>279</volume>             <fpage>457</fpage>             <lpage>461</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Shawar1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shawar</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Humble</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dalfsen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Rapid screening of natural products for antimycobacterial activity by using luciferase-expressing strains of <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> BCG and <italic>Mycobacterium intracellulare</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>             <volume>41</volume>             <fpage>570</fpage>             <lpage>574</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Jacobs1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>WR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barletta</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Udani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kalkut</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Rapid assessment of drug susceptibilities of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> by means of luciferase reporter phages.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>260</volume>             <fpage>819</fpage>             <lpage>822</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Carriere1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riska</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zimhony</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kriakov</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bardarov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Conditionally replicating luciferase reporter phages: improved sensitivity for rapid detection and assessment of drug susceptibility of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>3232</fpage>             <lpage>3239</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Riska1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riska</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>WR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McKitrick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Specific identification of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> with the luciferase reporter mycobacteriophage: use of p-nitro-alpha-acetylamino-beta-hydroxy propiophenone.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>3225</fpage>             <lpage>3231</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Riska2"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riska</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>WR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>The use of luciferase-reporter phage for antibiotic-susceptibility testing of mycobacteria.</article-title>             <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>             <volume>101</volume>             <fpage>431</fpage>             <lpage>455</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Banaiee1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banaiee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bobadilla-Del-Valle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bardarov</surname><given-names>S</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riska</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Luciferase reporter mycobacteriophages for detection, identification, and antibiotic susceptibility testing of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in Mexico.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>3883</fpage>             <lpage>3888</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Bardarov1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bardarov</surname><given-names>S</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenach</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banaiee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Detection and drug-susceptibility testing of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> from sputum samples using luciferase reporter phage: comparison with the Mycobacteria Growth Indicator Tube (MGIT) system.</article-title>             <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>53</fpage>             <lpage>61</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Pai1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kalantri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pascopella</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reingold</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Bacteriophage-based assays for the rapid detection of rifampicin resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: a meta-analysis.</article-title>             <source>J Infect</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>175</fpage>             <lpage>187</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Banaiee2"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banaiee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>January</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barthus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lambrick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roditi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Evaluation of a semi-automated reporter phage assay for susceptibility testing of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> isolates in South Africa.</article-title>             <source>Tuberculosis (Edinb)</source>             <volume>88</volume>             <fpage>64</fpage>             <lpage>68</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Arain2"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arain</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Resconi</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Reporter gene technology to assess activity of antimycobacterial agents in macrophages.</article-title>             <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>             <volume>40</volume>             <fpage>1542</fpage>             <lpage>1544</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Hickey1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arain</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shawar</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Humble</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Langhorne</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Luciferase <italic>in vivo</italic> expression technology: use of recombinant mycobacterial reporter strains to evaluate antimycobacterial activity in mice.</article-title>             <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>             <volume>40</volume>             <fpage>400</fpage>             <lpage>407</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Bonay1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bonay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchonnet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pelicic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lagier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grandsaigne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Effect of stimulation of human macrophages on intracellular survival of <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> Bacillus Calmette-Guerin. Evaluation with a mycobacterial reporter strain.</article-title>             <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>             <volume>159</volume>             <fpage>1629</fpage>             <lpage>1637</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Snewin1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Snewin</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gares</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gaora</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Assessment of immunity to mycobacterial infection with luciferase reporter constructs.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>67</volume>             <fpage>4586</fpage>             <lpage>4593</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Bouchonnet1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchonnet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boechat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bonay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hance</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Alpha/beta interferon impairs the ability of human macrophages to control growth of <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> BCG.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>3020</fpage>             <lpage>3025</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Turner1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyle</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Snewin</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gares</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>An <italic>ex vivo</italic> culture model for screening drug activity against <italic>in vivo</italic> phenotypes of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Microbiology</source>             <volume>148</volume>             <fpage>2929</fpage>             <lpage>2936</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Kampmann1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kampmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tena</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mzazi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Novel human in vitro system for evaluating antimycobacterial vaccines.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>72</volume>             <fpage>6401</fpage>             <lpage>6407</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-AlAttiyah1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Attiyah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shazly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Assessment of <italic>in vitro</italic> immunity to <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in a human peripheral blood infection model using a luciferase reporter construct of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv.</article-title>             <source>Clin Exp Immunol</source>             <volume>145</volume>             <fpage>520</fpage>             <lpage>527</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Heuts1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Heuts</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wigzell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rottenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Use of non-invasive bioluminescent imaging to assess mycobacterial dissemination in mice, treatment with bactericidal drugs and protective immunity.</article-title>             <source>Micro Infect</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>1114</fpage>             <lpage>1121</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Ranes1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ranes</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rauzier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lagranderie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gheorghiu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gicquel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Functional analysis of pAL5000, a plasmid from <italic>Mycobacterium fortuitum</italic>: construction of a “mini” mycobacterium-<italic>Escherichia coli</italic> shuttle vector.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>172</volume>             <fpage>2793</fpage>             <lpage>2797</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Stover1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de la Cruz</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fuerst</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burlein</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>New use of BCG for recombinant vaccines.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>351</volume>             <fpage>456</fpage>             <lpage>460</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Carroll1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schreuder</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Muwanguzi-Karugaba</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wiles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Sensitive Detection of Gene Expression in Mycobacteria under Replicating and Non-Replicating Conditions Using Optimized Far-Red Reporters.</article-title>             <source>PLoS One</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>e9823</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0009823" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0009823</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Bourn1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bourn</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stutz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Creation and characterisation of a high-copy-number version of the pAL5000 mycobacterial replicon.</article-title>             <source>Tuberculosis (Edinb)</source>             <volume>87</volume>             <fpage>481</fpage>             <lpage>488</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Qazi1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qazi</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Counil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cockayne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title><italic>agr</italic> expression precedes escape of internalized <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> from the host endosome.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>69</volume>             <fpage>7074</fpage>             <lpage>7082</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Ehrt1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>XV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ryou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Monteleone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Controlling gene expression in mycobacteria with anhydrotetracycline and Tet repressor.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>e21</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Barker1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porcella</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>The <italic>Mycobacterium marinum</italic> G13 promoter is a strong sigma 70-like promoter that is expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and mycobacteria species.</article-title>             <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>             <volume>175</volume>             <fpage>79</fpage>             <lpage>85</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Barker2"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>The identification of <italic>Mycobacterium marinum</italic> genes differentially expressed in macrophage phagosomes using promoter fusions to green fluorescent protein.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>1167</fpage>             <lpage>1177</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-LeDantec1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Le Dantec</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gicquel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Picardeau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Genomic sequence and transcriptional analysis of a 23-kilobase mycobacterial linear plasmid: evidence for horizontal transfer and identification of plasmid maintenance systems.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>183</volume>             <fpage>2157</fpage>             <lpage>2164</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Craney1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Craney</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hohenauer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Navani</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A synthetic <italic>luxCDABE</italic> gene cluster optimized for expression in high-GC bacteria.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>e46</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Zhao1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Characterization of coelenterazine analogs for measurements of <italic>Renilla</italic> luciferase activity in live cells and living animals.</article-title>             <source>Mol Imaging</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>43</fpage>             <lpage>54</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Davis1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Be</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lamichhane</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nimmagadda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pomper</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Bacterial thymidine kinase as a non-invasive imaging reporter for <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in live animals.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e6297</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Hardy1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>DeBoer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Extracellular replication of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> in the murine gall bladder.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>303</volume>             <fpage>851</fpage>             <lpage>853</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Kadurugamuwa2"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kadurugamuwa</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Modi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Coquoz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Reduction of astrogliosis by early treatment of pneumococcal meningitis measured by simultaneous imaging, <italic>in vivo</italic>, of the pathogen and host response.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>73</volume>             <fpage>7836</fpage>             <lpage>7843</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Wiles2"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wiles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> bioluminescence imaging of the murine pathogen <italic>Citrobacter rodentium</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>74</volume>             <fpage>5391</fpage>             <lpage>5396</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Glomski1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Glomski</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Piris-Gimenez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huerre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Primary involvement of pharynx and peyer's patch in inhalational and intestinal anthrax.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Pathog</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>e76</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Lane2"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alteri</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Expression of flagella is coincident with uropathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ascension to the upper urinary tract.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>16669</fpage>             <lpage>16674</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Sjolinder1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sjolinder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Imaging of disease dynamics during meningococcal sepsis.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>e241</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Kong1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kunimoto</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Secretion of human interleukin 2 by recombinant <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> BCG.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>63</volume>             <fpage>799</fpage>             <lpage>803</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Mederle1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mederle</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bourguin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ensergueix</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Badell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moniz-Peireira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Plasmidic versus insertional cloning of heterologous genes in <italic>Mycobacterium bovis BCG</italic>: impact on in vivo antigen persistence and immune responses.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>303</fpage>             <lpage>314</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Kumar1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Genetic rearrangements leading to disruption of heterologous gene expression in mycobacteria: an observation with <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> beta-galactosidase in <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> and its implication in vaccine development.</article-title>             <source>Vaccine</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>1212</fpage>             <lpage>1215</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Dennehy1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dennehy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bourn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Evaluation of recombinant BCG expressing rotavirus VP6 as an anti-rotavirus vaccine.</article-title>             <source>Vaccine</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>3646</fpage>             <lpage>3657</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Dennehy2"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dennehy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Factors influencing the immune response to foreign antigen expressed in recombinant BCG vaccines.</article-title>             <source>Vaccine</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>1209</fpage>             <lpage>1224</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Bastos1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bastos</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dellagostin</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barletta</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Doster</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Construction and immunogenicity of recombinant <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> BCG expressing GP5 and M protein of porcine reproductive respiratory syndrome virus.</article-title>             <source>Vaccine</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>21</fpage>             <lpage>29</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-daCruz1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>da Cruz</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Conceicao</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Expression of the B-cell and T-cell epitopes of the rabies virus nucleoprotein in <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> BCG and induction of an humoral response in mice.</article-title>             <source>Vaccine</source>             <volume>20</volume>             <fpage>731</fpage>             <lpage>736</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Dellagostin1"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dellagostin</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eales</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Activity of mycobacterial promoters during intracellular and extracellular growth.</article-title>             <source>Microbiology</source>             <volume>141 (Pt 8)</volume>             <fpage>1785</fpage>             <lpage>1792</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Wang1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Immune response induced by recombinant <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> BCG expressing ROP2 gene of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Parasitol Int</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>263</fpage>             <lpage>268</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Szittner1"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Szittner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meighen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Bright stable luminescent yeast using bacterial luciferase as a sensor.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>             <volume>309</volume>             <fpage>66</fpage>             <lpage>70</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Buckley1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rahim</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Luciferin detection after intranasal vector delivery is improved by intranasal rather than intraperitoneal luciferin administration.</article-title>             <source>Hum Gene Ther</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>1050</fpage>             <lpage>1056</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Wurdinger1"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wurdinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Badr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Kleine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weissleder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>A secreted luciferase for <italic>ex vivo</italic> monitoring of <italic>in vivo</italic> processes.</article-title>             <source>Nat Methods</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>171</fpage>             <lpage>173</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Loimaranta1"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loimaranta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tenovuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koivisto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Generation of bioluminescent <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> and its usage in rapid analysis of the efficacy of antimicrobial compounds.</article-title>             <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>1906</fpage>             <lpage>1910</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Francis1"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bellinger-Kawahara</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Visualizing pneumococcal infections in the lungs of live mice using bioluminescent <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> transformed with a novel gram-positive lux transposon.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>69</volume>             <fpage>3350</fpage>             <lpage>3358</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Koga1"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Bacterial luciferase activity and the intracellular redox pool in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Genet Genomics</source>             <volume>274</volume>             <fpage>180</fpage>             <lpage>188</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Galluzzi1"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Galluzzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Intracellular redox equilibrium and growth phase affect the performance of luciferase-based biosensors.</article-title>             <source>J Biotechnol</source>             <volume>127</volume>             <fpage>188</fpage>             <lpage>198</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Morin1"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaper</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Use of stabilized luciferase-expressing plasmids to examine <italic>in vivo</italic>-induced promoters in the <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> vaccine strain CVD 103-HgR.</article-title>             <source>FEMS Immunology &amp; Medical Microbiology</source>             <volume>57</volume>             <fpage>69</fpage>             <lpage>79</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Snapper1"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Snapper</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kieser</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>WR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
</person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Isolation and characterization of efficient plasmid transformation mutants of <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>1911</fpage>             <lpage>1919</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Parish1"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Parish</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Electroporation of mycobacteria.</article-title>             <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>             <volume>101</volume>             <fpage>129</fpage>             <lpage>144</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-BivasBenita1"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bivas-Benita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zwier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Junginger</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borchard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Non-invasive pulmonary aerosol delivery in mice by the endotracheal route.</article-title>             <source>European Journal of Pharmaceutics and Biopharmaceutics</source>             <volume>61</volume>             <fpage>214</fpage>             <lpage>218</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Garbe1"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garbe</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barathi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barnini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abou-Zeid</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>Transformation of mycobacterial species using hygromycin resistance as selectable marker.</article-title>             <source>Microbiology</source>             <volume>140 (Pt 1)</volume>             <fpage>133</fpage>             <lpage>138</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0010777-Guo1"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>XV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Monteleone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Klotzsche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kamionka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hillen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Silencing <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> by using tetracycline repressors.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>189</volume>             <fpage>4614</fpage>             <lpage>4623</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</article>