<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-05879</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Influenza</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular structures and organelles</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell membranes</subject><subj-group><subject>Membrane proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Transmembrane proteins</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Virology</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral transmission and infection</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral attachment</subject><subject>Viral load</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Viral enzymes</subject><subject>Viral replication</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Functional Balance between the Hemagglutinin and Neuraminidase of Influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 HA D222 Variants</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">HA-NA Balance of D222 H1N1pdm Variants</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casalegno</surname><given-names>Jean-Sébastien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¶</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraris</surname><given-names>Olivier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¶</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Escuret</surname><given-names>Vanessa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouscambert</surname><given-names>Maude</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergeron</surname><given-names>Corinne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linès</surname><given-names>Laetitia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>Thierry</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valette</surname><given-names>Martine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frobert</surname><given-names>Emilie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pillet</surname><given-names>Sylvie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pozzetto</surname><given-names>Bruno</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lina</surname><given-names>Bruno</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ottmann</surname><given-names>Michèle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Université de Lyon, Université Lyon 1, Faculté de Médecine Lyon Est, Laboratoire de Virologie et Pathologie Humaine, EA 4610, Lyon, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Laboratory of Virology, National Influenza Centre (South of France), Hospices Civils de Lyon, Bât A3, Bron, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>IRBA, Equipe Recherche Lyon, Lyon, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Université de Lyon, Université Lyon 1, Université Lyon 2, INSA de Lyon, École Centrale de Lyon, LIRIS UMR 5205 CNRS, Lyon, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Laboratoire de Bactériologie-virologie-hygiène, Hôpital Nord, CHU de Saint-Étienne, Saint-Étienne, France</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yue</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, CDC, China, China</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">jean-sebastien.casalegno@chu-lyon.fr</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JSC OF BL MO. Performed the experiments: JSC OF MB CB LL MO. Analyzed the data: JSC OF BL MO. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: VE MB MV EF SP BP. Wrote the paper: JSC OF BL MO. Designed the interactive web application Tomuss for data collection: TE.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn1" fn-type="other"><p>¶ J-SC and EF are first co-authors on this work.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e104009</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Casalegno et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>D222G/N substitutions in A(H1N1)pdm09 hemagglutinin may be associated with increased binding of viruses causing low respiratory tract infections and human pathogenesis. We assessed the impact of such substitutions on the balance between hemagglutinin binding and neuraminidase cleavage, viral growth and <italic>in vivo</italic> virulence.Seven viruses with differing polymorphisms at codon 222 (2 with D, 3 G, 1 N and 1 E) were isolated from patients and characterized with regards hemagglutinin binding affinity (Kd) to α-2,6 sialic acid (SAα-2,6) and SAα-2,3 and neuraminidase enzymatic properties (Km, Ki and Vmax). The hemagglutination assay was used to quantitatively assess the balance between hemagglutinin binding and neuraminidase cleavage. Viral growth properties were compared <italic>in vitro</italic> in MDCK-SIAT1 cells and <italic>in vivo</italic> in BALB/c mice. Compared with D222 variants, the binding affinity of G222 variants was greater for SAα-2,3 and lower for SAα-2,6, whereas that of both E222 and N222 variants was greater for both SAα-2,3 and SAα-2,6. Mean neuraminidase activity of D222 variants (16.0 nmol/h/10<sup>6</sup>) was higher than that of G222 (1.7 nmol/h/10<sup>6</sup> viruses) and E/N222 variants (4.4 nmol/h/10<sup>6</sup> viruses). The hemagglutination assay demonstrated a deviation from functional balance by E222 and N222 variants that displayed strong hemagglutinin binding but weak neuraminidase activity. This deviation impaired viral growth in MDCK-SIAT1 cells but not infectivity in mice. All strains but one exhibited low infectious dose in mice (MID50) and replicated to high titers in the lung; this D222 strain exhibited a ten-fold higher MID50 and replicated to low titers. Hemagglutinin-neuraminidase balance status had a greater impact on viral replication than hemagglutinin affinity strength, at least <italic>in vitro</italic>, thus emphasizing the importance of an optimal balance for influenza virus fitness. The mouse model is effective in assessing binding to SAα-2,3 but cannot differentiate SAα-2,3- from SAα-2,6- preference, nor estimate the hemagglutinin-neuraminidase balance in A(H1N1)pdm09 strains.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Institut de Microbiologie et Madalies Infectieuses and the National Influenza Center. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 virus (H1N1pdm) emerged in March 2009 and caused the first influenza pandemic of the new millennium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Itoh1">[1]</xref>. Despite appearing milder than expected, the severe cases and deaths that were reported worldwide far exceeded a classical seasonal flu. Worldwide, 18,500 deaths were reported but this figure was only based on laboratory-confirmed H1N1pdm cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Dawood1">[2]</xref>. One of the main features was the unusual occurrence of viral pneumonia amongst young and previously healthy individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Rykkvin1">[3]</xref>. Preliminary epidemiological studies from Norway reported a higher frequency of the D222G mutation in hemagglutinin (HA, H1 numbering) of influenza viruses cultured from severe cases compared with mild cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Rykkvin1">[3]</xref>. This epidemiological association has since been confirmed in larger sample sizes in other countries using sequences obtained directly from respiratory samples <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Rykkvin1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Ledesma1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Houng1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Piralla1">[6]</xref>. The D222G mutation in HA has only been detected sporadically and did not form a distinct phylogenetic cluster associated with a sustained chain of transmission <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Rykkvin1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Piralla1">[6]</xref>. Further analyses have revealed that polymorphisms D, G, N, and E can be detected at position 222 in the HA protein of H1N1pdm viruses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Wang1">[7]</xref> but their impact on human pathogenicity remains to be determined. In mouse models, conflicting results have been reported, with some suggesting that D222G H1N1pdm viruses acquire an enhanced pathogenicity while others fail to display evidence of such an effect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Chutinimitkul1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Abed1">[9]</xref>.</p>
<p>The 222 HA residue is located near the receptor-binding site of the viral HA. Previous studies have indicated that the D222G substitution influenced the receptor binding specificity of the 1918 pandemic influenza A(H1N1) virus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Stevens1">[10]</xref>. In human strains, it is D222 in HA that mostly favors binding to SAα-2,6; a receptor found in cells of the upper respiratory tract in humans. Binding to SAα-2,6 receptor is correlated with aerosol transmission. Whereas, in viruses emerging from the avian reservoir, it is G222 in HA that mostly favors binding to SAα-2,3. This receptor is found in avian cells but also in lower respiratory tract cells in humans (pneumocytes type II). Binding to SAα-2,3 receptor is correlated with viral pneumonia and pathogeny.</p>
<p>HA receptor binding properties are functionally dependent on the enzymatic properties of neuraminidase (NA). Indeed NA, like HA, engages glycan receptors on host cells, and their respective functional match is critical for viral fitness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Richard1">[11]</xref>. HA plays a role in viral entry into the target cell by recognizing the sialic acid receptor. The NA destroys the receptors by removing sialic acids. An optimal balance between these two functions and notably between HA binding affinity and NA sialidase activity is important for viral replication, as shown in culture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Richard1">[11]</xref> and <italic>in vivo</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Gen1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>In this study we assessed the properties of both HA and NA in relation to the <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> replication profiles of clinical H1N1pdm strains harboring a polymorphism at position 222. The purpose of our work was to assess if amino acid changes at position 222 only impacts the binding properties of the HA receptor or both the binding properties of HA and the HA-NA functional balance, and if this results in increased viral growth and virulence <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Ethics statement for influenza strains</title>
<p>The influenza A(H1N1) viruses described in this study were collected from community and hospital settings. The samples were sent to the National Influenza Centre of the South as part of the national French influenza surveillance system. Patients provided written informed consent.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Ethics statement for animal experiments</title>
<p>Animal care and experimental procedures were conducted according to French (décret 2001-131) and European (86/609/EEC directive) legislations. Protocols were approved by the Committee on Animal Experiments from the Université Lyon1 (Permit Number BH 2008–13). Animal welfare was checked daily and animal handling was performed after anesthesia with 5% isoflurane. Experiments were performed on six week-old female Balb/cByJ mice from Charles Rivers Laboratories.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Sample collection and clinical data</title>
<p>H1N1pdm strains were isolated from nasopharyngeal swab samples obtained from seven patients admitted to the hospital between December 2009 and December 2011 and sent to National Influenza Centre of the South of France as part of the national influenza surveillance scheme. Seven influenza H1N1pdm viruses were selected based on their displaying polymorphisms of the HA protein at position 222 and having been isolated from patients presenting a broad range of clinical features (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t001">Table 1</xref>). Amongst the seven isolates, two displayed HA D222 (Lyon09D, Ste10D), three G222 (Reu10G, Ste09G, Lim10G), one N222 (Lyon10N) and one E222 (Lyon11E). As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t001">Table 1</xref>, two patients with no comorbidities died from severe influenza, two patients recovered from severe influenza and three had mild symptoms. Isolates were obtained by culture of throat or nasal swabs on MDCK cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Lina1">[13]</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0104009-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Background information on the 2009 pandemic A H1N1 viruses.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104009-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HA 222 AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collection date</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient clinical symptom and outcome</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/Lyon/969/2009</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon09D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009/06/18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/StEtienne/1139/2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste10D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010/12/20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dead</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/StEtienne/1691/2009</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste09G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009/09/14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dead</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/Limoges/1159/2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lim10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010/12/22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/Reunion/803/2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reu10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010/09/16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/Lyon/52.016/2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010/12/26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Febrile Purpura, Convulsions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/Lyon/01.012/2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon11E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011/01/01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ressuscitation</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Virus, cells and in vitro replication kinetics</title>
<p>MDCK (ATCC, CCL34) cells were maintained in Ultra-MDCK serum free medium (Lonza) supplemented with 2 mM L-glutamine, 200 IU/ml penicillin (Lonza) and 200 IU/ml streptomycin (Lonza) at 37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Influenza viruses were propagated in MDCK cells at 34°C in EMEM (Lonza) supplemented with 1 µg/ml trypsin (Sigma-Aldrich). MDCK-SIAT1 cells, which express higher levels of SAα-2,6 than parent MDCK cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Matrosovich1">[14]</xref>, were maintained in DMEM (Lonza) supplemented with 2 mM L-glutamine, penicillin (200 IU/ml) and streptomycin (200 IU/ml, Lonza), 10% of heat inactivated fetal calf serum and 1 mg/ml G418 at 37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. MDCK-SIAT1 cells were infected at 34°C with viruses at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 0.001 TCID50/cell. To determine the virus yield, supernatants were harvested at fixed intervals post-infection and virus titers were assessed by endpoint titration in MDCK cells.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>DNA sequencing and analysis</title>
<p>Viral RNAs were extracted from the supernatant of infected MDCK cells using the QIAmp viral RNA mini kit (Qiagen) and reverse transcription was performed using Avian Myeloblastosis Virus Reverse Transcriptase (AMV RT, Promega). The cDNA products were amplified by high fidelity PCR (Phusion HotStart High-Fidelity DNA polymerase, Finnzymes) using primers specific for segments of the H1N1pdm virus (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0104009.s002">Table S2</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-WHO1">[15]</xref>. The PCR products were purified using the MinElute purification kit (Qiagen) and sequenced (GATC). All viral sequences were analyzed and aligned using the ClustalW BioEdit software (version 7.1.83). Sequences are available on GenBank (Accession numbers <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0104009.s003">Table S3</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Antigenic characterization</title>
<p>Hyperimmune rabbit antisera and post-infection ferret sera were prepared as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Kendal1">[16]</xref>. Briefly, hemagglutination inhibition (HI) tests were performed as follows: rabbit sera to the reference strain A/Brisbane/59/2007 H1N1 and ferret sera to the influenza reference strains (A/NewJersey/8/1976 H1N1, A/Auckland/3/2009 H1N1, A/California/7/2009 H1N1pdm and A/Lyon/969/2009 H1N1pdm) were treated with receptor destroying enzyme (RDE) to remove non-specific inhibitors. Reference strains and isolates were standardized to four hemagglutination units and incubated with serial dilutions of sera. The HI titer (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0104009.s001">Table S1</xref>) was defined as the highest dilution of serum that still inhibited the agglutination of guinea pig erythrocytes (Charles Rivers Laboratories®).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Hemagglutination assays</title>
<p>The hemagglutination assay (HA) was used to provide a quantitative assessment of the balance between HA binding and NA cleavage. HA titers were performed at two temperatures: 4°C and then 37°C. Viral supernatants (50 µl of a two-fold dilution in PBS) were incubated with 50 µl of 0.8% guinea pig erythrocytes in a 96 well plates for 75 minutes at 4°C. Viral elution was defined as the decrease in HA titer observed after incubation at 37°C for 2 additional hours. The HA assay was expressed as the mean of three experiments</p>
</sec><sec id="s2h">
<title>Kinetic analysis and end-point neuraminidase activities</title>
<p>The fluorometric NA activity assay and the half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC50) determination for oseltamivir (kindly provided by Hoffmann-La Roche) and zanamivir (kindly provided by GSK) were performed twice for each isolate as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Ferraris1">[17]</xref>. The Michaelis-Menten constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>) was measured from viral supernatants using the MUNANA substrate (Sigma-Aldrich) as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Casalegno1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-RameixWelti1">[19]</xref>. The 4-methylumbelliferone fluorescence was measured using the FLUOstar OPTIMA fluorometer (BMG LABTECH) at 37°C. The initial velocities (Vi) were calculated for each substrate concentration and integrated in a non-linear Michaelis-Menten equation by the MARS program (BMG) for <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> and V<sub>max</sub> determination. V<sub>max</sub> reflects the activity of the enzyme, but this constant is also dependent on the virus quantity. NA activity was normalized by a quantitative assessment of the virus titer using endpoint titration in MDCK cells and expressed as V<sub>max</sub> (nmol/h) per 10<sup>6</sup> viruses. The NA activity was expressed as the mean of three experiments. The <italic>K</italic><sub>i</sub> (affinity of NA for an inhibitor) was measured across a concentration range from 0.01 nM to 10 nM. The substrate was used at 20 µM. The Vi was calculated for each inhibitor concentration and integrated in a non-linear competitive inhibition equation using the GraphPad software (Prism) for the <italic>K</italic><sub>i</sub> calculation. Endpoint NA activity was measured by MU-NANA assay using a standardized HA titer of viruses at 37°C for 1 hr.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2i">
<title>Affinity and specificity for the sialic acid receptors</title>
<p>The HA affinity assays were performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Richard1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Ferraris2">[20]</xref>. Briefly, viral supernatants were coated onto 96-well plates overnight at room temperature. Biotynilated sialylglycopolymers Neu5Acα2-3Galβ1-4Glc-PAA-Biotin (3′SL) and Neu5Acα2-6Galβ1-4GlcNAc-PAA-Biotin (6′SLN) (Lectinity) were serially diluted in 10 nM of zanamivir and incubated for 2 h at 4°C. After washing, peroxidase-labeled anti-biotin antibodies (Euromedex) were added. TMB (KPL) was used as a substrate and absorbance was recorded at 450 nm (Microplate reader UMV340 Asys, Bioserv). The dissociation constant (Kd) was calculated with a non-linear one site specific binding equation using the GraphPad software.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2j">
<title>Mice challenge</title>
<p>Anesthetized mice were inoculated intra-nasally with virus (n = 3 per group; 20 µl of 10<sup>6</sup>, 10<sup>5</sup>, 10<sup>4</sup>, 10<sup>3</sup> or 10<sup>2</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub>). For determination of the mouse infectious dose (MID<sub>50</sub>), mice were euthanized at 3 days post infection (d.p.i.). Lungs were collected and stored at −70°C. The frozen tissues were thawed, homogenized in 0.5 ml of PBS, disrupted in a Tissue Lyser (Qiagen) and then clarified by centrifugation (2000 <italic>g</italic>) at 4°C. Supernatants were titrated by end point dilution using the MDCK cells and confirmed using the hemagglutination assays.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2k">
<title>Data collection</title>
<p>All data were saved using Tomuss, an interactive web application which allows multiple concurrent users to edit data tables.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Whole-genome analysis of influenza sequences from clinical isolates</title>
<p>We performed sequencing using early passages (&lt;3) of viral isolates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t002">Table 2</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t004">4</xref>), and classified the viruses into genetic groups according to the ECDC technical document of August/September 2011 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-ECDC1">[21]</xref>. Viruses isolated in 2009 (Ste09G and Lyon09D) were phylogenetically related to genetic group 1 that included the reference strain A/California/07/2009. Those isolated in 2010, (Ste10D, Lim10G, Lyon10N) were phylogenetically related to the genetic group 3, characterized by the mutations A134T and S183P in HA. Lyon11E and Reu10G were phylogenetically related to genetic group 6, characterized by the mutations D97N and S185T in HA. The differences between the coding sequences and among each group ranged from 11 to 29 amino acids, respectively.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0104009-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Amino acid divergence of the HA and NA of H1N1pdm viruses.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104009-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein</td>
<td colspan="12" align="left" rowspan="1">HA</td>
<td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA Positions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">441</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">451</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">394</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antigenic sites<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon09D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>D</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste10D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>D</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste09G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>G</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lim10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>G</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reu10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>G</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon11E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>E</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>Residues forming the receptor binding pocket are in bold.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>b</label><p>Amino acids in antigenic sites, Sb, Ca1 and Ca2.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0104009-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Amino acid divergence of the PB2, PB1 and PA of H1N1pdm viruses.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104009-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein</td>
<td colspan="10" align="left" rowspan="1">PB2</td>
<td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">PB1</td>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">PA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA Positions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">344</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">511</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">526</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">574</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">588</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">353</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">566</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">645</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">648</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">652</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">479</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">581</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon09D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste10D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste09G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lim10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reu10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nd<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon11E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label>a</label><p>nd: not done.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0104009-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Amino acid divergence of the NP, M1, NS1, NS2 and PA-X of H1N1pdm viruses.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104009-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein</td>
<td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">NP</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">NS1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS2</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">PA-X</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA Positions</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">373</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">433</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon09D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste10D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste09G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lim10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reu10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon11E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>All seven isolates harbored P83S and I321V substitutions in the HA. The HA sequences of Lyon09D and Ste09G differed by D222G and L32I, while those of Ste10D, Lim10G and Lyon10N were strictly identical except for the 222 polymorphism.</p>
<p>The NA protein sequences of Lyon09D and Ste09G were identical and apart from M15I, so too were those of Ste10D, Lim10G and Lyon10N. All viruses except for Ste09G harbored the NA substitution V106I. Lyon09D, Reu10G and Ste10D also harbored the NA N248D substitution. We found no mutation associated with resistance for NA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<p>One to eight mutations concerned NP, PB1 and PB2 and none to three substitutions NS1 and NS2. In contrast, the matrix protein (M) had one substitution (V80I or N133I). Overall, none of the substitutions detected has been reported to be associated with increased virulence. We assume that they reflected polymorphism.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Hemagglutinin properties</title>
<p>Using a panel of antisera raised against H1 influenza vaccine reference viruses, we determined the antigenic properties of the seven viruses by HI assays (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0104009.s001">Table S1</xref>). The HA of all seven viruses was antigenically related to that of the H1N1pdm reference strain. Therefore the substitutions observed in the HA proteins did not induce any antigenic drift.</p>
<p>To assess the changes in HA receptor binding induced by the 222 polymorphism, we evaluated the HA binding profiles of the seven isolates in terms of binding affinity (Kd) and binding specificity for SAα-2,6 (Neu5Acα2-6Galβ1-4GlcNAc-PAA-Biotin) and SAα-2,3 (Neu5Acα2-3Galβ1-4Glc-PAA-Biotin) sialylglycopolymers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t005">Table 5</xref>). For all of the viruses, the intensity of binding affinity to SAα-2,6 was higher than that to SAα-2,3 (mean Kd values of 0.15 µM and 1.19 µM, respectively). However, we noted marked differences amongst the the three G222 viruses (<italic>i.e</italic> Reu10G, Lim10G, Ste09G), the two D222 viruses (<italic>i.e</italic> Lyon09D, Ste10D) and the two N and E222 viruses (<italic>i.e</italic> Lyon10N, Lyon11E), with regards binding to SAα-2,3 and SAα-2,6. The G222 viruses bound SAα-2,3 (mean Kd value of 0.79 µM) with higher intensity and SAα-2,6 (mean Kd value 0.29 µM) with lower intensity compared with the two D222 viruses (mean Kd values to SAα-2,3 and SAα-2,6 of 2.57 µM and 0.06 µM, respectively). Finally, N and E222 viruses bound to both SAα-2,3 (mean Kd value of 0.41 µM) and SAα-2,6 (mean Kd value of 0.02 µM) with higher intensity compared with the other five viruses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t005">Table 5</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0104009-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
<title>HA and NA properties of H1N1pdm HA222 variants.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104009-t005-5" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HA 222</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">HA affinity</td>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">NA properties</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3′SL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6′SLN</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Km<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA activity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oseltamivir</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zanamivir</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Kd<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref> (µM)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(µM)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(nmol/h/10<sup>6</sup> viruses)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref> (nM)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref> (nM)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon09D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste10D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mean D222 viruses</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2.57±0.96</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.06±0.01</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>29.3±5.5</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>16.0±6.9</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.57±0.1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.93±0.5</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste09G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lim10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reu10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mean G222 viruses</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.79±0.11</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.29±0.09</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>33.9±3.3</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>1.7±0.1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.47±0.1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>1.0±0.4</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon11E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mean E/N 222 viruses</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.41±0.02</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.02±0.01</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>38.5±4.1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>4.4±0.1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.37±0.1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.62±0.1</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label>a</label><p>Dissociation constant Kd of the viruses for 6′SLN sialylglycopolymer (Neu5Acα2-6Galβ1-4GlcNAc-PAA-Biotin) and 3′SL sialylglycopolymer (Neu5Acα2-3Galβ1-4Glc-PAA-Biotin) were calculated using the non-linear one site specific binding equation using the GraphPad software. The values are the mean of two assays.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>b</label><p>Michaelis Menten constants (Km) were determined with MU-NANA ranging from 10 to 200 µM. Results are given as the mean Km values calculated using values derived from three separate assays.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>c</label><p>Neuraminidase inhibition assays (IC50) were performed on cell supernatants with MU-NANA as a substrate at a final concentration of 50 µM. Values were obtained from duplicate samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Altogether, these results indicate that the HA D222G substitution induced a shift in the binding profile by increasing the affinity for SAα-2,3 and decreasing the affinity for SAα-2,6, while the presence of N or E at position 222 increased the binding affinity for both SAα-2,3 and SAα-2,6 substrates.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Neuraminidase properties</title>
<p>All viruses were sensitive to both zanamivir and oseltamivir carboxylate with similar low IC<sub>50</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t005">Table 5</xref>) and inhibition constants (<italic>K</italic><sub>i</sub>) (data not shown). This is consistent with our sequence analysis showing a lack of the amino acid changes known to confer resistance in the NA sequence of the seven isolates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Ferraris3">[22]</xref>.</p>
<p>Kinetic analyses of the sialidase activity of NA were performed using the MUNANA fluorogenic substrate, a non-specific link substrate of sialidase. NA efficiency was determined using the Michaelis-Menten constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>), which reflects the affinity for the substrate, and the V<sub>max</sub>, which reflects the activity of the enzyme (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t005">Table 5</xref>). The <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> value for the MUNANA substrate of Ste10D (23.8 µM) was reduced compared with those measured for the other viruses (mean <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> 35.5 µM). Two viruses showed a high <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> value above 40 µM: Ste09D (40.4 µM) and Lyon11E (42.6 µM). The mean NA activity of the D222 HA viruses (16.0 nmol/h/106 viruses) was higher than the mean obtained for G222 HA viruses (1.7 nmol/h/106 viruses) and E/N222 viruses (4.4 nmol/h/106 viruses). Despite differing from the Lyon09D and Ste09G NA only by the M15I substitution, Ste10D NA activity was two to ten-fold higher (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t005">Table 5</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>HA-NA balance</title>
<p>We then used guinea pig red blood cells to provide a quantitative assessment of the binding and release of the seven viruses. The HA titer assay was first performed at 4°C in order to inhibit NA activity and then at 37°C to activate NA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0104009-g001">Figure 1</xref>). HA titers were reduced by four to five fold for the Lyon09D, Ste10D and Lim10G viruses, by two fold for Ste09G and Reu10G viruses and by one fold for Lyon11E and Lyon10N viruses. These data suggest that the HA-NA balance of Lyon09D, Ste10D and Lim10G differs from that of Lyon11E and Lyon10N.</p>
<fig id="pone-0104009-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Quantitative assessment of HA binding and the associated NA activity of H1N1pdm HA 222 variants.</title>
<p>Initial HA titers were measured using guinea pig red blood cells after 75 min incubation at 4°C and final HA titers were determined after 120 min incubation at 37°C as described in Methods. The end point NA activity was measured on 16 UHA viruses diluted ten-fold and incubated with MU-NANA at 37°C for 1 hr.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We then assessed the relationship between HA and NA activities by plotting the quantitative results from the HA binding affinity (Kd) assay with the NA activity assay (nmol/h/10<sup>6</sup> viruses) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0104009-g002">Figure 2</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Xu1">[23]</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0104009-g002">Figure 2</xref> highlights two major features: firstly, Lim10G, Reu10G and Ste10D viruses presented the same HA-NA balance. Yet while Lim10G and Reu10G viruses displayed a low HA binding intensity to sialic acids and a low NA activity, the Ste10D strain conversely displayed a high HA binding intensity to sialic acids and a high NA activity. Secondly, the Lyon11E and Lyon10N strains deviated from such balance with a high HA binding affinity and a low NA activity.</p>
<fig id="pone-0104009-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Functional HA-NA balance of H1N1pdm HA 222 variants.</title>
<p>The relationship between the activity of HA and NA was assessed by plotting the quantitative results from the HA binding affinity assay with the NA activity.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Growth properties in vitro and in vivo</title>
<p>The isolates displayed considerable differences in terms of viral growth and final titers <italic>in vitro</italic> in MDCK SIAT-1 cells, which express high levels of α-2,6-linked sialic acid receptors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0104009-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Indeed, while Ste10D and Lim10G viruses replicated efficiently (10<sup>5</sup> TCID50/ml at 48 hrs p.i.) in the MDCK SIAT-1 cells, Lyon11E and Lyon10N viruses displayed a more than two log<sub>10</sub> lower efficiency (&lt;10<sup>3</sup> TCID50/ml at 48 hrs p.i.). These findings confirm that, at least <italic>in vitro</italic>, an imbalance between the activities of HA and NA impairs the replicative capacities (i.e. fitness) of the viruses with N or E at position 222 of HA.</p>
<fig id="pone-0104009-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Replication kinetics of H1N1pdm viruses in MDCK-SIAT cells at a MOI of 0.001.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The mouse model has proven to be a useful tool to analyze influenza viruses associated with human infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Maines1">[24]</xref>. To evaluate the effect of both receptor specificity and HA-NA balance on the replicative ability of the viruses studied <italic>in vivo</italic>, the MID50 and virulence were determined in mice (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0104009-t006">Table 6</xref>). All H1N1pdm viruses but one exhibited an MID50 between 0.5×10<sup>3</sup> and 1.6×10<sup>3</sup> and replicated to high titers (&gt;10<sup>6.9</sup> TCID50/g lung) in the lungs of infected animals, indicating a high degree of infectivity in this model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Ferraris2">[20]</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Belser1">[25]</xref>. The Ste10D strain had a ten-fold higher MID50 (15×10<sup>3</sup> MID50) compared with the Lyon09D or Lim10G strains which was corroborated by low titers (10<sup>5.5</sup> TCID50/g lung) in the lungs of infected animals indicating a low infectivity of this strain in BALB/C mice. Taken together, these results indicate that N or E at position 222 of HA alters the replication of influenza in MDCK SIAT1 cells but not in mice. Moreover, the fitness of the Ste10D strain was altered in mice but not in MDCK SIAT1 cells.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0104009-t006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption>
<title>Infectivity and virulence of H1N1pdm HA 222 variants in mice.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104009-t006-6" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.t006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Virus</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Mice Infection</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>3</sup> MID50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Log TCID50/g lung ± SD<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">b</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon09D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3±0.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste10D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5±0.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ste09G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9±0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lim10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5±0.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reu10G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4±0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon10N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3±0.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyon11E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9±0.2</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>Three mice were intranasally infected with 10<sup>5</sup> TCID50 and were euthanized at 3 d.p.i. The results are given as the mean value of three infected mice.</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label>a</label><p>Mouse infectious dose 50% (MID50) were expressed as the TCID50/20 µl required for one MID50. Group of three mice were infected with 10<sup>6</sup>,10<sup>5</sup>, 10<sup>4</sup>, 10<sup>3</sup> or 10<sup>2</sup> TCID50 and viruses were titrated in the lungs.</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label>b</label><p>Viral titers in the lungs of inoculated mice (n = 3) with 10<sup>5</sup> TCID50 were determined at 3 d.p.i. SD: Standard Deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our work was designed to assess the impact of amino acid substitutions at HA 222 on HA receptor binding properties, on the HA-NA functional balance and on viral growth and virulence. We selected seven clinical isolates that reflected the HA 222 polymorphism. Firstly, we analyzed SAα-2,6 and SAα-2,3 HA receptor binding properties. Our results confirmed that HA G222 resulted in a higher binding intensity to SAα-2,3 and a lower binding intensity to SAα-2,6, as previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Chutinimitkul1">[8]</xref>. Moreover, we observed that HA N222 and E222 displayed an increased binding intensity for both SAα-2,3 and SAα-2,6. Secondly, we analyzed the enzymatic properties of NA and assessed the functional HA-NA balance. The mean NA activity of D222 HA viruses was higher than that of either the G222 HA viruses or E/N222 viruses. Accordingly, Lyon11E and Lyon10N viruses displayed a strong HA binding unbalanced by a weak NA activity. Therefore the HA-NA balance of Lyon11E and Lyon10N deviated from that of Lim10G, Reu10G, and Ste10D. We further evaluated potential differences in the HA-NA balance among viruses using the hemagglutination assay. In agreement with previous data, Lyon11E and Lyon10N viruses failed to elute red blood cells after 2 hrs whereas HA D222 and one of the HA G222 (Lim10G) viruses eluted efficiently <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Xu1">[23]</xref>. Lyon11E and Lyon10N did not replicate efficiently <italic>in vitro</italic> in MDCK SIAT-1 cells despite a higher binding intensity to SAα-2,6.</p>
<p>These findings confirm that, at least <italic>in vitro</italic>, an imbalance between the activities of HA and NA significantly impairs the replicative capacities (<italic>i.e.</italic> fitness) of the viruses. The HA D222G/E/N substitution increases the intensity of binding for SAα-2,6 and alters the HA-NA balance which may decrease viral fitness in a SAα-2,6 environment. This may explain why D222G and also D222E/N viruses are not able to be transmitted efficiently and are isolated only sporadically.</p>
<p>We observed some discrepancies between the HA binding affinity, NA activity and hemagglutination assays. Indeed, while Reu10G presented a similar functional balance to Lim10G, it's HA titer was reduced by two-fold compared to five-fold for Lim10G. This may be explained by the difference in sialic acid used in the HA binding affinity, NA activity and hemagglutination assays.</p>
<p>The use of human influenza isolates is one limitation of this study. Viruses not only exhibit a polymorphism on the segments encoding the surface glycoproteins, but also in the internal segments. While full genome sequencing did allow us to draw some conclusions with regards the lack of mutations known to confer specific properties found in the different segments of these isolates, we cannot exclude that some slight genetic differences may contribute towards a change in fitness <italic>in vivo</italic>. The limited number of isolated strains did not allow us to conclude on the potential impact of the D222G or HA-NA balance in human pathogenicity.</p>
<p>While acquisition of a lethal phenotype has been shown in viruses affecting mice following the acquisition of key mutations, one of which is D222G <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Chutinimitkul1">[8]</xref>, we found no such differences in human influenza viruses and D222G did not appear as a main virulence factor in mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Ferraris2">[20]</xref>. The use of the mouse model revealed a mouse infectious dose (MID50) ranging from 0.5×10<sup>3</sup> to 1.6×10<sup>3</sup> but no significant differences in the replication rate in the lungs for all viruses, except for the Ste10D virus. In accordance with other groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Maines1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Belser1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Lakdawala1">[26]</xref>, none of the viruses we studied with our mouse model showed an increase in virulence. The low fitness of the Ste10D virus may be due to the predominance of SAα-2,3 in mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Ibricevic1">[27]</xref> and a low HA binding affinity for the SAα-2,3 substrate. On the other hand, although Lyon11E and Lyon10N viruses replicated at low levels in the SAα-2,6 system (i.e. MDCK SIAT-1 cells), they had a low MID50 and replicated to high titers in the lungs of the mice. These results indicate that mice are an effective <italic>in vivo</italic> model to assess SAα-2,3 HA binding affinity, but not for assessing the receptor preference or the HA-NA balance as previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Lakdawala1">[26]</xref>. Other properties that affect the virulence of influenza viruses in mice, such as the complexity of the sialic acid species in the mouse respiratory tract, could also explain these discrepancies.</p>
<p>The NA activity of the Ste10D virus was higher compared with the other viruses studied, yet differed from the Lyon09D and Ste09G NA by only the M15I substitution. This position is located in the transmembrane domain and is not likely to affect the structure of the NA pocket. Such a polymorphism has already been observed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Ernst1">[28]</xref> but not analyzed functionally. This mutation may modify monomers in terms of their anchorage or interactions, with repercussions on NA expression on the virus surface.</p>
<p>This is the first report, to our knowledge, that has studied the functional balance of HA-NA in human strains regarding the impact of the D222G/N/E substitution on SAα-2,6 HA binding. These results confirm the importance of an optimal balance between HA affinity and NA activity for human influenza viruses with regards viral fitness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0104009-Wagner1">[29]</xref>. It appears therefore crucial to take into account both HA receptor binding and NA receptor cleavage in terms of the HA-NA balance in the context of a mutation affecting HA binding properties, by using enzymatic and biological tools.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0104009.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Hemagglutinin antigenic properties determined by the hemagglutination inhibition assay.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0104009.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Primers for the whole genome sequencing of H1N1pdm viruses.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0104009.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0104009.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>GenBank accession numbers for the seven H1N1pdm09 isolates.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank Mikhail Matrosovitch for providing the MDCK-SIAT1 cells. We are grateful to Nathalie Rivat, Sylvie Fiorini, Murielle Sabatier and Mendy Barthélemy-Bresson for their excellent technical support.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Itoh1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakoda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>In vitro and in vivo characterization of new swine-origin H1N1 influenza viruses</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>460</volume>: <fpage>1021</fpage>–<lpage>1025</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Dawood1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iuliano</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Estimated global mortality associated with the first 12 months of 2009 pandemic influenza A H1N1 virus circulation: a modelling study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>695</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Rykkvin1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rykkvin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kilander</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dudman</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hungnes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Within-patient emergence of the influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 HA1 222G variant and clear association with severe disease, Norway</article-title>. <source>Euro Surveill</source> <volume>18</volume>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Ledesma1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledesma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pozo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pineiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Substitutions in position 222 of haemagglutinin of pandemic influenza A (H1N1) 2009 viruses in Spain</article-title>. <source>J Clin Virol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Houng1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houng</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuschner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Emergent 2009 influenza A(H1N1) viruses containing HA D222N mutation associated with severe clinical outcomes in the Americas</article-title>. <source>J Clin Virol</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Piralla1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piralla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pariani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rovida</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campanini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muzzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Segregation of virulent influenza A(H1N1) variants in the lower respiratory tract of critically ill patients during the 2010–2011 seasonal epidemic</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e28332</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Wang1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soedjono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matlho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evidence of the circulation of pandemic influenza (H1N1) 2009 with D222D/G/N/S hemagglutinin polymorphisms during the first wave of the 2009 influenza pandemic</article-title>. <source>J Clin Virol</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Chutinimitkul1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chutinimitkul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herfst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Virulence-associated substitution D222G in the hemagglutinin of 2009 pandemic influenza A(H1N1) virus affects receptor binding</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>11802</fpage>–<lpage>11813</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Abed1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pizzorno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamelin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joubert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The 2009 Pandemic H1N1 D222G Hemagglutinin Mutation Alters Receptor Specificity and Increases Virulence in Mice but Not in Ferrets</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source> <volume>204</volume>: <fpage>1008</fpage>–<lpage>1016</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Stevens1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blixt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taubenberger</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palese</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Glycan microarray analysis of the hemagglutinins from modern and pandemic influenza viruses reveals different receptor specificities</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>355</volume>: <fpage>1143</fpage>–<lpage>1155</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Richard1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Care</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Traversier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barthelemy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Rescue of a H3N2 influenza virus containing a deficient neuraminidase protein by a hemagglutinin with a low receptor-binding affinity</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e33880</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Gen1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Attenuation of an influenza A virus due to alteration of its hemagglutinin-neuraminidase functional balance in mice</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol</source> <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>1003</fpage>–<lpage>1011</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Lina1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luciani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stagnara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Surveillance of community-acquired viral infections due to respiratory viruses in Rhone-Alpes (France) during winter 1994 to 1995</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>3007</fpage>–<lpage>3011</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Matrosovich1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matrosovich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matrosovich</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klenk</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of the alpha-2,6-sialyltransferase in MDCK cells increases influenza virus sensitivity to neuraminidase inhibitors</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>8418</fpage>–<lpage>8425</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-WHO1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">WHO (2009) Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/csr/resources/publications/swineflu/WHO_Diagnostic_RecommendationsH1N1_20090521.pdf" xlink:type="simple">www.who.int/csr/resources/publications/swineflu/WHO_Diagnostic_RecommendationsH1N1_20090521.pdf</ext-link> Accessed: 2014 Feb 3.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Kendal1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Kendal AP, Pereira M, Skehel JJ (1982) Concepts and Procedures for Laboratory-based Influenza Surveillance. US Department of Health and Human Services, CDC, Atlanta, GA.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Ferraris1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraris</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Sensitivity of influenza viruses to zanamivir and oseltamivir: a study performed on viruses circulating in France prior to the introduction of neuraminidase inhibitors in clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Antiviral Res</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Casalegno1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casalegno</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouscambert-Duchamp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schuffenecker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabatier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Oseltamivir-resistant influenza A(H1N1) viruses in south of France, 2007/2009</article-title>. <source>Antiviral Res</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-RameixWelti1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rameix-Welti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mardy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aubin</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Natural variation can significantly alter the sensitivity of influenza A (H5N1) viruses to oseltamivir</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>3809</fpage>–<lpage>3815</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Ferraris2"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraris</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Escuret</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouscambert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casalegno</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacquot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>H1N1 influenza A virus neuraminidase modulates infectivity in mice</article-title>. <source>Antiviral Res</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>374</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-ECDC1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">ECDC (2012) Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications/Publications/CNRL-July-2012.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications/Publications/CNRL-July-2012.pdf</ext-link> Accessed: 2014 Feb 3.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Ferraris3"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraris</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mutations of neuraminidase implicated in neuraminidase inhibitors resistance</article-title>. <source>J Clin Virol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Xu1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nycholat</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Functional balance of the hemagglutinin and neuraminidase activities accompanies the emergence of the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>9221</fpage>–<lpage>9232</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Maines1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maines</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belser</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wadford</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Transmission and pathogenesis of swine-origin 2009 A(H1N1) influenza viruses in ferrets and mice</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>325</volume>: <fpage>484</fpage>–<lpage>487</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Belser1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belser</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wadford</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gustin</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maines</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Pathogenesis of pandemic influenza A (H1N1) and triple-reassortant swine influenza A (H1) viruses in mice</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>4194</fpage>–<lpage>4203</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Lakdawala1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakdawala</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamirande</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Receptor specificity does not affect replication or virulence of the 2009 pandemic H1N1 influenza virus in mice and ferrets</article-title>. <source>Virology</source> <volume>446</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Ibricevic1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibricevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pekosz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newby</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Battaile</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Influenza virus receptor specificity and cell tropism in mouse and human airway epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>7469</fpage>–<lpage>7480</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Ernst1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zacherl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hacke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nickel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Differential transport of Influenza A neuraminidase signal anchor peptides to the plasma membrane</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>587</volume>: <fpage>1411</fpage>–<lpage>1417</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0104009-Wagner1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matrosovich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klenk</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Functional balance between haemagglutinin and neuraminidase in influenza virus infections</article-title>. <source>Rev Med Virol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>