<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-21502</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036736</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavioral ecology</subject>
              <subject>Evolutionary ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Zoology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal behavior</subject>
              <subject>Entomology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Communications</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
          <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>How to Join a Wave: Decision-Making Processes in Shimmering Behavior of Giant Honeybees (<italic>Apis dorsata</italic>)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Wave Propagation in Shimmering of Giant Honeybees</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kastberger</surname>
            <given-names>Gerald</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Weihmann</surname>
            <given-names>Frank</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hoetzl</surname>
            <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Weiss</surname>
            <given-names>Sara E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Maurer</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kranner</surname>
            <given-names>Ilse</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Institute of Zoology, University of Graz, Graz, Austria</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Institute for Computer Graphics and Vision, Graz University of Technology, Graz, Austria</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Institute of Botany, University of Innsbruck, Innsbruck, Austria</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Dornhaus</surname>
            <given-names>Anna</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Arizona, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">gerald.kastberger@uni-graz.at</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: GK. Performed the experiments: GK FW TH MM. Analyzed the data: GK FW TH MM. Wrote the paper: GK IK FW SEW.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>8</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e36736</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kastberger et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>Shimmering is a collective defence behaviour in Giant honeybees (<italic>Apis dorsata</italic>) whereby individual bees flip their abdomen upwards, producing Mexican wave-like patterns on the nest surface. <italic>Bucket bridging</italic> has been used to explain the spread of information in a chain of members including three testable concepts: first, <italic>linearity</italic> assumes that individual “agent bees” that participate in the wave will be affected preferentially from the side of wave origin. The <italic>directed-trigger</italic> hypothesis addresses the coincidence of the individual property of trigger direction with the collective property of wave direction. Second, <italic>continuity</italic> describes the transfer of information without being stopped, delayed or re-routed. The <italic>active-neighbours</italic> hypothesis assumes coincidence between the direction of the majority of shimmering-active neighbours and the trigger direction of the agents. Third, the <italic>graduality</italic> hypothesis refers to the interaction between an agent and her active neighbours, assuming a proportional relationship in the strength of abdomen flipping of the agent and her previously active neighbours. Shimmering waves provoked by dummy wasps were recorded with high-resolution video cameras. Individual bees were identified by 3D-image analysis, and their strength of abdominal flipping was assessed by pixel-based luminance changes in sequential frames. For each agent, the directedness of wave propagation was based on wave direction, trigger direction, and the direction of the majority of shimmering-active neighbours. The data supported the <italic>bucket bridging</italic> hypothesis, but only for a small proportion of agents: linearity was confirmed for 2.5%, continuity for 11.3% and graduality for 0.4% of surface bees (but in 2.6% of those agents with high wave-strength levels). The complimentary part of 90% of surface bees did not conform to <italic>bucket bridging</italic>. This fuzziness is discussed in terms of self-organisation and evolutionary adaptedness in Giant honeybee colonies to respond to rapidly changing threats such as predatory wasps scanning in front of the nest.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The paper had been granted by the Austrian Science Fund (FWF Project P 20515-B16)(Soziale Wellen bei Riesenhonigbienen), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fwf.ac.at/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fwf.ac.at/</ext-link>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="16"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><italic>Shimmering</italic> behaviour in Giant honeybees (<italic>Apis dorsata</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Ruttner1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Hepburn1">[2]</xref> involves a display of social waves with antipredatory impact <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Roepke1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger2">[9]</xref>. These waves originate at discrete areas on the surface of the nests, where <italic>generator bees</italic> have been identified <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Schmelzer1">[10]</xref> as leaders in the general responsiveness to external cues. These generator bees raise their abdomen first and affect their nest mates around them to follow them in sequential order. Such behavioural cascades generate self-organized <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Pasteels1">[13]</xref> patterns propagating across the nest surface in a fraction of a second. The visual domain of these spatial time patterns [<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s004">movies S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s005">S2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s006">S3</xref>] aim at repelling external addressees such as predatory wasps <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Procaccini1">[15]</xref> or mammals. It is reasonable to assume that the mechanoceptive domain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref> of shimmering is important for colony-intrinsic communication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>, because the waves affect most of the colony members not only in the surface layer, but in all layers of the bee curtain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>; they are even supposed to influence the bee curtain on the non-shimmering, opposite side of the comb <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger5">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The specific involvement of surface bees in wave propagation is not well understood. However, several features of shimmering can be compared with wave-like processes in general. For instance, colliding wave-fronts which extinguish each other would suggest the presence of refractory processes, which have been extensively studied in excitation physiology (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger5">[17]</xref>). Second, similar to water or sound waves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Phillips1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Holthuijsen1">[19]</xref>, shimmering waves reorient or fade out (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g001">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s004">movies S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s005">S2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s006">S3</xref>) at physical hindrances to the propagation of waves. In Giant honeybee nests, such hindrances can be architectural or functional structures, which are given at rim areas, attachment zones or at the <italic>mouth</italic> zone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Morse1">[20]</xref>). Third, similarity exists with other types of social waves such as the Mexican waves of human spectators in football stadiums, which has led some authors to classify shimmering as a Mexican-wave-like process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Farkas1">[21]</xref>.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0036736-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Experimental Giant honeybee nest.</title>
          <p>Chitwan (Nepal) in January 2009. (A) View of the whole nest; the green line gives the quiescent zone, where the bees are positioned with their heads upwards and the abdomens downwards; outside of this zone are the rim areas (left side and bottom), the attachment zone (top), and the mouth zone (right) marked with the yellow line; the green and yellow rectangles show nest areas which are displayed at a bigger scale in (B, quiescent area) and (C, mouth zone); white circles show the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> (r&lt;40 mm) and the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (r&lt;100 mm) of the selected <italic>focus bee</italic>, which is positioned in the centre of the circles. The outer black circle within the white size marker (bottom left of the nest) is 6 cm in diameter. (B) Area of the quiescent zone; the white dot shows the position of the thorax of the selected <italic>focus bee</italic>, defining the centre of the white open circle (r = 40 mm) of the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> and of the white square which indicates the detection area (60 x 60 px) of the selected bee to assess the <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref>). Note the differences in orientation of the surface bees between quiescent zone (B) and mouth zone (C).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>At first sight, and to the naked eye, shimmering appears to spread mostly in <italic>linear</italic> tracks. If examined more closely, the waves reveal a series of group-level properties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>. An example for the higher complexity in shimmering is the <italic>saltatoric</italic> spreading pattern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger6">[22]</xref>, where information “jumps” from one group of bees to a neighbouring one. Another indication for complex group-level properties is the variability of the directedness of propagation, which regularly shows linear, curved or even spiral patterns <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Born1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger7">[24]</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s004">movies S1</xref>).</p>
      <p>In this study, we investigated the propagation mechanisms of shimmering, paying particular attention to the principle of <italic>bucket bridging</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>. <italic>Bucket bridging</italic> can be regarded as the simplest group-level property in wave propagation, whereby cues are passed on from one individual in a chain to another (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). The term <italic>bucket bridging</italic> originates from a collective human behaviour, where a bucket of water is delivered to the site of fire by a chain of humans who pass the bucket from one individual to another. If one member in the chain quits his duty, the bucket transfer will be delayed, stopped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>), or rerouted to other individuals of the same or of another chain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>). If the propagation of shimmering waves was to conform strictly to the <italic>bucket-bridging</italic> hypothesis, the wave would spread according to the principles here defined as <italic>linearity, continuity</italic> and <italic>graduality.</italic></p>
      <fig id="pone-0036736-g002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Schematic of <italic>bucket bridging</italic> during shimmering and the aspects of <italic>linearity</italic> and <italic>continuity</italic> in propagation.</title>
          <p>(A) <italic>Linear</italic> and <italic>continuous</italic> transmittance: Information is transferred (symbolized by red arrows) from one agent bee to the next member of the chain. (B) <italic>Linear</italic> but <italic>discontinuous</italic> transmittance: one agent bee in the chain fails to act as transmitter but information is by-passed to the next agent in the chain. (C) Schema of a sample wave which spreads from left to right (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = <sub>from</sub>L<sub>to</sub>R) explaining the complex situation of the bee curtain of <italic>A. dorsata</italic> during shimmering, with <italic>non-linearity</italic> and <italic>discontinuity</italic> of transmittance; three types of agent bees are noted: <italic>red</italic>, strong transmittance corresponding to wave strength levels of c<sub>ws</sub>&gt;2; <italic>light red</italic>, weak transmittance corresponding to wave strength levels of 1≥c<sub>ws</sub>≤2; <italic>grey</italic>, no transmittance corresponding to a wave strength level of c<sub>ws</sub> = 0 (these bees were detected as agent bees but not further considered in the evaluation). The arrows signify that information is transmitted from any abdomen-flipping agent bee into all eight neighbourhood sectors (for definition of dir <sub>Nh</sub>, see sketch at the bottom right, see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036736-t001">Table 1</xref> for definitions of angular sectors).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p><italic>Linearity</italic> in <italic>bucket bridging</italic> assumes that information is delivered sequentially from one member of a chain to the next. In the case of shimmering, <italic>linear</italic> propagation would result in the wave front proceeding steadily from one surface bee to the next. An individual bee, here termed <italic>agent bee</italic>, with a disposition to participate in the wave, will be affected by the wave front preferentially from the site of wave origin. The <italic>directed-trigger</italic> hypothesis addresses here the coincidence of the individual property of <italic>trigger direction</italic> with the collective property of the <italic>wave direction</italic>. <italic>Continuity</italic> in shimmering is defined as the transfer of information by groups of surface bees without being stopped, delayed or re-routed. The stimuli that trigger continuous shimmering would come from the direction of maximal activity of neighbouring agents. This shimmering principle will be addressed by the <italic>active-neighbours</italic> hypothesis, investigating the coincidence between the angular sector where the majority of active neighbours are positioned, and the <italic>trigger direction</italic> of the selected individual. <italic>Graduality</italic> is the third principle of <italic>bucket bridging</italic> and also refers to the interaction between a surface bee and her neighbours. The <italic>graduality</italic> hypothesis assumes a proportional relationship in the strength of abdomen flipping of an agent bee and her previously active neighbours.</p>
      <p>However, shimmering depends upon a series of factors that can considerably curtail the above-mentioned principles of <italic>bucket bridging</italic>. Such factors include the architecture and the partitioning of the nest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>), the defence state of the colony <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Schmelzer1">[10]</xref>, and the sensory equipment of the bees. Individual surface bees are believed to be free to decide to join or not to join a shimmering wave <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>. If they do, they flip their abdomen with a variable angle of up to 120°, synchronizing and cascading their behaviours collectively, which, for the external observer, results in a wave-like pattern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger8">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Woyke1">[26]</xref> with a high level of complexity, sophistication and thus, unpredictability. Considering these restricting factors it seems likely that wave propagation in shimmering does not obey the strict laws of <italic>bucket bridging</italic> alone.</p>
      <p>This paper addresses the applicability and restrictions of the <italic>bucket-bridging</italic> hypothesis for wave propagation in shimmering <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref> in Giant honeybees, focusing on the principles of <italic>linearity, continuity</italic> and <italic>graduality</italic>. We precisely determined the position of individual agent bees over time in the three dimensions of space, thereby gaining information regarding the trigger conditions and the neighbourhood of <italic>focus bees</italic>. The behaviours were recorded with high-resolution and high-speed video. Bees at the surface of the bee curtain were re-identified on an individual basis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref> frame by frame by stereo imaging and automated tracking, enabling us to analyse the underlying mechanisms of wave propagation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Ethics Statement</title>
        <p>The office of the rector of the centre for international relations of Tribhuvan University (Kathmandu, Nepal) certified the research expedition entitled “Study on the behaviour of the Giant honeybees: Observations and Recording of behaviours at the nesting site” in Chitwan district of Nepal.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Experimental Site and Recording</title>
        <p>The shimmering behaviour of Giant honeybees (<italic>Apis dorsata</italic>) was studied under field conditions in Chitwan, Nepal, during two expeditions in February 2009 and November 2010. To obtain a detailed view of the movements of individual bees within the entirety of the bee curtain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref> the motions of hundreds of surface bees were measured simultaneously in the three directions of space. This was achieved by an adaptation of the stereoscopic imaging principle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Wheatstone1">[27]</xref> with its fundamental algorithms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>: segmentation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Freixenet1">[28]</xref>, matching <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Scharstein1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Zureiki1">[30]</xref> and reconstruction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Hartley1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Faugeras1">[32]</xref> by tracking and triangulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3A,B</xref>). Two video cameras (type DALSA Falcon 4M60) delivered black-and-white images with a resolution of 2352×1728 pixels (px). From the given working distance of 2 m, and with a calibrated focal length of 53 mm, about two thirds (700 mm in diameter) of the nest were recorded, whereby one px represented ∼ 0.30 mm in metric real-world coordinates. Therefore, the characteristic abdomen width of 6 mm of a bee was imaged by roughly 20 px. The cameras were able to capture 60 frames per sec (fps) and so resolve the abdomen-flipping phase of an individual bee of 200 ms within 12 frames (for further details see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0036736-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Schematic of the evaluation process to analyse properties of the propagation process in shimmering.</title>
            <p>The light-grey flow charts (A–G) address the single-agent analysis from image acquisition, stereoscopic imaging of individuals, wave incident detection, to the synchronization, categorization, and pooling of wave incidents. The black arrows and dashed lines on the right side symbolize that the stereoscopic analysis produced further data for hundreds of agent bees simultaneously. (A) The experimental nest was captured by two frame-locked video cameras positioned at an angle of 30° two meters in front of the nest. A single recording session lasted 15 s and included up to two shimmering waves which spread across the nest surface. Shimmering was elicited by a dummy wasp. (B) In the offline data assessment phase the acquired images were processed as follows: <italic>Segmentation</italic> distinguished single agent bees in the densely packed clusters of bees on the surface of the nest in each of the paired images, <italic>stereo matching</italic> identified corresponding agent bees in both paired images. These two processes enabled <italic>stereo tracking</italic> of the agents in subsequent frames throughout whole film scenes and the <italic>triangulation</italic> of their thoracic positions regarding the three dimensions of space (x,y,z) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>. (C) The stereoscopic analysis delivered identities of agent bees in subsequent image sequences. The arrival of the wave front at an individual agent was recognized by a movement detection algorithm (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g001">Fig.1B</xref>, white square). The grey arrow on the right with the stop bar symbolizes that a minority of identified agents did not participate in shimmering and was not evaluated further. (D) The detection of active participation in the wave allowed synchronization of wave incidents of individual agent bees at different positions of the nest. (E,F) Four categorizations of participating agents were discerned to define single <italic>focus bees</italic>: the wave direction dir<sub>WAV</sub> (F<sub>1</sub>); the wave strength level (c<sub>WS</sub>) as a measure of the response strength, which refers to the maximal <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values of a wave incident (F<sub>2</sub>); the trigger direction dir<sub>TRIG</sub> gives the angle of the triggering neighbour in the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> (F<sub>3</sub>); the oval area with its displacement from the centre shows the direction of the maximum activity of neighbours in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (F<sub>4</sub>); in (F<sub>5</sub>), the paradigm of <italic>direct-sector</italic> and <italic>opposite-sector</italic> analysis was introduced. (G) Pooling of synchronized and categorized 3D data (Δx, Δy, Δz) and wave strength values <sub>rel</sub>XYmov. (H-J) Using the parameters defined in F<sub>1–5</sub>, three criteria of <italic>bucket bridging</italic> were assessed (dark-grey flow charts H,I: <italic>linearity</italic>, <italic>continuity</italic>, <italic>graduality</italic>) and the respective hypotheses (<italic>directed-trigger-</italic>, <italic>active-neighbours-</italic> and <italic>gradual-transfer-</italic>) were tested (J<sub>1–3</sub>). The panels in D, F and I illustrate the results of the processes given in the grey or black boxes (see referenced figures and movies for details).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Identification of Surface Bees</title>
        <p>In a Giant honeybee nest, the colony members are arranged at both sides of the central comb in several layers. A nest has several functional regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) such as the <italic>mouth</italic> zone, the attachment zone, the rim zone and the quiescent zone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Morse1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Butani1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Butler1">[34]</xref>. Shimmering behaviour is displayed primarily by the surface bees in the quiescent zone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger9">[35]</xref>. More than 600 individually identified surface bees per frame were tracked (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3A,B</xref>; the identification of the positional coordinates defines them as “<italic>agent bees</italic>”), summing up to 14549 <italic>wave incidents</italic> which were documented in successive film sessions (defined as a sequence of images tracked continuously in the course of a single experiment). The identification of individual agent bees throughout a single session is challenging because Giant honeybees in a colony are extremely similar in morphology, are densely clustered, and show rapid movements in 3D during their abdominal flipping <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>. In addition, an individual bee that has sensed an incoming wave front due to the 3D movements of her neighbours is free to decide whether or not to join the wave, and if she joins, whether to raise her abdomen strongly or weakly. Weak participation of individuals in shimmering is difficult to detect by automated analysis. Furthermore, it is critical to distinguish active “movements”, i.e. abdominal flipping, from passive “motions” caused by the surrounding bee curtain.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Definition of the Wave Directions</title>
        <p>The architecture of the bee curtain of Giant honeybee nests is determined by three characteristics: first, by the orientation of surface bees which hang, particularly in the <italic>quiescent</italic> areas, with their heads upwards and their abdomens downwards (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>); second, by the particular structure of the nest, which suspends freely from overhead structures to which it is attached; and third, by the polarity between the nest centre of the mouth zone and the quiescent periphery. Four key directions of wave spreading were defined (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1-4; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036736-t001">Table 1</xref>), namely two horizontal directions (<italic>from Right to Left</italic> [<sub>from</sub>R<sub>to</sub>L], <italic>from Left to Right</italic> [<sub>from</sub>L<sub>to</sub>R]) and two vertical directions (from <italic>Bottom to Top</italic> [<sub>from</sub>B<sub>to</sub>T], <italic>from Top to Bottom</italic> [<sub>from</sub>T<sub>to</sub>B]), numbered clockwise, starting with <sub>from</sub>R<sub>to</sub>L. For that, shimmering waves in these key directions were identified visually from recorded movies.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0036736-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Definitions of categories of directions (<italic>dir</italic>) and sectors around a <italic>focus bee</italic>.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0036736-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Directions</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Sectors</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">from whence the activities started</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CATEGORIES dir<sub>Nh,</sub> dir<sub>TRIG</sub></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CATEGORIES dir<sub>WAV</sub></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ANGULAR RANGES α<sub>Nh,</sub> α<sub>tb</sub>, α<sub>TRIG,</sub> α<sub>WAV</sub></td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>from Right</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 [<sub>from</sub>R<sub>to</sub>L]</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0±22.5°</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>from Bottom-right</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45±22.5°</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>from Bottom</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 [<sub>from</sub>B<sub>to</sub>T]</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90±22.5°</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>from Bottom-left</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">135±22.5°</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>from Left</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 [<sub>from</sub>L<sub>to</sub>R]</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">180±22.5°</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>from Left-up</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">225±22.5°</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>from Top</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 [<sub>from</sub>T<sub>to</sub>B]</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">270±22.5°</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>from Right-up</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">315±22.5°</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>α<sub>Nh</sub>±22.5°, the sector of neighbourhood with α<sub>Nh</sub> as its central direction; α<sub>TRIG</sub>−22.5°&lt;α<sub>tb</sub> &lt;α<sub>TRIG</sub>+22.5°, the angular range where the triggering bee is located, synonymous to the trigger angle; α<sub>WAV,</sub> the angle from where the wave is spreading.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Assessment of the Motion Strength at the Individual Level</title>
        <p>For each identified agent bee (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3A,B</xref>) a set of data was available frame by frame <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>. We introduced the parameter <sub>rel</sub>XYmov (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3C,D</xref>) to categorize the motion strength of individual agents throughout the experiment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>. This measure allowed the assessment of the precise time of the arrival of a wave at an agent’s position. A reliable trigger criterion was found by detecting the luminance changes in two sequential frames (f<sub>i-1</sub>, f<sub>i</sub>) in a pixel-wise subtraction creating a difference image <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>. A <italic>region of interest</italic> (ROI; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g004">Fig.4A</xref>) of 60×60 px around an agent bee was defined, with the centre point positioned in the middle of the thorax corresponding to 18×18 mm in real-world coordinates. The size of the ROI was chosen in conformance with the mean side-to-side distances between surface bees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref> covering 80% of the agent bee, including most of the abdomen, and also considering the stretched-wing condition where the two wings on each side are presented separately without overlapping, which is characteristic of surface bees. A larger sensor field would have interfered too much with the motion activities of the neighbours. We recorded 8-bit px values regarding the differences in luminance (Δ lum) between two successive frames assessed by pixel-operated subtraction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref> with the references as <italic>black</italic> [Δ lum = 0] and <italic>white</italic> [Δ lum = 255].</p>
        <fig id="pone-0036736-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The time courses of wave strength of <italic>focus bees</italic> and their triggering neighbours.</title>
            <p>(A) Details about the assessment of the image-based <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref>); yellow square gives the 60×60 px region of interest (ROI) around the selected <italic>focus bee</italic>; the red circle defines the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> (r &lt; 40 mm); the white lines in the background show the eight sectors of neighbourhood (dir<sub>Nh</sub> = 1–8). (B) Time courses of the <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values of <italic>focus bees</italic> at different wave strength levels (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = <sub>from</sub>B<sub>to</sub>T; c<sub>ws</sub> = 1-6; n = 2908 wave incidents). The contours of the green areas show arithmetic means, vertical grey bars show mean errors. Black lines are means of <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values of the triggering neighbours (radius<sub>Nh</sub>&lt;40 m) regarding the paired, <italic>focus bee</italic>-related wave incidents; mean errors are not displayed here. Red vertical bars signify the time points t<sub>0</sub> defined by the rapid onset of shimmering activity (quantified by the ordinate<sub> rel</sub>XYmov values) of the <italic>focus bees</italic>. (C) How long does it take that information of shimmering is transferred from the neighbours in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (radius<sub>Nh</sub>&lt;100 mm) to the <italic>focus bees</italic>? Estimation exemplified for dir<sub>WAV</sub> = <sub>from</sub>R<sub>to</sub>L; abscissa, wave strength level; ordinate, time interval in ms in which information has been transferred, with means (red dots) ± SE (black vertical bars), n = 14 threshold levels (<sub>rel</sub>XYmov = 1.0–2.3 in steps of 0.1) for the neighbourhood activity; ordinate values are calculated by weighted interpolation and cross correlation of the time courses between <italic>focus bees</italic> (<italic>fb</italic>) and their trigger neighbours (<italic>nb</italic>) of the same wave strength level (N<sub>fb</sub> = 2824; N<sub>nb</sub> = 29237).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>These Δ lum values represented motion activities of a selected agent bee regarding the whole body within 16.67 ms. These motions were quantified by the parameter <sub>rel</sub>XYmov and include positional changes in horizontal (<italic>x</italic>-) and vertical (<italic>y</italic>-) directions, but also movements of head, abdomen, and extremities, such as legs, antennae or wings. This value is therefore affected by various behavioural contexts: first, by passive deflections of the whole body in x-, y- and z-directions which originate from the immediate neighbourhood <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>; second, by active movements of the body parts such as observed in flickering <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Weihmann1">[36]</xref> or shimmering <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, and third, by locomotor activities of the whole body such as moving around on the nest surface or penetrating into deeper layers of the nest. For quiescent conditions the Δ lum values typically were on average 3 per px, which summed up to <sub>rel</sub>XYmov = 1.08 * 10<sup>4</sup> for the whole 3600 px of the ROI. Massive shimmering activity reached on average tenfold <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values. Therefore, the <sub>rel</sub>XYmov value was an appropriate parameter to quantitatively describe the level of the individual participation of an agent bee in shimmering waves, i.e. the <italic>wave strength</italic> (<italic>ws</italic>) of a given wave incident <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Determination of the Time Zero of a Singular Wave Incident</title>
        <p>When a wave front reaches an agent bee, weak passive deflections are detectable, but when an agent bee starts raising her abdomen the <italic>ws</italic>-value sharply rise and peak within 40 ms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). This effect was utilized, first, to determine the starting time (t<sub>0</sub>) of an individual shimmering <italic>incident</italic>. The time point zero <italic>t<sub>0</sub></italic> was defined one frame before the time <italic>t<sub>1</sub></italic> at which the sharp rise of <sub>rel</sub>XYmov value was detected (t<sub>0</sub> = t [f<sub>1</sub>–1]). Second, this rapid rise of the <sub>rel</sub>XYmov value was also utilized to synchronize the multitude of shimmering incidents which took place, simultaneously or successively, at the various agents of the whole nest. For that, we defined an additional threshold level of Δ ws<sub>th</sub> = 10 to identify an agent bee which participated in the shimmering wave. An agent must have shown Δ ws-values which exceeded this threshold for at least five successive frames (Δ <sub>rel</sub>XYmov (t<sub>1</sub>,…t<sub>5</sub>) &gt; Δ ws<sub>th</sub>), to exclude noise-triggered processes. Both rules were important because the parameter <sub>rel</sub>XYmov was also used to categorize eight levels of participation of agent bees in shimmering (c<sub>ws</sub> = 1–8). The assignment of c<sub>ws</sub> = 1 served as the minimum level of shimmering activity of an agent bee (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3C,D</xref>) and unambiguously excludes sub-threshold shimmering activities.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>The Concept of the <italic>Focus Bee</italic></title>
        <p>The participation in shimmering varied strongly from agent to agent. This individual bias is caused by a series of agent-specific factors such as the location in the nest, the individual’s age, the direction of wave spreading at the agent’s location, the level of the passive participation (i.e. motion without abdominal flipping) or of the active participation (i.e. motion caused by abdominal flipping at variable strength), and lastly the participation of the neighbours of the selected agent in the wave. Therefore, we introduced the concept of the <italic>focus bee</italic> (<italic>fb</italic>) to enable the pooling and statistical evaluation of the data in particular. For every <italic>focus bee</italic>, we defined two areas of neighbourhood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g001">Fig. 1A,B</xref>), the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> (radius<sub>Nh</sub>&lt;40 mm) and the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (radius<sub>Nh</sub>&lt;100 mm), and selected those neighbour bees (<italic>nb</italic>) which participated in shimmering before the wave front had arrived at the <italic>focus bee</italic>. As a consequence, an agent bee was treated in the evaluation either as <italic>focus bee</italic> or as neighbour bee of a previously defined <italic>focus bee</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Triggering the Participation in Shimmering</title>
        <p>For a given <italic>focus bee</italic>, the <sub>rel</sub>XYmov value (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3C,D</xref>) was utilized to define the arrival time (t<sub>0</sub>) of the shimmering front and also the level of participation in shimmering (c<sub>ws</sub>-value). For the nest mates around a given <italic>focus bee</italic>, the rapid rise of the <sub>rel</sub>XYmov value at t<sub>1</sub> = t[f<sub>1</sub>] was used to assign the potential trigger neighbour (<italic>tn</italic>) for a given shimmering <italic>incident</italic> by considering three criteria: (a) The trigger neighbour had already participated in the same wave, but only for a maximum of 5 frames (Δt≤88 ms) before the <italic>focus bee</italic> itself had started her shimmering activity. (b) The trigger neighbour was closest of all other candidates to the <italic>focus bee</italic> and was positioned in her <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> which made up not more than 5–7 agents. This rule excluded those bees from analysis which generated daughter waves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger6">[22]</xref>. Such surface bees were flipping their abdomens singularly or in a small group and were farther away from other active bees than defined by the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic>. (c) Furthermore, the angular position of the trigger neighbour (α<sub>tn</sub>) defined the <italic>trigger direction</italic> (dir<sub>TRIG</sub>) of the <italic>focus bee</italic>. For that, eight sectors of neighbourhood (dir<sub>Nh</sub> = 1–8) circularly around the <italic>focus bee</italic> were defined in steps of angular ranges Δα<sub>Nh</sub> = 45° (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036736-t001">Table 1</xref>). Consequently, the <italic>trigger direction</italic> of the <italic>focus bee</italic> was defined by the angular sector (dir<sub>TRIG</sub> = 1–8) in which the trigger neighbour was positioned (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036736-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>Relative Time Scales</title>
        <p>The time point t<sub>0</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3D</xref>) of a <italic>focus bee</italic> defined the frame before the <italic>focus bee</italic> displayed the supra-threshold movement of abdomen flipping. This reference established a time scale for both partners in the trigger process, the triggered <italic>focus bee</italic> and her triggering neighbour. The time courses of the movements of both agents (<italic>fb,tn</italic>) were registered and synchronized to the time zero of either the <italic>focus bee</italic> herself (t<sub>0</sub>[<italic>fb</italic>]) or in the case of the triggering neighbours (<italic>tn</italic>), to the time zero of the <italic>focus bee</italic> to which they had been referred to. This synchronization conjoined the movements of both agents by the positional (<italic>x,y,z</italic>) parameters and by the wave strength (<sub>rel</sub>XYmov). Such wave processes of identified <italic>focus bees</italic> and of their neighbours collected at different locations and times were consecutively synchronized and sorted according to behavioural categories such as wave strength c<sub>ws</sub>, main wave direction dir<sub>WAV</sub> and trigger direction dir<sub>TRIG</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036736-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2j">
        <title>Stimulation by Dummy Wasps</title>
        <p>Waves were elicited using a cable car device <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref> with a dummy wasp positioned at the outer sun-oriented nest side below the mouth zone (shown on the bottom right side of the experimental nest in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s004">movies S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s005">S2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s006">S3</xref>). Using this computer-controlled device <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger9">[35]</xref>, the dummy wasp could be moved at variable velocities (0.1 - 0.5 m/s) and directions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig.3A</xref>). The dummy consisted of Styrofoam (L×W×H: 40×15×15 mm) with white, yellow and black painted stripes. The dummy was fastened to the cable car by a thin thread, so that is was freely swinging with the length axis horizontally. In the experiments described here, the dummy wasp was moved at an angle of 90° to the nest surface. For more intense stimulation we used the manual technique of moving a rod with a swinging dummy of the same geometrical pattern as under cable-car conditions.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Categorization of Active Participation in Shimmering</title>
        <p>Individual agent bees were identified on the surface of a Giant honeybee nest by stereoscopic imaging (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3A,B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>) for 66 manually selected shimmering waves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). Twenty-two independent data sets of four wave directions (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4) were analysed. Only a subset of 53.06±3.05% of identified agent bees were found to participate actively in shimmering, defined by flipping their abdomens at an above-threshold strength level (c<sub>WS</sub> = 1-6). Bees that did not participate above this threshold were excluded from further analyses. <italic>Focus bees</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3E</xref>) received the mechanical cues from their nest mates in the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic>. The category of <italic>focus bees</italic> constituted 75.72±2.90% (n = 22 data sets of 10715 identified bees) of those bees which actively contributed to shimmering. The complementary part of 24.28% active bees flipped their abdomens without having received a mechanical cue from their immediate neighbours. These bees were likely to be members of an alternative spreading mechanism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger6">[22]</xref> and were excluded from further evaluation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3E–H</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>The Time Courses of Wave Incidents of <italic>Focus Bees</italic> and Their Triggering Neighbours</title>
        <p>By definition, the <italic>focus bees</italic> started their participation in shimmering at t<sub>0</sub>, after they had received triggering cues from their active neighbours. Prior to t<sub>0,</sub> the shimmering activities rose slowly within 200 ms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>) which was caused in the arrival phase of the shimmering front by the movements of the neighbours <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>). This passive motion of the <italic>focus bees</italic> can be considered as a potential decision-enabling cue which may trigger, or at least influence, the start and strength of the subsequent participation. In particular at higher wave strength levels, the subsequent course of <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values displayed damped oscillations, which were due to resonance conditions of the bee curtain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>.</p>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g004">Fig. 4B</xref> also shows in black lines the curves of the neighbours in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> of the <italic>focus bees</italic> assembled in their trigger direction. For that, only those neighbours were selected that had flipped their abdomens at the same wave strength as the <italic>focus bee</italic>. This enabled the assessment of the time for the information to spread from the neighbours to the <italic>focus bees</italic> which lie at 47.29±1.12 ms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>; mean ± SE; n = 6 wave strength levels; averaged for threshold levels of 1.0≥<sub>rel</sub>XYmov≥2.3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). For small and higher wave strength values (c<sub>WS</sub> = 1; c<sub>WS</sub>&gt;4) the transfer times are significantly shorter. Taken in account the average distance of 62 mm between the <italic>focus bee</italic> and neighbours in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic>, <italic>bucket bridging</italic> achieved a speed of 1.311±0.030 m/s for this step of wave propagation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Testing <italic>Linearity</italic> of Wave Propagation</title>
        <p>In shimmering, the <italic>directed-trigger</italic> hypothesis.</p>
        <p><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e001" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1a)</label></disp-formula>can be tested at each <italic>focus bee</italic> by the coincidence of <italic>trigger direction</italic> and <italic>wave direction</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3H</xref><sub>1</sub>). We proved this aspect of <italic>linearity</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3I</xref><sub>1</sub>) using four independent data sets (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036736-t001">Table 1</xref>) of selected sample waves. In detail, we checked whether and how the angular positions of the triggering neighbour coincided either with the direction from where the wave came (conforming to equation 1a, ) or with the opposite direction, into which the wave spread.</p>
        <p><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e002" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1b)</label></disp-formula>Strict <italic>linearity</italic> in wave propagation would support that the participation of the <italic>focus bee</italic> is triggered from the side where the wave came from, but not that the trigger process is launched from the opposite direction.</p>
        <p>In a first step of analysis, the <italic>focus bees</italic> were screened for their participation in shimmering. In all four data sets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>) the normalized counts <sub>rel</sub>n<sub>fb</sub> were Gauss-distributed around mid-level strengths (c<sub>ws</sub> = 2–4); the reference (<sub>rel</sub>n<sub>fb</sub> = 1.00).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0036736-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Correspondence of trigger direction and wave direction in individual <italic>focus bees</italic> addressing <italic>linearity</italic> of wave spreading in shimmering.</title>
            <p>The ordinates show the rate of wave incidents assessed at individual <italic>focus bees</italic> (<sub>rel</sub>n<sub>fb</sub>) and normalized for the maximum number of incidents per wave direction (<sub>rel</sub>n<sub>fb</sub> = 1 for MAX n<sub>fb </sub>[dir<sub>WAV</sub>]). (A) Distribution of wave incidents regarding the four wave directions (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4). The <italic>focus bees</italic> were distinguished according to their individual wave strength levels (c<sub>ws</sub> = 1–6) in different colours; for evaluation, only those <italic>focus bees</italic> were selected that had been triggered by an immediate neighbour in the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> (radius<sub>Nh</sub>&lt;40 mm); <italic>red</italic>, from Right to Left (<sub>from</sub>R<sub>to</sub>L), n = 2825 wave incidents; <italic>green</italic>, from Bottom to Top (<sub>from</sub>B<sub>to</sub>T), n = 2908; <italic>orange</italic>, from Left to Right (<sub>from</sub>L<sub>to</sub>R), n = 2433; <italic>blue</italic>, from Top to Bottom (<sub>from</sub>T<sub>to</sub>B), n = 1256. (B-C) distributions of wave events regarding the <italic>trigger directions</italic> of individual <italic>focus bees</italic> (dir<sub>TRIG</sub> = 1–8; for definition, see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036736-t001">Table 1</xref>). Angular sector lines in (B) and abscissa in (C) show the <italic>trigger angle</italic> α<sub>TRIG</sub>. (C) The curves show the regression polynomials (for specification see Table 2); the grey vertical bars refer to the main wave directions coded by the median as α<sub>WAV</sub> (dark grey) and the tolerances of ± 45° (bright grey).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e003" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2a)</label></disp-formula>was the total number of wave incidents at a given <italic>wave direction</italic>. We then pooled the data of all <italic>wave strength</italic> levels (c<sub>ws</sub> = 1–6), and sorted them according to their <italic>trigger direction</italic> (dir<sub>TRIG</sub> = 1-8; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036736-t001">Table 1</xref>). The data sets showed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>) oval-shaped angular distributions with clearly positioned minima and maxima (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>). Furthermore, the maxima referred to those trigger angles (α<sub>TRIG</sub>) that conformed to the direction from where the wave came (equation 1a), while the minima were displayed at those trigger angles that conformed to the angle where the wave spread to (Equation 1b). Both results were replicated with four independent data sets, and reliably support the <italic>directed-trigger</italic> hypothesis which addresses the <italic>linearity</italic> principle in spreading (for test statistics see below).</p>
        <p>However, the results of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5</xref> also demonstrate that the propagation process is affected by a strikingly high level of fuzziness, unpredictability and <italic>non-linearity</italic>. In detail, the normalized counts <sub>rel</sub>n<sub>fb</sub> correlated along the trigger angle with the polynomial regression curves revealing maxima of 0.152±0.004 and a distance between minima and maxima of 0.055±0.004 (n = 4 data sets of dir<sub>WAV</sub>; further specifications of the polynomials of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s001">Table S1</xref>). An average base quantity of <italic>focus bees</italic> (0.097±0.002; n = 4 | dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4) was observed in each of the eight angular sectors of trigger direction. This means that for a socket of nearly 80% of <italic>focus bees</italic>, of a total of 100% per behavioural condition (n = 24 | c<sub>ws</sub> = 1–6; dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4), the trigger angles did not correlate with the main wave direction.</p>
        <p>Here, the question arises, to which extent the polynomial regression curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5</xref>) may then signal <italic>linearity</italic> in the propagation of shimmering waves. We confirmed this by a simple test considering the counts of those angular sectors (<italic>n<sub>s</sub></italic>) which coincide in wave and trigger direction in the four data sets (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4). <italic>Linearity</italic> would here be obvious if the <sub>rel</sub>n<sub>fb</sub>-values above median level (see ordinate values in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5</xref>) referred to the sectors of wave direction (<italic>s</italic><sub>WAV</sub> ≡ s<sub>TRIG</sub>), proving coincidence of both directional paradigms (dir<sub>WAV</sub> ≡ dir<sub>TRIG</sub>) in the shimmering process. To test this, we expanded the critical directional window by α<sub>WAVnew</sub> = α<sub>WAVorig</sub> ± 45° (which increased the numbers of critical sectors in the comparison by the factor of 3). This is legitimate because the manual selection of wave direction had a similar level of tolerance (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref>). Our results proved <italic>linearity</italic> because both quantities of <italic>n<sub>s </sub></italic>.<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e004" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2b)</label></disp-formula>coincided here at 100% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig.5C</xref>). In other words, the majority of <italic>focus bees</italic> were triggered from the direction where the wave came from<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e005" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2c)</label></disp-formula>and the minority of the focus bees were triggered from the direction where the wave was spreading to</p>
        <p><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e006" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2d)</label></disp-formula>In a next step, the level of <italic>linearity</italic> in wave propagation was estimated in two ways (A,B). For <italic>estimate<sub>A</sub></italic>, we integrated the percentages of participations above the fuzziness level (which was defined by the minima of the polynomials; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>). <italic>Estimate<sub>A</sub></italic> referred to 20.99±2.38% (n = 4 data sets of dir<sub>WAV</sub>) of the total of identified wave incidents and signifies the overall variability in directedness in spreading. For <italic>estimate<sub>B</sub></italic>, we summed the percentages of participations only above the median level of <sub>rel</sub>n<sub>fb</sub> = 0.1253±0.0015 (n = 4 data sets of dir<sub>WAV</sub>; equation 2e; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>).<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e007" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2e)</label></disp-formula></p>
        <p>This <italic>estimate<sub>B</sub></italic> was 6.15±1.05% (n = 4) of identified wave incidents and included only the excess quantities of wave incidents, which were primarily responsible for the directedness of shimmering waves.</p>
        <p>Summarizing, the data strongly support the <italic>directed-trigger</italic> hypothesis. However, the rates of <italic>focus bees</italic> conforming to equation 1a and considered by <italic>estimate<sub>B</sub></italic> were only 6.15% of all identified wave incidents. Therefore, the principle of directedness in spreading was extremely outnumbered by the complementary part of 93.85% of <italic>focus bees</italic> which were triggered from random directions, independently of the main propagation direction of the waves.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Testing <italic>Continuity</italic> of Wave Propagation</title>
        <p>We used the sample size of the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (radius<sub>Nh</sub>&lt;100 mm) of <italic>focus bees</italic> to characterise <italic>continuity</italic> in propagation by the circular distribution of nest mates which had been active in shimmering before the <italic>focus bee</italic> herself started to participate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3I</xref><sub>2</sub>) addressing the transmittance of information over a distance that was greater than that between immediate neighbours. The <italic>active-neighbours</italic> hypothesis is proved in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6</xref> which displays the respective results of normalized data of four independent tests (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1-4). The relative numbers of active neighbours (<sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub>) in the <italic>far neighbourhood.</italic></p>
        <fig id="pone-0036736-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Proof of <italic>linearity</italic> and <italic>continuity</italic> in wave spreading of shimmering as documented by neighbour-bee related analysis.</title>
            <p>(A) Arithmetic means (curves) and SE (vertical bars) of the relative numbers of shimmering neighbours (<sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub>) in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (radius<sub>Nh</sub>&lt;100 mm) around the <italic>focus bees</italic> regarding to the wave strength levels c<sub>ws</sub> = 1-5; abscissa: Δα<sub>TRIG | Nh</sub>, the deviation from the trigger angle in degrees at which the <italic>focus bees</italic> were activated to participate in shimmering, therefore Δα<sub>TRIG | Nh</sub> = 0 refers to the trigger angle (trigger direction). Four data sets representing different spreading directions of shimmering waves (for colour codes, see Fig. 5): <sub>from</sub>R<sub>to</sub>L, n<sub>nb</sub> = 138190 neighbours; <sub>from</sub>B<sub>to</sub>T, 105356; <sub>from</sub>L<sub>to</sub>R, 159417; <sub>from</sub>T<sub>to</sub>B, 93199; (B) arithmetic means (curves) of the relative numbers of shimmering neighbours in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (<sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub>), considering four classes of wave strength levels were considered: darkest grey lines, c<sub>ws</sub> = 4-5; brightest grey lines, c<sub>ws</sub> = 1–2. The curves show the respective regression functions of the means (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s002">Table S2</xref>); SEs are not shown. (C) Angular diagrams of relative numbers of shimmering neighbours (<sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub> ) of only those <italic>focus bees</italic> selected for mid-level wave strength activation (c<sub>ws</sub> = 3): <sub>from</sub>R<sub>to</sub>L, n<sub>nb</sub> = 4652 neighbours; <sub>from</sub>B<sub>to</sub>T, 4458; <sub>from</sub>L<sub>to</sub>R, 7182; <sub>from</sub>T<sub>to</sub>B, 2295; background sectors give the trigger angles α<sub>TRIG</sub> of the <italic>focus bees</italic> (C<sub>1</sub>) <italic>focus bees</italic> which were triggered in the direction where the wave had come from (equation 1a); (C<sub>2</sub>) <italic>focus bees</italic> which were triggered in the direction opposite to that under C<sub>1</sub> (equation 1b).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e008" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3a)</label></disp-formula>for Nh&lt;100 mm with max <sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub>(c<sub> BEHAV</sub>) = 1.0</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e009" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3b)</label></disp-formula>
          <disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e010" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3c)</label></disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>For a better survey on the intrinsic data structure, we offer three subsets of diagrams: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6A</xref> refers to the data pool for the wave strength levels c<sub>ws</sub> = 1-5, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6B</xref> distinguishes between different groups of wave strength levels (for details, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s002">Table S2</xref>), and the circular diagrams in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6C</xref> exemplify only data for the specific wave strength level c<sub>ws</sub> = 3.</p>
        <p>In total, 48 sectors of 20 behavioural conditions (c<sub>ws</sub> = 1-5, dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4) were evaluated. In all the four data sets the numbers of active neighbours were found to peak in the trigger directions (Δα<sub>TRIG | Nh</sub> = 0°). This means that the <italic>focus bees</italic> were triggered exactly (P&lt;0.001; t-test) from those directions where most of the neighbours had been active immediately before. The maxima of the graphs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>) increased above a level of <sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub> = 0.80, which corresponded to the number of n<sub>Nh</sub> = 16.63±0.42 (mean ± SE) active neighbours per <italic>focus bee</italic>. For the angular sectors adjacent to the peaks, the graphs dropped down to <sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub> = 0.60, which corresponded to 11.81±0.087 neighbours per <italic>focus bee</italic> and 71.97% of the maximal numbers of active neighbours. The complimentary value of 28.03%.<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e011" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3d)</label></disp-formula>gives a usable estimate of the excess rate of neighbours found in the trigger directions of the <italic>focus bees</italic>. With the reference of the trigger angle of active neighbours (equation 3b) this result delivers an estimate of <italic>continuity</italic> in wave propagation which was fourfold higher than the <italic>linearity</italic> aspect detected in the context of <italic>trigger direction</italic> and <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>).</p>
        <p>The curves of the normalized <sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub> values were robust regarding wave strength (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>). Interestingly, the preferences for the wave directions were remarkably dominant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6A-C</xref>) which is exemplified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6C</xref> for <italic>focus bees</italic> acting at mid-level wave strengths (c<sub>ws</sub> = 3). Here, the directional dependencies of the numbers of actively shimmering neighbours are displayed under two different conditions for the four regimes of wave directions (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1-4): In the left column, <italic>focus bees</italic> were selected that corresponded in trigger direction and wave direction (according to equation 1a). The angular graphs are oval-shaped with significant (P&lt;0.001; chi square test) preference for the wave direction. The values differed between max and min values by Δ<sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub> = 33%. In the right columns, the samples refer to <italic>focus bees</italic> that were triggered from the direction opposite to the wave direction (according to equation 1b). These wave incidents showed a much weaker but still significant (P&lt;0.001; chi square test; Δ<sub>rel</sub>n<sub>Nh</sub> = 22.65%) preference for the wave direction.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Testing <italic>Graduality</italic> in Propagation</title>
        <p>There are several ways how surface bees may participate in a shimmering wave. It may happen (a) as an all-or-none decision, to participate, for example, at full <italic>wave strength</italic>, if the surrounding activity had exceeded a certain threshold level. The circumstances of participation may be even more complex, if it were true that (b) a single <italic>focus bee</italic> has the freedom to decide whether or not to participate, and if she does, at which strength level. Finally, (c) it can also be a matter of <italic>graduality</italic> whereby <italic>focus bees</italic> respond with variable <italic>wave strengths</italic> dependent on the activity level of the surrounding neighbours.</p>
        <p>If a <italic>focus bee</italic> receives the signal to start abdominal flipping as a <italic>gradual</italic> message from her surrounding neighbours, she has, in theory, two options: first, she could match the strength of her abdominal flipping according to the <italic>numbers</italic> of neighbouring bees that flipped their abdomens immediately before. This aspect has already been demonstrated in two independent test sets: we showed (a) that the rate of shimmering incidents was higher if the <italic>focus bee</italic> was triggered in wave direction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5B,C</xref>), and (b), that the <italic>focus bee</italic> must have received stronger mechanical cues from her neighbours in her <italic>trigger direction</italic>, because at this angle more neighbours had been active (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Both findings, although highly significant, referred only to a minority of <italic>focus bees</italic>, at a proportion of less than 10% in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5B,C</xref> or up to a quarter in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6A,B</xref> of the full number of identified wave incidents.</p>
        <p>As a second option, a small number of very active neighbours may also elicit a strength level that could override smaller activities of a greater number of neighbours. To address this aspect, we correlated the <italic>wave strengths</italic> of <italic>focus bees</italic> with those of their neighbours in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic>. To simplify this survey, we concentrated on the neighbours in only two defined directional sectors of neighbourhood: (a) on the sectors of the trigger direction (<italic>ds</italic>: <italic>direct-sector</italic> analysis), and (b) on the sector opposite to the trigger direction (<italic>os</italic>: <italic>opposite-sector</italic> analysis). We then assessed the correlations (r<sub>ds</sub>, r<sub>os</sub>) that referred to the comparison of the <italic>wave strengths</italic> of <italic>focus bees</italic> with those of their neighbours in the selected sectors. The correlations either delivered <italic>proportional</italic> effects, if the wave strengths of <italic>focus bees</italic> correlated positively with those of their selected neighbours (with k&gt;0).<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.e012" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4a)</label></disp-formula>or they delivered <italic>antagonistic</italic> effects, if the wave strengths of <italic>focus bees</italic> correlated negatively (with k&lt;0 in equation 4a).</p>
        <p>In detail, we pooled the data of identified <italic>focus bees</italic> and their neighbours under 184 test conditions (n<sub>fb</sub> = 10911; n<sub>nb</sub> = 496162; c<sub>BEHAV</sub> = 184; dir<sub>TRIG</sub> = 1–8; dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4; c<sub>ws</sub> = 1–6) and received positive correlations under both (<italic>ds, os</italic>) conditions (r<sub>ds</sub> = 0.0594±0.0174; r<sub>os</sub> = 0.0381±0.0175; means ± SE; n<sub>r</sub> = c<sub>BEHAV</sub>), but the regression coefficient was only slightly higher for the direct-sector analysis (P = 0.1944, t-test). In a next step, we assessed the regression data separately for each wave strength level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g007">Fig. 7A,B</xref>; c<sub>ws</sub> = 1–6) and achieved significantly positive values under weak and higher strength levels (e.g. for c<sub>ws</sub> = 5: r<sub>ds</sub> = 0.1600±0.0426) which also delivered significant differences between <italic>ds-</italic> and <italic>os-</italic>analysis (P = 0.0017; t-test; c<sub>BEHAV</sub> = 24: dir<sub>TRIG</sub> = 1-8, dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4; n<sub>fb</sub> = 1 203; n<sub>nb</sub> = 25084), in particular for the strong participation in shimmering (c<sub>ws</sub> = 5). These results document that <italic>focus bees</italic> behave in a <italic>gradual</italic> and thus, <italic>directed</italic> manner if they responded at high <italic>wave strengths</italic> to the mechanical cues of those active neighbours from the trigger directions in the <italic>far neighbourhood.</italic> Similar responses are documented if the mechanical cues of the triggering neighbours were considered in the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>). Here the correlation between the <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values of the <italic>focus bees</italic> and their triggering neighbours were also higher at higher wave strengths, and there was also a sink of regression values at mid-strength-levels. However, at threshold conditions (c<sub>ws</sub> = 1) the correlations were extremely low.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0036736-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Proof of <italic>graduality</italic> in the wave strength between <italic>focus bees</italic> and their neighbours.</title>
            <p>Abscissa, wave strength levels of the <italic>focus bee</italic> (c<sub>ws [fb]</sub> = 1–6). (A) How are the <italic>focus bees</italic> influenced from their neighbours in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic>? Ordinate, the regression coefficients resulting from the comparison of wave strength values (<sub>rel</sub>XYmov) of <italic>focus bees</italic> (<italic>fb</italic>) and those of their nest mates (<italic>nb</italic>) in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (r&lt;100 mm); the data were pooled from all sets of wave directions (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1–4); white columns refer to <italic>direct-sector</italic> analysis, black columns refer to <italic>opposite-sector</italic> analysis (for further definition, see text and equations 4a–d); the white curve refers to the distribution of <italic>direct-sector</italic> data (polynomial: a<sub>2</sub> = 0.0324, a<sub>1</sub> = -0.1763, a<sub>0</sub> = 0.2379, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.975; n = 5 | c<sub>ws [fb]</sub> = 1–5). (B) How are <italic>focus bees</italic> influenced from their immediate triggering neighbours? Ordinate, regression coefficients resulting from the comparison of <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values of <italic>focus bees</italic> (<italic>fb</italic>) and those of their triggering neighbours (<italic>tn</italic>) in the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> (r&lt;40 mm), considering all wave incidences separately per wave direction (dir<sub>WAV</sub> = 1 to 4); polynomial: a<sub>4</sub> = −0.0037, a<sub>3</sub> = 0.0668, a<sub>2</sub> = −0.3926, a<sub>1</sub> = 0.896, a<sub>0</sub> = 0,5691, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9994; n = 6 | c<sub>ws [fb]</sub> = 1–6); means (full circles) and SE (bars). (C) Numbers of wave incidences selected for B.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Summarizing, the overall <italic>graduality</italic> in wave propagation displayed positive correlations between shimmering activities of <italic>focus bees</italic> and those of their neighbours. However, the overall achieved value with r<sub>ds</sub>&lt;0.06 can be used to estimate the occurrence of <italic>graduality</italic> in agents participating in shimmering. The coefficient of determination R<sup>2</sup> = r<sub>ds</sub><sup>2</sup> is here a measure of the goodness of the fit. Therefore, only 0.36% of agents participating in shimmering are controlled by the principle of <italic>graduality</italic>. If the <italic>wave strength</italic> levels were considered separately, the results proved <italic>graduality</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>; equations 4a) in particular for <italic>focus bees</italic> acting more forcefully (c<sub>ws</sub> = 5). Here, the regression coefficients achieved values of r<sub>ds</sub> = 0.16 (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.0256) representing 2.56% of the selected agents. These results also differed significantly between <italic>ds</italic>- and <italic>os</italic>-analyses. Such <italic>polar</italic> conditions preferentially occur at the very frontline of shimmering waves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger6">[22]</xref>. Conversely, the bees at mid-level wave strength (c<sub>ws</sub> = 2–3) which constituted up to 85% of all agents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g007">Fig. 7C</xref>), were not identified as candidates responsible for <italic>gradual</italic> propagation.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Properties of Wave Propagation in Shimmering</title>
        <p>Shimmering behaviour is one element of the defence behaviour in Giant honeybees and has repelling properties upon potential predators <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Roepke1">[3]</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>. When observed by naked eye, shimmering waves originate from particular nest areas around the mouth zone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Schmelzer1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref> and propagate to the periphery in a Mexican-wavelike <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Farkas1">[21]</xref> way, spreading seemingly <italic>linearly</italic> and <italic>continuously</italic> across the nest, mostly with a clearly visible front line (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s004">movie S1</xref>). In this study, we investigated three paradigms of this wave propagation, which can be assigned as <italic>linearity</italic>, <italic>continuity</italic> and <italic>graduality</italic> (summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3H-J</xref>), which affect direction, velocity and gain of the bucket-bridging processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref> in shimmering.</p>
        <p>We applied a set of recording techniques and analytical approaches that enabled us to investigate the propagation features of shimmering waves with four single-agent-based concepts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3</xref>): (1) the (re-) identification of single agent bees at the nest surface and tracing them throughout the recorded sessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>); (2) the detection of the participation of agent bees in shimmering, defining the starting time and the relative time scale of individual abdominal flipping episodes (termed as <italic>wave incidents</italic>), enabling synchronisation of wave incidents in subsequent pooling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3C,D</xref>); (3) the measurement of the movement strength to quantify the participation in a wave (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3F</xref><sub>2</sub>); and (4) the implementation of the concept of the <italic>focus bee</italic> as the addressee of the trigger process (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref>), who receives directional information from the triggering neighbours in the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> or from other agents in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3F</xref><sub>3</sub>). All directional properties assessed for a <italic>focus bee</italic> lastly refer to the partitioning of her neighbourhood into eight angular sectors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3F</xref><sub>3,4</sub>).</p>
        <sec id="s4a1">
          <title>Linearity and continuity in propagation of shimmering</title>
          <p>The <italic>directed-trigger</italic> hypothesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3H</xref><sub>1</sub>–J<sub>1</sub>) assumes <italic>linearity</italic> in spreading and predicts that <italic>focus bees</italic> receive signals to join shimmering predominantly from the direction from where the wave spread. Confirming slight but reliable tendencies of directionality of the trigger process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5B,C</xref>), repeatedly for four independent data sets of different spreading directions, the results supported the <italic>directed-trigger hypothesis</italic> for a small proportion of 6.15% of <italic>focus bees</italic>, but also documented a high level (93.75%) of non-<italic>linearity</italic> and unpredictability in the directedness of shimmering.</p>
          <p>The paradigm of <italic>continuity</italic> addresses how the mode of wave propagation is preserved rather than how the directedness of spreading is established. For instance, a <italic>discontinuous</italic> process occurs in a shimmering wave locally if an agent bee fails to pass on the information received by an abdomen-flipping neighbour in the <italic>bucket bridging</italic> process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>. Consequently, the spreading of information will either stop or by-pass to an alternative neighbour (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g002">Fig. 2B,C</xref>). Otherwise, <italic>discontinuity</italic> could also be a group-level property which is different to <italic>bucket bridging.</italic> For example, while the mechanoceptive nature of abdomen flipping is the main driving cue for <italic>bucket bridging</italic>, saltatoric events <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger6">[22]</xref> are operative only through external visual cues in the vicinity of the nest which affect some specific trigger bees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Schmelzer1">[10]</xref>. Saltatoric processes forward the information of jumping-like arousal to neighbouring chains of agents some bee widths or bee lengths away. These target agents would then be able to generate daughter waves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger6">[22]</xref>, but nonetheless, <italic>bucket bridging</italic> continues further on around such generator agents.</p>
          <p>The aspect of <italic>continuity</italic> in bucket-bridging was assessed by proving the <italic>active-neighbours</italic> hypothesis. It predicts that most of the energy produced by abdominal flipping arrives at the <italic>focus bee</italic> from the <italic>trigger direction</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3J</xref><sub>2</sub>). This hypothesis is based on two <italic>focus bee</italic>-specific definitions, (a) on the <italic>trigger process</italic> which refers to a single triggering neighbour selected from 4–6 agents in the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic>, and (b) on the sectoral majority of active neighbours selected from 20–30 agents in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic>. <italic>Continuity</italic> refers to the proportion of neighbours and their angular positions from which the wave was propagated towards the <italic>focus bee</italic>. The results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6</xref>) support the <italic>active-neighbours</italic> hypothesis proving <italic>continuity</italic> at a level of 27% of the full scale of identified wave incidents, confirmed through four independent tests with rich data sets.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a2">
          <title>Graduality in propagation of shimmering</title>
          <p>A <italic>gradual</italic> transfer of information occurs if the level of participation of <italic>focus bees</italic> correlates with the shimmering activity of their neighbours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g003">Fig. 3J</xref><sub>3</sub>), i.e., information transfer was <italic>gradual</italic> if a <italic>focus bee</italic> passed on a signal with the same intensity that she had previously received. However, <italic>gradual</italic> information transfer may also deliver variable results. In particular, in the initial phase of the wave, agent bees are likely to transmit signals at an even higher energy level than their predecessors, driving the shimmering episode into the peaking phase, which usually occurred 200–500 ms after the start of the wave. In this phase, the shimmering process shows a <italic>positive feedback</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>. In the phase before the shimmering wave dies away, agents transmit the information in the <italic>bucket bridging</italic> transfer weaker than their predecessors, showing <italic>negative feedback</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>. In the course of a single shimmering episode, wave propagation may switch consecutively between g<italic>raduality</italic> and non-<italic>graduality</italic>, and between <italic>positive</italic> and <italic>negative feedback</italic>.</p>
          <p>We tested <italic>graduality</italic> among two groups of surface bees with different memberships in bucket-bridging chains. We investigated (a) the transfer of information towards a <italic>focus bee</italic> from her nest mates in the <italic>far neighbourhood</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>), and (b) the transfer of information towards a <italic>focus bee</italic> from her triggering neighbour in the <italic>near neighbourhood</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g007">Fig. 7B,C</xref>). These results confirm <italic>graduality</italic> and <italic>positive feedback</italic> in propagation for maximal 15% of the identified wave incidents, particularly at high wave strength levels. These conditions usually occur at the climax of the shimmering waves, but also at the very frontline of the waves, when strong mechanical <italic>cues</italic> are transmitted in the bee curtain for some hundreds of milliseconds.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a3">
          <title>Hallmarks of bucket bridging summarized</title>
          <p>The main result of this paper is that during shimmering waves only a small minority of surface bees transmit information through <italic>bucket bridging</italic>. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s003">Table S3</xref> summarizes the hallmarks of shimmering: Only 53.06±0.03% (n = 22 data sets, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s003">Table S3,c</xref>) of identified surface bees took part in shimmering; hence, the other half of the surface bees did hardly pass on any information. 75.72% of the subset of shimmering bees (corresponding to 40.18% of all surface bees, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s003">Table S3,d</xref>) were triggered by their immediate neighbours; 85% of the latter (34.15% of all surface bees, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s003">Table S3,e</xref>) responded at medium wave strengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). Only a much smaller proportion participated in shimmering either weakly (5%) or strongly (10%), corresponding to only 2.01 % (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s003">Table S3,f</xref>) or 4.02 % (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s003">Table S3,g</xref>) of the total of surface bees.</p>
          <p>Regarding the principles of <italic>bucket bridging</italic> only a small minority of shimmering bees of 6.15% conformed to the concept of <italic>linearity</italic> (2.47% of all surface bees, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s003">Table S3,h</xref>), and 28.03% of the shimmering active bees (11.26% of all surface bees) conformed to the principle of <italic>continuity.</italic> Proportional transmission of information, as proposed by the <italic>graduality</italic> hypothesis was found in 0.36% of the surface bees, and 1.94% respectively 2.56% (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s003">Table S3,j,k</xref>) which showed strong (c<sub>ws</sub> = 5 ) abdominal flipping (0.124% respectively 0.163% of surface bees).</p>
          <p>The compilation of a wave also needs the coordination of single-agent activities to form group activities in form of semi-synchronized and cascadic sequences. <italic>Refractory</italic> processes are here decisive because they implement latency effects. Theoretically, without refractory processes, surface bees would hardly be able to produce any directed visual pattern such as a shimmering wave. The existence of a refractory phase would preclude that bees at the nest surface maintain abdomen-flipping activities at high frequency, after the wave front had already passed by. In shimmering, the <italic>refractory phase</italic> can be indirectly estimated by the repetition rate of waves under high-arousal conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger5">[17]</xref> which is 0.8 - 1.5 Hz; a typical value of 1.200±0.006 Hz (n = 66) was assessed at maximal arousal which would give a <italic>refractory phase</italic> of around 800 ms.</p>
          <p>Interestingly, Giant honeybee colonies usually produce also collective motion patterns of abdomen-flipping surface bees, which are guided conversely to shimmering. It happens in a stochastic way, thus non-periodic and non-cascadic, and is called <italic>flickering</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Weihmann1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger7">[24]</xref>. We have observed that <italic>flickering</italic> has a diurnal rhythm and happens particularly in the early morning hours. It is likely that a colony passes through an asynchronous phase of flickering before it is capable to produce the highly synchronized and cascading patterns of shimmering <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Roepke1">[3]</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Schmelzer1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Self Organization in Shimmering</title>
        <p>Evidence is emerging that shimmering possesses a series of properties which categorize this behaviour as a self-organized process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>. Two points to consider are, first, the adaptive value of the signal for external addressees. It is known <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref> that shimmering can change in appearance and goal setting if a single parameter changes. For example, we found that the distance between a wasp and a Giant honeybee nest alone causes a <italic>bifurcating</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref> situation for the attacking wasp to assess the shimmering pattern either as <italic>defensive</italic> or <italic>attractive</italic>. The second point to consider is the underlying mechanism of pattern formation. In this context, this paper gives a series of hallmark data to quantify the spatial and temporal propagation mechanisms.</p>
        <p>Self-organised collectives such as densely clustered surface bees in Giant honeybees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Krebs1">[37]</xref> guide their actions by simple behavioural rules. One of the simplest rules that play a role in wave propagation generally <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref> is that agents acquire information by monitoring their nearest neighbours. Here, this principle has been addressed for three paradigms of wave propagation in shimmering, <italic>linearity</italic>, <italic>continuity</italic> and <italic>graduality</italic>. The question was if and in which way these paradigms concur with the concept of self-organization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>. For wider comparison, we consider three collective animal behaviours, fish schooling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Partridge1">[38]</xref>, bird flocking <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Potts1">[39]</xref>, and fire-fly flashing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Lloyd1">[40]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Buck1">[42]</xref>. All these behaviours are supposedly self organized <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref> and utilize neighbourhood parameters, but differ essentially in their specific design and goals.</p>
        <sec id="s4b1">
          <title>Comparison of fish schooling and shimmering</title>
          <p>Both fish schooling (and similarly bird flocking <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Procaccini1">[15]</xref>) and shimmering exhibit the so-called <italic>Trafalgar Effect</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Treherne1">[43]</xref> by which special group-level properties allow rapid transfer of information throughout the collective. In fish schools these properties happen as evasive manoeuvres <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>, whereas shimmering behaviour in Giant honeybees is meant to deter external addressees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>. Both fish schooling and shimmering occur as a wave of collective reactions that propagate essentially faster than the approaching predator <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref> and group coordination is largely based on individuals which observe the preceding activity of neighbouring agents. Although the individuals time their own activities to coincide with the arrival from their neighbours <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Potts1">[39]</xref>, the responses are semi-synchronous as a consequence of latency and thus resemble <italic>bucket-bridging</italic> processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Farkas1">[21]</xref>. In addition, both, fish schooling and shimmering have special group-level properties that allow a variety of tactics which may lead to striking changes of the collective formations. For instance, when threatened, fish schools <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref> display evasive reactions known as the <italic>flash expansion effect</italic> (to rapidly expand the collective with radial bursts) or the <italic>fountain effect</italic> (to outmanoeuvre a predator by splitting into two groups). Similarly, shimmering in Giant honeybees is highly flexible in its dynamics, although shimmering bees essentially remain at the same location. The shape of the virtual motion patterns specifically depends on the movements of external threatening cues in space and time, such as scanning predatory wasps. In this case, the visual patterns “follow” the predator as a moving projection at the nest surface until the threatening object is “wiped off” from the nest area <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger9">[35]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4b2">
          <title>Comparison of firefly flashing and shimmering</title>
          <p>Fireflies produce a coordinated rhythm of synchronised flashing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Buck1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>. Each firefly primarily detects the flashes of immediate neighbours adjusting the timing of its own flash. The group pattern emerges as a result of multiple interactions among the individuals achieving flash synchrony in the collective <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Buck1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>. However, this kind of synchronisation happens without the concept of latency which would produce time lags in the reactions of followers. It is a matter of anticipation of the starting times of flashes which are expected from the immediate neighbours.</p>
          <p>In Giant honeybees shimmering patterns also emerge as a result of multiple interactions of agents. But in contrast to fireflies, the primary goal of honeybees in shimmering is not to produce synchronised events, but a coordinated rhythm of cascades. The coordination of individual contributions is due to the principles of information transfer such as <italic>bucket-bridging</italic>, and can be <italic>linear</italic> and <italic>non-linear</italic>, <italic>continuous</italic> and <italic>discontinuous</italic>, <italic>gradual</italic> and <italic>non-gradual</italic>, with positive or negative feedback. Information is transferred from one neighbour to the next, which is coupled with the latency aspect. This means that the individuals, which follow others in their actions, “wait” for the “right” moment to participate in the wave until they receive a key signal from their neighbourhood. This is a principle of leader- and followership which generates a cascade of responses and evolves into wave-like patterns. It cannot achieve pure synchrony as in fire fly flashing. In fireflies the overall rhythm is determined by the collective timing and not imposed by any influence from outside the system, such as a leader or supervisor of external physical cues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref>. Conversely, shimmering waves depend on the activity of trigger cohorts generating parental and daughter waves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Schmelzer1">[10]</xref>.</p>
          <p>The adaptive value of flash synchronization in fireflies is the production of a joint flash of males to attract females <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Buck1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Camazine1">[11]</xref> more than single flashes of individuals could achieve. High-level synchrony generally amplifies flash intensity, increases the range of coverage for a distant observer, and sharpens the advertence of females to visit the most attractive leks for mating <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Bradbury1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Gibson1">[45]</xref>. In contrast to the females-attracting flashes in fire flies, shimmering in giant honeybees deters potential predators <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>. The adaptive value lies in a semi-synchronous, cascading sequence of abdominal flipping of a significant sample of agents. The short latency of sequential events fuses into emergent visual patterns. This increases the range of coverage for a distant observer just by the virtual moving of the pattern.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4b3">
          <title>The adaptive value of fuzziness in shimmering</title>
          <p>The number of surface bees which expressed undirectedness in propagation, in the sense of <italic>nonlinearity</italic>, <italic>discontinuity</italic> and <italic>nongraduality</italic> exceeded 90% of the identified wave incidents (see hallmarks of <italic>bucket brid</italic>ging). Here, the question arises why shimmering waves have such a high level of fuzziness regarding their propagation properties. In social networks such as the bee curtain of Giant honeybees a series of reasons may cause fuzziness in propagation of information: (a) Refractory processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger5">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Klabunde1">[46]</xref> prohibit participation in shimmering immediately after wave incidents. (b) Individual surface bees possess different activation levels for abdominal flipping (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>), which establishes a bias in the responsiveness to sense signals from the neighbours and to deliver responses towards others. (c) Lastly, Giant honeybees regularly undergo different group-level properties such as periodic mass flight activity or quiescence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger8">[25]</xref>, or workloads such as the membership to the mouth zone or to quiescent areas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g001">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>We propose that a high level of fuzziness in shimmering is required for rising to the challenging behaviour of scanning wasps. If this predator is to be repelled by visual patterns through shimmering, the bees have to respond to rapidly changing constellations. To follow the wasp, which usually changes the flight direction abruptly within a fraction of a second <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger9">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger7">[24]</xref>, shimmering needs an adaptive capacity of surface bees to re-direct, refresh and repeat wave generation and propagate adequate collective responses. It is known that saltatoric processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger9">[35]</xref> would accelerate a wave beyond the basic capacities of <italic>bucket bridging</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger6">[22]</xref>. Although surface bees are generally disposed to receive information via mechanical <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">[16]</xref> or visual <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">[14]</xref> cues, we assume that only some individuals, the <italic>subordinate generator</italic> bees, are able to effectively integrate both types of information <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036736-Kastberger6">[22]</xref>. These jumping-like abilities of those bees in combination with the high level of fuzziness in shimmering may provide the required speed of re-orienting and propagation of an ongoing wave. Thus, fuzziness in wave propagation may be adaptive for a more flexible propagation of visually bound signals enabling the bees to respond to rapidly changing threats.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0036736.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Equations of the polynomial regressions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0036736.s002" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Specifications of the polynomials in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036736-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0036736.s003" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summarization of numbers referring to group memberships in <italic>bucket bridging</italic> in Giant honeybee shimmering.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0036736.s004" mimetype="video/quicktime" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Movie S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Experimental Giant honeybee (<italic>Apis dorsata</italic>) nest in Sauraha (Chitwan, Nepal). The computer-controlled cable-car device on the bottom right hand side moved a dummy wasp (L×W×H: 40×15×15 mm) at constant velocity and direction. The dummy wasp provoked shimmering waves which spread in a complex, repetitive pattern. The nest was situated 1 m in front of, and parallel to the back wall. The black-and-white marker with double circles on the wall in the back is 6 mm in diameter. Note the mouth zone on the bottom right hand side of the nest. The waves were generated on the left side of the mouth zone. A LED was installed on the left bottom side for triggering additional cameras and sensors. The film was recorded by a high definition camera (Panasonic DVCPRO HD) at 50 Hz.</p>
          <p>(MOV)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0036736.s005" mimetype="video/quicktime" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Movie S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>This movie shows the same film session as displayed in movie 1, but recorded with one of the high resolution black and white cameras at 60 Hz and from another viewing angle.</p>
          <p>(MOV)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0036736.s006" mimetype="video/quicktime" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0036736.s006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Movie S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>This movie shows the same film session as displayed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0036736.s005">movie S2</xref>. A single surface bee, identified as <italic>focus bee</italic> 20 (red closed circle marking the thorax) was selected for measurement of the movement strength <sub>rel</sub>XYmov. The red dot in the lower graph marks the relative observation time, and the <sub>rel</sub>XYmov values show the motion of the <italic>focus bees</italic>. Time zero of the wave incident of the <italic>focus bee</italic> was defined one frame before the onset of movement activity. Two wave incidents are displayed in this session. Note that there are damped oscillations due to the mechanical resonance effect of the bee curtain. The recording frequency was 60 Hz.</p>
          <p>(MOV)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Dr. Madhu Singh, Dr. S.M. Man, Dr. R. Thapa and Dr. M. B. Gewali from the Tribhuvan University, Kathmandu, for their support regarding logistics, Klaus Maresch, Bonn for his help with handling of the bees in Chitwan, and Horst Bischof and Mathias Rüther from the Technical University of Graz, Austria, for support with the development of the specific software used for this study.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Ruttner1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruttner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Biogeography and Taxonomy of Honeybees.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Springer Verlag</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Hepburn1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hepburn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hepburn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Bibliography of the Giant honeybees, <italic>Apis dorsata Fabricius</italic> (1793) and <italic>Apis laboriosa</italic> F. Smith (1871) Apidologie</article-title>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>219</fpage>             <lpage>220</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Roepke1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roepke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1930</year>             <article-title>Beobachtungen an indischen Honigbienen, insbesondere an <italic>Apis dorsata</italic>.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Wageningen</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>H. Veenman&amp;Zonen</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Lindauer1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1956</year>             <article-title>Über die Verständigung bei indischen Bienen.</article-title>             <source>Zeitschrift für vergleichende Physiologie</source>             <volume>Bd.38</volume>             <fpage>521</fpage>             <lpage>557</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Sakagami1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakagami</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1960</year>             <article-title>Preliminary report on the specific difference of behavior and other ecological characters between European and Japanese honeybees.</article-title>             <source>Acta Hymenoptera</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>171</fpage>             <lpage>198</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Seeley1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aratanakul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>Colony defence strategies of the honeybees in Thailand.</article-title>             <source>Ecological monographs</source>             <volume>52</volume>             <fpage>43</fpage>             <lpage>63</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Kastberger1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmelzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kranner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Social waves in Giant honeybees repel hornets.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <issue>9</issue>             <fpage>e3141</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Koeniger1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koeniger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1975</year>             <article-title>Zur Kolonieverteidigung der asiatischen Honigbienen.</article-title>             <source>Tierpsychologie</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>99</fpage>             <lpage>106</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Kastberger2">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raspotnig</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winder</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Evidence of Nasonov scenting in colony defence of the Giant honeybee <italic>Apis dorsata</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Ethology</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>27</fpage>             <lpage>37</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Schmelzer1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmelzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>“Special agents” trigger social waves in Giant honeybees (<italic>Apis dorsata</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Naturwissenschaften</source>             <volume>96</volume>             <fpage>1431</fpage>             <lpage>1441</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Camazine1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camazine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deneubourg</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sneyd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theraula</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <source>Self-organization in biological systems New Jersey: Princeton University Press</source>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Camazine2">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camazine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sneyd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>A model of collective nectar source selection by honey bees: self-organization through simple rules.</article-title>             <source>J Theor Biol</source>             <volume>149</volume>             <fpage>547</fpage>             <lpage>571</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Pasteels1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pasteels</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deneubourg</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>Self-organization mechanisms in ant societies [I]: trail recruitment to newly discovered food sources.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>In From individual to Collective Behavior in Social Insects. Edited by</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Pasteels JM, Deneubourg JL. Basel: Birkhauser Verlag</publisher-name>             <fpage>155</fpage>             <lpage>175</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Kastberger3">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weihmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoetzl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Self-Assembly Processes in Honeybees: The Phenomenon of Shimmering.</article-title>             <source>In Honeybees of Asia Edited by: Hepburn R, Radcliff S Chapter</source>             <volume>18</volume>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Procaccini1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Procaccini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orlandi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavagna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giardina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoratto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Propagating waves in starling, <italic>Sturnus vulgaris</italic>, flocks under predation.</article-title>             <source>Animal Behaviour</source>             <volume>82</volume>             <fpage>759</fpage>             <lpage>765</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Kastberger4">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weihmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruether</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoetzl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Stereoscopic motion analysis in densely packed clusters: 3D analysis of the shimmering behaviour in Giant honey bees.</article-title>             <source>Frontiers in Zoology</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>3</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Kastberger5">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weihmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoetzl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Transmittance of the mechanical impulses of shimmering waves through the central comb of the nest in Giant honeybees (<italic>Apis dorsata</italic>).</article-title>             <publisher-name>In preparation</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Phillips1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1977</year>             <source>The dynamics of the upper ocean Cambridge University Press, USA</source>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Holthuijsen1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holthuijsen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Waves in oceanic and coastal waters.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Morse1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laigo</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1969</year>             <article-title><italic>Apis dorsata</italic> in the Phillippines.</article-title>             <publisher-name>Phillip Assoc Entomol</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Farkas1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helbing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vicsek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Social behaviour: Mexican waves in an excitable medium.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>419</volume>             <fpage>131</fpage>             <lpage>132</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Kastberger6">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weihmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoetzl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2012</year>             <article-title>Transient mechanisms in the propagation of the shimmering waves in Giant honeybees.</article-title>             <publisher-name>In preparation</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Born1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Born</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <source>Principles of Optics, 7th edition, Cambridge University</source>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Kastberger7">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>The Magic Trees of Assam - Documentary film about the biology of the Giant honeybee <italic>Apis dorsata</italic>.</article-title>             <publisher-name>National Geographic, ZDF, ORF epo-film Wien</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Kastberger8">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winder</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hötzl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raspotnig</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Behavioural features of a periodic form of massed flight activity in the Giant honeybee <italic>Apis dorsata</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Apidologie</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>381</fpage>             <lpage>395</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Woyke1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woyke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Comparison of Defense Body Movements <italic>of Apis laboriosa, Apis dorsata dorsata</italic> and <italic>Apis dorsata breviligula</italic> Honey Bees.</article-title>             <source>J Insect Behav</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>481</fpage>             <lpage>494</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Wheatstone1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheatstone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1838</year>             <article-title>Contributions to the physiology of Vision - part the first. On some remarkable, and hitherto unobserved, phenomena of binocular vision.</article-title>             <source>Philosophical Transactions</source>             <volume>128</volume>             <fpage>371</fpage>             <lpage>394</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Freixenet1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freixenet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muñoz</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raba</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martí</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cufí</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Yet Another Survey on Image Segmentation: Region and Boundary Information Integration.</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the 7th European Conference on Computer Vision-Part III, LNCS</source>             <volume>2352</volume>             <fpage>408</fpage>             <lpage>422</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Scharstein1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scharstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szeliski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>A taxonomy and evaluation of dense two-frame stereo correspondence algorithms.</article-title>             <source>International Journal of Computer Vision</source>             <volume>47</volume>             <fpage>7</fpage>             <lpage>42</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Zureiki1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zureiki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatila</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Stereo Matching using Reduced-Graph Cuts. Proceedings Int. Conf.</article-title>             <source>on Image Processing</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>237</fpage>             <lpage>240</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Hartley1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zisserman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <source>Multiple View Geometry in Computer Vision Cambridge: Cambridge University Press</source>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Faugeras1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faugeras</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <source>Three-Dimensional Computer Vision Cambridge: The MIT Press</source>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Butani1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butani</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1950</year>             <article-title>An <italic>Apis dorsata</italic> colony in New Delhi.</article-title>             <source>Indian Bee J</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>115</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Butler1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1962</year>             <article-title>The world of the honeybee.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Collins</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Kastberger9">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weihmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoetzl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Complex social waves of Giant honeybees provoked by a dummy wasp support the special-agent hypothesis.</article-title>             <source>Communicative &amp; Integrative Biology</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <issue>2</issue>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>2</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Weihmann1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weihmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoetzl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Training for defence: the transition from stochasticity to synchronization of collective behaviours in Giant honeybees (<italic>Apis dorsata</italic>) [abstract]. DGaaE.</article-title>             <source>Annual Meeting S</source>             <volume>89</volume>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Krebs1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>Behavioural Ecology.</article-title>             <publisher-name>An Evolutionary Approach. Sinauer Associates, Sunderland, Massachusetts</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Partridge1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>The structure and function of fish schools.</article-title>             <source><italic>Scientific American</italic></source>             <volume>246</volume>             <fpage>114</fpage>             <lpage>123</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Potts1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>The chorus-line hypothesis of manoeuvre coordination in avian flocks.</article-title>             <source><italic>Nature</italic></source>             <volume>309</volume>             <fpage>344</fpage>             <lpage>345</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Lloyd1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1979</year>             <article-title>Sexual selection in luminescent beetles.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>InMS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lum</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>eds</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selection</surname><given-names>Sexual</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Insects</surname><given-names>ReproductiveCompetitionin</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>pp.293–342</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Otte1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smiley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1977</year>             <article-title>Synchrony in Texas fireflies with a consideration of male interaction model.</article-title>             <source><italic>Biology of Behaviour</italic></source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>143</fpage>             <lpage>158</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Buck1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1976</year>             <article-title>Synchronous fireflies.</article-title>             <source><italic>Scientific American</italic></source>             <volume>234</volume>             <issue>5</issue>             <fpage>74</fpage>             <lpage>85</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Treherne1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Treherne</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Group transmission of predator avoidance in a marine insect: the Trafalgar Effect.</article-title>             <source><italic>Animal Behaviour</italic></source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>911</fpage>             <lpage>917</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Bradbury1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1983</year>             <article-title>Leks and mate choice.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateson</surname><given-names>InP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>ed</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choice</surname><given-names>Mate</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>109–138</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Gibson1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1986</year>             <article-title>Male and female strategies on sage grouse leks.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>InDI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wrangham</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>eds</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evolution</surname><given-names>EcologicalAspectsofSocial</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>379–398</source>             <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0036736-Klabunde1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klabunde</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title><italic>Cardiovascular physiology concepts</italic>.</article-title>             <publisher-name>Chapter 2 “Electrical activity of the heart”. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>