<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-47458</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087781</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Renal system</subject><subj-group><subject>Drug excretion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunity</subject><subj-group><subject>Inflammation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Escherichia coli</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunity</subject><subj-group><subject>Inflammation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Model organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal models</subject><subj-group><subject>Chicken</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Renal system</subject><subj-group><subject>Drug excretion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Drugs and devices</subject><subj-group><subject>Pharmacokinetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Drug absorption</subject><subject>Drug distribution</subject><subject>Drug excretion</subject><subject>Drug metabolism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gastroenterology and hepatology</subject><subj-group><subject>Stomach and duodenum</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Escherichia coli</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Veterinary science</subject><subj-group><subject>Veterinary diseases</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Veterinary medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Veterinary pharmacology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title><italic>E. coli</italic> Infection Modulates the Pharmacokinetics of Oral Enrofloxacin by Targeting P-Glycoprotein in Small Intestine and CYP450 3A in Liver and Kidney of Broilers</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Infection Affects Enrofloxacin Pharmacokinetics</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Mengjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bughio</surname><given-names>Shamsuddin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Xiaohua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Weilong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Liping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Laboratory of Veterinary Pharmacology and Toxicology, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, PR China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>College of Food Science and Pharmacy, Xinjiang Agricultural University, Urumqi, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassaganya-Riera</surname><given-names>Josep</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Virginia Tech, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">wlp71@163.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LW. Performed the experiments: MG YS SB. Analyzed the data: MG WR. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MG YZ XD. Wrote the paper: LW MG.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<elocation-id>e87781</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Guo et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>P-glycoprotein (P-gp) expression determines the absorption, distribution, metabolism and excretion of many drugs in the body. Also, up-regulation of P-gp acts as a defense mechanism against acute inflammation. This study examined expression levels of <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA and localization of P-gp protein in the liver, kidney, duodenum, jejunum and ileum in healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers by real time RT-PCR and immunohistochemistry. Meanwhile, pharmacokinetics of orally administered enrofloxacin was also investigated in healthy and infected broilers by HPLC. The results indicated that <italic>E. coli</italic> infection up-regulated expression of <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA levels significantly in the kidney, jejunum and ileum (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05), but not significantly in the liver and duodenum (<italic>P</italic>&gt;0.05). However, the expression level of <italic>CYP 3A37</italic> mRNA were observed significantly decreased only in liver and kidney of <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) compared with healthy birds. Furthermore, the infection reduced absorption of orally administered enrofloxacin, significantly decreased C<sub>max</sub> (0.34 vs 0.98 µg mL<sup>−1</sup>, <italic>P</italic> = 0.000) and AUC<sub>0-12h</sub> (4.37 vs 8.88 µg mL<sup>−1</sup> h, <italic>P</italic> = 0.042) of enrofloxacin, but increased T<sub>max</sub> (8.32 vs 3.28 h, <italic>P</italic> = 0.040), T<sub>1/2a</sub>(2.66 vs 1.64 h<sup>−1</sup>, <italic>P</italic> = 0.050) and V/F (26.7 vs 5.2 L, <italic>P</italic> = 0.040). Treatment with verapamil, an inhibitor of P-gp, significantly improved the absorption of enrofloxacin in both healthy and infected broilers. The results suggest that the <italic>E. coli</italic> infection induces intestine P-gp expression, altering the absorption of orally administered enrofloxacin in broilers.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The study was supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 30972220), Natural Science Foundation of Jiangsu Province of China (No. BK2012771), the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (KYZ201105), and the Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions (PAPD). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Colibacillosis is a common disease in poultry, affecting the growth of broilers and also the physiological function of the small intestine in the chickens. Fluoroquinolones have been successfully used to treat colibacillosis in poultry, among which enrofloxacin is most frequently applied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Haritova1">[1]</xref>. Pharmacokinetic studies of enrofloxacin, which were performed in pets and food-producing animals under healthy conditions via various routes of administration, show that enrofloxacin exhibits good absorption, high bioavailability, large volume of distribution and low protein-binding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Bregante1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Elmas1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Cox1">[4]</xref>. Enrofloxacin is metabolized to ciprofloxacin via de-ethylation of the ethyl group on the piperazine ring <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Tyczkowska1">[5]</xref> and mainly excreted as a parent drug and its metabolite by glomerular filtration and tubular secretion in the kidney, however, the rate of deethylation is various in different species<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Vancutsem1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-McKellar1">[7]</xref>.</p>
<p>P-glycoprotein (P-gp) is encoded by <italic>abcb1</italic> gene, and belongs to ATP-binding cassette (ABC) superfamily, which is involved in drug transport <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Sharom1">[8]</xref>. P-gp, along with CYP 450 enzymes, also plays a key role in determining the dispositions of a variety of drugs in tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Russel1">[9]</xref>. <italic>In vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> studies have demonstrated that P-gp can modulate the pharmacokinetics of human medicines, resulting in drug-drug interactions of structurally diverse compounds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Lin1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Cox2">[11]</xref>. Accumulating evidence implicates that many veterinary drugs, such as ivermectin, macrolides and fluoroquinoles, are also the substrates of P-gp <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Molento1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Pulido1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Schrickx1">[14]</xref>. Therefore, there are increasing attentions to the role of P-gp together with CYP450 in veterinary therapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Schrickx1">[14]</xref>. It is well known that the expression of ABC transport proteins is regulated by a variety of factors, including pathological conditions, and in particular inflammatory reaction to infections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Haritova1">[1]</xref>. However, it is not well understood whether modulation of their expression may subsequently affect the pharmacokinetics of drugs, altering the efficacy and toxicity of the drugs in animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Haritova1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Schrickx1">[14]</xref>. The pharmacokinetics of enrofloxacin has been extensively studied in broilers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Bugyei1">[15]</xref>, but little is known about the relationship between the pharmacokinetics of enrofloxacin and the expression levels of P-gp and CYP450 enzymes in broilers, particularly following <italic>E. coli</italic> infection.</p>
<p>The present study examined the effects of <italic>E. coli</italic> infection on the expression levels of P-gp and CYP3A (cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily A) in the liver, kidney and small intestine to clarify whether different expression levels of P-gp and CYP3A affect intestinal absorption, biliary secretion and kidney excretion of enrofloxacin in broilers. Furthermore, we investigated the influence of verapamil, an inhibitor of P-gp, on the absorption of enrofloxacin. The results indicate that <italic>E. coli</italic> infection modulates the pharmacokinetics of orally administered enrofloxacin by increasing intestinal P-gp expression and decreasing CYP3A expression in the liver and kidney of broilers.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Animals and reagents</title>
<p>Ross 308 broilers (one-day old, male and female randomly) were purchased from a local commercial poultry farm (Nanjing, China). All birds were kept at 25°C, had free access to standard commercial feed (without additives) and water, and treated following the protocol approved by Nanjing Agricultural University Animal Care and Use Committee. Before starting the experiment at the age of 4-week old, all broilers were verified free from colibacillosis. Mouse monoclonal anti-P-gp (C219) antibody, used for immunohistochemistry (IHC), was from Covance (Princeton, New Jersey, USA). Rabbit anti-mouse IgG-horseradish peroxidase (HRP) was purchased from Boster (Wuhan, Hubei, China). Verapamil was purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA) and enrofloxacin was bought from China Institute of Veterinary Drug Control. All other reagents were purchased commercially with highest quality.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title><italic>E. coli</italic> infection model</title>
<p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (<italic>E. coli</italic>) O<sub>2</sub> strain, isolated from the broilers with colibacillosis, was kindly provided by the Laboratory of the Microbiology, Nanjing Agricultural University. The strain was stored at −80°C prior to use. The day before infection, <italic>E. coli</italic> was inoculated onto LB agar and incubated at 37°C for 24 h. Then eight colonies were suspended in 10 ml of broth and incubated at 37°C for 6 h when its OD<sub>600</sub> value was about 0.6, as quantified by ultraviolet spectrophotometry. At the age of 4-week old, each broiler was given 0.5 ml of the overnight culture containing 1.5×10<sup>8</sup> colony forming units (cfu) by pectoral muscle injection. Some broilers exhibited typical clinical signs of colibacillosis, including respiratory stress, and white loose droppings within 12 h after inoculation. Tissue samples collected from the dead broilers at necropsy were then cultured to confirm that the strain used to inoculate the birds caused the mortalities. In this study, three groups of broilers were infected with <italic>E. coli</italic>, including one group for immunohistochemistry of P-gp and mRNA quantitation (<italic>abcb1</italic>), and two groups for pharmacokinetic analysis of enrofloxacin.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>RNA isolation and real-time RT-PCR</title>
<p>Real time RT-PCR was used to detect the Abcb1 and CYP3A mRNA expression levels in the liver, kidney and different parts of small intestine in healthy (n = 5) and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected (n = 5) broilers. Total RNA was isolated from individual tissues of all birds using Trizol Reagent (Takara, Tokyo, Japan) according to the manufacturer's instructions. All RNA samples were treated with 100 U DNase I (RNase Free, Takara, Tokyo, Japan) for 30 min at 37°C to ensure that the samples were free of genomic DNA contamination. The total RNA concentration was then quantified using a Nanodrop photometer (ND-1000 Spectrophotometer, Rockland, DE, USA). Ratios of the optical density (OD) values at 260/280 nm of all preparations were between 1.8 and 2.0. Each RNA sample was subjected to electrophoresis on a 1.4% agarose formaldehyde gel to verify its integrity. Single-stranded cDNAs were synthesized and real time PCR was performed, as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Li1">[16]</xref>.Negative controls involved omission of RNA from the reverse transcription reactions and amplifications with specific primer/probe sets to confirm the lack of genomic DNA contamination. Primers specific for <italic>abcb1</italic>, CYP3A and β-actin were designed as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Haritova1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Ourlin1">[17]</xref> and commercially synthesized for real-time PCR analysis. Broiler β-actin was chosen as a housekeeping gene for normalization, based on experiments showing stable expression of β-actin mRNA in the small intestine, liver and kidney of broilers. The PCR products were sequenced to validate the identity of the amplicons. The 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Livak1">[18]</xref> was used to analyze the real-time RT-PCR data.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
<p>To study the localization and semi-quantitative protein expression of P-gp in the liver and small intestine of healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers at 4-week old, immunohistochemical staining was performed as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Guo1">[19]</xref>. Briefly, the tissues from 5 healthy birds and 5 <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers were collected. The tissue-sections were prepared and incubated overnight at 4°C with the primary antibody (C219, monoclonal anti-P-gp, 1:20) and at 37°C for 1 h with the secondary antibody (rabbit anti-mouse IgG-HRP), and the P-gp immunoreactivity was visualized with DAB staining. Sections without incubation with the primary antibody served as negative controls. Three semi-quantitative measurements for P-glycoprotein staining were performed by two experimental pathologists in a double-blind analysis under a light microscope (BX45-DP72; OLYMPUS, Tokyo, Japan) equipped with Plan Apo objectives connected to a CCD camera (U-TV0.63XC; OLYMPUS, Tokyo, Japan) as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Guo1">[19]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Experimental design for pharmacokinetic analysis of enrofloxacin in broilers</title>
<p>Forty 28-day old broilers were randomly divided into 4 groups with 10 broilers in each group in this study. Group I birds received enrofloxacin orally with single dose of 10 mg/kg b.w. through crop tube gavages. Group II was pre-treated with verapamil (15 mg/kg b.w.) orally for 30 min, followed by oral administration of enrofloxacin with single dose of 10 mg/kg b.w as previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Guo1">[19]</xref>. Group III was given with a single dose of enrofloxacin (10 mg/kg b. w) through oral administration after 12 h of <italic>E. coli</italic> challenge. Group IV, 30 min prior to enrofloxacin (10 mg/kg b. w.) oral administration, was treated with verapamil (15 mg/kg b. w.) orally following 12 h of <italic>E. coli</italic> challenge. Plasma samples for HPLC analysis were drawn in heparin tubes 20 min before and at 0.083, 0.25, 0.33, 0.5, 0.75, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8 and 12 h following enrofloxacin administration in each group. The samples were placed on ice before transporting to the laboratory and centrifuged at 1 500 g for 10 min. The centrifuged plasma was harvested and aliquot for storage at −80°C before HPLC analysis.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>HPLC assay for detection of enrofloxacin in plasma of broilers</title>
<p>The plasma concentrations of enrofloxacin were detected through Agilent 1200 high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) system as described previously with minor modification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Pulido1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Idowu1">[20]</xref>. Briefly, the blood samples thawed out at room temperature and centrifuged at 2 000 g for 5 min, the supernatant (0.5 ml) was applied to acetonitrile and the organic and water phases were separated by centrifugation. The organic phase was evaporated to dryness under a nitrogen stream and the residue was re-suspended with mobile phase solution. Twenty microliters of the mixture was injected into the HPLC column. The composition of the mobile phase was 0.1 M phosphoric acid (adjust pH to 3.0 with triethylamine)/acetonitrile (84:16, v/v). Enrofloxacin plasma concentration was determined using a Waters e2695 HPLC system (Waters, Japan). HPLC analysis was performed on Kromasil C<sub>18</sub> HPLC Columns (5 µm, 25 cm×4.6 mm). The flow rate of the mobile phase was set to 0.85 ml/min. UV absorbance was measured at 278 nm.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Pharmacokinetic analysis</title>
<p>Pharmacokinetic calculations were performed on each individual set of data using 3p97 practical pharmacokinetic software (Version97, Chinese Pharmacologic Association, Beijing, China). The best fit of compartment model was determined according to the Akaike’s Information Criterion. The area under the concentration–time curve (AUC<sub>0-12h</sub>) was calculated according to the linear trapezoidal method.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2h">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>All data were presented as mean ± S.E.M., and analyzed by one-way ANOVA using SPSS 16.0 for Windows followed by a least-significant difference (LSD) test for individual comparisons. Values of mRNA abundance were expressed as the fold change relative to the average value of one group. Pharmacokinetic parameters of enrofloxacin were analyzed using student <italic>t-</italic>test for independent samples. The significance level was set at <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Clinical observations and pathology in <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers</title>
<p>For colibacillosis model, each broiler was inoculated with 0.5 ml of <italic>E. coli</italic> culture containing 1.5×10<sup>8 </sup>cfu/ml by pectoral muscle injection. We found that within 12 h of inoculation, two broilers died of the infection and others showed clinical signs at different degrees. Some broilers exhibited typical clinical signs of colibacillosis, including respiratory stress, and white loose droppings. Necropsy lesions showed a layer of white cellulose pseudo-membranous covering the surface of the liver and heart. Also, severe bleeding and swelling were observed in most segments of the small intestine except duodenum. <italic>E. coli</italic> was also isolated in liver from the diseased birds.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>mRNA expression levels of <italic>abcb1</italic> and <italic>CYP 3A37</italic> in liver, kidney and small intestines in healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers</title>
<p>The expression level of P-gp encoding gene <italic>abcb1</italic> and <italic>CYP 3A37</italic> were detected by real time PCR with β-actin chosen as a housekeeping gene for normalization. Compared with the healthy group, the <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA level in the kidney and small intestines was up-regulated after <italic>E. coli</italic> infection. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087781-g001">Fig.1A</xref>, <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA was detected at significantly higher levels in kidney (<italic>P</italic> = 0.032), jejunum (<italic>P</italic> = 0.017) and ileum (<italic>P</italic> = 0.046) of infected birds than that of healthy broilers, whereas the mRNA levels in duodenum (<italic>P</italic> = 0.349) and liver (<italic>P</italic> = 0.264) were not significantly changed in <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers, though an increasing trend was observed. In different tissues of infected broilers, the highest level of <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA was observed in ileum, and followed by jejunum, liver, kidney and duodenum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087781-g001">Fig.1B</xref>). However, the expression level of <italic>CYP 3A37</italic> were observed significantly decreased only in liver and kidney of <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers compared with healthy birds, which was in contrast with the pattern of <italic>abcb1</italic> expression level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087781-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). In each tested tissues, infection sharply decreased CYP <italic>3A37</italic> and the level of CYP <italic>3A37</italic> in liver even lower than that of small intestine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087781-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0087781-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Expression levels of <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA in broilers by real time RT PCR (n = 5).</title>
<p>A: Differences of <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA level in liver, jejunum, ileum and duodenum between healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers; B: Comparison of <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA level in different tissues of infected broilers. β-actin was used as a reference gene for normalization. All data were presented as mean ± S.E.M. and analyzed by one-way ANOVA using SPSS 16.0 for Windows followed by a least-significant difference (LSD) test for individual comparisons. * <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, ** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0087781-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Expression levels of <italic>CYP3A37</italic> mRNA in broilers by real time RT PCR (n = 5).</title>
<p>A: Differences of <italic>CYP3A37</italic> mRNA level in liver, jejunum, ileum and duodenum between healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers; B: Comparison of <italic>CYP3A37</italic> mRNA level in different tissues of infected broilers. β-actin was used as a reference gene for normalization. The results were expressed as the mean ± S.E.M. and analyzed by one-way ANOVA using SPSS 16.0 for Windows followed by a least-significant difference (LSD) test for individual comparisons. * <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, ** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Effect of <italic>E. coli</italic> infection on P-gp localization and expression</title>
<p>To date, there are no reports on the effects of <italic>E. coli</italic> infection on the localization and expression level of P-gp in the small intestine, liver and kidney. In this study, IHC method was used to determine the localization and expression level of P-gp in broilers. The results showed that no background staining was observed in the negative controls (data not shown). Positive staining was detected in liver, kidney, jejunum and ileum of healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected birds as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087781-g003">Fig.3</xref>. In healthy birds, immunoreactivity of P-gp was both visualized on the apical surface of the enterocytes of ileum and jejunum, while in infected broilers, positive staining of P-gp remained localized in the membrane of the enterocytes but the intensity was significantly increased. Remarkable P-gp immunostaining was observed in the bile canalicular membranes of the hepatocytes in healthy broilers. However, P-gp was internalized into the cytoplasm away from the biliary membrane in liver from <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers. Similarly in kidney, the main staining was observed in the apical plasma membranes of proximal tubule cells of healthy broilers, but a punctuate labeling for P-gp was distributed widely throughout the cytoplasm in the kidneys of infected broilers. To validate our immunohistochemical results, we semi-quantified the stained liver, kidneys and small intestines from healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers using Image-Pro Plus 4.1 software. For each experimental group, IOD, positive area and score for 25 samples from each bird was analyzed, and a comparison was made between the average values obtained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087781-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). Compared with healthy birds in control group, <italic>E. coli</italic> infection treatment significantly enhanced (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) P-gp staining of jejunum and ileum via IOD, positive area and scores evaluation. Though the total P-gp level was increased in liver and kidney, the level in the bile canalicular membranes and apical plasma membranes of proximal tubule cells was not significantly changed via IOD, positive area and score estimates. In kidney, the area of positive staining was enhanced, but IOD and score were not changed. Quantification of P-gp staining in intestine provided additional validity to our studies at protein level, which was coincident with the trend of changes in mRNA expression changes between healthy and infected birds.</p>
<fig id="pone-0087781-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Immunohistochemical staining of P-glycoprotein in different tissues of healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers.</title>
<p>Mouse monoclonal anti-P-gp antibody (C219) was used to detect P-gp. These figures are representatives of typical samples from 5 broilers in each group. The arrow showed the positive staining of P-gp. Magnifications are indicated by bar.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0087781-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Semi-quantification of P-gp in both healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers.</title>
<p>The intensity of specific P-gp staining was evaluated by measuring the IOD, area of positive staining and scores of its expression respectively. Digital images of five sections from each broiler of the surface epithelium area were evaluated. Each section was divided into five sub-areas, and the IOD and positive area of the staining was analyzed using the Image-Pro Plus 4.1. software and scores were analyzed from 0 to 4 to estimate the positive staining in different areas under study.*<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, *<italic>*P</italic>&lt;0.01.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Pharmacokinetics of orally administered enrofloxacin in infected and healthy broilers</title>
<p>To further confirm whether P-gp and CYP3A expression levels are the main factors affecting the pharmacokinectics of enrofloxacin in broilers after infection, both infected and healthy broilers were administered a single dose of enrofloxacin orally. Following oral administration, a one-compartment open model was found to best fit concentration-time data of enrofloxacin. The plasma concentration <italic>vs</italic> time curves for enrofloxacin are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087781-g005">Fig.5A</xref>. Pharmacokinetic parameters of enrofloxacin in broilers before and after inoculation of <italic>E. coli</italic> are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087781-t001">Table 1</xref>. Lower plasma concentrations of enrofloxacin were found in infected broilers. Compared to healthy broilers, infected ones were observed with significantly decreased <italic>C<sub>max</sub></italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.000) and <italic>AUC<sub>0-12h</sub></italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.042, absorptive phase) as well as obviously longer <italic>T<sub>max</sub></italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.040)and <italic>T<sub>1/2a</sub></italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.045), indicating that the absorption of enrofloxacin was slower and inhibited. Consistent with these findings, higher mRNA expression of P-gp was observed in the small intestine in broilers after <italic>E. coli</italic> infection. However, infected birds demonstrated lowered <italic>Cl/F</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.038) but higher <italic>T<sub>1/2e</sub></italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.000) and volume of distribution (<italic>P</italic> = 0.040), compared with healthy birds, suggesting that the clearance of enrofloxacin was also inhibited by <italic>E. coli</italic> infection.</p>
<fig id="pone-0087781-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Mean plasma enrofloxacin concentrations in broilers after enrofloxacin administration.</title>
<p>A: enrofloxacin alone by single oral administration (10 mg/kg) to healthy (n = 10) and infected (n = 10) broilers; B: enrofloxacin after a single oral administration of 10 mg/kg alone (n = 10) and co-administration of verapamil (15 mg/kg, n = 10) to <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers C: enrofloxacin after a single oral administration of 10 mg/kg alone (n = 10) and co-administration of verapamil (15 mg/kg, n = 10) to healthy broilers. Each point represents the mean ±S.E.M. of 10 broilers.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0087781-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Parameters of oral enrofloxacin in healthy and infected broilers (mean ± S.E.M., n = 10).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0087781-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy broilers</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infected broilers</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ke (h<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21±0.007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024±0.003<sup>**</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ka (h<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43±0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46±0.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.851</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<italic><sub>1/2a</sub></italic> (h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64±0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66±0.88<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<italic><sub>1/2e</sub></italic> (h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36±0.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6±1.69<sup>**</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>max</sub> (h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28±0.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1±0.91<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>max</sub> (µg mL<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98±0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34±0.04<sup>**</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC<sub>0-12h</sub> (µg mL<sup>−1</sup> h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.88±0.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37±0.82<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V/F (L)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2±0.18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7±4.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cl</italic>/F (mL/min)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08±0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6±0.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>*</label><p><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, ** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01 significant difference vs. healthy broliers. <italic>K<sub>e:</sub></italic>,elimination rate constant; <italic>K<sub>a</sub></italic>, absorption rate constant; <italic>t</italic><sub>1/2a</sub>, the absorption half-life; <italic>t</italic><sub>1/2e</sub>, the elimination half-life; T<sub>max</sub>, the time to reach peak concentration; C<sub>max</sub>, the peak concentration; AUC<sub>0-12h</sub>, the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from zero to 12h; V/F, volume of distribution/F, where F is the faction of dose absorbed; Cl/F, Clearance/F, where F is the faction of dose absorbed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Effect of verapamil on pharmacokinetics of orally administered enrofloxacin</title>
<p>To investigate whether <italic>E. coli</italic> infection modulates the pharmacokinetics of oral enrofloxacin by targeting the intestinal P-glycoprotein expression, the pharmacokinetics of enrofloxacin was also studied after exposure to verapamil (a potent and selective inhibitor of P-gp inhibitor) for 30 min in both healthy and infected groups. The plasma concentration of enrofloxacin in the presence or absence of oral verapamil (15 mg/kg b.w.) was measured after oral administration of enrofloxacin (10 mg/kg). The plasma concentration-time profiles are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087781-g005">Fig.5B and 5C</xref>. According to the pharmacokinetic parameters presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087781-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087781-t003">3</xref>, verapamil showed a non-negligible effect on the pharmacokinetic of enrofloxacin. After treated with verapamil, C<sub>max</sub> (1.46- and 2.94-fold) and AUC <sub>0-12h</sub> (1.33-fold and 2.39-fold) of enrofloxacin increased in healthy and infected broilers, respectively. Meanwhile, the T<sub>max</sub> of enrofloxacin was significantly short and Ka of enrofloxacin was significantly higher when P-gp was inhibited with verapamil. The plasma concentration of enrofloxacin was altered in both healthy and <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers, which was prevented by verapamil, indicating that the absorption was P-gp-dependent.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0087781-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Parameters of oral enrofloxacin in healthy broilers with and without verapamil (mean±S.E.M., n = 10).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0087781-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENRO</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENRO+VER</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ke (h<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21±0.007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09±0.01<sup>**</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ka (h<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43±0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02±0.17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>1/2a</sub> (h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64±0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79±0.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>1/2e</sub> (h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36±0.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.43±1.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>max</sub> (h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28±0.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86±0.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.429</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>max</sub> (µg mL<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98±0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43±0.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC<sub>0-12h</sub> (µg mL<sup>−1</sup> h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.88±0.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.79±1.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V/F</italic>( L )</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2±0.18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.98±0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.466</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cl</italic>/F(mL/min)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08±0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51±0.03<sup>**</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label>*</label><p><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01 significant difference between parameters of enrofloxacin in the presence and absence of verapamil in healthy broilers.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0087781-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Parameters of oral enrofloxacin in infected broilers with and without verapamil (mean±S.E.M., n = 10).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0087781-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087781.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENRO</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENRO+VER</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ke (h<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024±0.003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1±0.009<sup>**</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ka (h<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46±0.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88±0.13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>1/2a</sub> (h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66±0.88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95±0.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.273</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>1/2e</sub> (h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6±1.69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.92±0.73<sup>**</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>max</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1±0.91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13±0.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>max</sub> (µg mL<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34±0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0±0.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC<sub>0-12h</sub> (µg mL<sup>−1</sup> h)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37±0.82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.43±0.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V/F</italic>( L )</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7±4.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.12±2.83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cl</italic>/F (mL/min)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6±0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21±0.27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label>*</label><p><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01 significant difference between parameters of enrofloxacin in the presence and absence of verapamil in infected broilers.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study, we focused on clarifying whether <italic>E. coli</italic> infection affects the pharmacokinetic parameters of enrofloxacin by modifying P-gp expression levels in the tissues of 4-week old broilers. The main finding of the present study is that <italic>E. coli</italic> infection resulted in an increased expression of <italic>abcb1</italic> and P-gp in the small intestine and kidney. The observed changes in the expression level of P-gp mRNA/protein suggest that <italic>E. coli</italic> infection affected P-gp expression at the transcriptional and translation levels. Likely, <italic>E. coli</italic> infection-induced change in the absorption of enrofloxacin was due to increased expression of P-gp in the small intestine. This is also supported by the data that decreased C<sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>0-12h</sub> of enrofloxacin in <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers was paralleled to increased <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA and P-gp protein in jejunum and ileum. The decrease in plasma level of enrofloxacin was especially evident shortly after enrofloxacin administration, suggesting that the intestinal uptake was inhibited. Though the absorption of enrofloxacin declined, volume of distribution increased and terminal half-life became longer, which might be associated with decreased CYP<sub>450</sub> level or attenuated function of P-gp in liver and kidney, leading to decreased clearance of enrofloxacin in infected birds compared with healthy ones.</p>
<p>Injection of bacterial lipopolysaccharide (LPS) is a widely used model of inflammation and is well characterized regarding its effect on P-gp expression. LPS-medicated induction of pro-inflammatory cytokines activates a variety of cell signaling molecules, including c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) and nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κB) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Ghose1">[21]</xref>. Activation of JNK leads to suppression of pregnane X receptor (PXR) and constitutive androstane receptor (CAR), and subsequently their target genes including <italic>abcb1</italic> and <italic>CYP450</italic> are rapidly and significantly repressed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Ghose2">[22]</xref>. Our results showed that <italic>E. coli</italic> infection up-regulated P-gp expression in broilers, which is much different from that in mammals where LPS induced down-regulation of P-gp during the acute phase response via nuclear receptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Cherrington1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Moriguchi1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Tomita1">[25]</xref>. Possibly, this is due to the different types of inflammation inducers used (LPS vs. <italic>E. coli</italic> bacteria); <italic>E. coli</italic> may induce more cytokines mediating more cell signaling pathways. It has been pointed out that LPS is not a generic substitute for bacterial infection to study its effect on P-gp expression, function and on drug pharmacokinetics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Post1">[26]</xref>. Alternatively, this might be due to different species used (chickens vs. rats). Till now, there are few studies available about <italic>E. coli</italic> infection or LPS on the P-gp expression in poultry. Clearly, further research is required to address this issue. Nevertheless, our results are in line with other findings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Moriguchi1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Tomita1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Post1">[26]</xref>. It has been described that tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) induces <italic>bAbcb1</italic>mRNA and protein in mammary epithelial monolayer and BME-UV cells as well as in mice, and Shiga-like toxin II increases P-gp expression in mouse brain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Zhao1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Quesnell1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-AlBataineh1">[29]</xref>. This increase involves signaling through the TNF-R1 receptor, ETA and ETB receptors, NOS, PKC and the transcription factor NF-κB <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Moriguchi1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Tomita1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Post1">[26]</xref>. Taken together, our and other findings suggest novel signaling pathways through which inflammation can up-regulate P-gp expression and activity.</p>
<p>The increase in the levels of <italic>abcb1</italic> by <italic>E. coli</italic> infection following therapy was likely to reflect a beneficial effect on the bird, as this up-regulation might improve the barrier function of the gastro-intestinal tract through effluxing toxins, including LPS, and enhance the resistance against further infections by viruses and bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Panwala1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Lee1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Raviv1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Schwab1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Leslie1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Crowe1">[35]</xref>. However, meanwhile, induction of intestinal P-gp by <italic>E. coli</italic> infection also reduced absorption of orally administered enrofloxacin. Therefore, when antimicrobial agents are used in clinics to treat <italic>E. coli</italic> infections, both of the above two aspects should be taken into consideration in order to reach effective concentrations of the drugs in animal body.</p>
<p>We found that the efflux rate of enrofloxacin through bile canalicular and tubular secretion was not paralleled to up-regulation trend of <italic>abcb1</italic> mRNA in liver and kidney in infected broilers based on the longer half-life time and volume of distribution (7.32- and 5.13-fold more than that of healthy birds, respectively). The present experiments were designed to test the hypothesis that loss of P-gp transport activity of bile canaliculus and tubule is accompanied by a shift in transporter protein from the luminal membrane to a compartment where it can no longer function as an efflux transporter. Therefore, we further detected the expression of P-gp and its localization using IHC method. The images showed that P-gp was internalized into the cytoplasm away from the biliary membrane in the liver and apical plasma membranes of proximal tubule in the kidney of <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers but not in healthy birds (showed by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087781-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). This indicated that <italic>E. coli</italic> infection might have adversely affected protein trafficking as P-gp went to the cell surface or led to mislocalization of P-gp on the plasma membrane, resulting in a reduced capacity to transport substrate. The result was similar to the finding that LPS can induce the translocation of MRP2 from the canalicular membrane into cytoplasmic membrane vesicles by failure to anchor properly the membrane protein to the cytoskeleton, resulting in mislocalization in the cell membrane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Elferink1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Apodaca1">[37]</xref>. Recent reports also reveal that the mechanism of rapid loss of P-gp activity in response to TNF-α/PKCbI or VEGF/Src <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> is posttranslational and dependent on protein phosphorylation-based signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Hawkins1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087781-Rigor1">[39]</xref>. However, it remains unclear why the P-gp localization in the enterocytes of small intestine is not changed in response to <italic>E. coli</italic> infection.</p>
<p>In summary, here, for the first time, we showed that <italic>E. coli</italic> infection increased mRNA and P-gp expression in the intestine, but decreased CYP3A expression in the liver and kidney in broilers. Consequently, this modulated the pharmacokinetics of enrofloxacin in broilers. The findings provide strong evidence that it is essential to optimize the usage and dosage of enrofloxacin in <italic>E. coli</italic> infected broilers for a better treatment of colibacillosis. Also, from the present study, we should be aware that a healthy animal model cannot substitute for an infection animal model to evaluate the pharmacokinetics of enrofloxacin in broilers.</p>
</sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors would like to thank Prof. Zhang Shuxia, who is a specialist in pathology in Nanjing Agricultural University, for the kind instruction in immunohistochemistry. We also thank all other laboratory members for their kind assistance during the collection of blood samples.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Haritova1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haritova</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rusenova</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rusenov</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schrickx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lashev</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Effects of fluoroquinolone treatment on MDR1 and MRP2 mRNA expression in Escherichia coli-infected chickens</article-title>. <source>Avian Pathol</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Bregante1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bregante</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aramayona</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fraile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Comparative pharmacokinetics of enrofloxacin in mice, rats, rabbits, sheep, and cows</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1111</fpage>–<lpage>1116</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Elmas1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elmas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tras</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bas</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yazar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Pharmacokinetics of enrofloxacin after intravenous and intramuscular administration in Angora goats</article-title>. <source>Can J Vet Res</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Cox1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papich</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frazier</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Allometric analysis of ciprofloxacin and enrofloxacin pharmacokinetics across species</article-title>. <source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Tyczkowska1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyczkowska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedeen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aucoin</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aronson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>High-performance liquid chromatographic method for the simultaneous determination of enrofloxacin and its primary metabolite ciprofloxacin in canine serum and prostatic tissue</article-title>. <source>J Chromatogr</source> <volume>493</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Vancutsem1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vancutsem</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babish</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwark</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>The fluoroquinolone antimicrobials: structure, antimicrobial activity, pharmacokinetics, clinical use in domestic animals and toxicity</article-title>. <source>Cornell Vet</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-McKellar1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKellar</surname><given-names>QA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benchaoui</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Avermectins and milbemycins</article-title>. <source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Sharom1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharom</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>ABC multidrug transporters: structure, function and role in chemoresistance</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenomics</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Russel1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Russel FGM (2010) Transporters: Importance in Drug Absorption, Distribution, and Removal. 27–49.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Lin1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Role of P-glycoprotein in pharmacokinetics: clinical implications</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Cox2"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eddington</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Effect of P-glycoprotein on the pharmacokinetics and tissue distribution of enaminone anticonvulsants: analysis by population and physiological approaches</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source> <volume>302</volume>: <fpage>1096</fpage>–<lpage>1104</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Molento1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molento</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lifschitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sallovitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lanusse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Influence of verapamil on the pharmacokinetics of the antiparasitic drugs ivermectin and moxidectin in sheep</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Pulido1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pulido</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mendoza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Interaction of enrofloxacin with breast cancer resistance protein (BCRP/ABCG2): influence of flavonoids and role in milk secretion in sheep</article-title>. <source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Schrickx1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrickx</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fink-Gremmels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Implications of ABC transporters on the disposition of typical veterinary medicinal products</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source> <volume>585</volume>: <fpage>510</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Bugyei1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bugyei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Pharmacokinetics of enrofloxacin given by the oral, intravenous and intramuscular routes in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Can J Vet Res</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Li1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grossmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Leptin stimulates hepatic activation of thyroid hormones and promotes early posthatch growth in the chicken</article-title>. <source>Comp Biochem Physiol A Mol Integr Physiol</source> <volume>160</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Ourlin1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ourlin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baader</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halpert</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cloning and functional expression of a first inducible avian cytochrome P450 of the CYP3A subfamily (CYP3A37)</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source> <volume>373</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Livak1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Guo1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bughio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Age-Related P-Glycoprotein Expression in the Intestine and Affecting the Pharmacokinetics of Orally Administered Enrofloxacin in Broilers</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e74150</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Idowu1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Idowu</surname><given-names>OR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peggins</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Simple, rapid determination of enrofloxacin and ciprofloxacin in bovine milk and plasma by high-performance liquid chromatography with fluorescence detection</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Biomed Anal</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Ghose1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghose</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vallejo</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Differential role of Toll-interleukin 1 receptor domain-containing adaptor protein in Toll-like receptor 2-mediated regulation of gene expression of hepatic cytokines and drug-metabolizing enzymes</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>874</fpage>–<lpage>881</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Ghose2"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghose</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Regulation of gene expression of hepatic drug metabolizing enzymes and transporters by the Toll-like receptor 2 ligand, lipoteichoic acid</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source> <volume>481</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Cherrington1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherrington</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slitt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klaassen</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Lipopolysaccharide-mediated regulation of hepatic transporter mRNA levels in rats</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>734</fpage>–<lpage>741</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Moriguchi1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moriguchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirotani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ijiri</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Effects of lipopolysaccharide on intestinal P-glycoprotein expression and activity</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source> <volume>565</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Tomita1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanbayashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakaike</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Effect of lipopolysaccharide on P-glycoprotein-mediated intestinal and biliary excretion of rhodamine123 in rats</article-title>. <source>Int J Pharm</source> <volume>392</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Post1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The effect of endotoxin and dexamethasone on enrofloxacin pharmacokinetic parameters in swine</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source> <volume>304</volume>: <fpage>889</fpage>–<lpage>895</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Zhao1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanazawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cen</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Shiga-like toxin II modifies brain distribution of a P-glycoprotein substrate, doxorubicin, and P-glycoprotein expression in mice</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source> <volume>956</volume>: <fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Quesnell1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quesnell</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Apical electrolyte concentration modulates barrier function and tight junction protein localization in bovine mammary epithelium</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source> <volume>292</volume>: <fpage>C305</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-AlBataineh1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Bataineh</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Der Merwe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Molecular and functional identification of organic anion transporter isoforms in cultured bovine mammary epithelial cells (BME-UV)</article-title>. <source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Panwala1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panwala</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viney</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A novel model of inflammatory bowel disease: mice deficient for the multiple drug resistance gene, mdr1a, spontaneously develop colitis</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> <volume>161</volume>: <fpage>5733</fpage>–<lpage>5744</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Lee1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeang</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pastan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Effect of ABC transporters on HIV-1 infection: inhibition of virus production by the MDR1 transporter</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>516</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Raviv1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raviv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>P-glycoprotein-overexpressing multidrug-resistant cells are resistant to infection by enveloped viruses that enter via the plasma membrane</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>515</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Schwab1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tabatabaei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huwyler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Comparison of in vitro P-glycoprotein screening assays: recommendations for their use in drug discovery</article-title>. <source>J Med Chem</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1716</fpage>–<lpage>1725</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Leslie1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deeley</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Multidrug resistance proteins: role of P-glycoprotein, MRP1, MRP2, and BCRP (ABCG2) in tissue defense</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source> <volume>204</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Crowe1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bebawy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>ABCB1 (P-glycoprotein) reduces bacterial attachment to human gastrointestinal LS174T epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source> <volume>689</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Elferink1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elferink</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olinga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Draaisma</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merema</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>LPS-induced downregulation of MRP2 and BSEP in human liver is due to a posttranscriptional process</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source> <volume>287</volume>: <fpage>G1008</fpage>–<lpage>1016</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Apodaca1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Apodaca</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Endocytic traffic in polarized epithelial cells: role of the actin and microtubule cytoskeleton</article-title>. <source>Traffic</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Hawkins1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rigor</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Rapid loss of blood-brain barrier P-glycoprotein activity through transporter internalization demonstrated using a novel in situ proteolysis protection assay</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1593</fpage>–<lpage>1597</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087781-Rigor1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigor</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Activation of PKC isoform beta(I) at the blood-brain barrier rapidly decreases P-glycoprotein activity and enhances drug delivery to the brain</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1373</fpage>–<lpage>1383</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>