<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-06008</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017864</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Enzymes</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Enzyme structure</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Metabolism</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Biological transport</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Proteins</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Structural proteins</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biophysics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Protein folding</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Molecular cell biology</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Biophysics</subject>
          <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Structural Basis for Cellular Uptake of GST-Fold
                    Proteins</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Cell Entry of GSTM2-2</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Morris</surname>
            <given-names>Melanie J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Dan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Weaver</surname>
            <given-names>Llara M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Board</surname>
            <given-names>Philip G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Casarotto</surname>
            <given-names>Marco G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                        <sup>*</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
                <addr-line>The John Curtin School of Medical Research, Australian National
                    University, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Uversky</surname>
            <given-names>Vladimir</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of South Florida College of Medicine, United States of
                America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">Marco.Casarotto@anu.edu.au</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MJM PGB MGC. Performed the
                        experiments: MJM DL LMW. Analyzed the data: MJM LMW PGB MGC. Contributed
                        reagents/materials/analysis tools: PGB MGC. Wrote the manuscript: MJM PGB
                        MGC.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e17864</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Morris et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
                terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
                distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>It has recently emerged that glutathione transferase enzymes (GSTs) and other
                    structurally related molecules can be translocated from the external medium into
                    many different cell types. In this study we aim to explore in detail, the
                    structural features that govern cell translocation and by dissecting the human
                    GST enzyme GSTM2-2 we quantatively demonstrate that the α-helical C-terminal
                    domain (GST-C) is responsible for this property. Attempts to further examine the
                    constituent helices within GST-C resulted in a reduction in cell translocation
                    efficiency, indicating that the intrinsic GST-C domain structure is necessary
                    for maximal cell translocation capacity. In particular, it was noted that the
                    α-6 helix of GST-C plays a stabilising role in the fold of this domain. By
                    destabilising the conformation of GST-C, an increase in cell translocation
                    efficiency of up to ∼2-fold was observed. The structural stability profiles
                    of these protein constructs have been investigated by circular dichroism and
                    differential scanning fluorimetry measurements and found to impact upon their
                    cell translocation efficiency. These experiments suggest that the globular,
                    helical domain in the ‘GST-fold’ structural motif plays a role in
                    influencing cellular uptake, and that changes that affect the conformational
                    stability of GST-C can significantly influence cell translocation
                    efficiency.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by Grant DP0558315 Australian Research Council (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arc.gov.au/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.arc.gov.au/</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study
                    design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the
                    manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Glutathione transferases (GSTs) are an important family of enzymes that participate
                in detoxification reactions by conjugating the tripeptide glutathione (GSH) to a
                wide range of electrophilic and generally hydrophobic compounds. By doing so, toxic,
                non-polar molecules are rendered more water soluble and are ultimately exported from
                the cell through ATP-dependent Phase III transporters such as the multidrug
                resistance associated proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Hayes1">[1]</xref>. GSTs can be broadly divided into at least three
                categories that include the soluble cytoplasmic GSTs, the microsomal bound GSTs and
                a mitochondrial GST. The soluble cytoplasmic GST family is widespread across all
                organisms and consists of a large number of enzymes that can be further
                characterised into classes. Despite the relatively low sequence homology between
                some GST classes, all cytosolic GSTs share the same general structure – an
                N-terminal thioredoxin fold motif and a strongly helical C-terminal domain as shown
                in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g001">Figure 1</xref>. It must be noted
                that in addition to the GST family of enzymes, several other proteins which do not
                possess GST enzymic activity, are known to display the same structural fold
                (GST-fold) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Dulhunty1">[2]</xref>,
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Shield1">[3]</xref>.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0017864-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Structural GST-fold.</title>
          <p>Ribbon diagram demonstrating the GST-fold structure of GSTM2 complexed to
                        2,4-dinitrophenyl glutathione (not shown in figure). Note the N-terminal
                        thioredoxin fold and C-terminal α-helices. The figure was generated by
                        use of the DS modelling 1.1 program (Accelrys) from the accession bank file
                        RCSB-1XW5. The arrow denotes the cleavage site (residue 88) that separates
                        the two domains.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In an unexpected finding, it has been reported in independent studies that the
                    <italic>Schistosoma japonicum</italic> glutathione transferase (Sj.GST26)
                effectively enters cells through an energy-dependent process involving endocytosis
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Morris1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Namiki1">[5]</xref>. Furthermore, it
                was found that this phenomenon extended beyond Sj.GST26 to other classes of GST
                proteins as well as to proteins lacking GST enzyme activity but possessing a
                GST-fold. It was therefore proposed that the GST structural fold played some
                undefined role in cell entry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Morris1">[4]</xref>. The overall aim in the current study is to strategically
                dissect a typical human GST enzyme (GSTM2-2) and investigate which structural
                elements are responsible for its cell translocation properties. By targeting
                specific amino acid residues we aim to test the hypothesis that the GST-fold is
                responsible for cell translocation of these molecules. Our investigation revealed
                that entry of the C-terminal domain of GSTM2 (GST-C) into cells is responsible for
                cell translocation. Furthermore, by targeting the α6 helix of GST-C by
                site-directed mutagenesis we showed that significant gains in cell entry were
                obtained by de-stabilising the protein structure.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Proteins possessing a GST-fold structure have previously been shown to be capable of
                efficiently transfecting various cell lines and tissue types <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Morris1">[4]</xref>. Within this structural protein
                family the CLIC2 protein was shown to possess the greatest translocation efficiency,
                while the GSTM2 protein along with several other GST family members displayed
                marginally less but distinct cell translocation properties. The GSTM2 protein was
                chosen as a representative GST due to its stability, ease of expression/purification
                and for its ability to accommodate amino acid modifications <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Ross1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Tetlow1">[7]</xref>. In this study we have
                investigated the structural characteristics of GSTM2 that govern the efficiency of
                its translocation into L929 cells.</p>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>The C-terminal domain of GSTM2 is responsible for cell translocation</title>
        <p>As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g001">Figure 1</xref>, GST-fold
                    proteins are comprised of an N-terminal thioredoxin fold motif and a strongly
                    helical C-terminal domain. It was of initial interest to determine whether the
                    cell translocation properties of GSTM2 could be attributed to one of these
                    domains. In order to accurately assess the uptake of the individual N and
                    C-terminal domains of GSTM2, these fragments were recloned into the pHUE vector
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Catanzariti1">[8]</xref>,
                    expressed and purified. Unfortunately, the N-terminal thioredoxin fold proved to
                    be insoluble during expression, however the C-terminal α-helical domain
                    (GST-C) was efficiently expressed and purified. The efficiency of cell entry of
                    the Oregon Green labeled GSTM2 protein (GSTM2-OG) and its labeled C-terminal
                    fragment (GST-C-OG) are compared in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g002">Figure 2</xref>. Surprisingly, the level of internalisation of GST-C
                    exceeded that of the full length protein by a factor of at least four over a
                    three hour period.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0017864-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Cellular uptake of GSTM2-2 full length protein compared with its
                            C-terminal domain (GST-C).</title>
            <p>L-929 cells were incubated with 200 nM GSTM2-OG (◆) or 200 nM
                            GST-C-OG (■) for the indicated time periods and intracellular
                            fluorescence measured by flow cytometry. The mean cell fluorescence of
                            each sample was normalised for the degree of fluorescence labeling of
                            that protein. The data represent the mean ± SD of three
                            independent experiments.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To investigate whether the translocation of GST-C utilises the same mechanism of
                    cell entry as its parent molecule, the uptake of GST-C-OG was initially compared
                    by confocal laser scanning microscopy. After a one hour incubation period,
                    images of the Oregon Green labeled GSTM2 (Panel A) and GST-C (Panel B) revealed
                    a similar punctate pattern throughout the cytoplasm of cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g003">Figure 3a</xref>). Control
                    experiments using Oregon Green labelled BSA revealed no cell uptake (data not
                    shown). Further investigation of the mechanism of GST-C translocation was
                    performed by measuring cell uptake after treatment of cells with the known
                    endocytotic inhibitors chlorpromazine, amiloride and filipin. Chlorpromazine
                    dissociates the clathrin lattice from coated pits, amiloride prevents
                    macropinosome membrane ruffling and filipin restricts lipid raft and caveolae
                    endocytosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Orlandi1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Wang1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-West1">[11]</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g003">Figure
                        3b</xref> displays the results of endocytic inhibition of GST-C-OG uptake
                    alongside that of GSTM2-OG as well as other representative GST enzymes Sj.GST-OG
                    and GSTZ1-OG. GST-C translocation clearly follows the same trends as that of the
                    full-length GSTs, with chlorpromazine and amiloride having a negative effect on
                    the level of uptake, whilst filipin had a positive effect. However, the degree
                    of inhibition to GST-C translocation caused by amiloride was considerably
                    greater than that imposed on the full-length GSTs suggesting that
                    macropinocytosis may have a more pronounced role in the translocation of the
                    C-terminus.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0017864-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>GST-C and GSTM2 proteins show comparable localisation and endocytosis
                            inhibition profiles in L-929 cells.</title>
            <p>(a) L-929 cells were incubated for 1 hr with 200 nM GSTM2-OG (A) and 200
                            nM GST-C-OG (B), washed and then observed by confocal microscopy. The
                            fluorescence from both GSTM2 and GST-C is in a punctate pattern in the
                            cytoplasm, whilst minimal cell fluorescence is observed from BSA. (b)
                            Impact of pathway-specific endocytosis inhibitors on GST-C uptake. L-929
                            cells were incubated for 2 hrs with 200 nM GST-C alongside GSTM2-OG,
                            GSTZ1-OG and Sj.GST-OG after inhibition of endocytosis pathways by 8
                            µg/mL chlorpromazine (white), 5 mM amiloride (light grey), or 10
                            µg/mL filipin (dark grey). The impact of inhibitors on GST
                            internalisation was measured quantitatively by flow cytometry. Data is
                            presented as the percentage intracellular fluorescence in treated cells
                            compared to intracellular fluorescence in the absence of inhibitors
                            (dashed line represents uninhibited control). Error bars represent the
                            SD of three independent experiments.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Given the accumulating evidence that GST-C is the domain responsible for cell
                    translocation, the structure of the GSTM2 C-terminus was further shortened and
                    these constructs examined for their cell translocation efficiency. A series of
                    constructs were designed to include different helical segments present in the
                    full-length GSTM2 crystal structure (PDB-1XW5). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g004">Figure 4a</xref> shows a summary of the helical
                    fragments which retained solubility after recombinant expression and
                    purification, in addition to two shorter synthesized peptides. Because of the
                    smaller size and fewer available lysine and arginine residues, the shorter
                    C-terminal peptides were not amenable to amine-labeling with Oregon Green, and
                    only the larger, multi-helical peptides, H4–7, H5–8 and H7–8
                    achieved a satisfactory dye-to-protein ratio. To verify the translocation of
                    these fragments, flow cytometry was performed on the fluorescently-labeled
                    forms. The two largest C-terminal fragments (H4–7 and H5-8) had a lower
                    translocation rate than GST-C over 3 hrs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g004">Figure 4b</xref>) and the translocation capacity of
                    the H7–8 peptide was diminished still further. The viability of all
                    fragment-treated cells was not compromised at these concentrations, as judged by
                    membrane permeability to 7-AAD.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0017864-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Structural and cell translocation analysis for α-helical
                            fragments derived from GST-C.</title>
            <p>(a) Schematic diagram outlining α-helical fragment constructs of
                            GSTM2. Peptides H6 and H7–8 were synthesized. The peptides in bold
                            denote fragments that have been tested. (b) Comparative cellular uptake
                            of GSTM2 C-terminal peptides. L-929 cells were incubated with 200 nM
                            OG-labelled peptides, GSTM2 protein (X), GST-C (◆) and H4–7
                            (■), H7–8 (●), H5–8 (▲) fragments of GST-C
                            for the indicated time periods and intracellular fluorescence measured
                            by flow cytometry. The mean cell fluorescence of each sample was
                            normalised for the degree of fluorescent labeling of that protein. Data
                            represents the average of triplicate measurements from three independent
                            experiments ± SEM. (c) Circular dichroism spectra for the
                            full-length GSTM2 protein (dark blue) versus GST-C (green) and
                            H4–7 (cyan), H7–8 (orange), H5–8 (pink) fragments of
                            GST-C. All proteins/peptides were measured at 4–5 µM
                            concentration in 10 mM sodium phosphate buffer pH 7.2.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Circular dichroism was employed to ascertain the overall secondary structure
                    (particularly the helical content) of the C-terminal domain and its peptide
                    fragments. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g004">Figure 4c</xref>
                    confirms that the strong helical component present in the GSTM2 full-length
                    protein is retained by the GST-C as well as peptides H4–7 and H5–8
                    – note the varying spectra amplitudes reflect differences in peptide sizes
                    and not structural content. In contrast, the H7–8 peptide has a very
                    different structure to the other fragments and appears to be disordered in
                    nature. The CD spectra of synthesized peptide fragments corresponding to the
                    helix 4 and helix 6 sequences were also found to be unstructured (data not
                    shown) indicating that the individual helical fragments are not sufficient to
                    adopt α-helical structures.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Structural stability of GSTM2-2 and GST-C fragments</title>
        <p>The data so far suggests that the overall structure of the GST C-terminus may be
                    important for optimal cell uptake. Visualisation of a ribbon structure model of
                    GST-C (based on the x-ray crystallography structure of the whole protein)
                    reveals that the α-6 helix forms the hydrophobic core of this domain and is
                    surrounded by helices 4, 5, 7 and 8, and connected through a series of ionic and
                    hydrophobic interactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g005">Figure
                        5</xref>). This overall helical configuration is also strikingly evident in
                    structural models of the other GST-fold superfamily proteins, including CLIC2
                    which has been noted to display comparable structural features to α
                    pore-forming toxin proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Cromer1">[12]</xref>. This configuration seems to suggest that H6 could
                    play a central role in the translocation of this class of molecule.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0017864-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Ribbon structure model of the C-terminal domain of GSTM2, taken from
                            the crystal structure of the full-length protein – PDB file
                            1XW5.</title>
            <p>The α-6 helix is highlighted in bold and is surrounded by other
                            α-helical elements of GST-C. Residues mutated to probe the role of
                            the α-6 helix in cell translocation are displayed and labeled.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To test this possibility, we aimed to disrupt key contacts between the α-6
                    helix and surrounding helices, and monitor changes in cell uptake efficiency. By
                    analysing the X-ray crystallography structure of the entire GSTM2 protein
                    (RCSB-1XW5), four residues within the α-6 helix were initially identified as
                    being in close proximity (&lt;5 Å) to partner amino acid residues located
                    in helices 5, 7 and 8, thereby potentially participating in hydrogen-bond,
                    electrostatic or hydrophobic interactions. Four modified GST-C proteins were
                    produced by mutating each of the selected residues (Y160; F157; L163; D156) to
                    an alanine residue with the specific aim of disrupting these contacts. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g005">Figure 5</xref> displays the ribbon
                    structure of the C-terminal domain with the position of all mutated residues
                    highlighted. The D156A mutant could not be recombinantly expressed, and the
                    L163A mutant expressed only in low quantities and was highly unstable in
                    solution, suggesting that the conformation of the α-6 helix is a key element
                    in the folding and hence the stability of the C-terminal domain. The contact
                    residues for the D156 side chain are F147 and Thr153 (amide backbone) while for
                    L163 hydrophobic contacts are made with the side chains of F103 and F183.
                    However, the Y160A and F157A were successfully purified to levels that enabled
                    fluorescence labeling. To monitor the effect of these structural mutations on
                    the translocation of the GSTM2 C-terminus, Oregon Green labeled variants and
                    wildtype GST-C were incubated with L-929 cells, and the amount of protein
                    internalised after two hours measured by flow cytometry. The translocation
                    efficiency of each variant relative to that of the wildtype GST-C is shown in
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g006">Figure 6</xref>. The two
                    destabilising mutations, F157A and Y160A, resulted in greater uptake of the
                    C-terminus by approximately 45 and 85%, respectively, indicating that
                    these structural contacts to the α-6 helix are significant for GST
                    translocation. To explore whether the mutations made to the C-terminus protein
                    sequence produced a change in secondary structure, circular dichroism was
                    performed on all C-terminal variants (data not shown). At room temperature no
                    discernable change in secondary structure was observed between the F157A, Y160A
                    variants and wildtype GST-C.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0017864-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effect of substitution mutations within the GSTM2 α-6 helix upon
                            cellular translocation of the C-terminal domain (GST-C).</title>
            <p>L-929 cells were treated for 2 hours with 200 nM Oregon Green-labelled
                            GST-C variants and GST-C wildtype. The mean cellular fluorescence of
                            each sample was normalised for the degree of fluorescent labeling of
                            that protein. Data represents the average of four to six independent
                            experiments ± SEM. Significantly changed translocation efficiency
                            (as determined by student's paired t-Test; one-tailed) is indicated
                            by an asterisk (* = P&lt;0.05;
                            ** = P&lt;0.01).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Even though there were no substantial secondary structure differences observed
                    between GSTM2, the GST-C or the mutated GST-C molecules, this does not
                    necessarily signify that the mutations/truncations made to GSTM2 are
                    structurally inert. Given that the mutants were engineered to abolish key
                    protein intra-molecular interaction, it is highly probable that the
                    modifications could lead to changes in the structural stability of these GST-C
                    variants. To test this possibility we performed denaturing experiments using
                    circular dichroism (CD) and differential scanning fluorimetry (DSF) techniques.
                    For CD experiments, the secondary structure profiles of GST-C and its mutants
                    were monitored in the presence of varying concentrations (0–5 M) of the
                    denaturant guanidine HCl. In this case, the molar elipticity at 222 nm (an
                    indicator of α-helical structure) was measured as a function of guanidine
                    concentration and presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g007">Figure 7a</xref>. It has been previously noted that for some dimeric
                    proteins (including GSTs) that an intermediate unfolding state is detectable
                    when a three-state unfolding model is applied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Grimsley1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Neet1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Zhou1">[15]</xref>. It is not clear whether this
                    is the case for GST-C or its mutants since fitting of the data using a
                    three-state unfolding model or a two-state model were of similar quality. Using
                    the two state-model eqn 1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Szpikowska1">[16]</xref> (experimental) the transition state parameters of the
                    three GST-C variants were obtained (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0017864-t001">Table 1</xref>). The free energy of unfolding was
                    greatest for the GST-C wild-type construct followed F157A and Y160A.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0017864-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Stability studies of GSTM2-2 and GST-C variants measured by circular
                            dichroism (CD) and differential scanning fluorimetry.</title>
            <p>(a) Normalised molecular ellipticity at 222 nm as a function of guanidine
                            HCl concentration (0–5 M) as measured by CD experiments, GST-C
                            (■), Y160A (▼) and F157A (▲). (b) Differential scanning
                            fluorimetry profiles of GST-C wildtype (black), GST-C/Y160A (red),
                            GST-C/F157A (green) and hen egg-white lysozyme control (blue). Melting
                            temperatures (T<sub>m</sub>) are denoted by vertical broken lines.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0017864-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Thermodynamic parameters characterising the guanidine-induced
                            unfolding transition of GST-C and the mutants F157A and Y160A.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0017864-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTM2-2 Variant</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ΔG(kcal/M)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">m(kcal/M)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[X]<sub>half</sub>(M)</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GST-C</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.20±0.88</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.50±0.39</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.08±0.04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y160A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.87±0.72</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.68±0.35</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.82±0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F157A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.95±0.59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.31±0.24</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.15±0.03</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>Measurements were performed by monitoring the molar ellipticity at
                                222 nm (CD) using guanidine HCl (0–5 M) as a denaturant.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>The stability of these proteins was also assessed by DSF by comparing the melting
                    temperatures of the GST-C and the Y60A, F157A mutants. These mutants have a
                    negative effect upon stability with the Y160A mutant showing the lowest meting
                    temperature at 35.7°C followed by the F157A mutant at 38.0°C. The GST-C
                    protein shows a melting temperature of 46.3°C while the control protein, hen
                    egg white lysozyme (which contains four intramolecular disulphide bridges) has
                    the highest T<sub>m</sub> at 63.4°C. Combined with the CD denaturation data
                    we can conclude that F157 and Y160 participate in stabilising the C-terminal
                    domain of GSTM2. Notably, the degree of protein stability is inversely
                    proportional to the capacity of the GST-C protein to enter cells.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>The C-terminus of GSTM2-2 drives cell translocation</title>
        <p>It is apparent from these studies that the driving force for GST cell
                    translocation resides with the α-helical C-terminal domain rather than the
                    entire GST-fold structure itself. This conclusion is borne out of the domain
                    studies where the C-terminal domain of GSTM2 (GST-C) was found to be
                    approximately four fold more efficiently translocated in L929 cells compared to
                    the full protein. Although we were unable to express and test the thioredoxin
                    domain separately, an investigation by Namiki et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Namiki1">[5]</xref> found that
                        <italic>E.coli</italic> thioredoxin was not translocated into cells,
                    suggesting that the thioredoxin domain of Sj.GST26 and by inference the
                    thioredoxin domain of GST-fold proteins in general may not be responsible for
                    cell translocation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Namiki1">[5]</xref>. Unlike protein transduction domains whose core
                    translocating properties can often be ascribed to short
                    ‘cell-penetrating’ peptides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Derossi1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Elmquist1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Vives1">[19]</xref>, the most efficient
                    translocation module of GST proteins appears to be the C-terminal domain in its
                    entirety. Attempts to minimize the size of the GST-C to smaller fragments that
                    are still capable of equivalent rates of cell uptake revealed a reduced capacity
                    for cell translocation. Therefore in the case of GST-C, it seems that all the
                    helices of the C-terminus act in a concerted manner to promote cell
                    translocation. The mechanism of cell translocation remains unclear but does
                    involve endocytosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Morris1">[4]</xref> and is likely to take place through an interaction
                    with a cell-surface receptor and/or by insertion into the cell lipid bilayer. By
                    removal of the thioredoxin domain from GSTM2, it is possible that recognition of
                    a cell surface receptor is enhanced, or equally, the structural changes within
                    the C-terminal helices may facilitate more effective membrane insertion.</p>
        <p>An important finding arising from this study is that the core structure of the
                    GST C-terminal domain is essential for cell translocation, with the hydrophobic
                    helix α-6 playing a structurally central role. The topology of the GST-C
                    domain belongs to the well-known globin family and the specific orientation of
                    the α-helices forms a particular subset within this family where the two
                    layers of helices sit almost orthogonal to each other <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Branden1">[20]</xref> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017864-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Alpha pore-forming toxins such as
                    endotoxins, colicins, and diphtheria toxin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Choe1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Elkins1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Lakey1">[23]</xref> are members of this family
                    and it has been proposed that the membrane-penetrating domains of these proteins
                    contains a buried, hydrophobic helical hairpin structure which inserts into the
                    lipid bilayer of cell membranes (or endosomal membrane in the case of diphtheria
                    toxin) and facilitates pore formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Gonzalez1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Parker1">[25]</xref>. Such a structure is also
                    present within some members of the Bcl family of apoptosis-regulating proteins,
                    although whether membrane insertion correlates with their pro-apoptopic function
                    is not currently clear <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Minn1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Schendel1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Schendel2">[28]</xref>. It has been noted that the low pH environment
                    associated with the membrane surface may play a role in promoting cell insertion
                    of the colicins, diptheria toxin and Bcl-X<sub>L</sub>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Minn1">[26]</xref>.</p>
        <p>It has been previously suggested by Cromer et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Cromer1">[12]</xref> that one potential
                    mechanism of cell association by CLIC proteins - proteins that possess a
                    GST-fold - involves the insertion of hydrophobic helix-6 into the cell membrane
                    as part of a pore-forming process. All GST-fold proteins contain at least one
                    hydrophobic helix surrounded by a bundle of other helices in their C-terminal
                    domain. This single helix may be sufficient to interact with cell membranes and
                    thereby directly enhance the rate of endocytosis of these proteins, or
                    alternatively enable greater access to a membrane receptor capable of promoting
                    endocytosis. It is also possible that this hydrophobic helix forms a hairpin
                    structure in conjunction with a neighbouring helix (α-5 or α-7 in the
                    case of GST-C), creating a structural feature common to the aforementioned
                    toxins.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Decreased stability within GST-C enhances cell translocation</title>
        <p>By modifying the structural elements within GSTM2 we have demonstrated a capacity
                    to affect the level of cell translocation. This is evident on a number of
                    fronts. It was previously noted that substitution of key catalytic amino acids
                    in GSTM2 (Y7F), GSTA1(Y9F) and GSTO1 (C32A) resulted in significant increases
                    (up to four fold) in cell translocation efficiency <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Morris1">[4]</xref>. These mutations, which are
                    located in the thioredoxin domain of the enzymes, not only served to inactivate
                    these enzymes but we suggest also initiate structural and dynamic changes that
                    are transmitted across to the enzyme C-terminal domain. This idea is supported
                    by crystallographic evidence where apo and holo (GSH) GSTA1-1 structures show
                    large structural and dynamic differences in the α-helical C-terminal domain,
                    despite the fact that GSH binds primarily through the thioredoxin domain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-LeTrong1">[29]</xref>. We
                    propose that the removal of the thioredoxin domain of GSTM2 also has structural
                    and dynamic effects upon the C-terminal domain of GSTM2 which is reflected in a
                    ∼four fold increase in cell translocation efficiency.</p>
        <p>A set of experiments designed to test the idea that structural instability
                    affects the translocation efficiency of GST-C was performed by mutating two
                    residues in helix α-6 in GST-C (F157A and Y160A). By altering these key,
                    targeted residues within GST-C we were able to demonstrate a considerable
                    increase in cell translocation efficiency. Moreover, for this set of three
                    proteins, we were able to correlate the efficiency of cell translocation with
                    protein stability as judged by CD denaturing and differential scanning
                    fluorimetry experiments.</p>
        <p>In conclusion we have demonstrated that the structural element responsible for
                    GSTM2 cell translocation is the C-terminal globin-like domain and that gains in
                    cell translocation efficiency may be achieved by altering the conformational
                    stability of this domain. We have shown that the conserved globular fold of this
                    domain which is found in all GST-fold proteins displays a remarkable structural
                    similarity to the α pore-forming toxin domains. What remains to be resolved
                    is whether the mechanism of cell entry of these two functionally unrelated
                    protein classes are alike, an issue that will be pursued in future studies.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Materials</title>
        <p>All cellular inhibitors were purchased from Sigma. Oregon Green 488 carboxylic
                    acid succinimidyl ester ‘5-isomer’ was from Molecular Probes and
                    7-amino-actinomycin D (7-AAD) was from BD PharMingen.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Expression and Labeling of Recombinant Proteins</title>
        <p>GSTM2-2 was expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> and purified by GSH affinity
                    chromatography as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Ross1">[6]</xref>. The cDNA encoding the
                    fragments of GSTM2-2 were amplified by PCR and cloned in-frame downstream of a
                    poly-histidine-tagged ubiquitin sequence in the plasmid pHUE. Protein was
                    purified and the ubiquitin tag cleaved as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Catanzariti1">[8]</xref>. In the
                    accepted nomenclature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Mannervik1">[30]</xref> GSTM2-2 refers to the dimer of this protein. However
                    in the interest of simplicity, the enzyme will be referred to as GSTM2
                    hereafter.</p>
        <p>Purified proteins were dialysed into PBS prior to fluorescent labeling of primary
                    amines with Oregon Green succinimidyl ester according to manufacturer's
                    instruction. Labeled proteins were passed through size-exclusion sephadex
                    columns then dialysed for 48 hours against PBS at 4°C to ensure efficient
                    removal of free dye. Protein concentration and dye to protein ratios were
                    calculated from protein absorbance at 280 nm and 496 nm according to the
                    manufacturer's labeling protocol. All Oregon Green-labeled proteins were
                    aliquoted and stored at −20°C. Synthesized peptides were resuspended
                    in PBS and labeled following the same procedure. To distinguish labeled proteins
                    the suffix –OG has been added to the nomenclature i.e. GSTM2-OG.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Cell Culture</title>
        <p>L-929 mouse fibroblast cell line was obtained from ATCC and routinely maintained
                    in RPMI 1640 medium, supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS)
                    (v/v), 2 mM glutamine and 2 g/L NaHCO<sub>3</sub> at 5% CO<sub>2</sub>
                    and 37°C. Cultures were passaged using PBS containing 0.05% trypsin
                    and 0.02% EDTA (v/v). All cell culture reagents were purchased from
                    Gibco.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Flow Cytometry</title>
        <p>To quantitatively investigate the cellular uptake of GSTM2 and its fragments, as
                    well as the effect of endocytosis inhibitors upon cell uptake, L-929 cells were
                    seeded at a density of 8×10<sup>4</sup> per well in 12-well plates
                    (Nunclon) in 10% FBS/RPMI 1640 medium. After 24 hrs the cells were rinsed
                    with serum-free RPMI 1640 medium before addition of inhibitors or
                    fluorescently-labelled proteins in serum-free medium. Following protein
                    incubation, cells were washed several times with PBS and detached by
                    trypsinization for 10 minutes at 37°C. Cells were centrifuged at 4°C,
                    washed in cold PBS containing 2% FBS (v/v) then resuspended in 2%
                    FBS/PBS containing 0.5 ng/µL 7-amino-actinomycin D (7-AAD) in order to
                    label nuclei of membrane-damaged cells. Cells were incubated at room temperature
                    in the dark for 10 minutes prior to fluorescence-activated cell sorting of
                        10<sup>4</sup> counts on a FACScan flow cytometer (Becton Dickinson). Cells
                    with 7-AAD fluorescence were considered nonviable and excluded from histogram
                    acquisition, and the geometric mean fluorescence of the viable population was
                    used for standardization. To compare cellular uptake of different proteins,
                    geometric mean fluorescence values were divided by the dye to protein ratio to
                    give a normalised value independent of the efficiency of individual protein
                    fluorescence labeling (calculated according to labeling protocol – see
                    method above).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Quantification of GST uptake</title>
        <p>To compare the rate of uptake of GSTM2, GST-C and various GST-C fragments, the
                    Oregon Green-labeled proteins were added to cells at 200 nM concentration and
                    cells incubated at 37°C/5% CO<sub>2</sub> for up to 3 hrs. Untreated
                    cells were used for the initial zero time point. Samples were harvested and
                    prepared for flow cytometry at different time points as described above. Mean
                    fluorescence for each GST time point was standardised to the fluorophore to
                    protein ratio for that particular GST, after subtraction of the untreated cell
                    control fluorescence.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>Confocal Laser Scanning Microscopy</title>
        <p>Cells were seeded onto no. 1 glass coverslips (Lomb Scientific) in 12-well plates
                    in 10% FBS/RPMI 1640 medium the day before experimentation. Live L-929
                    cells were used in microscopy experiments to avoid the possibility of artificial
                    localisation. All incubations were performed in serum-free RPMI 1640 medium.
                    Coverslips were rinsed in PBS and viewed in PBS in a heated chamber. Confocal
                    images were obtained with 60× 1.4 N.A. or 100× 1.4 N.A. oil
                    immersion lenses of a Nikon Eclipse TE300 microscope equipped with Biorad
                    Radiance 2000 Laser Scanning system. Excitation was with an argon laser using
                    515/30 bp emission filters. Data was recorded and analysed using LaserSharp2000
                    software.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>Circular Dichroism (CD) equilibrium unfolding experiments</title>
        <p>GST-C protein fragments were diluted to 4–5 µM (0.1 mg/ml) for CD
                    measurements, and the pH values and solution conditions adjusted to pH 7.2 and
                    10 mM PO<sub>4</sub><sup>2−</sup>, respectively. Spectra were recorded on
                    an Applied Photophysics Chirascan spectrometer at 20°C. A cell with a 0.10
                    cm path length was used for spectra recorded between 190 to 250 nm. The
                    following parameters were employed: spectral bandwidth 1 nm, step size 0.5 nm
                    and time-per-point 0.5 s. Each spectrum was obtained by averaging several scans
                    and the protein CD spectra were corrected for buffer contributions. The
                    temperature was controlled by a Melcor peltier temperature controller. For GST-C
                    denaturing experiments, the molecular ellipticity at 222 nm was recorded at a
                    guanidine HCl concentration range of 0 to 5 M.</p>
        <p>Guanidine unfolding curves were fitted to a two-state (N<sub>2</sub>↔2 U)
                    unfolding model (1) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Szpikowska1">[16]</xref> using Graphpad Prism and the quality of the fits were
                    assessed by considering the R<sup>2</sup> value which typically were
                            &gt;0.99.<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.e001" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where Y<sub>obs</sub> is given by the
                    observed ratios mentioned above, and Y<sub>N</sub>, S<sub>N</sub>,
                    Y<sub>U</sub>, S<sub>U</sub> are intercepts and slopes of the pre-transition and
                    post-transition baselines, [X] is the guanidine concentration,
                        [X]<sub>half</sub> is the guanidine concentration at the midpoint
                    of transition state, m is the free energy dependence on guanidine concentration
                    and R is the gas constant (1.987×10<sup>−3</sup>). The free energy
                    change from a folded to an unfolded state can be expressed
                            as<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017864.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4h">
        <title>Differential Scanning Fluorimetry</title>
        <p>The thermal stability of GST-C wildtype versus the Y160A and F157A mutants was
                    investigated by thermal denaturation in the presence of SYPRO orange
                    (Invitrogen) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Niesen1">[31]</xref>. Proteins diluted to 1 mg/ml in pH 7.5 Hepes buffer
                    were mixed 9∶1 v/v with freshly diluted (1∶50, v/v) SYPRO orange.
                    Each protein sample was run in triplicate on an Applied Biosystems 7900HT
                    quantitative real-time PCR instrument using SYBR green settings. Fluorescence
                    was monitored over a temperature gradient of 10–90°C with a 1%
                    ramp rate. Hen egg-white lysozyme (Sigma) was used as a positive control and
                    showed thermal denaturation at 63.4°C, which is comparable to literature
                    values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017864-Knubovets1">[32]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We would like to thank Mr Hugh French for his contribution to this manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Hayes1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Glutathione and glutathione-dependent enzymes represent a
                        co-ordinately regulated defence against oxidative stress.</article-title>
                    <source>Free Radic Res</source>
                    <volume>31</volume>
                    <fpage>273</fpage>
                    <lpage>300</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Dulhunty1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dulhunty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chelvanayagam</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>The glutathione transferase structural family includes a nuclear
                        chloride channel and a ryanodine receptor calcium release channel
                        modulator.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>276</volume>
                    <fpage>3319</fpage>
                    <lpage>3323</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Shield1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shield</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Functional characterisation of ganglioside-induced
                        differentiation-associated protein 1 as a glutathione
                        transferase.</article-title>
                    <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
                    <volume>347</volume>
                    <fpage>859</fpage>
                    <lpage>866</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Morris1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casarotto</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Transport of glutathione transferase-fold structured proteins
                        into living cells.</article-title>
                    <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
                    <volume>1788</volume>
                    <fpage>676</fpage>
                    <lpage>685</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Namiki1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Namiki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Intracellular delivery of glutathione S-transferase into
                        mammalian cells.</article-title>
                    <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
                    <volume>305</volume>
                    <fpage>592</fpage>
                    <lpage>597</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Ross1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>Molecular cloning and heterologous expression of an alternatively
                        spliced human Mu class glutathione S-transferase transcript.</article-title>
                    <source>Biochem J</source>
                    <volume>294</volume>
                    <issue>Pt 2</issue>
                    <fpage>373</fpage>
                    <lpage>380</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Tetlow1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tetlow</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Polymorphism of human mu class glutathione
                        transferases.</article-title>
                    <source>Pharmacogenetics</source>
                    <volume>14</volume>
                    <fpage>359</fpage>
                    <lpage>368</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Catanzariti1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Catanzariti</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soboleva</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jans</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>An efficient system for high-level expression and easy
                        purification of authentic recombinant proteins.</article-title>
                    <source>Protein Sci</source>
                    <volume>13</volume>
                    <fpage>1331</fpage>
                    <lpage>1339</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Orlandi1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orlandi</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>Brefeldin A blocks the response of cultured cells to cholera
                        toxin. Implications for intracellular trafficking in toxin
                        action.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>268</volume>
                    <fpage>12010</fpage>
                    <lpage>12016</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Wang1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothberg</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>Mis-assembly of clathrin lattices on endosomes reveals a
                        regulatory switch for coated pit formation.</article-title>
                    <source>J Cell Biol</source>
                    <volume>123</volume>
                    <fpage>1107</fpage>
                    <lpage>1117</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-West1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bretscher</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1989</year>
                    <article-title>Distinct endocytotic pathways in epidermal growth
                        factor-stimulated human carcinoma A431 cells.</article-title>
                    <source>J Cell Biol</source>
                    <volume>109</volume>
                    <fpage>2731</fpage>
                    <lpage>2739</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Cromer1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cromer</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>From glutathione transferase to pore in a CLIC.</article-title>
                    <source>Eur Biophys J</source>
                    <volume>31</volume>
                    <fpage>356</fpage>
                    <lpage>364</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Grimsley1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimsley</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholtz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>Organophosphorus hydrolase is a remarkably stable enzyme that
                        unfolds through a homodimeric intermediate.</article-title>
                    <source>Biochemistry</source>
                    <volume>36</volume>
                    <fpage>14366</fpage>
                    <lpage>14374</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Neet1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neet</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Timm</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1994</year>
                    <article-title>Conformational stability of dimeric proteins: quantitative
                        studies by equilibrium denaturation.</article-title>
                    <source>Protein Sci</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>2167</fpage>
                    <lpage>2174</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Zhou1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casarotto</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2011</year>
                    <article-title>Novel folding and stability defects cause a deficiency of human
                        glutathione transferase omega 1.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>286</volume>
                    <fpage>4271</fpage>
                    <lpage>4279</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Szpikowska1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szpikowska</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Urea-induced equilibrium unfolding of single tryptophan mutants
                        of yeast phosphoglycerate kinase: evidence for a stable
                        intermediate.</article-title>
                    <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>
                    <volume>335</volume>
                    <fpage>173</fpage>
                    <lpage>182</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Derossi1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Derossi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joliot</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chassaing</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prochiantz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1994</year>
                    <article-title>The third helix of the Antennapedia homeodomain translocates
                        through biological membranes.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>269</volume>
                    <fpage>10444</fpage>
                    <lpage>10450</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Elmquist1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartfai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>VE-cadherin-derived cell-penetrating peptide, pVEC, with carrier
                        functions.</article-title>
                    <source>Exp Cell Res</source>
                    <volume>269</volume>
                    <fpage>237</fpage>
                    <lpage>244</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Vives1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vives</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lebleu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>A truncated HIV-1 Tat protein basic domain rapidly translocates
                        through the plasma membrane and accumulates in the cell
                        nucleus.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>272</volume>
                    <fpage>16010</fpage>
                    <lpage>16017</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Branden1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Branden</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tooze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <source>Introduction to Protein Structure</source>
                    <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Garland Publishing</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Choe1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curmi</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kantardjieff</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>1992</year>
                    <article-title>The crystal structure of diphtheria toxin.</article-title>
                    <source>Nature</source>
                    <volume>357</volume>
                    <fpage>216</fpage>
                    <lpage>222</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Elkins1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bunker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stauffacher</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>A mechanism for toxin insertion into membranes is suggested by
                        the crystal structure of the channel-forming domain of colicin
                        E1.</article-title>
                    <source>Structure</source>
                    <volume>5</volume>
                    <fpage>443</fpage>
                    <lpage>458</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Lakey1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakey</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slatin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Pore-forming colicins and their relatives.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source>
                    <volume>257</volume>
                    <fpage>131</fpage>
                    <lpage>161</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Gonzalez1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bischofberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pernot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Goot</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Bacterial pore-forming toxins: the (w)hole story?</article-title>
                    <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>
                    <volume>65</volume>
                    <fpage>493</fpage>
                    <lpage>507</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Parker1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Pore-forming protein toxins: from structure to
                        function.</article-title>
                    <source>Progress in Biophysics and Molecular Biology</source>
                    <volume>88</volume>
                    <fpage>91</fpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Minn1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Minn</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schendel</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muchmore</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>Bcl-x(L) forms an ion channel in synthetic lipid
                        membranes.</article-title>
                    <source>Nature</source>
                    <volume>385</volume>
                    <fpage>353</fpage>
                    <lpage>357</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Schendel1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schendel</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Bcl-2 family proteins as ion-channels.</article-title>
                    <source>Cell Death Differ</source>
                    <volume>5</volume>
                    <fpage>372</fpage>
                    <lpage>380</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Schendel2">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schendel</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montal</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>Channel formation by antiapoptotic protein Bcl-2.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>94</volume>
                    <fpage>5113</fpage>
                    <lpage>5118</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-LeTrong1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Trong</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stenkamp</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibarra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adman</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>1.3-A resolution structure of human glutathione S-transferase
                        with S-hexyl glutathione bound reveals possible extended ligandin binding
                        site.</article-title>
                    <source>Proteins</source>
                    <volume>48</volume>
                    <fpage>618</fpage>
                    <lpage>627</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Mannervik1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannervik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Listowsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Nomenclature for mammalian soluble glutathione
                        transferases.</article-title>
                    <source>Methods Enzymol</source>
                    <volume>401</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>8</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Niesen1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niesen</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vedadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>The use of differential scanning fluorimetry to detect ligand
                        interactions that promote protein stability.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Protoc</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>2212</fpage>
                    <lpage>2221</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017864-Knubovets1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knubovets</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osterhout</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klibanov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Structure, thermostability, and conformational flexibility of hen
                        egg-white lysozyme dissolved in glycerol.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>96</volume>
                    <fpage>1262</fpage>
                    <lpage>1267</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>