<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-22512</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072701</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Association between Polymorphisms in the Renin-Angiotensin-Aldosterone System Genes and Essential Hypertension in the Han Chinese Population</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">RAAS Polymorphisms and Hypertension</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Lindan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Xiaobo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Lina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Lijuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Lin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Jia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>Lissy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yaping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Biochemistry, School of Medicine, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Resources and Evolution, Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Preventive Medicine, School of Medicine, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Pathology, School of Medicine, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Cardiology, The Affiliated Ningbo No.1 Hospital, School of Medicine, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Yong-Gang</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, China</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">xujin1@nbu.edu.cn</email> (JX); <email xlink:type="simple">zhangyp@mail.kiz.ac.cn</email> (YZ)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LJ JX YZ. Performed the experiments: LJ XC LF JX. Analyzed the data: LZ LW LL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JS. Wrote the paper: LJ JX YZ.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e72701</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Ji et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>Renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) is the most important endocrine blood pressure control mechanism in our body, genes encoding components of this system have been strong candidates for the investigation of the genetic basis of hypertension. However, previous studies mainly focused on limited polymorphisms, thus we carried out a case-control study in the Han Chinese population to systemically investigate the association between polymorphisms in the RAAS genes and essential hypertension.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>905 essential hypertensive cases and 905 normotensive controls were recruited based on stringent inclusion and exclusion criteria. All 41 tagSNPs within RAAS genes were retrieved from HapMap, and the genotyping was performed using the GenomeLab SNPstream Genotyping System. Logistic regression analysis, Multifactor dimensionality reduction (MDR), stratified analysis and crossover analysis were used to identify and characterize interactions among the SNPs and the non-genetic factors.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>Serum levels of total cholesterol (TC) and triglyceride (TG), and body mass index (BMI) were significantly higher in the hypertensive group than in the control group. Of 41 SNPs genotyped, rs3789678 and rs2493132 within <italic>AGT</italic>, rs4305 within <italic>ACE</italic>, rs275645 within <italic>AGTR1</italic>, rs3802230 and rs10086846 within <italic>CYP11B2</italic> were shown to associate with hypertension. The MDR analysis demonstrated that the interaction between BMI and rs4305 increased the susceptibility to hypertension. Crossover analysis and stratified analysis further indicated that BMI has a major effect, and rs4305 has a minor effect.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>These novel findings indicated that together with non-genetic factors, these genetic variants in the RAAS may play an important role in determining an individual’s susceptibility to hypertension in the Han Chinese.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This study was financially supported by Zhejiang Natural Science Foundation (LQ13C060001), Ningbo Natural Science Foundation (2012A610237), Research Project of Zhejiang Education Department (Y201224146), as well as the KC Wong Magna Fund in Ningbo University. The funders had no role in the study design, data collection, analysis, decision to publish or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="6"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Essential hypertension, defined as high blood pressure (BP) with no identifiable cause, affecting 95% of hypertensive patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Carretero1">[1]</xref>. It is considered to be the consequence of an interaction between environmental and genetic factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Joseph1">[2]</xref>. Hitherto, many candidate genes in the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS), the sympathetic nervous system, and water-sodium balance system have been widely studied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Simino1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Franceschini1">[6]</xref>. Among all these genes which play important roles in the etiology of hypertension, those encoding the main components of the RAAS are deemed the most possible candidate genes since the RAAS plays a fundamental role in the maintenance of blood pressure and cardiovascular homeostasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Schmieder1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Navar1">[8]</xref>.</p>
<p>RAAS genes encoding renin (<italic>REN</italic>), angiotensinogen (<italic>AGT</italic>), angiotensin-converting enzyme (<italic>ACE</italic>), angiotensin type 1 receptor (<italic>AGTR1</italic>) and aldosterone synthase gene (<italic>CYP11B2</italic>) have been widely investigated in different ethnic populations, and dozens of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) within RAAS genes have been reported to be significantly associated with essential hypertension <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Konoshita1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Wang1">[11]</xref>. However, previous studies focused on limited SNPs like <italic>AGT</italic> M235T, <italic>AGT</italic> A6G, <italic>AGT</italic> T174M, <italic>ACE</italic> I/D, <italic>AGTR1</italic> A1166C, and <italic>CYP11B2</italic> C3344T, and the results are often inconsistent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Ji1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Sookoian1">[15]</xref>. Moreover, dozens of genome-wide association studies (GWAS) on hypertension have been carried out, but none of these hot polymorphisms was significantly associated with hypertension <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Kurtz1">[16]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-International1">[19]</xref>. It is possible that environmental factors, population variation, relatively small sample size, patient selection, and limited genetic alleles may contribute to the conflicting or even contradictory results <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Farahani1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Staessen1">[22]</xref>.</p>
<p>Given these limitations, this study was designed and conducted in a large, homogeneous sample of Han Chinese, which would minimize the potential influence of mixed factors on hypertension. The objective of the present study was to systemically examine the association between polymorphisms in the RAAS candidate genes (<italic>REN</italic>, <italic>AGT</italic>, <italic>ACE</italic>, <italic>AGTR</italic>, and <italic>CYP11B2</italic>) and hypertension. Thus, we first conducted a case-control study in the Han Chinese population and genotyped all tagSNPs within RAAS genes. Subsequently, we analyze the interaction among different SNPs and non-genetic risk factors for hypertension, which may give more information on the roles of genetic factors.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>The protocol of this study was reviewed and approved by the medical ethics committee of Ningbo University. The health records and blood samples of the participants were collected with informed written consent.</p>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Study Participants</title>
<p>The participants were chosen from our established community-based epidemiologic study of common diseases. With informed written consent, we collected more than 10,000 health records. Subsequently, participants who fulfilled the following criteria were put into our database: 30 to 75 years old, Han Chinese, living in Ningbo City (East coast of China) for at least three generations without migration history. Finally, 905 essential hypertensive cases and 905 normotensive controls were chosen from this database, which were matched for age and sex. In addition, participants without cardiovascular diseases, diabetes, kidney diseases, or other major chronic illnesses according to their health records were recruited as controls.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Measurement of Blood Pressure and Clinical Parameters</title>
<p>Blood pressure was measured in the morning after the participants had been in sitting position for 10 minutes. Three readings were taken 5 minutes apart using standard mercury sphygmomanometer and the average of last two measurements was recorded. Hypertension in this study was defined as sitting systolic blood pressure (SBP) ≥140 mmHg and/or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) ≥90 mmHg, or self-reported use of anti-hypertensive medication. Patients with secondary hypertension were excluded. Normal blood pressure was defined with SBP≤120 mmHg and DBP≤80 mmHg.</p>
<p>With informed written consent, two milliliter of venous blood was collected with ethylene diamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA) as anticoagulant. Subsequently, serum levels of total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoprotein (HDL), triglyceride (TG) were measured enzymatically on a Hitachi automatic biochemistry analyzer 7100. Clinical information including body mass index (BMI), and weekly alcohol and cigarettes consumption were also obtained. In this study, who consumed ≥70 g of alcohol per week for more than 1 year were defined as individuals with alcohol abuse. Moreover, who smoked ≥70 cigarettes per week for more than 1 year were defined as individuals with smoking habit.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>SNP Genotyping</title>
<p>All 41 tagSNPs were retrieved from HapMap (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hapmap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" xlink:type="simple">http://hapmap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>), with tagger pairwise method in CHB: R<sup>2</sup> cut off = 0.8 and minor allele frequency (MAF) cut off = 0.1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072701.s001">Table S1</xref>). The genomic DNA was extracted from the whole blood using standard phenol-chloroform extraction method. Genotyping was performed using the GenomeLab SNPstream Genotyping System (Beckman Coulter Inc.) according to the manufacturer’s protocol <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Bell1">[23]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Continuous variables were presented as the mean ± SD and analyzed by t-test between two groups. Statistical analysis of allele and genotype frequencies between case and control groups were compared by chi-squared test. Effect of confounding variables were identified by logistic regression (SPSS 16.0, SPSS Inc.). Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) was calculated in controls by the software PEDSTATS V0.6.8 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sph.umich.edu/csg/abecasis/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.sph.umich.edu/csg/abecasis/</ext-link>). Multifactor dimensionality reduction (MDR), stratified analysis and crossover analysis were used to identify and characterize interactions among the SNPs and the non-genetic factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Motsinger1">[24]</xref>. The software used for MDR is distributed in a JAVA platform with a graphical user interface and is freely available online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epistasis.org/mdr.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.epistasis.org/mdr.html</ext-link>).</p>
<p>All tests were two-sided, and <italic>P</italic> values less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant. For chi-squared test, the <italic>P</italic> values were adjusted for the total number of tested SNPs using the Bonferroni correction method (α = 0.05/41 ≈ 0.0012).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The baseline characteristics of our study participants are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072701-t001">Table 1</xref>. The male to female ratio was equal in both groups, and mean age of hypertensive participants and controls were similar, demonstrating that the hypertensive and control groups were well-matched and are appropriate for the following analyses. Serum high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and percentage of regular smoking and alcohol abuse showed no difference between hypertensive and control groups. However, serum levels of TG and TC, and BMI were significantly higher in the hypertensive groups than in the control group (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0072701-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Baseline characters of the investigated participants.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0072701-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">905</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">905</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male/Female</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392/513</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392/513</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (y)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.91±7.37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.60±7.51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI(Kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.65±3.24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.21±2.86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL (mM)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41±0.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41±0.32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (mM)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.34±1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17±0.93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (mM)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02±1.68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63±1.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking habit</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol abuse</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.80</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>BMI, body mass index; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglyceride.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The <italic>P</italic> value of 41 tagSNPs within RAAS genes were shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072701-g001">Figure 1</xref>. The rs10935724 within <italic>AGTR1</italic> and rs6414 within <italic>CYP11B2</italic> were failed in genotyping, and the genotyping success rate of other 39 SNPs was 99%<monospace>. </monospace>Two of 39 SNPs, rs3789678 and rs10086846, deviated from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05). However, the genotype distribution and MAF of these two SNPs were similar to those of HapMap CHB. To exclude the genotyping error, we randomly regenotyped 20% of the samples for these two SNPs by Tm-shift genotyping method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Wang2">[25]</xref>, the results were same. Therefore, they were still included in the following analyses. In addition, with the prevalence, odds ratio (OR), and MAF in this study, the Genetic Power Calculator (available online <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/gpc/" xlink:type="simple">http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/gpc/</ext-link>) indicated that the sample size is big enough to do case-control analysis with 80% power <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Purcell1">[26]</xref>. According to the chi-square test <italic>P</italic> values (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) and odds ratios, rs3789678 and rs2493132 within <italic>AGT</italic>, rs4305 within <italic>ACE</italic>, rs275645 within <italic>AGTR1</italic>, rs3802230 and rs10086846 within <italic>CYP11B2</italic> were shown to associate with hypertension (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072701-t002">Table 2</xref>). No significant association was found between polymorphisms within <italic>REN</italic> and hypertension. The genotype information for the remaining 35 SNPs that did not reach significance in the association analyses were shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072701.s002">Table S2</xref>. After Bonferroni correction, only rs4305 and rs3802230 were still significant, the other 4 SNPs were marginally significant.</p>
<fig id="pone-0072701-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Negative Log <italic>P</italic> values for the association of 41 single-nucleotide polymorphisms in 5 candidate genes of renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system with hypertension.</title>
<p>The <italic>P</italic> values were obtained from the comparison of two allele frequencies. Labeled SNPs had a <italic>P</italic> value less than 0.01.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0072701-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Genotype distributions of those SNPs significantly associated with hypertension.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0072701-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Genotype</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAF</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> Value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3789678</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AGT</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">690 (CC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (CT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (TT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10–1.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">626 (CC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236 (CT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (TT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs2493132</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AGT</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">373 (CC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410 (CT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (TT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07–1.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">316 (CC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">452 (CT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 (TT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs4305</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ACE</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155 (AA)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">441 (AG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300 (GG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10–1.44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (AA)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450 (AG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">348 (GG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs275645</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AGTR1</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">455 (AA)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (AG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (GG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09–1.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">535 (AA)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333 (AG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (GG)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3802230</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CYP11B2</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (AA)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">348 (AC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">470 (CC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13–1.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (AA)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428 (AC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">385 (CC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs10086846</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CYP11B2</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469 (CC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277 (CT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (TT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06–1.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413(CC)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318 (CT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172 (TT)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>The <italic>P</italic> values were obtained from the comparison of two allele frequencies. OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Considering the effect of confounding variables, we further carried out logistic regression analysis with genetic and non-genetic factors. The result showed that rs2493132, rs10086846, and TC were no longer associated with hypertension (<italic>P</italic>&gt;0.05, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072701-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0072701-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Logistic regression for genetic and non-genetic factors.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0072701-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp (B)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3789678</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.033</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.241</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02–1.51</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs2493132</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.140</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97–1.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs4305</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.242</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.273</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10–1.47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs275645</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.276</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.318</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11–1.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3802230</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.011</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.368</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08–1.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs10086846</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.551</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.065</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87–1.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.154</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12–1.19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.080</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97–1.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.148</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06–1.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.432</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>The <italic>P</italic> values of 6 SNPs were obtained from the comparison of two allele frequencies. BMI, body mass index; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglyceride.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>*</label><p><italic>P</italic> value was less than 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Moreover, MDR was used to analyze the interaction among ‘significant’ SNPs and non-genetic risk factors for hypertension. After input the genotypes of 6 SNPs together with information about TG, TC, and BMI, the software output the best model for ‘BMI and rs4305’ with 10/10 Cross-validation Consistency (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072701-t004">Table 4</xref>). In order to delineate how BMI and rs4305 interacts to cause hypertension, we carried out crossover analysis. The result showed that both BMI and the A allele of rs4305 increased the susceptibility to hypertension, but BMI had the main effect (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072701-t005">Table 5</xref>). The stratified analysis further showed that when BMI ≥25, the A allele of rs4305 has no association with hypertension [<italic>P = </italic>0.85, OR = 1.02, 95% confidence interval (CI) = 0.81–1.30] (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072701-t006">Table 6</xref>). However, when BMI &lt;25, the A allele showed significant association with hypertension (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001, OR = 1.41, 95% CI = 1.19–1.66) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072701-t006">Table 6</xref>), which also indicates that BMI has the major effect, and rs4305 had a minor effect.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0072701-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>MDR analysis of gene-environment interaction.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0072701-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Best model</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TestingAccuracy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testing Sensitivity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testing Odds Ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testing X<sup>2</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-validation Consistency</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26 (95%CI: 1.20–4.27)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.011)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, rs4305</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 (95%CI: 1.27–4.23)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.62 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.006)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, rs275645, rs3802230</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 (95%CI: 1.01–3.29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.047)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/10</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0072701-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
<title>Crossover analysis of interaction between BMI and rs4305.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0072701-t005-5" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allele</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> Value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">581</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">876</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12–3.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14–3.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">451</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">484</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19–1.66</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>The <italic>P</italic> values were obtained from the comparison of two allele frequencies. OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0072701-t006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption>
<title>Stratified analysis of interaction between BMI and rs4305.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0072701-t006-6" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.t006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> Value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">581</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">451</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19–1.66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">271</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">334</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">876</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">484</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81–1.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt106"><label/><p>The <italic>P</italic> values were obtained from the comparison of two allele frequencies. OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Since RAAS is the most important mechanism regulates blood pressure in our body <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Marteau1">[27]</xref>, genes encoding components of this system have been strong candidates for the investigation of the genetic basis of hypertension and major targets for antihypertensive drugs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Nebert1">[28]</xref>. However, previous studies mainly focused on limited polymorphisms, thus we carried out a case-control study to systemically investigate the association between polymorphisms in the RAAS genes and essential hypertension. The present study identified several novel genetic variants in the RAAS genes that may play critical roles in BP regulation and susceptibility for hypertension. According to Chi-square test and logistic regression analysis, rs3789678 within <italic>AGT</italic>, rs4305 within <italic>ACE</italic>, rs275645 within <italic>AGTR1</italic>, rs3802230 within <italic>CYP11B2</italic> were shown to associate with hypertension.</p>
<p>Similar to this study, some of the susceptibility SNPs were also found to be associated with hypertensive traits in previous studies. The rs4305 has been related to the risk of hypertension (<italic>P = </italic>3.0×10<sup>−5</sup>), and associated with SBP (<italic>P = </italic>4.6×10<sup>−4</sup>) and DBP (<italic>P = </italic>6.0×10<sup>−5</sup>) in a study compromising 23 cohorts of three independent studies [Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epidemiology Consortium (CHARGE); Global BPgen Consortium; and Women’s Genome Health Study] and a total of 86,588 participants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Johnson1">[29]</xref>. Furthermore, a recent GWAS for ACE enzyme activity found strong association of rs4343 with increased activity in the Han Chinese (<italic>P = </italic>3.0×10<sup>−25</sup>), and the mean ACE activity among subjects with G allele of rs4343 increased by 3.5 IU/L per copy of the allele <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Chung1">[30]</xref>. The G allele of rs4343 is in strong linkage disequilibrium (LD) with A allele of rs4305 (HapMap JPT/CHB D’ = 0.97, r<sup>2</sup> = 0.80), suggesting a potential common link between the studies. In the present study, A allele of rs4305 increases the susceptibility to hypertension, which might be associated with increased ACE activity.</p>
<p>Prior to our study, Chen <italic>et al</italic>. also studied the association of <italic>CYP11B2</italic> gene and essential hypertension in southwest Han Chinese population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Chen1">[31]</xref>. Four tag SNPs (rs4536, rs4545, rs3097, and 3802230) within the <italic>CYP11B2</italic> gene were selected through HapMap. In addition, C344T (rs1799998) and K173R (rs4539) polymorphisms that previous studies were mostly interested, were also selected for the study. The result showed that among the six SNPs, only the C allele of rs3802230 was significantly more prevalent in the hypertension subjects than in the control subjects (<italic>P = </italic>0.006, OR = 1.28, 95% CI: 1.07–1.52). Since the results of both studies were similar, we further calculated the pooled <italic>P</italic> value and OR. The combined <italic>P = </italic>0.001, OR = 1.20, 95% CI = 1.08–1.34, I<sup>2</sup> = 0.0% (<italic>P = </italic>0.39), which means no heterogeneity existed between two studies, and the C allele of rs3802230 might be a risk factor for essential hypertension in the Han Chinese population. Chen <italic>et al.</italic> also analyzed these SNPs in Yi and Hani Minorities of China, and found rs4536 was significantly associated with hypertension in the Hani minority, however, no association was found in the Yi minority <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Chen2">[32]</xref>.</p>
<p>Pickering and colleagues have initially suggested that hypertension and blood pressure are complex traits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Pickering1">[33]</xref>, and previous epidemiologic studies have found dozens of risk factors, such as obesity, high-fat diets, smoking, alcohol abuse, excessive salt intake, mental stress, and others to associate with high blood pressure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Kotchen1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Horan1">[36]</xref>. There is growing evidence that interactions among multiple genes and environmental factors may play an important role in determining the susceptibility to various common diseases including hypertension <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Kunes1">[37]</xref>. Our previous study indicated that interaction analysis might give a little more information than the single genetic study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Xu1">[38]</xref>. In the present study, high BMI and serum TG level were confirmed as risk factors for hypertension by logistic regression analysis. The MDR analysis further demonstrated that the interaction between BMI and rs4305 was associated with hypertension. Since BMI represents the internal metabolic and physiological environment that plays a key role in development of high blood pressure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Feng1">[39]</xref>, and ACE is one of the most important target for design of anti-hypertensive drugs, it’s not surprising that the interaction of them may play an important role in the susceptibility to hypertension. Previous genetic epidemiologic study also found the interactions between <italic>MMP3</italic> gene polymorphism rs679620 and BMI in predicting blood pressure in African-American women with hypertension <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Taylor1">[40]</xref>. The recent important genetic studies are mainly carried out in well-organized cohorts like Global BPgen, CHARGE, and GenSalt Study, which means the epidemiologic data are readily available <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-International1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Levy1">[41]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-GenSaltCollaborativeResearch1">[43]</xref>. With the development of statistic methods for evaluation of gene-environment interaction, we can expect more missing inheritability to be found <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Mukherjee1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072701-Kazma1">[45]</xref>.</p>
<p>In conclusion, we identified several genetic variants in the RAAS genes that were significantly associated with hypertension in the Han Chinese population. Most notable, the interaction between BMI and rs4305 increased the susceptibility to hypertension, meanwhile BMI has a major effect, and rs4305 has a minor effect.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0072701.s001" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>All 41 tagSNPs within genes coding for RAAS.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0072701.s002" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0072701.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Genotype distributions of 35 SNPs not associated with hypertension.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors acknowledge Ms. Shifang Wu, Chunlin Zhu, and Jieqiong Jin from Kunming Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, for helpful technical support.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Carretero1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carretero</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oparil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Essential hypertension. Part I: definition and etiology</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Joseph1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pare</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Exploring gene-environment relationships in cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Can J Cardiol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Simino1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Novel findings and future directions on the genetics of hypertension</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Brand1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genetics, genomics and other molecular approaches: example of salt-sensitive hypertension</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>879</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Basson1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Between candidate genes and whole genomes: time for alternative approaches in blood pressure genetics</article-title>. <source>Curr Hypertens Rep</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Franceschini1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franceschini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heiss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Recent findings in the genetics of blood pressure and hypertension traits</article-title>. <source>Am J Hypertens</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Schmieder1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmieder</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hilgers</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schlaich</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Renin-angiotensin system and cardiovascular risk</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>369</volume>: <fpage>1208</fpage>–<lpage>1219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Navar1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Navar</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kobori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Villalobos</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Intratubular renin-angiotensin system in hypertension</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Konoshita1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konoshita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Genomic Disease Outcome Consortium Study</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Do genetic variants of the Renin-Angiotensin system predict blood pressure response to Renin-Angiotensin system-blocking drugs?: a systematic review of pharmacogenomics in the Renin-Angiotensin system</article-title>. <source>Curr Hypertens Rep</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-He1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hixson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic variants in the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system and blood pressure responses to potassium intake</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1719</fpage>–<lpage>1730</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Wang1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genetic variants in the renin-angiotensin system and blood pressure reactions to the cold pressor test</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2422</fpage>–<lpage>2428</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Ji1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Association of angiotensinogen gene M235T and angiotensin-converting enzyme gene I/D polymorphisms with essential hypertension in Han Chinese population: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Pereira1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis of the association of 4 angiotensinogen polymorphisms with essential hypertension: a role beyond M235T?</article-title> <source>Hypertension</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>778</fpage>–<lpage>783</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Mottl1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mottl</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shoham</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>North</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Angiotensin II type 1 receptor polymorphisms and susceptibility to hypertension: a HuGE review</article-title>. <source>Genet Med</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>560</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Sookoian1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sookoian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gianotti</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pirola</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Association of the C-344T aldosterone synthase gene variant with essential hypertension: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Kurtz1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide association studies will unlock the genetic basis of hypertension.: con side of the argument</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1021</fpage>–<lpage>1025</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Dominiczak1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Dominiczak AF, Munroe PB (2010) Genome-wide association studies will unlock the genetic basis of hypertension: pro side of the argument. Hypertension 56: 1017–1020; discussion 1025.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Ehret1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehret</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide association studies: contribution of genomics to understanding blood pressure and essential hypertension</article-title>. <source>Curr Hypertens Rep</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-International1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">International Consortium for Blood Pressure Genome-Wide Association S, Ehret GB, Munroe PB, Rice KM, Bochud M, et al</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic variants in novel pathways influence blood pressure and cardiovascular disease risk</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>478</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Farahani1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farahani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dolovich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Exploring design-related bias in clinical studies on receptor genetic polymorphism of hypertension</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Beeks1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beeks</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kessels</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Klauw</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Leeuw</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genetic predisposition to salt-sensitivity: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1243</fpage>–<lpage>1249</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Staessen1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Staessen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thijs</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis of blood pressure and the CYP11B2 polymorphism highlights the need for better designed studies</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Bell1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bell PA, Chaturvedi S, Gelfand CA, Huang CY, Kochersperger M, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2002) SNPstream UHT: ultra-high throughput SNP genotyping for pharmacogenomics and drug discovery. Biotechniques Suppl: 70–72, 74, 76–77.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Motsinger1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motsinger</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The effect of reduction in cross-validation intervals on the performance of multifactor dimensionality reduction</article-title>. <source>Genet Epidemiol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>546</fpage>–<lpage>555</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Wang2"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahluwalia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Umblas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>High-throughput SNP genotyping by single-tube PCR with Tm-shift primers</article-title>. <source>Biotechniques</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>893</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Purcell1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cherny</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sham</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genetic Power Calculator: design of linkage and association genetic mapping studies of complex traits</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Marteau1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marteau</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaiou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siest</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Visvikis-Siest</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genetic determinants of blood pressure regulation</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2127</fpage>–<lpage>2143</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Nebert1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nebert</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Polymorphisms in drug-metabolizing enzymes: what is their clinical relevance and why do they exist?</article-title> <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Johnson1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newton-Cheh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chasman</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehret</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Association of hypertension drug target genes with blood pressure and hypertension in 86,588 individuals</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>903</fpage>–<lpage>910</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Chung1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fann</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leu</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A genome-wide association study identifies new loci for ACE activity: potential implications for response to ACE inhibitor</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenomics J</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Chen1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Association of the human CYP11B2 gene and essential hypertension in southwest Han Chinese population: a haplotype-based case-control study</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Hypertens</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Chen2"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Haplotype-based case-control study of the human CYP11B2 gene and essential hypertension in Yi and Hani minorities of China</article-title>. <source>Biochem Genet</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Pickering1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1959</year>) <article-title>The nature of essential hypertension</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1027</fpage>–<lpage>1030</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Kotchen1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotchen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Obesity-related hypertension: epidemiology, pathophysiology, and clinical management</article-title>. <source>Am J Hypertens</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1170</fpage>–<lpage>1178</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Wang3"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vasan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology of uncontrolled hypertension in the United States</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>1651</fpage>–<lpage>1662</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Horan1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenfant</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology of blood pressure and predictors of hypertension</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>I20</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Kunes1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zicha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Developmental windows and environment as important factors in the expression of genetic information: a cardiovascular physiologist’s view</article-title>. <source>Clin Sci (Lond)</source> <volume>111</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Xu1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Xu J, Ji LD, Zhang LN, Dong CZ, Fei LJ, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2012) Lack of association between STK39 and hypertension in the Chinese population. J Hum Hypertens.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Feng1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>BMI is strongly associated with hypertension, and waist circumference is strongly associated with type 2 diabetes and dyslipidemia, in northern Chinese adults</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>323</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Taylor1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mosley</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kardia</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Interactions between metallopeptidase 3 polymorphism rs679620 and BMI in predicting blood pressure in African-American women with hypertension</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2312</fpage>–<lpage>2318</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Levy1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehret</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verwoert</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Launer</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide association study of blood pressure and hypertension</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>677</fpage>–<lpage>687</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-NewtonCheh1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newton-Cheh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gateva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bochud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide association study identifies eight loci associated with blood pressure</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>666</fpage>–<lpage>676</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-GenSaltCollaborativeResearch1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>GenSalt Collaborative Research</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>GenSalt: rationale, design, methods and baseline characteristics of study participants</article-title>. <source>J Hum Hypertens</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>646</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Mukherjee1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Testing gene-environment interaction in large-scale case-control association studies: possible choices and comparisons</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>175</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0072701-Kazma1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babron</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Genin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic association and gene-environment interaction: a new method for overcoming the lack of exposure information in controls</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>173</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>