<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-36831</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064626</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Agricultural production</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Agroecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Agronomic ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Forestry</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Soil science</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant science</subject><subj-group><subject>Botany</subject><subj-group><subject>Mycology</subject><subj-group><subject>Fungal biochemistry</subject><subject>Fungal physiology</subject><subject>Fungi</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant-environment interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant biochemistry</subject><subject>Plant physiology</subject><subject>Plants</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Carbon Transfer from the Host to <italic>Tuber melanosporum</italic> Mycorrhizas and Ascocarps Followed Using a <sup>13</sup>C Pulse-Labeling Technique</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Carbon Transfer to <italic>Tuber melanosporum</italic> Ascocarps</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Tacon</surname><given-names>François</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>Bernd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plain</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossann</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bréchet</surname><given-names>Claude</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robin</surname><given-names>Christophe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>INRA, UMR 1136, Interactions Arbres/Microorganismes (IAM), Centre INRA de Nancy, Champenoux, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Université de Lorraine, UMR 1136, Interactions Arbres/Microorganismes (IAM), Faculté des Sciences, Vandoeuvre les Nancy, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>INRA, UR 1138, Biogéochimie des Ecosystèmes Forestiers (BEF), Centre INRA de Nancy, Champenoux, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>INRA, UMR 1137, Ecologie et Ecophysiologie Forestières (EEF), Centre INRA de Nancy, Champenoux, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Université de Lorraine, UMR 1137, Ecologie et Ecophysiologie Forestières (EEF), Faculté des Sciences, Vandoeuvre les Nancy, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Université de Lorraine, UMR 1121 « Agronomie &amp; Environnement » Nancy-Colmar, Vandœuvre les Nancy, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><addr-line>INRA, UMR 1121 « Agronomie &amp; Environnement » Nancy-Colmar, Centre INRA de Nancy, Vandœuvre les Nancy, France</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Roehampton University, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">zeller@nancy.inra.fr</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: FLT BZ. Performed the experiments: BZ CP CR FLT. Analyzed the data: CP BZ FLT CR. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CH CB CP. Wrote the paper: FLT. Edited the manuscript: FLT CR CP BZ.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e64626</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Le Tacon et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Truffles ascocarps need carbon to grow, but it is not known whether this carbon comes directly from the tree (heterotrophy) or from soil organic matter (saprotrophy). The objective of this work was to investigate the heterotrophic side of the ascocarp nutrition by assessing the allocation of carbon by the host to <italic>Tuber melanosporum</italic> mycorrhizas and ascocarps. In 2010, a single hazel tree selected for its high truffle (<italic>Tuber melanosporum</italic>) production and situated in the west part of the Vosges, France, was labeled with <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub>. The transfer of <sup>13</sup>C from the leaves to the fine roots and <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> mycorrhizas was very slow compared with the results found in the literature for herbaceous plants or other tree species. The fine roots primarily acted as a carbon conduit; they accumulated little <sup>13</sup>C and transferred it slowly to the mycorrhizas. The mycorrhizas first formed a carbon sink and accumulated <sup>13</sup>C prior to ascocarp development. Then, the mycorrhizas transferred <sup>13</sup>C to the ascocarps to provide constitutive carbon (1.7 mg of <sup>13</sup>C per day). The ascocarps accumulated host carbon until reaching complete maturity, 200 days after the first labeling and 150 days after the second labeling event. This role of the <italic>Tuber</italic> ascocarps as a carbon sink occurred several months after the end of carbon assimilation by the host and at low temperature. This finding suggests that carbon allocated to the ascocarps during winter was provided by reserve compounds stored in the wood and hydrolyzed during a period of frost. Almost all of the constitutive carbon allocated to the truffles (1% of the total carbon assimilated by the tree during the growing season) came from the host.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>For this work, the authors utilized the online continuous flow CN analyzer (Carlo Erba NA1500) coupled with an isotope ratio mass spectrometer (Finnigan delta S) and DNA sequencing facilities at INRA-Nancy financed by INRA and the Regional Council of Lorraine. The pulse-labeling experiment was supported by the SYSTRUF programme (An integrated approach for sustainable management of ecosystems producing Black Truffle, <italic>Tuber melanosporum</italic>) financed by the French ANR (Agence Nationale de la Recherche; programme SYSTERRA, ANR-09-STRA-10-02). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Despite their renown, the life cycle of the true truffles belonging to the genus <italic>Tuber,</italic> which are members of the Ascomycota, is not well understood. These species form ectomycorrhizas with different hosts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Paolocci1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Riccioni1">[2]</xref>. For sexual reproduction, it is hypothesized that haploid mycorrhizas of one mating type form an antheridium producing male gametes and, through an ascogonial filament or cord, an ascogonial apparatus composed of ascogonial cells and a trichogyne. The female haploid trichogyne of one mating type is assumed to collect the male gametes of the opposite mating type, allowing the ascogonial apparatus to form, after plasmogamy, an ascogenous heterokaryotic tissue, which appears to be surrounded by homokaryotic maternal tissues. The growth of these tissues gives rise to the ascocarp.</p>
<p>In contrast to ectomycorrhizal basidiomycota sporocarps, such as those of <italic>Boletus</italic>, <italic>Amanita</italic> or <italic>Laccaria</italic>, which develop over a number of days directly from diploid mycorrhizas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Teramoto1">[3]</xref>, <italic>Tuber</italic> ascocarps grow more slowly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Olivier1">[4]</xref>.</p>
<p>It takes at least six months between the production of the primordia and full ascocarp development. We thus hypothesize that the processes involved in ascocarp development and carbon acquisition are different from those of basidiocarps. It is not known whether the developing ascocarp is fed <italic>via</italic> a direct transfer of carbohydrates from the host tree through the mycorrhizas and the ascogonial structure or whether the ascocarp becomes independent of its host some weeks or months after its development. In the latter case, it is assumed that truffles might be able to use dead host tissues or soil organic matter as carbon (C) and nitrogen (N) sources, as indicated by some authors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Barry1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Callot1">[6]</xref>, through a saprotrophic process. This feeding behavior cannot be excluded because the truffle ascocarp can develop an external mycelium from its peridium. This mycelium could colonize dead cells from living roots, dead roots, other dead organic tissues or mineral structures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Callot1">[6]</xref>. Similarly, in pure cultures, the mycelium of <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> might use cellulose, cellobiose, lignin, chitin and tannins as carbon sources <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Mamoun1">[7]</xref>. However, sequencing of the <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> genome showed that this fungus exhibits a restricted repertoire of genes coding for Carbohydrate Active enZymes (CAZymes) that are able to degrade dead organic matter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Martin1">[8]</xref>. <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> presents many fewer GH-encoding genes than saprotrophs, and cellulases from families GH6 and GH7 are absent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Martin1">[8]</xref>. These findings suggest that the saprotrophic ability of <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> is weak. In addition, <italic>T. melanosprum</italic> has an invertase gene that allows plant-derived sucrose to be hydrolyzed, suggesting the ability to use simple sugars from the host.</p>
<p>Our previous results based on the natural abundance of <sup>13</sup>C and <sup>15</sup>N in the ascocarp indicate that <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> behaves like a true ectomycorrhizal fungus and that the ascocarp cannot be mainly supplied <italic>via</italic> saprotrophic pathways from surrounding soil organic matter or dead host tissues. Our previous findings also suggest that <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> ascocarps cannot be completely independent at any time during their development, even during late maturation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Zeller1">[9]</xref>. Similarly, <italic>Tuber</italic> ascocarps never develop when separated from their host <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Rouquerolle1">[10]</xref>.</p>
<p>However, <italic>in situ</italic> <sup>13</sup>C and <sup>15</sup>N labeling experiments are the only way to definitively answer the questions regarding carbon and nitrogen allocation during <italic>Tuber</italic> ascocarp differentiation. The technical difficulties inherent in this methodology are numerous, which is likely why no convincing experiments have yet been conducted to address this topic.</p>
<p>Numerous <italic>in situ</italic> <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse-labeling experiments have been conducted on annual crops or grasslands. These studies all demonstrated a rapid carbon flux pathway from the host to the roots <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Robin1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Leake1">[12]</xref> and from the roots to the rhizosphere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Leake1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-NGuyen1">[13]</xref>. Some of these studies include arbuscular mycorrhizas (AM). For example, Johnson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Johnson1">[14]</xref> showed that between 5 and 8% of the carbon lost by plants was respired by the AM mycelium over the first 21 h after labeling.</p>
<p>Several studies on carbon allocation in trees have been performed using pulse labeling. Most of these analyses were conducted in microcosms or mesocosms under controlled conditions with young seedlings. <sup>14</sup>C pulse labeling followed by autoradiography or counting by scintillation was employed in these experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Leake1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Ek1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Simard1">[24]</xref>. To our knowledge, very few studies have been conducted <italic>in situ</italic> with adult trees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Hgberg1">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Subke1">[28]</xref>. None of these experiments have considered the fructification of the associated fungi.</p>
<p>The aim of our work was to assess the allocation of carbon by the host to <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> mycorrhizas and ascocarps. This assessment was achieved <italic>via</italic> an <italic>in situ</italic> <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse-labeling experiment performed on a 20-year-old hazel tree in a truffle orchard established in the northeast of France.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>The Experimental Site</title>
<p>The experiment was performed in Rollainville, which is situated in the west part of the Vosges in France on a limestone plateau of the Jurassic period (latitude 48° 18′ 42″; longitude 5° 44′ 13″; elevation 360 m; annual rainfall 941 mm with a maximum in July; mean annual temperature 9.5°C). The soil is a brown calcisoil (WRB 2006) with a silty clay texture, a high alkaline pH (water pH 7.97), a moderate content of organic matter (9.4%) and a limestone content of 8.8%. This soil is poor in available phosphorus and moderate in available potassium and magnesium. It is free-draining, highly granular and aerated.</p>
<p>The truffle orchard in which the experiment was conducted was established in 1991 by one of us (Christophe Robin). It was previously a cultivated site. No protected species were sampled. Hazel trees inoculated with <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> (Vittad.) (black Perigord truffle) marketed by the Naudet nurseries (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pepinieres-naudet.com/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pepinieres-naudet.com/</ext-link>) were planted <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Chevalier1">[29]</xref>. The first truffle harvest began in November 2005.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Labeling</title>
<p>In 2010, a single tree (A11, 4 m in height) was selected based on its high truffle producing. Two stainless steel scaffolds 6 m in height were built in parallel with one another on both sides (east and west) of the tree to install the labeling chamber. The two scaffolds were secured and attached to one another with stainless steel bars. The base of the chamber was sealed around the stems of the tree using adhesive tape with a width of 100 mm. The entire tree was enclosed in a 28-m<sup>3</sup> cylindrical 200-µm polyethane film chamber into which pure <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> gas was injected. The hazel tree was pulse-labeled first on the 10<sup>th</sup> of July 2010 and a second time on the 1<sup>st</sup> of September 2010. In July, the tree was watered one day before labeling (30 mm of water under the crown). The air temperature and air humidity inside the chamber were recorded with a single probe (HMP50, Vaisala, Finland) and a datalogger (CR1000, Campbell UK) at 30 s intervals. The labeling chamber was closed at 6∶36 UT for the first labeling and at 10∶41 UT for the second. Prior to injection, the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the chamber was impoverished through leaf assimilation. Then, 15 l of <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> (99 atom %, CORTECNET, France) were injected at a flow rate setting between 0.11 and 0.18 l min<sup>−1</sup>. Injection was initiated when the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration reached 139 µmol.mol<sup>−1</sup> for the first labeling (7∶40 UT) and 150 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> for the second (10∶57 UT). Total CO<sub>2</sub> was regulated at 380 vpm using a <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub>/<sup>12</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> IRGA (S710, SICK/MAIHAC, Germany), and the evolution of the <sup>12</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> and <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations was recorded inside the chamber. The concentration of <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> inside the chamber reached 300 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> in the two labelings. Then, it declined to 73 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> during the first labeling event and 63 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> during the second. Finally, the chamber was opened at 9∶15 UT for the first labeling and 13∶04 UT for the second. The two labeling periods lasted 01∶45 h and 02∶07 h, respectively.</p>
<p>Based on the obtained data, the tree assimilated a total of 16.7 g of <sup>13</sup>C during the two pulse-labeling periods. From October 2010 to March 2011, the crown of the tree was enclosed in a net to prevent any direct transfer of carbon to the soil through the falling of dead leaves, branches, nuts or catkins. These materials were collected regularly from the inside of the net. From December 2010 to February 2011, the soil under the tree was protected from frost using straw mulch (15 cm of straw enclosed in a plastic net).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Sampling</title>
<p>Four quadrats of 1 m<sup>2</sup> were positioned under the tree at the four cardinal directions (south, north, west and east) at a distance of one meter from the trunk. On eight dates (1, 4, 83, 101, 133, 168, 204 and 264 days from the first sampling performed on the 7<sup>th</sup> of July 2010), ascocarps, ectomycorrhizal root tips, fine roots, bulk soil, mycorrhizospheric soil and ascocarpic soil were collected from the 0 to 10 cm depth in each of the four squares. During the same period, ascocarps were collected under control trees. Leaves, branches, catkins and buds were also collected in different periods and at the four positions (south, north, west and east).</p>
<sec id="s2c1">
<title>Tree fine roots and mycorrhizas</title>
<p>Tree fine roots (≤2 mm diameter) and mycorrhizas were carefully retrieved from the soil and washed in water under a dissecting microscope. <italic>Tuber melanosporum</italic> mycorrhizas were identified <italic>via</italic> morphotyping on the basis of color, mantle shape and surface texture and some also by molecular typing. Fine roots and mycorrhizas were then treated for ten minutes with 1 M hydrochloric acid and then washed with water to eliminate soil calcium carbonate.</p>
<p>Mycorrhizas were confirmed as being associated with <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> using molecular methods. Genomic DNA was extracted with the DNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen SA, Courtaboeuf, France) following the manufacturer’s instructions. <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> mycorrhizas were checked using species-specific ribosomal-DNA, internally transcribed-spacer (ITS) primers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Paolocci2">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Rubini1">[31]</xref>. A microsatellite genotyping of <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> mycorrhizas was performed using primer pairs corresponding to ten SSR markers. This data were then used to analyze the fine scale spatial genetic structure of <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> at the Rollainville site <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Murat1">[32]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c2">
<title>Soil</title>
<p>Bulk soil was collected at least 10 cm from any mycorrhizas or ascocarps. Mycorrhizospheric soil was obtained by carefully shaking roots with mycorrhizas and using needles or forceps. Ascocarpic soil was obtained by removing the soil adhering to the ascocarps using needles and forceps.</p>
<p>The soil samples collected in the field were immediately placed in an icebox and transferred to the laboratory at 4°C. After separation of the ascocarpic and mycorhizospheric soil, all of the samples were maintained at –80°C. They were not treated with hydrochloric acid.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c3">
<title>Soil water extracts</title>
<p>To perform <sup>13</sup>C and <sup>12</sup>C measurements in soil water extracts, we used a portion of the samples held at –80°C. All of the samples were cleaned by removing small stones and shells using forceps under a dissecting microscope but were not treated by hydrochloric acid or ground. Living and dead mycorrhizas were removed from the mycorrhizospheric soil using forceps under a dissecting microscope.</p>
<p>For each sample, approximately 100 mg of soil was introduced into an Eppendorf tube with 0.5 ml of distilled water. The samples were shaken at 4°C for 24 h and then centrifuged for 5 minutes at 10,000 g. A 400 µl aliquot of the obtained supernatant was removed and immediately stored at −80°C. The 400 µl sample was then reduced to 100 µl using a cryodessicator and dried in a metal capsule. Each metal capsule was weighed before use and after drying to obtain the dry weight of organic matter dissolved in 400 µl. The dry weight of the soil introduced into each Eppendorf was also determined.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c4">
<title>Ascocarps</title>
<p>During the 2010–2011 period of truffle production, 24 ascocarps produced beneath the labeled tree were found by chance inside the four squares or located by a dog outside of the four squares when mature. The ascocarps were carefully retrieved from the soil using a small garden trowel, as in the four squares. Harvesting was performed at five different times: 83, 101, 133, 168 and 204 days after the first labeling. During the following period of production (2011–2012), 3 ascocarps produced beneath the labeled tree were harvested (558 days after the first labeling). Ascocarps were also harvested under non labeled trees at three different times during the 2010–2011 period of production and at one time (01 16 2012) during following period of production. The ascocarps were also confirmed as belonging to T. melanosporum using molecular methods. The fresh weight of all of the ascocarps was determined after cleaning. Ten ascocarps were oven dried to obtain the average dry weight percentage (58.9%).</p>
<p>All of the ascocarps were also described morphologically and microscopically and classified using the following criteria (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064626-t001">Table 1</xref>):</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0064626-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Description of the maturation stages of <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> ascocarps (modified from Giovanni Pacioni, personal communication).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0064626-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size or Weight</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5a (Ascospores beginning to form)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fertile veins with asci and ascospores beginning to form.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 cm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5b (Smooth ascospores)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No echinulated ascospores; Brown-black peridium; White gleba; No aroma.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–2 g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6a (Ornamented ascospores)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White echinulated ascospores; Brown-to-black peridium. Numerous open cracks. New wartsin formation; White-to-clear brown gleba; white veins clearly visible; Weak aroma.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–5 g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6b (Ornamented brown ascospores)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black-brown peridium with few closed cracks; Grey-black gleba between white veins;80% echinulated ascopsores, brown to dark brown; 20% of white echinulated ascopsores;Fairly developed aroma; Not completely mature.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5–15 g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6c (Brown-to-dark brown echinulated ascospores)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black-brown peridium with few closed cracks; Black gleba between white veins; Very welldeveloped aroma; Completely mature.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15–100 g and more</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>The first stages (truffles of less than 1 g) could not be harvested. We attempted to quantify the constitutive carbon derived by the ascocarps from the host by assuming that, during the 2010–2011 period of production, the 24 ascocarps were present at the time of the first crop and that they all grew in a synchronized manner. The ascocarps of the last crop were partly desynchronized from the previous ascocarps. Their growth was slowed by low temperatures. Consequently, we excluded the last harvest and considered only the 18 ascocarps harvested from 28 September to 22 December 2010. We also considered only the gleba in the calculations, as the weight of the peridium was negligible. We used the average C concentration in the 18 ascocarps cropped under the labeled tree (43.48% C). For each date, the accumulated weight of constitutive carbon in the ascocarps (ΣCW) was as follows:<disp-formula id="pone.0064626.e001"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where CW is the average constitutive carbon on that date, and n is the total number of ascocarps harvested from the beginning of the study.</p>
<p>On each date, the weight of <sup>13</sup>C derived from the host (<sup>13</sup>CW) was calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="pone.0064626.e002"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where Σ<italic>CW</italic> is the accumulated weight of constitutive carbon in the ascocarps; <sup>13</sup>C<sub>labelled</sub> is the measured <sup>13</sup>C abundance on each date; and <sup>13</sup>C<sub>natural abundance</sub> is the natural abundance.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c5">
<title>Leaves</title>
<p>On each date, ten leaves were collected around the crown in the middle part of the tree at the four cardinal points and pooled together to obtain one sample per cardinal point.</p>
<p>For each date, there were four replicates of each type of material (leaves, fine roots, mycorrhizas, soil, soil solutions), with the exception of ascocarps, the number of which depended on the harvest. The samples were first air dried, then dried at 60°C for 48 h and ground to a fine powder using a shaker with steel beads.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c6">
<title>Isotopic analysis</title>
<p>The percentages of total C and the C isotopic compositions in the leaves, fine roots, mycorrhizas, ascocarps, bulk soil, mycorrhizospheric soil, ascocarpic soil and solutions of bulk, myco-rhizospheric and ascocarpic soil were determined at INRA Nancy using an online continuous flow CN analyzer (Carlo Erba NA 1500) coupled to an isotope ratio mass spectrometer (Finnigan delta S). Values were reported using standard notation (δ<sup>13</sup>C ‰) relative to Vienna PeeDee Belemnite (VPDB), employing polyethylene foil (IAEA-CH-7) as a standard.</p>
<p>δ<sup>13</sup>C values were calculated with the usual formula:<disp-formula id="pone.0064626.e003"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where R is the molar ratio of <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>12</sup>C, and R<sub>PDB</sub> is the molar ratio of PeeDee Belemnite. For ascocarps, the natural abundance δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰) value was calculated by averaging the δ<sup>13</sup>C values of ten ascocarps collected during the same period beneath an unlabeled hazel tree. For each organ, Excess (‰) δ<sup>13</sup>C = δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>labeled</sub> –δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>natural abundance</sub>. For soil samples, the amount of soluble <sup>13</sup>C was expressed in nanograms per 100 mg of dried soil.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Statistical Analyses</title>
<p>Analyses of variance for experimental data were conducted using the R software (R project for Statistical computing, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link>). Analyses of variance were performed using Type-II sum of squares (Anova function from package "car") when data were missing, causing unbalanced design. When necessary, data were transformed prior to the Anova using the Box-Cox method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Box1">[33]</xref>. The criterion for statistical significance was set at p&lt;0.05.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The flux of pulse-derived <sup>13</sup>C from the leaves to the fine roots, mycorrhizas, ascocarps and soil was traced and quantified over a seven-month post-labeling period.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Leaves</title>
<p>The natural δ<sup>13</sup>C abundance in the leaves presented an average value of −27.66 ‰ prior to the first labeling (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064626-t002">Table 2</xref>). Leaf δ<sup>13</sup>C reached a level of almost 300 ‰ just after the end of the first <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> injection, after which it decreased rapidly (to 35 ‰ after 5 days) but remained positive until the second labeling, when it peaked at 470 ‰. The δ<sup>13</sup>C subsequently decreased until reaching a negative value at leaf fall. Dormant buds sampled during winter showed high <sup>13</sup>C abundance, as did branches formed in 2010 whose <sup>13</sup>C concentration was higher than in older branches. The δ<sup>13</sup>C reached 76 ‰ in the following spring in the newly formed leaves, just after bud break.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0064626-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Kinetics of δ<sup>13</sup>C (in ‰) in leaves of the hazel tree A11 after pulse labeling and δ<sup>13</sup>C of buds and branches sampled during the winter following the pulses.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0064626-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from thefirst labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from thesecond labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaves (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.66(1.51) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290.71(173.00) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.26(55.63) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.65(57.88) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469.07(211.2) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.45(12.75) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.45(12.45) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.70(43.24) a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dormant buds (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.53 (18.36)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010 branches (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.81 (10.88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009 branches (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.11 (4.88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008 branches (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.96 (5.37)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005 branches (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.84 (2.66)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>One-way Anova has been performed using R; data have been raised to power minus 2 prior to Anova as suggested by the Box-Cox method in order to ensure the normality of residuals. Standard errors of means are given in brackets and mean values followed by a different letter are significantly different from the others at p&lt;0.05 (Mean comparison Tukey’s test).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Fine Roots and Mycorrhizas</title>
<p>Mycorrhizas were significantly more labeled than fine roots (p&lt;0.01) and there was a date effect (p&lt;0.001) but no interaction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064626-t003">Table 3</xref>). A nonsignificant increase of the δ<sup>13</sup>C was visible in fine roots sampled 26 days after the first labeling. The δ<sup>13</sup>C level in fine roots always remained below zero throughout the period following the first <sup>13</sup>C pulse. The δ<sup>13</sup>C was higher after the second labeling, from the sampling at 149 days after the second pulse where it peaked at 9.87 ‰ (January 2011). There was a transfer of <sup>13</sup>C to the <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> mycorrhizas that became positive 80 days and 165 days after the first labeling (113 days after the second one). The mycorrhizal δ<sup>13</sup>C level peaked at +22.75 ‰, 80 days after the first pulse and then decreased. It increased again after the second labeling, reaching a maximum of +55.35 ‰ prior to decreasing again.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0064626-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Kinetics of δ<sup>13</sup>C (in ‰) in the fine roots and <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> mycorrhizas beneath hazel tree A11 in 2010–2011 after the pulse labelings of the leaves with <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub>.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0064626-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from the first labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from the second labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fine roots (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.62(0.29) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.62(2.28) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 9.73(33.52) ab</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.15(13.60) ab</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−19.34(3.51) ab</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 10.12(12.06) ab</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.87(41.20) ab</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82(17.52) b</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mycorrhizas (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.60(0.19) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.09(5.35) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.60(2.24) a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.75(47.97) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.31(19.33) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3(12.08) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.35(35.06) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.85(7.23) b</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>Two-way Anova has been performed using R; data have been raised to the power minus 2 prior to Anova as suggested by the Box-Cox method in order to ensure the normality of residuals. Anova showed a ‘date’ (p&lt;0.01) and ‘organ’ (p&lt;0.001) effects but no interaction. Standard errors of means are given (in brackets). Mean comparison has been made for simple effects (Tukey test): for d<sup>13</sup>C in fine roots and d<sup>13</sup>C in mycorrhizas respectively, means followed by a different letter are significantly different.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Ascocarps</title>
<p>The first ascocarps beneath the labeled tree were harvested on the 28<sup>th</sup> of September 2010 and the last on the 27<sup>th</sup> of January, 2011 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064626-t004">Table 4</xref>). The first ascocarps were immature (stages 5b to 6a). They matured gradually, and in January 2011, all of the harvested ascocarps were fully ripened (stage 6c). The synchronization between the ascocarps was not complete, and there were some variations in the maturation stage on each date.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0064626-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>(A) Maturity, numbers and fresh weight of ascocarps harvested beneath the labeled tree A11; (B) δ<sup>13</sup>C (in ‰) in <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> ascocarps (peridium and gleba) beneath the labeled tree A11, and beneath non-labeled trees (natural abundance) at each sampling date from October 2010 to January 2011.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0064626-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Harvest date</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sept-28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oct-16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nov-17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dec-22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan-27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan-16</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>A</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from the first labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">555</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from the second labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">503</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage of maturity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5b to 6a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6a to 6b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6b to 6c</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6c</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average fresh weight (g)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of ascocarps harvested</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh weight harvested (g)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accumulated fresh weight harvested (g)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">446</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>B</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C in the peridium in ‰, labeled tree A11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+87.01 (34.23) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+60.36 (12.67) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+69.56 (34.30) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+59.43 (6.35) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+77.36 (26.08) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.84 (0.37) b</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C in the gleba in ‰, labeled tree A11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+125.4 (29.93) c</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+78.94 (12.33) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+79.13 (22.37) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+67.17 (15.67) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+82.12 (27.87) b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.22 (0.46) a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C in the peridium in ‰, Controls</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.11 (0.32)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.65 (0.60)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.84 (0.87)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.16 (0.61)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C in the gleba in ‰, Controls</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.71 (0.18)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.93 (0.70)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.39 (0.34)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.79 (0.83)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><p>n = 3 to 7 ascocarps harvested at each sampling date. Two-way Anova has been performed using R (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064626-t004">table 4B</xref>); data have been log transformed prior to Anova as suggested by the Box-Cox method in order to ensure the normality of residuals. Anova showed a ‘date’ (p&lt;0.05) and ‘organ’ (p&lt;0.001) effects but no interaction. Standard errors of means are given (in brackets). Mean comparison has been made for simple effects (Tukey test): for δ<sup>13</sup>C in the peridium and δ<sup>13</sup>C in the gleba, means followed by a different letter are significantly different.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>At the end of September, the average fresh weight of the ascocarps was less than two grams. The ascocarps continued to grow until the end of December to reach an average of 35 g. The ascocarps harvested at the end of January 2011 were smaller than those from December 2010, most likely due to low soil temperatures, differences in primordium production times and maturation desynchronization among the different ascocarps. The 24 collected ascocarps produced a total of 446 g fresh weight.</p>
<p>In the peridium and the gleba, the δ<sup>13</sup>C was highest in the first harvest (87 and 125‰ respectively). It subsequently decreased and then increased again after the second labeling. The <sup>13</sup>C enrichment was significantly higher in the gleba than in the peridium (p = 0.034), and the δ<sup>13</sup>C in the peridium and gleba were significantly higher than natural abundance, whatever the sampling date.</p>
<p>At the end of December, the gleba of the ascocarps, which had reached full growth, were 35% more enriched in <sup>13</sup>C than the mycorrhizas and almost three times more enriched than the fine roots. The δ<sup>13</sup>C in the ascocarps harvested in 2012 under the labeled tree, 555 days after the first labeling, displayed a value identical to the natural abundance. In the controls, the δ<sup>13</sup>C values in the ascocarps were not different between the gleba and the peridium and remained very stable between −25 and −26‰ throughout the period of maturation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Constitutive <sup>13</sup>C Derived by the Ascocarps from the Host</title>
<p>From the 28<sup>th</sup> of October to the 22<sup>th</sup> of December, 2010, the ascocarps continuously absorbed <sup>13</sup>C from the host (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064626-t005">Table 5</xref>). A total of 160.4 mg of <sup>13</sup>C was derived to provide constitutive carbon to the ascocarps at a flux of 1.7 mg per day until the 22<sup>nd</sup> of December, representing 0.96% of the <sup>13</sup>C assimilated by the tree during the two labeling periods. The <sup>13</sup>C allocated to the ascocarps to provide constitutive carbon was even higher, as there were only 18 fruiting bodies considered in this case, instead of 24. The increase in derived <sup>13</sup>C used as constitutive carbon in the ascocarps was similar to the increase in total constitutive carbon.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0064626-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
<title>Characteristics of the <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> ascocarps harvested in 2010–2011 beneath the labeled hazel tree A11 and estimations of the amounts of ascocarpic <sup>13</sup>C derived from the host tree.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0064626-t005-5" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">2010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Harvest date</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sept-28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oct-16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nov-17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dec-22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan-27</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of ascocarps harvested</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average dry weight (g)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascocarp dry weight harvested (g; 24 ascocarps)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.08</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.73</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accumulated ascocarp dry weight (g; 24 ascocarps)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.67</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183.97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accumulated dry weight in g (18 ascocarps)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">361.80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accumulated constitutive carbon in the ascocarps in g (SCW)(18 ascocarps)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157.38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>13</sup>C derived from the host in mg (<sup>13</sup>CW)(18 ascocarps)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.81</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160.37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>From Fine Roots to Ascocarps</title>
<p>Despite appearing nonstatistically significant, the transfer of<sup> 13</sup>C was effective in the fine roots, which never accumulated <sup>13</sup>C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064626-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The transfer of <sup>13</sup>C from the fine roots to the mycorrhizas was delayed for several weeks. From the mycorrhizas to the ascocarps, the <sup>13</sup>C transfer was intensive 80 days after the first injection of <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub>. It then decreased, followed by increasing from days 113 to 149 after the second labeling. It was not possible to harvest truffles in early stages (less than 1 g). The early transfer of <sup>13</sup>C from the host towards the ascocarps probably occurred at least 60 days after the first labeling.</p>
<fig id="pone-0064626-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Temporal variation of δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰) in the fine roots, mycorrhizas and peridium and gleba of ascocarps beneath hazel tree A11 in 2010–2011.</title>
<p>Error bars represent the standard deviation of the means.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Soil and Soil Water Extracts</title>
<p>The δ<sup>13</sup>C values did not differ significantly between the three soil compartments (bulk, mycorhizospheric and ascocarpic soil) and remained constant (average −25.22‰) from July 7 2010 (before the first labeling) to January 2011 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064626-t006">Table 6</xref>). There was a date effect (p = 0.0011), the last sampling date presenting higher δ<sup>13</sup>C values than at 1, 98 and 130 days after the first labeling.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0064626-t006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption>
<title>δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰) in the soil compartments (bulk soil, mycorhizospheric soil, soil adhering to the ascocarps) following the pulse labelings of the A11 hazel tree.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0064626-t006-6" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">2010</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2011</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Harvest date</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">July-07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">July-10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sept-28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oct-16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nov-17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dec-22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan-27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">March-28</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from the first labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from the second labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C in the bulk soil (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.46 (0.80)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.13 (0.80)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.28 (1.26)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.98 (0.42)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.29 (0.89)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.15 (0.43)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.33 (0.39)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C in the myco-rhizospheric soil (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.53 (1.29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.51 (0.38)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.96 (0.38)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.17 (0.48)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−23.74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−23.55 (1.99)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C in the adherent ascocarpic soil (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.84 (0.82)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.07 (0.73)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.39 (1.98)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.06 (3.14)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><p>Two-way Anova has been performed using R; data have been log transformed prior to Anova as suggested by the Box-Cox method in order to ensure the normality of residuals. Anova showed a ‘date’ effect (p = 0.0011) but no ‘organ effect’ and no interaction. Analysis of variance was performed using Type-II sum of squares (Anova function from package "car") because of unbalanced design resulting from missing data. When available, standard errors of means are given (in brackets).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The C content in water soil extracts was higher in the mycorhizospheric soil (173.5 ng per 100 mg of dry soil) than in the bulk soil (107.9 ng per 100 mg of dried soil) (p&lt;0.001) or in the ascocarpic soil (131.7 ng per 100 mg of dried soil) (p&lt;0.05).</p>
<p>The δ<sup>13</sup>C values in the soil water extracts did not differ significantly between the three compartments and remained constant throughout the period investigated, with an average value of −24.45‰ (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064626-t007">Table 7</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0064626-t007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t007</object-id><label>Table 7</label><caption>
<title>δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰) in soil water extracts following the pulse labeling of the A11 hazel tree.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0064626-t007-7" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064626.t007" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">2010</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2011</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Harvest date</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">July-07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">July-10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sept-28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oct-16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nov-17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dec-22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan-27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">March-28</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from the first labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in days from the second labeling</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C of the bulk soil solution (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.20 (1.02)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.73 (1.73)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.97 (1.02)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.09 (1.94)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.89 0.79)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.68 (1.97)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.75 (0.71)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.25 (0.40)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soluble <sup>13</sup>C (ng for 100 mg soil)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.5 (25.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.6 (11.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.2 (14.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159.5 (56.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.1 (25.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.2 (13.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.7 (10.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185.9 (30.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C of the myco-rhizospheric soil solution (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.24 (0.95)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.24 (0.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−23.49 (0.66)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.00 (0.61)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22.76 (4.15)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soluble <sup>13</sup>C (ng for 100 mg soil)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168.6 (73.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221.1 (95.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C of the ascocarpic soil solution (‰)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.40 (0.67)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.08 (0.18)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22.13 (3.88)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22.68 (3.77)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soluble <sup>13</sup>C (ng for 100 mg soil)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.9 (7.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.6 (23.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.6 (50.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.9 (27.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><p>Two-way Anova has been performed using R; data have been log transformed prior to Anova as suggested by the Box-Cox method in order to ensure the normality of residuals. Anova showed no main effects and no interaction. Analysis of variance was performed using Type-II sum of squares (Anova function from package "car") because of unbalanced design resulting from missing data. Anova showed a slight date effect (p = 0.046) and no interaction. When available, standard errors of means are given (in brackets).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion and Conclusions</title>
<p>It is accepted that ectomycorrhizal fungi do not rely on dead organic matter as a carbon source. Using <sup>14</sup>C as a tracer in forest conditions (Oak Ridge Reservation, Tennessee), Treseder et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Treseder1">[34]</xref> demonstrated that basidiomycota ectomycorrhizal fungi acquired most or all of their carbon from their hosts and that less than 2% of the carbon in the ectomycorrhizal biomass originated from the litter. Similarly, in several studies examining changes in photoperiods or photosynthesis rates, the defoliation or girdling of the host suggested that basidiomycota sporocarps depend strongly on newly synthesized carbon from the host <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Godbout1">[35]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Last1">[39]</xref>. However, 75% defoliation of a <italic>Pinus pinaster</italic> stand affected the mycorrhizal community but did not decrease basidiomycota sporocarp biomass or abundance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Pestaa1">[40]</xref>.</p>
<p>However, Hobbie et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Hobbie1">[41]</xref>, using the <sup>14</sup>C signal from 1950s to 1960s thermonuclear testing, suggested that some ectomycorrhizal fungi like <italic>Cortinarius</italic>, <italic>Leccinum</italic> or <italic>Tuber</italic> could be able to use some insoluble soil organic matter.</p>
<p>In our experiment, the transfer of <sup>13</sup>C from the hazel tree leaves to the mycorrhizas via the fine roots was very slow. This result contrasts with what is observed in herbaceous plants, in which allocation to the roots is far more rapid <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Robin1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-NGuyen1">[13]</xref>. Furthermore, the carbon allocation by the host to the ectomycorrhizas appeared to take place very slowly compared to what has been found in arbuscular mycorrhizal plants. For example, Leake et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Leake2">[18]</xref> observed peak transfer from cores colonized by AM mycelium 9–14 h after labeling. This transfer was also slower than the transfer observed by Högberg et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Hgberg1">[25]</xref> in a <italic>Pinus sylvestris</italic> forest, where the <sup>13</sup>C content peaked after 4–7 days in ectomycorrhizal pine roots.</p>
<p>In our experiment, the fine roots acted mainly as a conduit. They did not accumulate <sup>13</sup>C and transferred it slowly to the mycorrhizas. The mycorrhizas first formed a carbon sink and accumulated <sup>13</sup>C prior to ascocarp development. Then, the mycorrhizas transferred <sup>13</sup>C to the truffles, which accumulated carbon from the host until reaching complete maturity, 200 days after the first labeling and 150 days after the second labeling. This role of the <italic>Tuber</italic> ascocarps as a carbon sink was observed several months after the end of carbon assimilation by the host, which lost its leaves, and at low temperature. This finding suggests that the carbon allocated to the ascocarps during fall and winter was provided by reserve compounds stored in the trunk, branches, buds or thick roots. In the labeled tree, there was <sup>13</sup>C accumulation in the dormant buds and in the newly formed branches.</p>
<p>Tissues of deciduous trees store starch in autumn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Essiamah1">[42]</xref>. This starch is partly hydrolyzed during dormancy. In poplar trees during autumn and winter, starch hydrolysis results in a huge increase in sucrose and its galactosides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Sauter1">[43]</xref>. This process represents a mechanism for protection against frost <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Palonen1">[44]</xref>. Starch resynthesis occurs at the end of dormancy, and new hydrolysis of starch into simple sugars is observed at bud break <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Bollmark1">[45]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Landhusser1">[47]</xref>. Carbon remobilization in deciduous trees could provide up to approximately 40% of the C used for new tissue formation and can contribute to early wood formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Kagawa1">[48]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Maurel1">[50]</xref>. Under the conditions of the present study, we can assume that the carbon allocated by the host to <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> ascocarps at the end of their development is in the form of simple sugars produced <italic>via</italic> starch hydrolysis during tree dormancy, rather than from amylase activity prior to or during bud breaking. Nevertheless, under a Mediterranean climate, the carbon used for growth of <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> ascocarps could enter into competition with the carbon necessary for bud bursting or early wood formation. However, the quantity of carbon necessary for ascocarp development (approximately 1% of the assimilated C) is not comparable to the quantity of C necessary for bud breaking. In 2012, when the ascocarp δ<sup>13</sup>C content was found to be equal to the natural abundance, it became clear that the carbon allocated to the fruiting bodies was only coming from the carbon assimilated by the tree during the growing season.</p>
<p>Using <italic>Pinus densiflora</italic> seedlings in mycorrhizal association with <italic>Laccaria amethystina</italic> and labeled with <sup>14</sup>CO<sub>2</sub>, Teramoto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Teramoto1">[3]</xref> showed that there was transfer of host carbon to the sporocarps over one or a number of days in rhizoboxes based on autoradiography and radioactivity counting. This finding indicates that the fungus primarily used recently assimilated carbon. This result obtained in an ectomycorhizal member of Basidiomycotina producing fruitbodies over a number of days contrasts with our results obtained with an ectomycorrhizal member of the Ascomycotina, in which the development of ascocarps requires carbon stored in the trunk or roots of the host, and the process takes several weeks/months.</p>
<p>These results demonstrate, for the first time under field conditions, that <italic>Tuber</italic> mycorrhizas provide a slow, but dominant pathway for carbon flux from trees to ascocarps. From September 28 2010 until December 22 2010, 1.7 mg <sup>13</sup>C was transferred per day from the mycorrhizas to the ascocarps to provide constitutive carbon. The total amount of constitutive <sup>13</sup>C transferred was approximately 1% of the <sup>13</sup>C assimilated by the tree during the two labeling periods. These data do not include the carbon respired by the ascocarps.</p>
<p>This <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse-labeling experiment corroborates our previous results based on natural <sup>13</sup>C and <sup>15</sup>N abundance showing that carbon allocation for ascocarp development could not be supplied mainly <italic>via</italic> saprotrophic pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Zeller1">[9]</xref>. According to our pulse-labeling experiment, almost all of the carbon allocated to the truffle ascocarps came from the host. These findings also corroborate the results of sequencing of the <italic>T. melanosporum</italic> genome, which showed that this fungus has a limited repertoire of genes coding for CAZymes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Martin1">[8]</xref>. Nevertheless, we cannot exclude the possibility of weak carbon allocation to the ascocarps from soil organic matter. Soil labeling experiments (<sup>15</sup>N and <sup>13</sup>C) are necessary to determine whether truffle ascocarps can also use dead host tissues or soil organic matter as carbon and nitrogen sources.</p>
<p>Several questions remain concerning the mode of carbon transfer between the host tree and developing ascocarps. Based on our results, it is clear that this transfer cannot occur through the soil. The soil and the soil solutions never appeared to be enriched in <sup>13</sup>C, regardless of the compartment considered. Epron et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064626-Epron1">[26]</xref> also observed an absence of bulk soil enrichment after <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse labeling of three species (<italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic>, <italic>Quercus petraea</italic> and <italic>Pinus pinaster</italic>).</p>
<p>This transfer also cannot take place <italic>via</italic> the external mycelium of the mycorrhizas. This mycelium extends to a maximum of a few millimeters from the mantle, and the ascocarps generally develop at least several cm from the mycorrhizas. The most likely hypothesis to explain this type of carbon transfer is a transport through the ascogonial structure, which could provide a direct connection between mycorrhizas and ascocarps.</p>
<p>In conclusion, it appears evident that <italic>Tuber</italic> ascocarps are dependent on their hosts throughout their development. These results contradict the statements of well-recognized truffle handbooks and could be of some importance for improvement of truffle cultivation methods, for example, through using caution regarding tree pruning at truffle primordium production and during truffle growth.</p>
</sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We want to thank Biela, our dog, which hunted the labeled truffles with success. Jean Villerd, (UMR 1121, Université de Lorraine) for his help with the statistical analysis. Erik Hobbie, for his constructive comments, which helped us to improve the manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Paolocci1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paolocci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riccioni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arcioni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Re-evaluation of the life cycle of Tuber magnatum</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>2390</fpage>–<lpage>2393</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Riccioni1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riccioni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belfiori</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Passeri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arcioni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Tuber melanosporum outcrosses: analysis of the genetic diversity within and among its natural populations under this new scenario</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>466</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Teramoto1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teramoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hogetsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Transfer of <sup>14</sup>C-photosynthate to the sporocarp of an ectomycorrhizal fungus Laccaria amethystina</article-title>. <source>Mycorrhiza</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Olivier1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Olivier J-M, Savignac J-C, Sourzat P (2012) Truffe et trufficulture, Fanlac editor, Périgueux, France.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Barry1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staunton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Callot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Mode of the absorption of water and nutrients by ascocarps of Tuber melanosporum and Tuber aestivum. A radioactive tracer technique</article-title>. <source>Can J Bot</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Callot1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Callot G, Byé P, Raymond M, Fernandez D, Pargney JC, <etal>et al</etal>.. (1999) La truffe, la terre, la vie: Quae, INRA. 210 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Mamoun1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mamoun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Influence du substrat carboné et de la forme d’azote minéral sur la croissance de T. melanosporum Vittad. en culture pure. Application à la production de biomasse mycélienne</article-title>. <source>Agronomie</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>527</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Martin1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balestrini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Perigord black truffle genome uncovers evolutionary origins and mechanisms of symbiosis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>464</volume>: <fpage>1033</fpage>–<lpage>1038</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Zeller1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bréchet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maurice</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Tacon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Saprotrophic versus symbiotic strategy during truffle ascocarp development under holm oak. A response based on <sup>13</sup>C and <sup>15</sup>N natural abundance</article-title>. <source>Ann For Sci</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>614</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Rouquerolle1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouquerolle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Payre</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Conséquences de quelques particularités biologiques des Tuber sur les caractères des cultures de mycélium et sur la formation des truffes</article-title>. <source>Rev Mycol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Robin1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaillant</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vansuyt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zinsou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Assimilate partitioning in Pachyrhizus erosus L. during long-day vegetative development</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Leake1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leake</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostle</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rangel-Castro</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Carbon fluxes from plants through soil organisms determined by field <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse-labelling in an upland grassland</article-title>. <source>Applied Soil Ecology</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-NGuyen1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>NGuyen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Todorovic</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christophe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guckert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Continuous monitoring of rhizosphere respiration after labelling of plant shoots with <sup>14</sup>CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source> <volume>212</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Johnson1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leake</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ineson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>In situ <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse-labelling of upland grassland demonstrates a rapid pathway of carbon flux from arbuscular mycorrhizal mycelia to the soil</article-title>. <source>New Phythol</source> <volume>153</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Ek1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The influence of nitrogen fertilization on the carbon economy of Paxillus involutus in ectomycorrhizal association with Betula pendula</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Finlay1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>The structure and function of the vegetative mycelium of ectomycorrhizal plants. 1. The translocation of <sup>14</sup>C-labelled carbon between plants interconnected by a common mycelium</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Horwath1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horwath</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pregitzer</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title><sup>14</sup>C Allocation in tree-soil systems</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1163</fpage>–<lpage>1176</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Leake2"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leake</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Rates and quantities of carbon flux to ectomycorrhizal mycelium following <sup>14</sup>C pulse labeling of Pinus sylvestris seedlings: effects of litter patches and interaction with a wood-decomposer fungus</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Leanne1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leanne</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Minimum pulses of stable and radioactive carbon isotopes to detect belowground carbon transfer between plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source> <volume>308</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Miller1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durall</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rygiewicz</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Temporal allocation of <sup>14</sup>C to extramatrical hyphae of ectomycorrhizal ponderosa pine seedlings</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Norton1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Firestone</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Carbon flow in the rhizosphere of Ponderosa pine seedlings</article-title>. <source>Soil Biol Biochem</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Ostle1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ostle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sleep</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ineson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Active microbial RNA turnover in a grassland soil estimated using a <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> spike</article-title>. <source>Soil Biol Biochem</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>885</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Rygiewicz1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rygiewicz</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Mycorrhizae alter quality and quantity of carbon allocated below ground</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>369</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Simard1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durall</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Carbon allocation and carbon transfer between Betula papyrifera and Pseudotsuga menziesii seedlings using a <sup>13</sup>C pulse-labeling method</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source> <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Hgberg1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Högberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Högberg</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gottlicher</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Betson</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keel</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>High temporal resolution tracing of photosynthate carbon from the tree canopy to forest soil microorganisms</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>177</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Epron1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Epron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ngao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dannoura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Seasonal variations of belowground carbon transfer assessed by in situ <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse labelling of trees</article-title>. <source>Biogeosciences</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1153</fpage>–<lpage>1168</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Plain1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maillard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dannoura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Tracing of recently assimilated carbon in respiration at high temporal resolution in the field with a tuneable diode laser absorption spectrometer after in situ <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse labelling of 20-year-old beech trees</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1433</fpage>–<lpage>1445</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Subke1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vallack</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keel</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Short-term dynamics of abiotic and biotic soil <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> effluxes after in situ <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse labelling of a boreal pine forest</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Chevalier1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poitou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Study of important factors affecting the mycorrhizal development of the truffle fungus in the field using plants inoculated in nurseries</article-title>. <source>Agric Ecosyst Environ</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Paolocci2"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paolocci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granetti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arcioni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Rapid molecular approach for a reliable identification of Tuber spp. ectomycorrhizae</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Rubini1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paolocci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granetti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arcioni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Single step molecular characterization of morphologically similar black truffle species</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source> <volume>164</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Murat1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Murat C, Rubini A, Riccioni C, De la Varga H, Akroume E, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2013) Fine scale spatial genetic structure of the black truffle (<italic>Tuber melanosporum</italic>) investigated with neutral microsatellites and functional mating type genes. New Phytol doi: 10.1111/nph.12264.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Box1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Box</surname><given-names>GEP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>An analysis of transformation, Journal of the Royal Statistical Society</article-title>. <source>Series B (Methodological)</source><volume>26–2</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Treseder1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Treseder</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torn</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masiello</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>An ecosystem-scale radiocarbon tracer to test use of litter carbon by ectomycorrhizal fungi</article-title>. <source>Soil Biol Biochem</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1082</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Godbout1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Godbout</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Effects of nitrogen fertilization and photoperiod on basidiome formation of Laccaria bicolor associated with container-grown jack pine seedlings</article-title>. <source>Can J Bot</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Hgberg2"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Högberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nordgren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>AFS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ekblad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Large-scale forest girdling shows that current photosynthesis drives soil respiration</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>789</fpage>–<lpage>792</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Kuikka1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuikka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Härmä</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Markkola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rautio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roitto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Severe defoliation of Scots pine reduces reproductive investment by ectomycorrhizal symbionts</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>2051</fpage>–<lpage>2061</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Lamhamedi1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamhamedi</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Godbout</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Dependence of Laccaria bicolor basidiome development on current photosyn- thesis of Pinus strobus seedlings</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1797</fpage>–<lpage>1804</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Last1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Last</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pelham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ingleby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Influence of leaves on sporophore production by fungi forming sheathing mycorrhizas with Betula spp</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Pestaa1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pestaña</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santolamazza-Carbone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Defoliation negatively affects plant growth and the ectomycorrhizal community of Pinus pinaster in Spain</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source> <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>723</fpage>–<lpage>733</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Hobbie1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hobbie EA, Quimette AP, Schuur EAG, Kierstead D, Trappe JM, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2012) Radiocarbon evidence for the mining of organic nitrogen from soil by mycorrhizal fungi. Biogeochemistry doi: 10.1007/s10533-012-9779-z.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Essiamah1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Essiamah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eschrich</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Changes of starch content in the storage tissues of deciduous trees during winter and spring</article-title>. <source>IAWA Bulletin</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Sauter1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Cleve</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Storage, mobilization and interrelations of starch, sugars, protein and fat in the ray storage tissue of poplar trees</article-title>. <source>Trees</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Palonen1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palonen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buszard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Changes in carbohydrates and freezing tolerance during cold acclimation of red raspberry cultivars grown in vitro and in vivo</article-title>. <source>Physiol Plant</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Bollmark1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bollmark</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sennerby-Forsse</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ericsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Seasonal dynamics and effects of nitrogen supply rate on nitrogen and carbohydrate reserves in cutting-derived Salix viminalis plants</article-title>. <source>Can J For Res</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Johansson1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Seasonal changes in contents of root starch and soluble carbohydrates in 4–6 year old Betula pubescens and Populus tremula</article-title>. <source>Scand J For Res</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Landhusser1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landhäusser</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lieffers</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Seasonal changes in carbohydrate reserves in mature northern Populus tremuloides clones</article-title>. <source>Trees - Structure and Function</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Kagawa1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kagawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maximov</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>2006a</year>) <article-title><sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> pulse-labelling of photoassimilates reveals carbon allocation within and between tree rings</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1571</fpage>–<lpage>1584</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Kagawa2"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kagawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maximov</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>2006b</year>) <article-title>Seasonal course of translocation, storage and remobilization of <sup>13</sup>C pulse-labeled photoassimilate in naturally growing Larix gmelinii saplings</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>171</volume>: <fpage>793</fpage>–<lpage>803</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064626-Maurel1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonhomme</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guilliot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rageau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Trophic control of bud break in peach (Prunus persica) trees: a possible role of hexoses</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>588</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>