<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
    <publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
    <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
    </journal-meta><article-meta>
			<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-19922</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074471</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
    <subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group>
				<article-title>Relationship between Differential Hepatic microRNA Expression and Decreased Hepatic Cytochrome P450 3A Activity in Cirrhosis</article-title>
			<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Regulation of Hepatic CYP3A by MicroRNA</alt-title>
      </title-group>
			<contrib-group>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Vuppalanchi</surname>
						<given-names>Raj</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Liang</surname>
						<given-names>Tiebing</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Goswami</surname>
						<given-names>Chirayu Pankaj</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Nalamasu</surname>
						<given-names>Rohit</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Li</surname>
						<given-names>Lang</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Jones</surname>
						<given-names>David</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Wei</surname>
						<given-names>Rongrong</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Liu</surname>
						<given-names>Wanqing</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Sarasani</surname>
						<given-names>Vishal</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Janga</surname>
						<given-names>Sarath Chandra</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib xlink:type="simple" contrib-type="author">
					<name name-style="western">
						<surname>Chalasani</surname>
						<given-names>Naga</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
					<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref>
				</contrib>
			</contrib-group>
			<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Medicine, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, Indiana, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
			<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Center for Computational Biology and Bioinformatics, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, Indiana, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
			<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Medicinal Chemistry &amp; Molecular Pharmacology, College of Pharmacy, Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
			<contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ray</surname>
            <given-names>Ranjit</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
        </contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Saint Louis University, United States of America</addr-line></aff><author-notes>
				<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">nchalasa@iu.edu</email></corresp>
				<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RV LT NC. Performed the experiments: CG RN LL DJ RW WL. Analyzed the data: RV LT CG NC WL VS SCJ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LT DJ WL. Wrote the manuscript: RV NC. </p></fn>
			</author-notes>
			<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e74471</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history><permissions>
    <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Vuppalanchi et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license>
    </permissions><abstract>
				<sec sec-type="headed">
					<title>Background and Aim</title><p>Liver cirrhosis is associated with decreased hepatic cytochrome P4503A (CYP3A) activity but the pathogenesis of this phenomenon is not well elucidated. In this study, we examined if certain microRNAs (miRNA) are associated with decreased hepatic CYP3A activity in cirrhosis.</p>
				</sec>
				<sec sec-type="headed">
					<title>Methods</title><p>Hepatic CYP3A activity and miRNA microarray expression profiles were measured in cirrhotic (n=28) and normal (n=12) liver tissue. Hepatic CYP3A activity was measured via midazolam hydroxylation in human liver microsomes. Additionally, hepatic CYP3A4 protein concentration and the expression of CYP3A4 mRNA were measured. Analyses were conducted to identify miRNAs which were differentially expressed between two groups but also were significantly associated with lower hepatic CYP3A activity.</p>
				</sec>
				<sec sec-type="headed">
					<title>Results</title><p>Hepatic CYP3A activity in cirrhotic livers was 1.7-fold lower than in the normal livers (0.28 ± 0.06 vs. 0.47 ± 0.07mL* min<sup>-1</sup>*mg protein<sup>-1</sup> (mean ± SEM), P=0.02). Six microRNAs (miR-155, miR-454, miR-582-5p, let-7f-1*, miR-181d, and miR-500) had &gt;1.2-fold increase in cirrhotic livers and also had significant negative correlation with hepatic CYP3A activity (range of r = -0.44 to -0.52, P &lt;0.05). Notably, miR-155, a known regulator of liver inflammation, had the highest fold increase in cirrhotic livers (2.2-fold, P=4.16E-08) and significantly correlated with hepatic CYP3A activity (r=-0.50, P=0.017). The relative expression (2<sup>-ΔΔCt</sup> mean ± SEM) of hepatic CYP3A4 mRNA was significantly higher in cirrhotic livers (21.76 ± 2.65 vs. 5.91 ± 1.29, P=2.04E-07) but their levels did not significantly correlate with hepatic CYP3A activity (r=-0.43, P=0.08).</p>
				</sec>
				<sec sec-type="headed">
					<title>Conclusion</title><p>The strong association between certain miRNAs, notably miR-155, and lower hepatic CYP3A activity suggest that altered miRNA expression may regulate hepatic CYP3A activity.</p>
				</sec>
			</abstract>
		<funding-group><funding-statement>Administrative supplements awarded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (ARRA) for 3K24DK069290-05S1 to Dr. Chalasani. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta>
	</front>
	<body>
		<sec id="s1" sec-type="introduction">
			<title>Introduction</title>
			<p>Cirrhosis is associated with altered drug disposition and often requires dosage adjustments in order to prevent adverse effects resulting from excessive drug/metabolite accumulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Although altered drug distribution and impaired renal elimination could contribute to overall drug disposition, altered activity of drug metabolizing enzymes is the predominant factor determining drug disposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A is the most abundant hepatic drug metabolizing enzyme and accounts for the clearance of more than 50% of those drugs that undergo biotransformation in the liver including calcium channel blockers, protease inhibitor anti-retrovirals, most statins and macrolide antibiotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Although there is considerable inter-individual variability (~ 50 fold) in the CYP3A activity in healthy humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], it is variably and non-uniformly reduced in cirrhosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Prior studies evaluating the CYP activity in cirrhosis have also shown that the loss of CYP activity is selective and dependent on the etiology (cholestatic vs. noncholestatic) and severity of liver disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. George et al. showed CYP3A activity (using testosterone β-hydroxylase activity) and protein reduction only in livers of patients from cirrhosis due to non-cholestatic liver disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Frye et al. proposed a “sequential progressive model of hepatic dysfunction” to explain their data demonstrating selective impairment of CYPs with severity of liver disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Unfortunately, CYP3A activity was not evaluated in their study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Our group has previously reported a 2-fold reduction in CYP3A activity in patients with cirrhosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p>
			<p>In healthy humans, the genetic variability in CYP3A activity could to a certain degree be explained through cis-acting elements e.g. genetic polymorphisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] and/or trans-acting factors such as pregnane X receptor (PXR, or nuclear receptor subfamily 1, group I, member 2 [NR1I2]) and constitutive androstane receptor (CAR, or nuclear receptor subfamily 1, group I, member 3 [NR1I3]) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Wolbold et al. have also shown a positive correlation between PXR and CYP3A4 mRNA and protein expression in a collection of human liver biopsy tissue samples, suggesting that PXR strongly regulates the expression of CYP3A4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Some studies have suggested pre-translational regulation of CYP3A mRNA expression and activity through modulation of PXR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Others have suggested epigenetic modification for CYP3A4 gene promoters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. More recently, Klein et al., have reported that peroxisome proliferator–activated receptor-α (<italic>PPAR</italic> α or nuclear receptor subfamily 1, group C, member 1 [NR1C1]) is also involved in the regulation of CYP3A protein in liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. However, in pathological situations like cirrhosis, inflammatory signaling pathways may interfere with constitutive expression, leading to significant downregulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. The exact mechanisms behind these translational or posttranscriptional regulations of hepatic CYP3A in cirrhosis are currently not well understood.</p>
			<p>Recently discovered, microRNAs (miRNAs / miRs) are small (18-25 nucleotides), non-coding RNAs that bind to the 3’-untranslated region (3’-UTR) of mRNA and negatively regulate gene expression. These miRNAs regulate gene expression by one of the two following mechanisms - by blocking protein translation or by cleaving the mRNA and thus could at least in part contribute to post-transcriptional regulation of gene. The physiological and biological significance of miRNAs in liver function is well illustrated through down regulation of hepatocyte nuclear factor 4α (HNF4α), a key transcription factor regulation of endogenous, xenobiotic metabolizing enzymes and transporters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Similarly, in-silico [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] and experimental analysis have also suggested that miRNAs are important regulators for CYP3A as well as PXR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. For example, miR27-b and mmu-miR298 decreased CYP3A4 mRNA and protein expression level in human embryonic kidney cells in transient transfection experiment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. Furthermore, down-regulation of vitamin D receptor (VDR) by the two miRNA led them to conclude that CYP3A4 gene expression could be regulated by miRNAs at both the transcriptional and post-transcriptional level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. Takagi et al. investigated the interindividual variability of CYP3A4 mRNA reported that miR-148a post-transcriptionally regulated human PXR, resulting in the modulation of the inducible and/or constitutive levels of CYP3A4 in human liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. On the other hand, earlier studies profiling miRNAs in liver diseases have identified a number of miRNAs significantly up- or down-regulated in human liver diseases including cirrhosis (for review: Gastroenterology. 2012 Jun; 142(7):1431-43.), suggesting that miRNAs are critical regulators for liver function in liver disease. It is thus plausible to expect significant hepatic miRNA changes in cirrhosis that could potentially mediate the altered CYP activity, via transcriptional or translational regulations. We hypothesized in this study that the decreased CYP3A activity in cirrhosis is associated with significantly upregulated miRNAs that regulate CYP3A4 gene expression by targeting nuclear receptors (PXR, CAR or PPARα) mRNA or directly targeting CYP3A4 mRNA. The purpose of the current study is to determine the differentially expressed miRNAs in cirrhosis that are significantly associated with decreased CYP3A activity and examine the relationship with the nuclear receptor gene expression.</p>
		</sec>
		<sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
			<title>Materials and Methods</title>
			<sec id="s2.1">
				<title>Human liver samples</title>
				<p>This study was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Review Board (IUPUI # 0504-58 and EX0904-11) at Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA. The institutional review board waived the need for consent. This study is based on 40 human liver tissue samples collected from individuals with cirrhosis and those with normal liver tissue (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074471-t001">Table 1</xref>). Liver tissue was collected from individuals with established cirrhosis (n=28) at the time of their liver transplantation procedure in the operating room. Demographic data, etiology of cirrhosis and other relevant information such as medication, alcohol use, and smoking history were captured at the time of enrollment. Normal liver tissue (n=12) was obtained from patients undergoing liver resection for metastatic/benign liver lesions with no underlying chronic liver disease. Histopathological evaluation with hematoxylin and eosin staining was used to assess tumor adjacent normal liver tissue in order to exclude occult chronic hepatitis and cirrhosis. Liver tissue samples were snap frozen using liquid nitrogen and stored at -80°C until use. All samples were collected and handled equally except for duration of storage.</p>
				<table-wrap id="pone-0074471-t001" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Select demographics, gene expression and CYP3A activity in study cohort.</title>
					</caption>
					<table>
						<colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cirrhosis</bold> (n=28)</th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Normal</bold> (n=12)</th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Demographics</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years (mean ± SD)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4 ± 13.7</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5 ± 18.8</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females (%)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic white (%)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI kg/m<sup>2</sup> (mean ± SD)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6 ± 5.7</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not available</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes (%)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not available</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">History of smoking (%)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not available</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Etiology of cirrhosis (%)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-	NASH (n=17)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-	Cholestatic (n=11)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Concomitant HCC (n=5)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Relative gene expression</bold> (2<sup>-ΔΔCt</sup> mean ± SEM)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>P</underline> <underline>value</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYP3A4 mRNA</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.76 ± 2.65</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91 ± 1.29</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04E-07</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PXR mRNA</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.15 ± 0.45</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45 ± 0.87</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAR mRNA</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26 ± 0.43</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55 ± 0.71</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0008</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPARα mRNA</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 ± 0.06</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 ± 0.01</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90029E-12</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CYP3A activity</bold> (mL*min<sup>-1</sup>*mg protein<sup>-1</sup>) (mean ± SEM)</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 ± 0.06</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 ± 0.07</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<table-wrap-foot>
						<fn>
							<p>N/A: not applicable</p>
						</fn>
					</table-wrap-foot>
				</table-wrap>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s2.2">
				<title>CYP3A activity in cirrhosis and normal liver tissue</title>
				<p>Liver homogenates were prepared and suspended in buffer and stored in a -80°C freezer until use. The protein concentration of the homogenates was assayed using Lowry method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. Hepatic microsomes were prepared as published previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] and stored at −80°C until used. The CYP3A activity was quantified in human liver microsomes using midazolam 1’-hydroxylation as probe reaction. In brief, midazolam (0.25-75 µmol/L) was incubated with human liver microsomes (0.25-800 µg total protein), 100 mmol/L phosphate buffer pH = 7.4, and 2 mmol/L reduced nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate for 2 minutes. The reaction was stopped with an equal volume of acetonitrile. 1’-OH midazolam was quantified from the supernatant with HPLC-UV (λ = 254) using alprazolam as the internal standard. The maximum velocity of metabolite formation (V<sub>max</sub>, pmols*mg protein<sup>-1</sup>*min<sup>-1</sup>), and the Michaelis constant (K<sub>m</sub>, µM) were estimated using a single enzyme model with WinNonlin Standard Edition v2.0 (Pharsight, Palo Alto CA). In vitro intrinsic clearance (CL<sub>int</sub>) of CYP3A was given as V<sub>max</sub> / K<sub>m.</sub></p>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s2.3">
				<title>miRNA microarray</title>
				<p>Global microRNA expression analysis (485 miRNA probes passed statistical filtering) was performed by Thermo Scientific Dharmacon RNAi Discovery and Therapeutic Services (Lafayette, Colorado, USA). The Thermo Scientific Dharmacon microRNA expression profiling platform utilizes a proprietary, two-color high-density 8-plex slide comprised of probes to capture all human, mouse and rat mature microRNAs in the Sanger database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://microrna.sanger.ac.uk" xlink:type="simple"><underline>http://microrna.sanger.ac.uk</underline></ext-link>). The microRNA expression data has been uploaded to Gene Expression Omnibus archive and is set for data release as of August 15<sup>th</sup> 2013 (Accession number GSE49012).</p>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s2.4">
				<title>Confirmation of candidate microRNA and quantification of mRNA expression using qRT-PCR</title>
				<p>Total RNA including miRNA was isolated from the liver tissue using mirVana™ miRNA isolation Kit (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY). To eliminate residual genomic DNA contamination, the RNA samples were incubated with DNase I (RNase-Free DNase Set, QIAGEN) on columns according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The RNA quantity and quality were measured using both Nano drop and Agilent bioanalyzer to ensure the good quality of RNA. The amplification primers for PXR, CAR and PPARα were designed using <italic>Vector NTI</italic>. With the ABI 7300 qPCR system, TaqMan chemistry was used for microRNA quantification and the SybrGreen was applied to quantify mRNA levels. Following reverse transcription of the RNA (Life Technologies), an aliquot of each reverse transcription reaction was amplified in triplicate in an ABI 7300 qPCR system. This system generates quantitative data based on the PCR at early cycles when amplification is in the linear range and PCR fidelity is the highest. GAPDH and 18s rRNA were used as internal controls for mRNA quantification and U6 was used as internal control for miRNA quantification. We quantified CYP3A4, PXR, and CAR mRNA and miRNA levels using comparative method (ΔΔCT method) and PPARα mRNA levels using relative standard curve method (Life Science htpp://www.appliedbiosystems.com) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>].</p>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s2.5">
				<title>Western Blotting of CYP3A4</title>
				<p>Randomly selected cirrhotic (n=5) and normal liver samples (n=5) were used to measure the hepatic CYP3A4 protein expression. Briefly, 10mg of liver tissue was homogenized using the Mini-Beadbeater-16 (Biospec Products, OK, USA). The homogenates were centrifuged and the supernatant was collected. Total protein concentration of each supernatant sample was measured using Qubit® 2.0 Fluorometer (Life Technologies, CA, USA) and normalized to same concentration prior to western blotting. For western blotting, 500ng total protein of each sample was separated using 12% SDS-PAGE gel electrophoresis, transferred to nitrocellulose membranes, and then blotted with anti-CYP3A4 (XenoTech, KS, USA) and anti-GAPDH (Abcam, MA, USA) as an internal control. The blotted proteins were detected and visualized using the ECL Western Blotting kit (Amersham Biosciences, NJ, USA). Quantification of the intensity of blotted band was conducted using ImageJ (http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/). The relative expression of CYP3A4 was determined by normalizing the CYP3A4 band intensity to that of GAPDH of the same sample.</p>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s2.6">
				<title>Statistical and bioinformatics analyses</title>
				<p>Batch effect in the miRNA microarray samples was removed statistically. ANOVA analysis with False Discovery Rate (FDR) and multiple test correction were performed to identify differentially expressed miRNAs between cirrhotic and control liver tissue samples. Comparisons of mRNA expression were made between groups by using Student’s t-test. Pearson’s correlation test was utilized to assess the correlation between miRNA expression and CYP3A activity and between mRNA expression of PXR, CAR or PPARα and CYP3A4 mRNA. Nonparametric Mann-Whitney test was used to compare the difference in the relative CYP3A4 protein expression between cirrhotic and normal livers. Results from correlation analysis and ANOVA analysis were merged to identify a subset of differentially expressed miRNAs which are significant upregulated in the cirrhotic group (P&lt;0.05) and yet had significant negative correlation with CYP3A activity (P&lt;0.05). A P-value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
				<p>To predict the potential binding sites of the miRNAs identified to control the CYP3A4 gene in this study, we first obtained the transcripts encoded by this gene’s locus. Current annotations from the Ensembl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] suggest that two major transcripts ENST00000336411 and ENST00000354593 are responsible for the protein expression of CYP3A4. So we obtained the 3’ UTR sequences of these transcripts using Ensembl biomart. The 3’ UTR sequence of ENST00000336411 comprised of 464 base pair while that of ENST00000354593 was 1172 base pair in length. Fasta sequences of 14 microRNAs found to correlate with CYP3A activity were obtained from miRbase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. Genomic targets for microRNAs were predicted by using microRNA Target detection software miRanda [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Miranda is a machine learning method for ranking microRNA target sites by a down-regulation score by integrating gene expression and sequence level features. The algorithm trains a regression model on sequence and contextual features extracted from high confidence miRanda-predicted target sites and hence can predict non-canonical and non-conserved sites. Target sites and their locations were identified for the miRNAs of interest using the max score threshold set to 110. A total of 55 sites were identified on the 3’ UTRs of these two transcripts. Target sites predicted by miRNA were formatted into a General Feature Format (GFF) file using the binding co-ordinates with respect to the UTR regions, to visualize the location of the binding sites using GFF2PS tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>].</p>
			</sec>
		</sec>
		<sec id="s3" sec-type="results">
			<title>Results</title>
			<sec id="s3.1">
				<title>Hepatic CYP3A activity and protein expression</title>
				<p>Hepatic CYP3A activity in cirrhotic liver samples was significantly lower compared to normal liver tissue by 1.7-fold (0.28 ± 0.06 vs. 0.47 ± 0.07mL* min<sup>-1</sup>*mg protein<sup>-1</sup> (mean ± SEM), P=0.02) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074471-g001">Figure <bold>1A</bold></xref>). Similarly, CYP3A protein level in cirrhotic liver samples was significantly lower than in control liver samples by western blotting (P=0.01) and a quantitative image analysis showed a 2.5-fold lower level of CYP3A protein in cirrhotic livers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074471-g001">Figure <bold>1B</bold></xref>).</p>
				<fig id="pone-0074471-g001" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Cytochrome P450 3A activity and protein expression in cirrhosis and normal liver tissue samples.</title>
						<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Decreased CYP3A activity as determined by the intrinsic clearance based on formation of 1’-OH midazolam formation in cirrhosis and normal liver tissue samples. (<bold>B</bold>) CYP3A4 protein expression in randomly selected cirrhotic (n=5) and normal liver samples (n=5) detected by western blotting (upper panel). Quantified CYP3A4 expression relative to GAPDH was shown as well (bottom panel). Experiments were repeated twice and the representative sample was shown.</p>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.g001"/>
				</fig>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s3.2">
				<title>Differential hepatic miRNA expression and their relationship to hepatic CYP3A activity</title>
				<p>A total of 183 miRNAs were differentially expressed in cirrhotic liver tissue compared to normal liver tissue with P&lt;0.05 and a fold-change ranging from -2.47 to 2.27. Several miRNAs had significant correlation with hepatic CYP3A activity and also had significant differential expression between cirrhotic and control liver tissues (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074471.s001">Figure <bold>S1</bold></xref>). To generate a list of miRNAs that potentially regulated hepatic CYP3A activity, we merged the results of the ANOVA and correlation analyses which identified a subset of miRNAs with significantly higher expression in cirrhotic livers and also had significant negative correlation with hepatic CYP3A activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074471-g002">Figure <bold>2</bold></xref>). This merged analysis revealed 14 miRNAs with higher expression in cirrhotic livers but had negative correlation with hepatic CYP3A activity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074471-t002">Table <bold>2</bold></xref>). Among the miRNAs, miR-155, miR-454, miR-582-5p, let-7f-1*, miR-181d, and miR-500 had &gt; 1.2-fold increase in cirrhotic liver samples (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074471-t002">Table <bold>2</bold></xref>). Of particular interest is miR-155 which had the highest fold increase in cirrhotic livers (2.2-fold, P=4.16E-08) and negatively correlated with CYP3A activity (r = -0.50, P=0.017). There was a significant negative correlation between mean expression of all 14 miRNAs combined and hepatic CYP3A activity (r = -0.53, P=0.012).</p>
				<fig id="pone-0074471-g002" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Correlation between correlation of expression of selected miRNA with CYP3A activity (X-axis) in cirrhosis group and the correlation of the expression of the same miRNA with CYP3A activity in the normal liver group (Y-axis).</title>
						<p>Each point in the figure represents a single miRNA.</p>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.g002"/>
				</fig>
				<table-wrap id="pone-0074471-t002" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label>
					<caption>
						<title>miRNAs that are upregulated in cirrhotic livers and had significant negative correlation with hepatic CYP3A activity.</title>
					</caption>
					<table>
						<colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>miRNA</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Correlation (r value</bold>)<bold> of miR expression with CYP3A activity</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P (for differential miRNA expression</bold>)</th>
								<th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Fold-Change (cirrhosis/control</bold>)<sup>¶</sup></th>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Microarray</bold></th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>qRT-PCR</bold></th>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-155</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.50</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16E-08</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-454</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.44</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29E-06</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-582-5p</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.44</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.47E-06</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-let-7f-1*</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.44</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.73E-05</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-181d</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.46</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000212</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-500</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.44</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000412</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-181c</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.52</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005571</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-411</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.50</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008032</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-532-5p</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.44</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011412</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-363</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.48</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016422</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-381</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.49</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017241</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-302c*</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.49</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030258</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-652</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.47</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036603</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsa-miR-452</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.50</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040303</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<table-wrap-foot>
							<p>NA: No data available as qRT-PCR was only performed on top 6 microRNA.</p>
							<p>The fold change of hepatic miRNA in cirrhosis is in comparison to healthy liver control tissue samples.</p>
						<p>¶ The fold change of hepatic miRNA in cirrhosis is in comparison to healthy liver control tissue samples.</p>
					</table-wrap-foot>
				</table-wrap>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s3.3">
				<title>Relationship between CYP3A4 and selected nuclear receptor gene expression</title>
				<p>The CYP3A4, PXR, CAR and PPARα mRNA were detected in all liver samples and they exhibited significant variability in their expression both in cirrhotic and normal liver tissue (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074471-t003">Table <bold>3</bold></xref>). Their relative expression was significantly higher in cirrhotic livers compared to normal liver samples (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074471-t003">Table <bold>3</bold></xref>). To investigate the association between selected nuclear receptors (PXR, CAR and PPARα) and <italic>CYP3A4</italic> gene expression, their correlation was examined in cirrhotic and control groups separately. CYP3A4 mRNA tightly correlated with PXR mRNA (r=0.91, P= 2.50E-08), CAR mRNA (r=0.93, P= 5.42E-09) and PPARα mRNA (r=0.92, P= 9.56E-09) in the control group. Although not as stronger, this relationship was still apparent in cirrhotic livers where CYP3A4 mRNA correlated with PXR (r=0.46, P=0.01), CAR (r=0.51, P=0.006) and PPARα (r=0.54, P=0.003) mRNA expression.</p>
				<table-wrap id="pone-0074471-t003" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label>
					<caption>
						<title>CYP3A4, PXR, CAR and PPARα mRNA expression in cirrhotic and normal liver samples.</title>
					</caption>
					<table>
						<colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Intra-group variability in mRNA expression</bold><hr/></th>
								<th colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Relative mRNA expression</bold><hr/></th>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Normal (n=12</bold>)</th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cirrhosis (n=28</bold>)</th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Normal (n=12</bold>)</th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cirrhosis (n=28</bold>)</th>
								<th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P-value</bold></th>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CYP3A4 mRNA</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">449-fold</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209-fold</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91 ± 1.29</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.76 ± 2.65</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04E-07</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PXR mRNA</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">490-fold</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14-fold</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45 ± 0.87</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.15 ± 0.45</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CAR mRNA</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172-fold</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24-fold</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55 ± 0.71</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26 ± 0.43</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0008</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PPARα mRNA</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3637-fold</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225-fold</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 ± 0.01</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 ± 0.06</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90029E-12</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
				</table-wrap>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s3.4">
				<title>Relationship between selected nuclear receptors mRNA, CYP3A4 mRNA and CYP3A activity</title>
				<p>The negative correlation between CYP3A4 mRNA and hepatic CYP3A activity in cirrhotic liver samples failed to reach statistical significance (r = -0.43, P=0.08). In cirrhotic liver samples, there was generally a negative correlation between CYP3A activity and CAR, PXR and PPARα mRNA expression, but the association was significant only for PXR mRNA (r= -0.54, P=0.02). Interestingly, in the normal liver tissue there was no significant association between hepatic CYP3A activity and CYP3A4, CAR, PXR or PPARα mRNA expression.</p>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s3.5">
				<title>Relationship between miRNAs and mRNA expression of selected nuclear receptors mRNA and CYP3A4 mRNA</title>
				<p>In order to examine the potential role of the selected 14 miRNA in the regulation of hepatic CYP3A activity through post-transcriptional regulation, a correlation analysis was performed in normal and cirrhosis groups separately between miRNA and mRNA expression of CYP3A4 and selected nuclear receptors. In the normal liver tissue, the majority of miRNA correlated with mRNA expression of CYP3A4 (57%) and nuclear receptors (up to 93% for PPARα). In contrast, this degree of correlation was not seen in cirrhosis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074471-t004">Table <bold>4</bold></xref>). Only two miRNA (has-let 7f 1* and has-miR 500) correlated with CYP3A4 mRNA and only one miRNA (has-miR 181d) correlated with PXR mRNA.</p>
				<table-wrap id="pone-0074471-t004" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Correlation analysis between miRNA and mRNA expression of CYP3A4 and select nuclear receptors (PXR, CAR and PPARα) in cirrhosis and normal liver tissue.</title>
					</caption>
					<table>
	<colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup>
						<thead>
<tr><td colspan="9" rowspan="1"><bold>Cirrhosis</bold><hr/></td>
</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/></td>
								<td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><underline><italic>CYP 3A4</italic></underline></bold> <bold><underline><italic/></underline></bold><hr/></td>
								<td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><underline><italic>PXR</italic></underline></bold><hr/></td>
								<td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><underline><italic>CAR</italic></underline></bold><hr/></td>
								<td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><underline><italic>PPARα</italic></underline></bold><hr/></td>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Normal</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>R</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>R</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>R</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>R</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_302c_*</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084364</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.20</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.387729</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.10</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.663752</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.36</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109445</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_582_5p</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107842</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.15</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512426</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.937971</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.23</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.322844</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_let_7f_1_*</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>0.044578</italic></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.23</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.316745</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.10</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.657649</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.32</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151573</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_411</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067978</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.27</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232043</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.17</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.473656</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.11</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63548</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_381</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.156986</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.19</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.397427</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.06</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.797608</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901204</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_454</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068732</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.41</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067509</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.25</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267514</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.26</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248468</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_181c</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.260728</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.27</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244541</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.17</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471892</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.08</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7299</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_181d</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069606</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.44</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>0.048326</italic></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.34</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.137086</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.13</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.566524</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_155</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101412</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.31</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173238</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.20</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38348</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.16</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.480846</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_532_5p</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057871</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.988572</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41248</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.22</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.340639</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_500</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>0.031564</italic></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.13</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.571989</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.02</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.927534</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.16</td>
						<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.483486</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_652</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080473</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.23</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31141</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.10</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653354</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.13</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574028</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_363</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128097</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.16</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.475747</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.06</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.800896</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.04</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.873588</td>
						</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_452</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15923</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.04</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.861106</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.539199</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.20</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382359</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_302c_*</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.61</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.036424</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.65</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.021117</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.73</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.007031</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.001124</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_582_5p</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.59</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.044251</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.64</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.024298</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.68</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.014715</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.011959</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_let_7f_1_*</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.038018</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.66</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.019887</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.71</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.00951</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.004071</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_411</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.57</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053899</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.62</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.032519</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.70</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.011777</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.001961</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_381</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.55</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065207</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.59</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.042576</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.57</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.051956</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.110354</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_454</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.48</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114549</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.57</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053069</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.63</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.027302</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.007791</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_181c</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.59</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.043219</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.61</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.034777</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.70</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.011955</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.000837</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_181d</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.59</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.04374</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.61</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.03656</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.68</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.014522</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.002116</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_155</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.50</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.099561</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.53</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075015</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.60</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.038651</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.016024</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_532_5p</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.57</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050579</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.61</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.03519</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.67</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.018061</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.0041</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_500</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.55</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066793</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.59</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.043274</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.65</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.021733</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.007229</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_652</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.65</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.023005</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.71</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.009294</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.78</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.002854</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.001057</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_363</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.52</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084987</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.56</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057266</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.64</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.02412</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.00571</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>hsa_miR_452</bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.77</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.003249</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.80</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.001671</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.85</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.000485</underline></bold></td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
								<td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><underline>0.000736</underline></bold></td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
				</table-wrap>
			</sec>
			<sec id="s3.6">
				<title>In silico verification of CYP3A binding by miRNAs</title>
				<p>In this study, to identify the binding locations of the 14 miRNAs found to be associated with CYP3A4 gene, we used miRanda algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. A total of 55 binding sites were identified in the 3’ UTRs of the CYP3A4 transcripts (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074471.s002">Table S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074471-g003">Figure 3</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074471-g003">Figure 3</xref> shows the distribution of these binding sites across the UTRs of the two transcripts. While 14 miRNAs were detected to have a binding site in the UTR of the longer transcript ENST00000354593, a total of 8 miRNA binding sites were detected in the untranslated regions of the second transcript.</p>
				<fig id="pone-0074471-g003" position="float">
					<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Block diagram showing the distribution of miRNA binding sites in the 3’ Untranslated regions (UTR) of the CYP3A4 transcripts.</title>
						<p>UTR regions of the both the transcripts ENST00000354593 (length 1172 bp) and ENST00000336411 (474 bp) are aligned to the left and shown from <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5’ to 3’</named-content> orientation. When multiple miRNAs were found to overlap in their binding locations on the respective transcripts, different tracks are used to improve the layout.</p>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:type="simple" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.g003"/>
				</fig>
			</sec>
		</sec>
		<sec id="s4" sec-type="discussion">
			<title>Discussion</title>
			<p>It has been long recognized that hepatic CYP3A activity is decreased in cirrhosis and this reduced hepatic CYP3A activity is a very clinical relevant issue because nearly 50% of all prescribed medicines are CYP3A substrates. But it is not well understood why cirrhosis is associated with lower hepatic CYP3A activity. Intuitively, one might consider decreased hepatic synthesis of CYP3A protein as the most likely explanation for this phenomenon, but there has not been a consistent relationship between hepatic CYP3A mRNA expression and hepatic CYP3A protein concentration or CYP3A activity. We examined if hepatic miRNAs influence hepatic CYP3A activity in cirrhosis and in fact we found evidence to suggest that certain miRNAs may play a role in the pathogenesis of decreased hepatic CYP3A activity in cirrhosis. The main observations are our study are: (a) it confirms that cirrhosis is associated with lower hepatic CYP3A activity as well as protein concentration; (b) some miRNAs are associated with lowered hepatic CYP3A activity in cirrhosis; and (c) the expression of CYP3A4 mRNA as well as a number of nuclear receptors (PXR, CAR and PPARα) known to regulate CYP3A expression is higher in cirrhosis. Based on these observations we speculate that cirrhosis is associated with increased expression of certain miRNAs which interfere with translation of CYP3A4 mRNA and synthesis of CYP3A protein. There may be a resulting compensatory increase in the expression of nuclear receptors and CYP3A4 mRNA. The increase in the expression of nuclear receptors and CYP3A4 mRNA is suggestive of post-transcriptional regulation of hepatic CYP3A activity by miRNA in cirrhosis.</p>
			<p>We observed 14 miRNAs which had significantly higher expression in cirrhotic livers but also had significant negative correlation with hepatic CYP3A activity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074471-t002">Table 2</xref>). Computational methods have played an important role in the prediction of miRNAs from the very beginning. Traditionally, some major features such as the hairpin-shaped stem loop structure, high minimal folding free-energy, gene expression relationships between miRNA-mRNA pairs and high evolutionary conservation of the seed regions have been used in the computational identification of miRNAs. A previous study from our institution had predicted eleven of these fourteen (79%) miRNAs (hsa-miR-454, has-miR-582-5p, has-miR-181d, has-miR-500, has-miR-181c, has-miR-411, has-miR-363, has-miR-381, has-miR-302c*, has-miR-652 and has-miR-452), to target CYP3A4/5/7 3’-UTR using in silico approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. In this study, to identify the binding locations of the 14 miRNAs found to be associated with CYP3A4 gene, we used miRanda algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. A total of 55 binding sites were identified in the 3’ UTR of the CYP3A4 transcripts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074471-g003">Figure 3</xref>). While 14 miRNAs were detected to have a binding site in the UTR of the longer transcript ENST00000354593, a total of 8 miRNA binding sites were detected in the untranslated regions of the second transcript. We found several combinations of miRNAs including miRNA-155, miRNA-181 and miRNA-652 as well as miRNA-363, miRNA-532 and miRNA-582 which clustered or overlapped in their binding locations on these UTRs, suggesting possible competition for binding to control gene expression in a combinatorial fashion.</p>
			<p>Importantly, several of the differentially expressed miRNAs have previously been suggested to have a role in the pathogenesis of liver fibrosis. Of significant interest are miRNAs with pro-fibrotic effect (miR-32, miR-155 and miR-15b*) exhibiting an increased expression, and miRNAs with an anti-fibrotic effect (miR-18a, miR-18*, miR-19a*, miR-19b-1*, miR-200a* and miR-335*) showing lower expression in cirrhotic livers (data not shown) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. Among these differentially regulated microRNA, miR-155 appears to be the most prominent regulator as it was significantly associated with lower hepatic CYP3A activity and &gt; 2-fold higher expression in the cirrhotic livers. Previous studies have shown miR-155, a regulator of inflammation, to be increased in different types of chronic liver diseases such as alcoholic liver disease, drug induced liver injury and hepatocellular cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Our study is unable to discern why miR-155 and miR-32 (and other 12 miRNAs) are overexpressed in cirrhosis, but it is possible that underlying etiological factors (e.g., hepatitis C, alcohol, insulin resistance), hepatic inflammation or liver fibrosis may play a role. Our findings suggest that inhibiting these miRNAs by antisense oligonucleotides might be an approach to correct hepatic CYP3 dysregulation in cirrhosis, although admittedly the clinical relevance of such a strategy is debatable.</p>
			<p>Certain aspects of our study need further discussion. Our study used microarrays to investigate the miRNAs and we admit that next generation high-throughput, high-resolution sequencing technology may discover new miRs and bring added value, but the costs were still prohibitive when this study was planned. Currently, microarray (microchip) profiling and quantitative real-time reverse transcription PCR (qRT-PCR) are the two most common methods. However, the results from microarray and qRT-PCR do not always concur. In order to address this concern, the top 5 candidate miRNAs from the microarray profiling were further confirmed by qRT-PCR to validate the accuracy of our microarray findings (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074471-t002">Table 2</xref>). Second, CYP3A5 mRNA was not measured in the current study. However, it is unlikely that the differential expression of CYP3A5 mRNA would affect our conclusions since its contribution to total liver CYP3A activity is minor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. Moreover, subjects enrolled in our study are all but one non-Hispanic Caucasian and are less likely to express <italic>CYP3A5 *1</italic> allele which leads to substantially expression of CYP3A5 protein and greater contribution to the total CYP3A activity. Our study could not confirm the previously reported relationship between miR-27b, mmu-miR298 and miR-148a and CYP3A activity. We speculate that difference in the study design i.e. human liver tissue expression vs. cell line transfection experiments may account for the disparity. In addition to miRNA regulation, post-transcriptional/translation regulation may also be due to the altered protein synthesis, modification and/or trafficking which we have not investigated in this study.</p>
		</sec>
		<sec id="s5">
			<title>Conclusions</title>
			<p>CYP3A activity is significantly lower in cirrhosis and was associated with differential expression of hepatic miRNA. The significant association between decreased CYP3A activity and up-regulation of select hepatic miRNA in cirrhosis is strongly suggestive of their regulatory role. Our study points towards miR-155 and miR-32 as two potential miRNA which may a play in the pathogenesis of decreased hepatic CYP3A activity in cirrhosis.</p>
		</sec>
		<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
			<title>Supporting Information</title>
			<supplementary-material xlink:type="simple" position="float" id="pone.0074471.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.s001" mimetype="image/tiff">
				<label>Figure S1</label>
				<caption>
					<p>Correlation between correlation of expression of miRNA with CYP3A activity i.e. intrinsic clearance (X-axis) in disease (cirrhosis) group and the correlation of the expression of the same miRNA with CYP3A activity in the control (normal) liver group (Y-axis).Each point in the figure represents a single miRNA. The size of the point represents that significance of the correlation in the cirrhosis group (there was no significant correlation of these miRNA with the CYP3A activity in the healthy livers). Left upper quadrant of the figure shows all the miRNAs which have positive correlation with CYP3A in healthy group (Y-axis), and negative correlation in the disease group (X-axis). The miRNAs in blue color are upregulated in the cirrhosis group, and those in red color are down regulated in expression. Circles represent miRNAs whose expression is statistically significantly correlated with CYP3A activity while triangles represent miRNA with no significant correlation. Thus, miRNA of interest for the study are those in the orange color, biggest in size and represented in the left upper quadrant.</p>
				<p>(TIF)</p></caption>
				</supplementary-material>
			<supplementary-material xlink:type="simple" position="float" id="pone.0074471.s002" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0074471.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document">
				<label>Table S1</label>
				<caption>
					<p>List of miRNA target sites for CYP3A4 gene.The binding locations of the miRNAs are shown with respect to the UTR co-ordinates of the respective transcripts.</p>
				<p>(DOCX)</p></caption>
				</supplementary-material>
		</sec>
	</body>
	<back>
		<ack>
			<p>We thank Todd C. Skaar, PhD, Associate Research Professor, Division of Clinical Pharmacology, Department of Medicine, Indiana University Medical Center, Indianapolis, Indiana, USA, for his critical review and thoughtful suggestions.</p>
		</ack>
		<ref-list>
			<title>References</title>
			<ref id="B1">
				<label>1</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verbeeck</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Pharmacokinetics and dosage adjustment in patients with hepatic dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>1147</fpage>-<lpage>1161</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00228-008-0553-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00228-008-0553-z</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18762933" xlink:type="simple">18762933</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B2">
				<label>2</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="web" xlink:type="simple"><comment>Guidance for Industry Pharmacokinetics in Patients with Impaired Hepatic Function: Study Design, Data Analysis, and Impact on Dosing and Labeling</comment> <collab xlink:type="simple">Food and Drug Administration website</collab>. <comment>Available: </comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/downloads/drugs/guidancecomplianceregulatoryinformation/guidances/ucm072123.pdf" xlink:type="simple"><underline>http://www.fda.gov/downloads/Drugs/GuidanceComplianceRegulatoryInformation/Guidances/UCM072123.pdf</underline></ext-link>. <comment>Accessed</comment> 2013 July 4.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B3">
				<label>3</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Clinical pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic considerations in patients with liver disease. An update</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>370</fpage>-<lpage>391</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2165/00003088-199529050-00005" xlink:type="simple">10.2165/00003088-199529050-00005</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8582120" xlink:type="simple">8582120</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B4">
				<label>4</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodighiero</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Effects of liver disease on pharmacokinetics. An update</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>-<lpage>431</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2165/00003088-199937050-00004" xlink:type="simple">10.2165/00003088-199937050-00004</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10589374" xlink:type="simple">10589374</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B5">
				<label>5</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zgheib</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaves-Gnecco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rabinovitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Liver disease selectively modulates cytochrome P450--mediated metabolism</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>245</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.clpt.2006.05.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.clpt.2006.05.006</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16952490" xlink:type="simple">16952490</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B6">
				<label>6</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Drug metabolism in end-stage liver disease. In vitro activities of some phase I and phase II enzymes</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0168-8278(90)91484-E" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0168-8278(90)91484-E</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2398265" xlink:type="simple">2398265</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B7">
				<label>7</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wrighton</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schuetz</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thummel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korzekwa</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The human CYP3A subfamily: practical considerations</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Rev</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>339</fpage>-<lpage>361</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1081/DMR-100102338" xlink:type="simple">10.1081/DMR-100102338</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11139133" xlink:type="simple">11139133</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B8">
				<label>8</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamba</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schuetz</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thummel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Genetic contribution to variable human CYP3A-mediated metabolism</article-title>. <source>Adv Drug Deliv Rev</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>1271</fpage>-<lpage>1294</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0169-409X(02)00066-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0169-409X(02)00066-2</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12406645" xlink:type="simple">12406645</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B9">
				<label>9</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbekai</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korashy</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Kadi</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The effect of liver cirrhosis on the regulation and expression of drug metabolizing enzymes</article-title>. <source>Curr Drug Metab</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>-<lpage>167</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2174/1389200043489054" xlink:type="simple">10.2174/1389200043489054</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15078193" xlink:type="simple">15078193</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B10">
				<label>10</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Different alterations of cytochrome P450 3A4 isoform and its gene expression in livers of patients with chronic liver diseases</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>-<lpage>363</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12532467" xlink:type="simple">12532467</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B11">
				<label>11</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mudra</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The effects of gender, age, ethnicity, and liver cirrhosis on cytochrome P450 enzyme activity in human liver microsomes and inducibility in cultured human hepatocytes</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source> <volume>199</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>209</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.taap.2004.01.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.taap.2004.01.010</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15364537" xlink:type="simple">15364537</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B12">
				<label>12</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolars</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turgeon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merion</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wrighton</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The erythromycin breath test selectively measures P450IIIA in patients with severe liver disease</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>238</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/clpt.1992.17" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/clpt.1992.17</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1544283" xlink:type="simple">1544283</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B13">
				<label>13</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liddle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Pre-translational regulation of cytochrome P450 genes is responsible for disease-specific changes of individual P450 enzymes among patients with cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>873</fpage>-<lpage>881</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0006-2952(94)00515-N" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0006-2952(94)00515-N</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7741759" xlink:type="simple">7741759</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B14">
				<label>14</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalasani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gorski</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galinsky</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Hepatic and intestinal cytochrome P450 3A activity in cirrhosis: effects of transjugular intrahepatic portosystemic shunts</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>1103</fpage>-<lpage>1108</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1053/jhep.2001.29306" xlink:type="simple">10.1053/jhep.2001.29306</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11731998" xlink:type="simple">11731998</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B15">
				<label>15</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willson</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The human orphan nuclear receptor PXR is activated by compounds that regulate CYP3A4 gene expression and cause drug interactions</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>1016</fpage>-<lpage>1023</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1172/JCI3703" xlink:type="simple">10.1172/JCI3703</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9727070" xlink:type="simple">9727070</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B16">
				<label>16</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liddle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The orphan human pregnane X receptor mediates the transcriptional activation of CYP3A4 by rifampicin through a distal enhancer module</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharmacol</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1329</fpage>-<lpage>1339</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10570062" xlink:type="simple">10570062</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B17">
				<label>17</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The far and distal enhancers in the CYP3A4 gene co-ordinate the proximal promoter in responding similarly to the pregnane X receptor but differentially to hepatocyte nuclear factor-4alpha</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>409</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>250</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1042/BJ20070613" xlink:type="simple">10.1042/BJ20070613</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17764444" xlink:type="simple">17764444</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B18">
				<label>18</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toriyabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aratsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Unveiling a new essential cis element for the transactivation of the CYP3A4 gene by xenobiotics</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharmacol</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>677</fpage>-<lpage>684</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1124/mol.108.050575" xlink:type="simple">10.1124/mol.108.050575</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19074998" xlink:type="simple">19074998</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B19">
				<label>19</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D’Costa</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liddle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of the human CYP3A4 gene by the constitutive androstane receptor</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharmacol</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>-<lpage>365</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1124/mol.62.2.359" xlink:type="simple">10.1124/mol.62.2.359</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12130689" xlink:type="simple">12130689</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B20">
				<label>20</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolbold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burk</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nüssler</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Sex is a major determinant of CYP3A4 expression in human liver</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>978</fpage>-<lpage>988</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1053/jhep.2003.50393" xlink:type="simple">10.1053/jhep.2003.50393</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14512885" xlink:type="simple">14512885</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B21">
				<label>21</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Post-transcriptional regulation of human pregnane X receptor by micro-RNA affects the expression of cytochrome P450 3A4</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>9674</fpage>-<lpage>9680</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M709382200" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M709382200</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18268015" xlink:type="simple">18268015</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B22">
				<label>22</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kacevska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wyss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kasela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>DNA methylation dynamics in the hepatic CYP3A4 gene promoter</article-title>. <source>Biochimie</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>2338</fpage>-<lpage>2344</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biochi.2012.07.013" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.biochi.2012.07.013</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22906825" xlink:type="simple">22906825</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B23">
				<label>23</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nussler</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>PPARA: a novel genetic determinant of CYP3A4 in vitro and in vivo</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>1044</fpage>-<lpage>1052</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/clpt.2011.336" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/clpt.2011.336</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22510778" xlink:type="simple">22510778</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B24">
				<label>24</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Gene-specific effects of inflammatory cytokines on cytochrome P450 2C, 2B6 and 3A4 mRNA levels in human hepatocytes</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1687</fpage>-<lpage>1693</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1124/dmd.107.015511" xlink:type="simple">10.1124/dmd.107.015511</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17576808" xlink:type="simple">17576808</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B25">
				<label>25</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs regulate human hepatocyte nuclear factor 4alpha, modulating the expression of metabolic enzymes and cell cycle</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>4415</fpage>-<lpage>4422</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M109.085431" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M109.085431</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20018894" xlink:type="simple">20018894</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B26">
				<label>26</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramamoorthy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaedigk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>In silico and in vitro identification of microRNAs that regulate hepatic nuclear factor 4alpha expression</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>726</fpage>-<lpage>733</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1124/dmd.111.040329" xlink:type="simple">10.1124/dmd.111.040329</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22232426" xlink:type="simple">22232426</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B27">
				<label>27</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Surapureddi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coulter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Human CYP2C8 is post-transcriptionally regulated by microRNAs 103 and 107 in human liver</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharmacol</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>-<lpage>540</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1124/mol.112.078386" xlink:type="simple">10.1124/mol.112.078386</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22723340" xlink:type="simple">22723340</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B28">
				<label>28</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The role of microRNAs in hepatocyte nuclear factor-4alpha expression and transactivation</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1829</volume>: <fpage>436</fpage>-<lpage>442</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bbagrm.2012.12.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2012.12.009</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23298640" xlink:type="simple">23298640</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B29">
				<label>29</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramamoorthy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skaar</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>In silico identification of microRNAs predicted to regulate the drug metabolizing cytochrome P450 genes</article-title>. <source>Drugs Metab Lett</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>126</fpage>-<lpage>131</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2174/187231211795305258" xlink:type="simple">10.2174/187231211795305258</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21457141" xlink:type="simple">21457141</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B30">
				<label>30</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs from biology to future pharmacotherapy: regulation of cytochrome P450s and nuclear receptors</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Ther</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>-<lpage>337</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pharmthera.2011.04.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pharmthera.2011.04.009</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21565218" xlink:type="simple">21565218</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B31">
				<label>31</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taniya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA regulates the expression of human cytochrome P450 1B1</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>9090</fpage>-<lpage>9098</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-06-1403" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-06-1403</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16982751" xlink:type="simple">16982751</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B32">
				<label>32</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs regulate CYP3A4 expression via direct and indirect targeting</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>2112</fpage>-<lpage>2117</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1124/dmd.109.027680" xlink:type="simple">10.1124/dmd.109.027680</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19581388" xlink:type="simple">19581388</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B33">
				<label>33</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takamiya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Human CYP2E1 is regulated by miR-378</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>1045</fpage>-<lpage>1052</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bcp.2009.11.015" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.bcp.2009.11.015</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19945440" xlink:type="simple">19945440</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B34">
				<label>34</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Lentiviral transgenic microRNA-based shRNA suppressed mouse cytochromosome P450 3A (CYP3A) expression in a dose-dependent and inheritable manner</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e30560</fpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0030560" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0030560</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22291988" xlink:type="simple">22291988</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B35">
				<label>35</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorski</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wrighton</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Characterization of dextromethorphan N-demethylation by human liver microsomes. Contrib Cytochrome P450 3A (CYP3A) subfamily</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B36">
				<label>36</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimpel</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McClintick</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skillman</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Candidate genes for alcohol preference identified by expression profiling in alcohol-preferring and -nonpreferring reciprocal congenic rats</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>R11</fpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-2-r11" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2010-11-2-r11</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20128895" xlink:type="simple">20128895</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B37">
				<label>37</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Habegger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foroud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellison</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Glutathione S-transferase 8-8 expression is lower in alcohol-preferring than in alcohol-nonpreferring rats</article-title>. <source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1622</fpage>-<lpage>1628</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/01.ALC.0000145686.79141.57" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/01.ALC.0000145686.79141.57</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15547447" xlink:type="simple">15547447</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B38">
				<label>38</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flicek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amode</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Ensembl 2013</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>D48</fpage>-<lpage>D55</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gks1236" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gks1236</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23203987" xlink:type="simple">23203987</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B39">
				<label>39</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozomara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>miRBase: integrating microRNA annotation and deep-sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>D152</fpage>-<lpage>D157</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkr817" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkr817</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21037258" xlink:type="simple">21037258</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B40">
				<label>40</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Betel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koppal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agius</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive modeling of microRNA targets predicts functional non-conserved and non-canonical sites</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>R90</fpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-8-r90" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2010-11-8-r90</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20799968" xlink:type="simple">20799968</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B41">
				<label>41</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abril</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guigó</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>gff2ps: visualizing genomic annotations</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>743</fpage>-<lpage>744</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/16.8.743" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/16.8.743</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11099262" xlink:type="simple">11099262</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B42">
				<label>42</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pogribny</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Starlard-Davenport</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tryndyak</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Difference in expression of hepatic microRNAs miR-29c, miR-34a, miR-155, and miR-200b is associated with strain-specific susceptibility to dietary nonalcoholic steatohepatitis in mice</article-title>. <source>Lab Invest</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>1437</fpage>-<lpage>1446</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/labinvest.2010.113" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/labinvest.2010.113</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20548288" xlink:type="simple">20548288</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B43">
				<label>43</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pottier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maurin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puisségur</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lebrigand</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Identification of keratinocyte growth factor as a target of microRNA-155 in lung fibroblasts: implication in epithelial-mesenchymal interactions</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e6718</fpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0006718" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0006718</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19701459" xlink:type="simple">19701459</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B44">
				<label>44</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vettori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Distler</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Role of MicroRNAs in Fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Open Rheumatol J</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>130</fpage>-<lpage>139</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2174/1874312901206010130" xlink:type="simple">10.2174/1874312901206010130</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22802911" xlink:type="simple">22802911</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B45">
				<label>45</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petrasek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mundkur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Circulating microRNAs in exosomes indicate hepatocyte injury and inflammation in alcoholic, drug-induced, and inflammatory liver diseases</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1946</fpage>-<lpage>1957</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/hep.25873" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/hep.25873</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22684891" xlink:type="simple">22684891</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B46">
				<label>46</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Up-regulation of microRNA-155 promotes cancer cell invasion and predicts poor survival of hepatocellular carcinoma following liver transplantation</article-title>. <source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00432-011-1076-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00432-011-1076-z</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22071603" xlink:type="simple">22071603</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B47">
				<label>47</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marcos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kodys</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Csak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Up-regulation of microRNA-155 in macrophages contributes to increased tumor necrosis factor {alpha} (TNF{alpha}) production via increased mRNA half-life in alcoholic liver disease</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>1436</fpage>-<lpage>1444</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M110.145870" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M110.145870</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21062749" xlink:type="simple">21062749</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B48">
				<label>48</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA Signature in Alcoholic Liver Disease</article-title>. <source>Int J Hepatol</source> <year>2012</year>: <fpage>498232</fpage>. <publisher-name>PubMed</publisher-name>: <comment>22518321</comment></mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B49">
				<label>49</label>
				<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Westlind-Johnsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malmebo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name> <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Comparative analysis of CYP3A expression in human liver suggests only a minor role for CYP3A5 in drug metabolism</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>755</fpage>-<lpage>761</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1124/dmd.31.6.755" xlink:type="simple">10.1124/dmd.31.6.755</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12756208" xlink:type="simple">12756208</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
		</ref-list>
	</back>
</article>