<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0127111</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-57373</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Obesity, Metabolic Syndrome and Risk of Atrial Fibrillation: A Swedish, Prospective Cohort Study</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Obesity, Metabolic Syndrome and Risk of Atrial Fibrillation</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Nyström</surname>
<given-names>Petter K.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Carlsson</surname>
<given-names>Axel C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Leander</surname>
<given-names>Karin</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>de Faire</surname>
<given-names>Ulf</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff004" ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Hellenius</surname>
<given-names>Mai-Lis</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff004" ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Gigante</surname>
<given-names>Bruna</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff005" ref-type="aff"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Unit of Cardiovascular Epidemiology, Institute of Environmental Medicine, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Centre for Family Medicine, Department of Neurobiology, Care Sciences and Society, Karolinska Institutet, Huddinge, Sweden</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Medical Sciences, Molecular Epidemiology and Science for Life Laboratory, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Department of Cardiology, Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Department of Clinical Sciences, Danderyds Hospital, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Maeda</surname>
<given-names>Norikazu</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Graduate School of Medicine, Osaka University, JAPAN</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BG UdF. Performed the experiments: PKN BG. Analyzed the data: PKN ACC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MLH. Wrote the paper: PKN BG ACC KL UdF.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">nype90@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>15</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e0127111</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>3</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>10</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Nyström et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0127111" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Aim</title>
<p>We aimed to investigate whether different measures of obesity could similarly predict atrial fibrillation, and whether the atrial fibrillation risk associated with obesity is dependent on presence of metabolic syndrome.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Material and Methods</title>
<p>We performed our study in a population-based longitudinal cardiovascular study, comprising 1 924 men and 2 097 women, aged 60 years, from Stockholm. Body mass index, waist circumference, sagittal abdominal diameter and components of metabolic syndrome (systolic- and diastolic blood pressure, fasting glucose, triglycerides, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol) were recorded at baseline. Participants were classified by their body mass index (normal weight, overweight or obese), waist circumference (normal, semi-elevated or elevated), and according to presence of metabolic syndrome. Atrial fibrillation risk was estimated by Cox proportional hazards regression models, adjusted for common atrial fibrillation risk factors, expressed as HR and 95% CI.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>During a mean follow-up of 13.6 years, 285 incident atrial fibrillation cases were recorded. One standard deviation increment of each obesity measure was associated with increased atrial fibrillation risk as: body mass index 1.25 (1.12 – 1.40), waist circumference 1.35 (1.19 – 1.54) and sagittal abdominal diameter 1.28 (1.14 – 1.44). Compared to normal weight subjects without metabolic syndrome, increased atrial fibrillation risk was noted for overweight subjects with metabolic syndrome, 1.67 (1.16 – 2.41), obese subjects without metabolic syndrome, 1.75 (1.11 – 2.74) and obese subjects with metabolic syndrome, 1.92 (1.34 – 2.74). Compared to subjects with normal waist circumference without metabolic syndrome, subjects with elevated waist circumference and metabolic syndrome suffered increased atrial fibrillation risk, 2.03 (1.44 – 2.87).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Body mass index, waist circumference and sagittal abdominal diameter could similarly predict atrial fibrillation. Obesity was associated with an increased atrial fibrillation risk regardless of metabolic syndrome, whereas overweight and elevated waist circumference was associated with increased atrial fibrillation risk only if metabolic syndrome was present.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by Hjärt-Lung Fonden (grant n. 20130220 to Udf), URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www3.hjart-lungfonden.se" xlink:type="simple">https://www3.hjart-lungfonden.se</ext-link>; Karolinska Insitutet (2013Fobi38181 to BG), URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ki.se" xlink:type="simple">https://www.ki.se</ext-link>; Stockholms läns landsting (grant n. 20130053 to BG), URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.forskningsstod.sll.se/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.forskningsstod.sll.se/</ext-link>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="0"/>
<table-count count="6"/>
<page-count count="14"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All the data necessary to replicate the findings presented in this work are available in the tables in the main manuscript and in the <xref rid="pone.0127111.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. Due to legal restrictions imposed by the Swedish Secrecy Act, requests for access to sensative data can be sent to <email xlink:type="simple">bruna.gigante@ki.se</email>.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Obesity, a modifiable cardiovascular risk factor [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], has reached endemic proportions and has roughly doubled its world-wide prevalence since 1980 [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Obesity is also associated with an increased risk of atrial fibrillation (AF) [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], one of the most common atrial arrhythmias [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p>
<p>Several observational studies have shown that anthropometric measures of obesity body mass index (BMI) [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>],waist circumference (WC) [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], hip circumference (HC) [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and waist-hip ratio (WHR) [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] are incrementally associated with an increased risk of AF. However, it is unknown whether sagittal abdominal diameter (SAD), an alternate measure of abdominal obesity [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] strongly associated with CVD risk [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p>
<p>Risk of cardiovascular diseases (CVD) in obese individuals is partly dependent on the presence of the metabolic syndrome (MetS); a condition that, besides obesity, is characterized by impaired glucose homeostasis, high blood pressure, reduced high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol (HDL-C) and elevated triglycerides [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. It was recently shown that the prevalence of MetS among obese adults ranges from 24% in Italian women to 78% in Finnish men [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. MetS, defined as ≥ 3 of its components, is associated with an increased risk of atherosclerotic CVD [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], cardiovascular mortality [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and AF [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In AF patients, MetS carries an additional risk of stroke beyond the risk predicted by the CHADS<sub>2</sub> score [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Relevance of MetS as a CVD risk factor in obese individuals is supported by the observation that obese individuals without MetS, the so-called metabolically healthy obese (MHO) [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], are exposed to a risk of incident myocardial infarction (MI) that is not substantially higher than the risk of MI in normal weight individuals without MetS [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, it is unknown to which extent the presence of MetS affects the risk of AF associated with obesity.</p>
<p>The aims of our study were to investigate whether different anthropometric measures of body size can equally predict AF and if the risk of AF associated with obesity is dependent on presence of MetS. The present study was performed in a large community-based prospective cardiovascular cohort, the 60-year-old men and women from Stockholm.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Material and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Study population</title>
<p>From August 1997 to March 1999, every third man and woman living in Stockholm County, born between July 1<sup>st</sup>, 1937 and June 30<sup>th</sup>, 1938, was randomly selected from the population register in Sweden and invited to participate in a thorough health-screening study. Of the 5640 individuals (2681 women and 2779 men) invited to participate the response rate was 78%, resulting in 4232 participants (2181 women and 2033 men). Health screening included a physical examination, blood sampling after overnight fasting, a 12-lead ECG recording and an extensive questionnaire regarding lifestyle, health and indicators of socioeconomic status [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p>
<p>Incident cases of AF were obtained from the hospital discharge register in Sweden (100% follow-up), using codes of International Classification of Diseases, 10<sup>th</sup> revision (ICD-10): I48.0, I48.1, I48.2, I48.3, I48.4 and I48.9, covering paroxysmal AF, persistent AF, chronic AF, typical atrial flutter type 1, atypical atrial flutter type 2, atrial- fibrillation and flutter unspecified. Atrial flutter was included, because the arrhythmia is closely related to AF and is associated with a similar risk of stroke [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Both main- and secondary diagnoses of AF were recorded. Extraction from the registers was done yearly until December 31<sup>st</sup>, 2012.</p>
<p>Participants were excluded from the present analysis if they had missing data regarding any measure of body size or MetS status (n = 135), were underweight (BMI &lt; 18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, n = 29), or had AF prior to enrollment (n = 47). Prior AF was defined as either AF on the baseline ECG, history of AF reported in the questionnaire or as ICD-10-code I48, obtained from the hospital discharge register in Sweden prior to enrollment date. The exclusion represented 5.0% of the original population, and 4021 participants remained eligible for analyses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Ethics</title>
<p>The cohort of 60 years old men and women from Stockholm was designed and conducted in accordance with the Helsinki Declaration. The study was approved 1996 (Dnr 96–398) by the Regional Ethics Review Board at Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden. All the study participants gave their informed oral consent to be enrolled in the study, since at the time the study was initiated (1997) no forms for the written consent were available or in current use. Participation was voluntary and involved no evident risks and only study participants who agreed to participate in the study received the questionnaire and were invited for the medical examination. This consent procedure was approved by the Regional Ethics Review Board at Karolinska Institutet.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Measures of body size and cardiometabolic parameters</title>
<p>Weight was obtained with an electronic scale, rounding the number to nearest 0.1 kg. Height was measured without shoes, rounding the number to nearest 0.5 cm. BMI was calculated as weight (kg), divided by the height (m) squared [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. WC was measured after a normal expiration with patient standing up, wearing only underwear, rounding the number to nearest 0.5 cm. The measure was taken in the mid-point between the bottom of the lowest rib and the top of the iliac crest [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. HC was measured at symphysis trochanter level [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and the measure was rounded to nearest 0.5 cm. WHR was calculated by dividing WC in cm with HC in cm. SAD was measured after a normal expiration, with participant in supine position with straight legs and no clothes in the abdominal area. The measure was taken at the highest point of the belly, around the level of the iliac crest, with a ruler and a water level to ensure a vertical measure [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The measure was rounded to nearest 0.1 cm.</p>
<p>Systolic- and diastolic blood pressure were measured (HEM 711, OMROM Health Care) twice, in the right arm, after five minutes of rest, patient lying down. The mean of the two measures was calculated and rounded to nearest 0.1 mm Hg.</p>
<p>Venous blood samples were drawn after overnight fasting. Serum glucose was measured with an enzymatic colorimetric test (Bayer Diagnostics, Tarrytown, NY) and rounded to nearest 0.1 mmol/l, which was converted to mg/dl, by dividing values with 0.0555. Serum- cholesterol and triglycerides were analyzed using enzymatic methods (Bayer Diagnostics, Tarrytown, NY) and were rounded to nearest 0.1 mmol/l. Triglyceride levels were converted to mg/dl by dividing with 0.0113. Serum HDL-C was measured enzymatically, after isolation of low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol and very-low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol (Boehringer Mannheim GmbH, Germany), and rounded to nearest 0.01 mmol/l, which was converted to mg/dl by dividing values with 0.0259.</p>
<p>Medication for hypertension, diabetes and dyslipidemia was self-reported in the questionnaire. Birth country was self-reported and participants were classified as Swedish-born, or not Swedish-born. Smoking status was retrieved from the questionnaire and participants were classified as smokers or non-smokers. Consumption of alcoholic beverages was self-reported and converted to grams of alcohol per day [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Level of physical activity (PA) was self-reported and classified participants as performing regular exercise on at least moderate-intensity level, or not [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. History of myocardial infarction (MI) was self-reported in the questionnaire, or recorded during follow-up, as codes of ICD-10: I21—I25, retrieved from the hospital discharge register in Sweden.</p>
<p>In the present study we have defined Mets according to the harmonized Mets definition reported in Alberti K et al [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In particular, this latest statement does not include obesity, defined by WC, as a mandatory criterion for MetS [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and leaves the possibility to define obesity according to ethnicity and country specific guidelines. For the purpose of this analysis, MetS was defined as presence of ≥ 3 of the following: elevated WC [WC ≥ 102 cm in men and WC ≥ 88 cm in women], elevated triglycerides [triglycerides ≥ 150 mg/dl (1.7 mmol/l) or current medication for elevated triglycerides], reduced HDL-C [HDL-C &lt; 40 mg/dl (1.9 mmol/l) in men, HDL-C &lt; 50 mg/dl (1.3 mmol/l) in women, or current medication for reduced HDL-C], high blood pressure [systolic blood pressure (SBP) ≥ 130 mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) ≥ 85 mm Hg or current use of antihypertensive medication] and elevated fasting glucose [fasting glucose ≥ 100 mg/dl (5.6 mmol/l) or current use of antidiabetic medication].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>Baseline characteristics of study participants were presented as means ± standard deviation (SD) for continuous variables and percentages for categorical variables. To determine differences between participants who developed AF and participants who did not, a Students t-test was used for continuous variables and a chi<sup>2</sup>-test was used for binary- and categorical variables. Baseline data was complete in all variables except birth-country (n = 3) smoking status (n = 60) and PA level (n = 57), in which a separate category “missing” was introduced.</p>
<p>Cox proportional hazards regression models were used to assess the risk of new-onset AF associated with obesity and MetS status. Time was defined as days from inclusion to either incident AF, or censoring through death or end of follow-up.</p>
<p>We analyzed the risk of new-onset AF associated with 1 standard deviation (SD) increment in weight, height, WC, HC, SAD, BMI and WHR. Risk was expressed as hazard ratios (HR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI). Crude risk estimates were adjusted by hypertension, elevated fasting glucose, sex, birth country (Sweden, not Sweden, missing), smoking status (smoker, non-smoker, missing), alcohol intake (g/day), regular moderate-intensity exercise (yes, no, missing) and history of MI.</p>
<p>To analyze the risk of AF associated with obesity and/or MetS we divided participants, according to their BMI and presence/absence of MetS, into 1 of 6 groups: normal weight (BMI 18.5–24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) ± MetS, overweight (BMI 25.0–29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) ± MetS and obese (BMI ≥ 30.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) ± MetS. HRs and 95% CIs were estimated, using normal weight subjects without MetS as reference. The multivariate model contained sex, birth country (Sweden, not Sweden, missing), smoking status (smoker, non-smoker, missing), alcohol intake (g/day), regular moderate-intensity exercise (yes, no, missing) and history of MI.</p>
<p>WC is the measure of obesity used in the MetS definition. Therefore, we also analyzed the risk of AF based upon WC level. In this analysis, elevated WC was excluded as a MetS component, and presence of ≥ 2 of the remaining 4 MetS components was regarded as Mets. Participants were classified according to their WC and presence/absence of MetS, into 1 of 6 groups: normal WC (&lt; 94.0 cm in men, &lt; 80.0 cm in women) ± MetS, semi-elevated WC (94.0–101.9 cm in men, 80.0–87.9 cm in women) ± MetS and elevated WC (≥ 102.0 cm in men, ≥ 88.0 cm in women) ± MetS. The WC interval defined as semi-elevated WC represents a WC level associated with increased risk for metabolic complications in Caucasian populations [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. HRs and 95% CIs were estimated, using subjects with normal WC without MetS as reference. The multivariate model contained sex, birth country (Sweden, not Sweden, missing), smoking status (smoker, non-smoker, missing), alcohol intake (g/day), regular moderate-intensity exercise (yes, no, missing) and history of MI.</p>
<p>Finally, in a secondary analysis, we assessed the risk of new-onset AF according to presence of each MetS component within each BMI- and WC-interval. HRs and 95% CIs were estimated using participants from the same BMI/WC-group without the actual MetS component, as the reference. The multivariate model contained sex, birth country (Sweden, not Sweden, missing), smoking status (smoker, non-smoker, missing), alcohol intake (g/day), regular moderate-intensity exercise (yes, no, missing), history of MI and the other components of MetS.</p>
<p>Significance level was set at a p-value &lt; 0.05. All statistical analyses were performed with STATA 11 software (Stata Corporation, College Station, TX, USA).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>A total of 4021 participants, of which 1924 (47.9%) were men, were eligible for analyses. MetS was present in 1 108 participants (27.6%) and 795 participants (19.8%) were classified as obese according to their BMI. Of the 4021 participants eligible for analyses, 3454 were alive at end of-follow-up and the mortality rate was 14.1%. Among those who died, CVD was the cause of death in 27.9% of cases. The proportion of study participants with MetS at baseline who were alive at the end of the follow up was 27.6%, as compared to 25.3% among those who died from CVD and 27.9% among those who died from other causes.</p>
<p>During follow-up, which on average was 13.6 years, 285 cases of incident AF were registered and the incidence rate was 5.2 per 1 000 person-years. Characteristics of the participants who developed AF and those who did not are summarized in <xref rid="pone.0127111.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and in <xref rid="pone.0127111.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. Participants who developed AF were more often men, had a higher prevalence of MetS, higher alcohol intake and were “bigger”, regardless of anthropometric measure used to assess body size. In both groups, hypertension was the most prevalent MetS component and elevated triglycerides was the least common.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0127111.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Baseline characteristics of study population.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0127111.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No atrial fibrillation (n = 3736)</bold></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Incident atrial fibrillation (n = 285)</bold></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.1</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight, kg</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.2 ± 13.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.7 ± 15.8</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height, cm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169.6 ± 9.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173.0 ± 9.1</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8 ± 4.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0 ± 4.9</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hip circumference, cm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.3 ± 8.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.4 ± 9.6</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist-hip ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 ± 0.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 ± 0.09</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sagittal abdominal diameter, cm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6 ± 2.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5 ± 3.3</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist circumference men, cm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5 ± 10.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.7 ± 11.7</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist circumference women, cm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.5 ± 11.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.5 ± 14.3</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated waist circumference, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.6</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.4</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated fasting glucose, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.160</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced HDL-cholesterol, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated triglycerides, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Components of metabolic syndrome</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 ± 1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 1.4</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic syndrome <xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swedish-born, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.0</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.514</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current smoker, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.8</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.212</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol intake, g/day</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 ± 14.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 ± 16.3</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physically active, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.5</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.580</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior myocardial infarction, %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.804</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>Continuous variables presented as means ± standard deviations.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Presence of ≥ 3 of: elevated waist circumference, hypertension, elevated fasting glucose, elevated triglycerides, reduced HDL-C.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref rid="pone.0127111.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> illustrates the risk estimates of incident AF, associated with increase of 1 SD in anthropometric measures of body size. Weight, height, WC, HC, SAD, BMI and WHR were positively associated with the risk of AF in univariate models, but the risk associated with WHR did not remain significant in the multivariate model. The highest risk estimate was observed for height and the risk estimates of the other measures were in the same order of magnitude.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0127111.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>AF risk associated with 1 SD increment in anthropometric measures of body size.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0127111.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measure of body size</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate modelHR (95% CI) <xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate model <xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup>HR</xref> (95% CI) <xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 (1.35–1.66)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 (1.31–1.65)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 (1.29–1.63)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 (1.44–2.04)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 (1.28–1.59)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 (1.19–1.54)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 (1.22–1.48)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 (1.24–1.53)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (1.23–1.52)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (1.14–1.44)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (1.15–1.42)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (1.12–1.40)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (1.11–1.41)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.88–1.25)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.588</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; CI, confidence interval; HC, hip circumference; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; HR, hazard ratio; MI, myocardial infarction; SAD, sagittal abdominal diameter; WC, waist circumference; WHR, waist-hip ratio.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Expressed per 1 SD increment of each measure: Weight = 14.2 kg, Height = 9.1 cm, WC = 12.4 cm, HC = 8.4 cm, SAD = 2.9 cm, BMI = 4.2 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, WHR = 0.087.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> Model containing: hypertension, elevated fasting glucose, sex, smoking (yes, no, missing), alcohol intake (g/day), history of MI, regular moderate-intensity PA (yes, no, missing), and Swedish-born (yes, no, missing).</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The risk estimates of incident AF associated with BMI classification and presence of MetS, as compared to the normal weight participants without MetS, are reported in <xref rid="pone.0127111.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Increased risk of AF was noted for overweight individuals with MetS, in uni- and multivariate models. Obesity, instead, was associated with an increased risk of AF regardless of MetS and obese subjects with MetS suffered only a marginally higher risk of AF than obese subjects without MetS.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0127111.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>AF risk according to BMI categories and presence of MetS.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0127111.t003g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate model HR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate model <xref rid="t003fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref> HR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal weight <xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, no MetS (n = 1 334)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal weight, MetS <xref rid="t003fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (n = 92)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (0.53–2.81)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.637</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.51–2.70)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.713</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight <xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, no MetS (n = 1 295)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.76–1.44)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.790</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.73–1.40)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.949</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight, MetS <xref rid="t003fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (n = 505)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 (1.26–2.60)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 (1.16–2.41)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obese <xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, no MetS (n = 284)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 (1.07–2.62)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 (1.11–2.74)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obese, MetS <xref rid="t003fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (n = 511)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 (1.41–2.85)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92 (1.34–2.74)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; CI, confidence interval; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; HR, hazard ratio; MetS, metabolic syndrome; MI; myocardial infarction; PA, physical activity; WC, waist circumference.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Normal weight, BMI 18.5–24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; overweight BMI 25.0–29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; obese BMI ≥ 30.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> Presence of ≥ 3 of: elevated WC, hypertension, elevated fasting glucose, elevated triglycerides, reduced HDL-C.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn004"><p><sup>c</sup> Model containing: sex, birth-country (Sweden, not Sweden, missing), smoking status (yes, no, missing), alcohol intake (g/day), regular moderate-intensity PA (yes, no, missing) and history of MI.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref rid="pone.0127111.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> shows the risk estimates of incident AF associated with degree of obesity, defined by WC level, and the presence or absence of MetS. Subjects with normal WC and no MetS were used as referent group. Increased risk of AF was observed only in subjects with elevated WC and MetS.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0127111.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>AF risk associated with increasing WC and presence of MetS.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0127111.t004g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate model HR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate model <xref rid="t004fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref> HR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal WC <xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, no MetS (n = 1041)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal WC, MetS <xref rid="t004fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (n = 281)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 (0.97–2.61)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 (0.88–2.38)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.148</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semi-elevated WC <xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, no MetS (n = 723)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.79–1.75)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.431</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (0.80–1.78)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.385</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semi-elevated WC, MetS <xref rid="t004fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (n = 473)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 (0.97–2.27)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (0.86–2.04)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated WC <xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, no MetS (n = 634)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (0.87–1.94)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.207</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (0.91–2.07)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated WC, MetS <xref rid="t004fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (n = 869)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09 (1.49–2.93)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03 (1.44–2.87)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; HR, hazard ratio; MetS, metabolic syndrome; MI; myocardial infarction; PA, physical activity; WC, waist circumference.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Normal WC: &lt; 94.0 cm in men, &lt; 80.0 cm in women; Semi-elevated WC: 94.0–101.9 cm in men, 80.0–87.9 cm in women. Elevated WC: ≥ 102.0 cm in men, ≥ 88.0 cm in women.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> Presence of ≥ 2 of: hypertension, elevates fasting glucose, elevated triglycerides, reduced HDL-C.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn004"><p><sup>c</sup> Model containing: sex, birth-country (Sweden, not Sweden, missing), smoking status (yes, no, missing), alcohol consumption (g/day), regular moderate-intensity PA (yes, no, missing) and history of MI.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Finally, we have analyzed the risk of incident AF, associated with presence of each one of the MetS components within each BMI interval (<xref rid="pone.0127111.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) as well as within each WC interval (<xref rid="pone.0127111.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). As summarized in <xref rid="pone.0127111.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, only hypertension was associated with an increased risk of AF in normal weight- and overweight participants, but did not significantly modify AF risk in the obese individuals. The other MetS components alone were not associated with the risk of AF in any BMI interval.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0127111.t005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t005</object-id>
<label>Table 5</label> <caption><title>AF risk estimates by BMI category and presence of each one of the components of MetS.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0127111.t005g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate model HR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate model <xref rid="t005fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> HR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal weight <xref rid="t005fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, elevated WC (3.2) <xref rid="t005fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.19–3.18)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.731</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.21–3.70)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal weight, hypertension (49.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12 (1.33–3.37)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 (1.31–3.37)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal weight, elevated fasting glucose (19.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (0.69–2.03)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.534</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.61–1.83)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.858</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal weight, elevated triglycerides (10.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.46–1.97)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87(0.40–1.87)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.714</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal weight, reduced HDL-C (13.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.49–1.85)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.889</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.50–2.01)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight <xref rid="t005fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, elevated WC (39.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.78–1.58)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.569</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.78–1.67)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.501</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight, hypertension (66.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 (1.26–2.95)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69 (1.09–2.62)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight, elevated fasting glucose (31.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (0.86–1.79)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.68–1.45)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.975</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight, elevated triglycerides (24.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 (0.98–2.11)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.77–1.76)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.460</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight, reduced HDL-C (24.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (0.91–1.96)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 (0.81–1.85)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.335</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obese <xref rid="t005fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref>, elevated WC (98.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 (0.46–4.66)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (0.43–4.52)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.585</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obese, hypertension (74.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 (0.84–2.51)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (0.75–2.36)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.332</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obese, elevated fasting glucose (49.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.56–1.35)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.525</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (0.49–1.21)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obese, elevated triglycerides (40.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.58–1.43)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.681</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.50–1.30)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.377</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obese, reduced HDL-C (38.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (0.78–1.90)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.384</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 (0.83–2.15)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.226</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t005fn001"><p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; CI, confidence interval; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; HR, hazard ratio; MetS, metabolic syndrome; MI; myocardial infarction; PA, physical activity; WC, waist circumference.</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Normal weight, BMI 18.5–24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; overweight BMI 25.0–29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; obese BMI ≥ 30.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> Model containing: sex, birth-country (Sweden, not Sweden, missing), smoking status (yes, no, missing), alcohol consumption (g/day), regular moderate-intensity PA (yes, no, missing), history of MI and the other components of MetS.</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn004"><p><sup><bold>c</bold></sup> Percentage of the participants with the MetS component, within the given BMI interval.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0127111.t006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t006</object-id>
<label>Table 6</label> <caption><title>AF risk estimates by increasing WC and presence of each one of the components of MetS.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0127111.t006g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.t006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate model HR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariate model <xref rid="t006fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> HR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal WC <xref rid="t006fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, hypertension (50.3) <xref rid="t006fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.61 (1.59–4.29)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54 (1.54–4.21)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal WC, elevated fasting glucose (19.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.54–1.73)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.907</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.42–1.36)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.351</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal WC, elevated triglycerides (9.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.46–2.19)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.984</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.35–1.83)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.594</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal WC, reduced HDL-C (11.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.51–2.05)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 (0.54–2.36)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.741</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semi-elevated WC <xref rid="t006fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, hypertension (61.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14 (1.27–3.62)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92 (1.10–3.33)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semi-elevated WC, elevated fasting glucose (27.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.63–1.68)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.908</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.52–1.45)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.596</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semi-elevated WC, elevated triglycerides (22.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (0.75–2.08)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.388</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 (0.66–1.92)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.677</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semi-elevated WC, reduced HDL-C (24.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.62–1.75)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.869</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.54–1.59)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.780</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated WC <xref rid="t006fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>, hypertension (72.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (0.89–2.00)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.168</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.77–1.79)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated WC, elevated fasting glucose (43.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (0.88–1.76)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.75–1.53)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.720</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated WC, elevated triglycerides (35.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.83–1.68)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.367</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.65–1.39)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.800</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated WC, reduced HDL-C (33.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 (1.01–2.04)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (0.95–2.03)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t006fn001"><p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; CI, confidence interval; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; HR, hazard ratio; MetS, metabolic syndrome; MI; myocardial infarction; PA, physical activity; WC, waist circumference.</p></fn>
<fn id="t006fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Normal WC: &lt; 94.0 cm in men, &lt; 80.0 cm in women; Semi-elevated WC: 94.0–101.9 cm in men, 80.0–87.9 cm in women. Elevated WC: ≥ 102.0 cm in men, ≥ 88.0 cm in women.</p></fn>
<fn id="t006fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> Model containing: sex, birth-country (Sweden, not Sweden, missing), smoking status (yes, no, missing), alcohol consumption (g/day), regular moderate-intensity PA (yes, no, missing), history of MI and the other components of MetS.</p></fn>
<fn id="t006fn004"><p><sup>c</sup> Percentage of the participants with the MetS component, within the given WC interval.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Similarly, when the analysis was performed using WC to define obesity (<xref rid="pone.0127111.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>), hypertension was the only MetS component associated with an increased risk of AF, in participants with normal or semi-elevated WC. Reduced HDL-C was associated with an increased risk of AF in participants with elevated WC in the univariate model, but not in the multivariate model.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our results show that anthropometric measures of obesity, except WHR, can similarly predict AF risk independently from other known AF risk factors and that obesity defined as a BMI ≥ 30.0 is associated with an increased risk of AF regardless of MetS. In individuals with overweight, defined as a BMI 25.0–29.9, or abdominal obesity, defined as an elevated WC, increased risk of AF was observed only if MetS was present.</p>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Anthropometric measures of body size and risk of atrial fibrillation</title>
<p>Our results mainly support previous findings showing an association of increases in weight [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], height [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], WC [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], HC [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], BMI [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and WHR [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], with the exception from WHR, which was not associated with the risk of AF in multivariate models. Aside from WHR, the anthropometric measures of obesity could equally predict AF risk, independently from other known cardiovascular risk factors. Since the denominator of WHR, HC, was itself strongly associated with an increased risk of AF, it was however expected that WHR could not predict AF risk. The other anthropometric measures of obesity investigated in the present study could equally predict AF risk, independently from other known cardiovascular risk factors.</p>
<p>Weight, height, body fat mass [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and BMI [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] are all incrementally associated with left atrial volume. Left atrial enlargement is in turn, regardless of left ventricular size, an independent precursor of AF through founding and prolongation of ectopic signals from the atrial tissue [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Thus, left atrium enlargement is a probable effect mediator between increased body size, regardless of how it is measured, and the development of AF.</p>
<p>In the present study we have also, for the first time, investigated SAD as a predictor of AF and found that SAD is incrementally associated with an increased risk of AF. WC and SAD are both measures of abdominal obesity, but SAD correlates better with MetS [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], CVD risk factors [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], incident CVDs [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and the amount of visceral- [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and epicardial [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] adipose tissue. Since visceral- and epicardial adipose tissue have a high secretion of inflammatory mediators, adipokines [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and because inflammation is associated with the risk of AF [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], we hypothesized that SAD would have a higher predictive value of AF risk than WC. However, the association with the AF risk was similar in strength between the two measures with a small advantage, if any, of WC in favor of SAD. However, the association of obesity with risk of AF is complex and probably not directly related to the body distribution of adipose tissue. In fact, recent data from a Danish cohort indicates that not only fat mass, but even fat free mass, derived from bioelectrical impedance, was associated with an increased risk of AF [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Although fat mass and fat free mass seem to correlate [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], more sensitive imaging modalities might be necessary [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] to fully understand how different types of tissue mass affect the risk of AF.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Obesity, metabolic syndrome and risk of atrial fibrillation</title>
<p>In the present study, we found that obesity, defined as a BMI ≥ 30.0, was associated with an increased risk of AF regardless of MetS. Nevertheless, overweight, defined as a BMI 25.0–29.9 was associated with an increased risk of AF only if MetS was present. These results were consistent regardless of whether elevated WC was included as a component of MetS or not. In a previous meta-analysis of 5 population-based cohorts with 78 602 subjects [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], the relative risk of AF was 1.39 for overweight- and 1.87 for obese subjects, as compared to normal weight subjects, defined as a BMI 18.5–24.9. We found risk estimates of similar magnitude in obese subjects, but we further suggest that sole overweight is not independently associated with AF risk, but dependent on MetS.</p>
<p>In contrast to obesity defined by BMI, we found that abdominal obesity defined as an elevated WC, was not associated with the risk of AF unless other commonly accompanying MetS components were present. Neither was MetS associated with the risk of AF in subjects without an elevated WC. Previous observational studies have described that an elevated WC [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], as well as MetS [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], is associated with the risk of AF.</p>
<p>Although BMI and WC are both obesity measures, closely correlating in the present cohort, the cutoff levels to define obesity targeted different groups of participants. Nearly all subjects with BMI ≥ 30.0 had also an elevated WC, but only half of the subjects with an elevated WC had also a BMI ≥ 30.0. Thus, the two groups of obese individuals, defined by the two measures, were not equivalent. In particular, the group of subjects with an elevated WC contained a high proportion of overweight subjects (BMI 25.0–29.9) and this presumably explains why this group of individuals was at increased risk of AF only when MetS was present.</p>
<p>When analyzing individual components of MetS, hypertension was the only individual MetS component associated with the risk of AF, in subjects defined as non-obese by either BMI or WC. Meanwhile hypertension is an established risk factor for AF [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] it has previously been questioned whether elevated triglycerides [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], reduced HDL-C [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and type 2 diabetes mellitus [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] have an impact on the AF risk in the general population. Consistently with previous findings, our results suggest that the association between MetS and the risk of AF in non-obese subjects is primarily dependent on presence of hypertension, while hypertension seems not to increase the AF risk associated with obesity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Strengths and limitations</title>
<p>Our study was a population-based cohort, with a high participation rate, an equal number of men and women and an almost complete follow-up (99.7%) from Swedish registers [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The study participants were asked to fill in a comprehensive questionnaire and participated in a detailed medical examination which allowed us to thoroughly characterize the participants and adjust for potential confounders. Of note, all participants were of the same age, thus eliminating potential age as potential confounding factor.</p>
<p>AF diagnosis was ascertained only via the hospital discharge register while data from Swedish primary health care centers were not available for the present analysis. A corollary of this limitation is that the risk of AF in obese individuals could have been overestimated if obese individuals had a higher hospitalization rate. However, the proportion of AF reported as a secondary diagnosis did not differ between subjects with a BMI ≥ 30.0 (0.45) as compared to subjects with a BMI &lt; 30.0 (0.46), and the risk estimates we report are in line with those reported in a recently published meta-analysis [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Also, it was recently described that of all AF diagnoses recorded in Stockholm County between years 2006 and 2010, only 12% were recorded in primary care exclusively [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Both AF and atrial flutter were used as main outcomes in the present analysis. While this might be correct from a clinical point of view since these two arrhythmias often coexist in the same patient and are associated with a similar risk of thromboembolic events [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], we cannot exclude that they might differ to a certain extent from an etiological point of view. Larger studies with a more detailed classification of the arrhythmia in the single patient are warranted to better define similarities and differences between these two clinical entities.</p>
<p>Our cohort had a high number of Swedish-born participants (81.2%) and extrapolation of our findings to other ethnic groups should be done with caution. Although we adjusted our results for several known confounders, we cannot exclude the presence of residual confounding as well as unmeasured factors. In particular, we lacked data on left atrium size, the inflammation marker C-reactive protein (CRP), body fat and cardiorespiratory fitness (CRF). Left atrium enlargement and systemic inflammation are both probable effect mediators between obesity and the development of AF and low levels of CRP has been suggested to play a role in the protective profile of MHO individuals [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Body fat is associated with the AF risk [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], but also with a better prognosis in subjects with coronary heart disease [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and heart failure [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. CRF is also associated with a better prognosis in patients with CVD [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] or heart failure [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Also, a recent meta-analysis indicates that a good CRF level is associated with a decreased risk of all-cause mortality in a general population, regardless of BMI [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Data on body fat mass and CRF would have allowed us a better definition of the obese phenotype associated with an increased risk of AF.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In the present study of 60 years old men and women we found that weight, height, WC, HC, SAD and BMI were similarly, incrementally, associated with an increased risk of AF. In order to screen for AF risk, any of these measures should suffice. Based on our results we would however not recommend WHR [<xref rid="pone.0127111.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], to estimate AF risk.</p>
<p>We also found that subjects with general obesity (BMI ≥ 30.0) were at increased risk of AF regardless of MetS, meanwhile subjects with overweight (BMI 25.0–29.9) or abdominal obesity, defined as an elevated WC, (WC ≥ 102 cm in men, ≥88 cm in women) suffered an increased AF risk only if MetS was present.</p>
<p>Further studies are required to confirm our findings in non-Scandinavian populations as well as to evaluate the relevance of inflammatory- and metabolic biomarkers as risk predictors of AF in non-obese individuals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0127111.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0127111.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Additional baseline characteristics of the study participants.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors would like to thank all investigators and participants of the cohort of 60-year-old men and women from Stockholm for their prized contribution to this paper.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavie</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McAuley</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milani</surname> <given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blair</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Obesity and cardiovascular diseases: implications regarding fitness, fatness, and severity in the obesity paradox</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1345</fpage>–<lpage>1354</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jacc.2014.01.022" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jacc.2014.01.022</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24530666</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alpert</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Omran</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehra</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ardhanari</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of obesity and weight loss on cardiac performance and morphology in adults</article-title>. <source>Prog Cardiovasc Dis</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pcad.2013.09.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pcad.2013.09.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24438730</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastien</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poirier</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemieux</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Despres</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Overview of epidemiology and contribution of obesity to cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Prog Cardiovasc Dis</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pcad.2013.10.016" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pcad.2013.10.016</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24438728</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanahita</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Messerli</surname> <given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bangalore</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gami</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Somers</surname> <given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinberg</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Atrial fibrillation and obesity—results of a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>155</volume>: <fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ahj.2007.10.004" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ahj.2007.10.004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18215602</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Go</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hylek</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henault</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selby</surname> <given-names>JV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Prevalence of diagnosed atrial fibrillation in adults: national implications for rhythm management and stroke prevention: the AnTicoagulation and Risk Factors in Atrial Fibrillation (ATRIA) Study</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>285</volume>: <fpage>2370</fpage>–<lpage>2375</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11343485</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fenger-Gron</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tjonneland</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Overvad</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Body fat, body fat distribution, lean body mass and atrial fibrillation and flutter. A Danish cohort study</article-title>. <source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1546</fpage>–<lpage>1552</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/oby.20706" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/oby.20706</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24436019</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parise</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D'Agostino</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names> <suffix>Sr</suffix></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vasan</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Obesity and the risk of new-onset atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>292</volume>: <fpage>2471</fpage>–<lpage>2477</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15562125</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verdecchia</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dagenais</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Healey</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dans</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chazova</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Blood pressure and other determinants of new-onset atrial fibrillation in patients at high cardiovascular risk in the Ongoing Telmisartan Alone and in Combination With Ramipril Global Endpoint Trial/Telmisartan Randomized AssessmeNt Study in ACE iNtolerant subjects with cardiovascular Disease studies</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1004</fpage>–<lpage>1014</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/HJH.0b013e3283522a51" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/HJH.0b013e3283522a51</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22495138</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riserus</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Faire</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berglund</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellenius</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sagittal abdominal diameter as a screening tool in clinical research: cutoffs for cardiometabolic risk</article-title>. <source>J Obes</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2010</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlsson</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riserus</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engstrom</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnlov</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melander</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leander</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Novel and established anthropometric measures and the prediction of incident cardiovascular disease: a cohort study</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes (Lond)</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1579</fpage>–<lpage>1585</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ijo.2013.46" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ijo.2013.46</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23609935</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alberti</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eckel</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grundy</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmet</surname> <given-names>PZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cleeman</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donato</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Harmonizing the metabolic syndrome: a joint interim statement of the International Diabetes Federation Task Force on Epidemiology and Prevention; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; American Heart Association; World Heart Federation; International Atherosclerosis Society; and International Association for the Study of Obesity</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>120</volume>: <fpage>1640</fpage>–<lpage>1645</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.109.192644" xlink:type="simple">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.109.192644</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805654</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alberti</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmet</surname> <given-names>PZ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Definition, diagnosis and classification of diabetes mellitus and its complications. Part 1: diagnosis and classification of diabetes mellitus provisional report of a WHO consultation</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9686693</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">National Cholesterol Education Program (NCEP) Expert Panel on Detection E, and Treatment of High Blood Cholesterol in Adults (Adult Treatment Panel III). Third Report of the National Cholesterol Education Program (NCEP) Expert Panel on Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Cholesterol in Adults (Adult Treatment Panel III) final report. Circulation. 2002;106.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Vliet-Ostaptchouk</surname> <given-names>JV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nuotio</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slagter</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doiron</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foco</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The prevalence of metabolic syndrome and metabolically healthy obesity in Europe: a collaborative analysis of ten large cohort studies</article-title>. <source>BMC Endocr Disord</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1472-6823-14-9" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1472-6823-14-9</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24484869</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzo</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haffner</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trend in the prevalence of the metabolic syndrome and its impact on cardiovascular disease incidence: the San Antonio Heart Study</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>630</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16505517</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isomaa</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Almgren</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuomi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forsen</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lahti</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nissen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Cardiovascular morbidity and mortality associated with the metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>689</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11315831</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanabe</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Darbar</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roden</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Metabolic syndrome and risk of development of atrial fibrillation: the Niigata preventive medicine study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>117</volume>: <fpage>1255</fpage>–<lpage>1260</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.744466" xlink:type="simple">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.744466</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18285562</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamberlain</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrose</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Folsom</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soliman</surname> <given-names>EZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Metabolic syndrome and incidence of atrial fibrillation among blacks and whites in the Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) Study</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>159</volume>: <fpage>850</fpage>–<lpage>856</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ahj.2010.02.005" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ahj.2010.02.005</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435195</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanner</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baber</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voeks</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soliman</surname> <given-names>EZ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Association of the metabolic syndrome with atrial fibrillation among United States adults (from the REasons for Geographic and Racial Differences in Stroke [REGARDS] Study)</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>108</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.03.026" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.03.026</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21530935</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavie</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dinicolantonio</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Keefe</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khatib</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Cardiometabolic risk factors and atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>Rev Cardiovasc Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>e73</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24448257</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavie</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiNicolantonio</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Keefe</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khatib</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Atrial fibrillation in the 21st century: a current understanding of risk factors and primary prevention strategies</article-title>. <source>Mayo Clin Proc</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>409</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.mayocp.2013.01.022" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.mayocp.2013.01.022</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23541013</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Additive effect of the metabolic syndrome score to the conventional CHADS(2) score for the thromboembolic risk stratification of patients with atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>352</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.hrthm.2013.11.014" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.hrthm.2013.11.014</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24252289</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karelis</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faraj</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bastard</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>St-Pierre</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brochu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prud'homme</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The metabolically healthy but obese individual presents a favorable inflammation profile</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>90</volume>: <fpage>4145</fpage>–<lpage>4150</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855252</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karelis</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Metabolically healthy but obese individuals</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>372</volume>: <fpage>1281</fpage>–<lpage>1283</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61531-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61531-7</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18929889</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morkedal</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vatten</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romundstad</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laugsand</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janszky</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Risk of myocardial infarction and heart failure among metabolically healthy but obese individuals: HUNT (Nord-Trondelag Health Study), Norway</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1071</fpage>–<lpage>1078</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jacc.2013.11.035" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jacc.2013.11.035</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24345592</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gigante</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leander</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vikstrom</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frumento</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carlsson</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bottai</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Elevated ApoB serum levels strongly predict early cardiovascular events</article-title>. <source>Heart</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1242</fpage>–<lpage>1245</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/heartjnl-2012-301852" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/heartjnl-2012-301852</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22760866</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lip</surname> <given-names>GY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Recent developments in understanding epidemiology and risk determinants of atrial fibrillation as a cause of stroke</article-title>. <source>Can J Cardiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>S4</fpage>–<lpage>S13</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cjca.2013.03.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cjca.2013.03.009</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23790597</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wandell</surname> <given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carlsson</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theobald</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>The association between BMI value and long-term mortality</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes (Lond)</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>577</fpage>–<lpage>582</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ijo.2009.36" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ijo.2009.36</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238160</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordhamn</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sodergren</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karlstrom</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vessby</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berglund</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reliability of anthropometric measurements in overweight and lean subjects: consequences for correlations between anthropometric and other variables</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>652</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10849590</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlsson</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wandell</surname> <given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halldin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Faire</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellenius</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Is a unified definition of metabolic syndrome needed? Comparison of three definitions of metabolic syndrome in 60-year-old men and women</article-title>. <source>Metab Syndr Relat Disord</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/met.2008.0078" xlink:type="simple">10.1089/met.2008.0078</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19284315</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekblom-Bak</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ekblom</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vikstrom</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Faire</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellenius</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>The importance of non-exercise physical activity for cardiovascular health and longevity</article-title>. <source>Br J Sports Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>48</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2012-092038" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/bjsports-2012-092038</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24167194</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><article-title>Obesity: preventing and managing the global epidemic. Report of a WHO consultation</article-title>. <source>World Health Organ Tech Rep Ser</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>894</volume>: <fpage>i</fpage>–<lpage>xii</lpage>, 1–253. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11234459</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosengren</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hauptman</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lappas</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilhelmsen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swedberg</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Big men and atrial fibrillation: effects of body size and weight gain on risk of atrial fibrillation in men</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1113</fpage>–<lpage>1120</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/eurheartj/ehp076" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/eurheartj/ehp076</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19304990</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tedrow</surname> <given-names>UB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ridker</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname> <given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koplan</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manson</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The long- and short-term impact of elevated body mass index on the risk of new atrial fibrillation the WHS (women's health study)</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>2319</fpage>–<lpage>2327</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jacc.2010.02.029" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jacc.2010.02.029</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20488302</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kannel</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of obesity on left ventricular mass and geometry. The Framingham Heart Study</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>266</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1829117</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaziri</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Echocardiographic predictors of nonrheumatic atrial fibrillation. The Framingham Heart Study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>724</fpage>–<lpage>730</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8313561</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barthelemy</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Felber</surname> <given-names>Dietrich D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imboden</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Premature atrial contractions in the general population: frequency and risk factors</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>126</volume>: <fpage>2302</fpage>–<lpage>2308</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.112300" xlink:type="simple">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.112300</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23048073</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayer</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Almafragy</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellyer</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Celermajer</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Body mass index is an independent determinant of left atrial size</article-title>. <source>Heart Lung Circ</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17560167</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wajchenberg</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Subcutaneous and visceral adipose tissue: their relation to the metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Endocr Rev</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>697</fpage>–<lpage>738</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11133069</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Souza</surname> <given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname> <given-names>EP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sagittal abdominal diameter shows better correlation with cardiovascular risk factors than waist circumference and BMI</article-title>. <source>J Diabetes Metab Disord</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/2251-6581-12-41" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/2251-6581-12-41</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23856008</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sampaio</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simoes</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Assis</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Validity and reliability of the sagittal abdominal diameter as a predictor of visceral abdominal fat</article-title>. <source>Arq Bras Endocrinol Metabol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>980</fpage>–<lpage>986</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17934666</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasques</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanaka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname> <given-names>Mda S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novaes</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pareja</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Sagittal abdominal diameter as a marker for epicardial adipose tissue in premenopausal women</article-title>. <source>Metabolism</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1032</fpage>–<lpage>1036</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.metabol.2013.01.022" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.metabol.2013.01.022</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23540720</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aviles</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>DO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Apperson-Hansen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Houghtaling</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rautaharju</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kronmal</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Inflammation as a risk factor for atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>108</volume>: <fpage>3006</fpage>–<lpage>3010</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14623805</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaziri</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D'Agostino</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belanger</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Independent risk factors for atrial fibrillation in a population-based cohort. The Framingham Heart Study</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>271</volume>: <fpage>840</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8114238</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Go</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosendorff</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hypertension and atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>Curr Cardiol Rep</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>430</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19863867</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manolis</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosei</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coca</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cifkova</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erdine</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kjeldsen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Hypertension and atrial fibrillation: diagnostic approach, prevention and treatment. Position paper of the Working Group 'Hypertension Arrhythmias and Thrombosis' of the European Society of Hypertension</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/HJH.0b013e32834f03bf" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/HJH.0b013e32834f03bf</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22186358</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanabe</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yagihara</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aizawa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kodama</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Association between lipid profile and risk of atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>Circ J</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>2767</fpage>–<lpage>2774</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21914959</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ostgren</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merlo</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rastam</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindblad</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>Atrial fibrillation and its association with type 2 diabetes and hypertension in a Swedish community</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Obes Metab</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15287930</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontes</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyass</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Massaro</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rienstra</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dallmeier</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schnabel</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Insulin resistance and atrial fibrillation (from the Framingham Heart Study)</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.08.008" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.08.008</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21996140</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almgren</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilhelmsen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samuelsson</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Himmelmann</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosengren</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname> <given-names>OK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Diabetes in treated hypertension is common and carries a high cardiovascular risk: results from a 28-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1311</fpage>–<lpage>1317</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17563546</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forslund</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wettermark</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wandell</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Euler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasselstrom</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hjemdahl</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Risk scoring and thromboprophylactic treatment of patients with atrial fibrillation with and without access to primary healthcare data: experience from the Stockholm health care system</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>170</volume>: <fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijcard.2013.10.063" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ijcard.2013.10.063</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24239153</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Schutter</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavie</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milani</surname> <given-names>RV</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of obesity on risk factors and prevalence and prognosis of coronary heart disease-the obesity paradox</article-title>. <source>Prog Cardiovasc Dis</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pcad.2013.08.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pcad.2013.08.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24438731</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavie</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alpert</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arena</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehra</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milani</surname> <given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura</surname> <given-names>HO</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of obesity and the obesity paradox on prevalence and prognosis in heart failure</article-title>. <source>JACC Heart Fail</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jchf.2013.01.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jchf.2013.01.006</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24621833</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McAuley</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beavers</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Contribution of cardiorespiratory fitness to the obesity paradox</article-title>. <source>Prog Cardiovasc Dis</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pcad.2013.09.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pcad.2013.09.006</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24438735</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0127111.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname> <given-names>VW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baruth</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beets</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durstine</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blair</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fitness vs. fatness on all-cause mortality: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Prog Cardiovasc Dis</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pcad.2013.09.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pcad.2013.09.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24438729</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>