<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0133898</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-12063</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Disturbances in Hypothalamic-Pituitary-Adrenal Axis and Immunological Activity Differentiating between Unipolar and Bipolar Depressive Episodes</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">HPA-Axis and Immune Disturbances in Unipolar and Bipolar Depression</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Becking</surname>
<given-names>Karlijn</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Spijker</surname>
<given-names>Annet T.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Hoencamp</surname>
<given-names>Erik</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref rid="econtrib001" ref-type="fn"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Penninx</surname>
<given-names>Brenda W. J. H.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff004" ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff005" ref-type="aff"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<xref rid="econtrib001" ref-type="fn"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Schoevers</surname>
<given-names>Robert A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Boschloo</surname>
<given-names>Lynn</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>University of Groningen, University Medical Center Groningen, Interdisciplinary Center Psychopathology and Emotion regulation (ICPE) and University Center Psychiatry (UCP), Groningen, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>PsyQ Rijnmond, Department of Mood Disorders, Rotterdam, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Leiden University, Institute of Psychology, Leiden, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>VU University Medical Center, Department of Psychiatry and EMGO+ Institute for Health and Care Research, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>Leiden University Medical Center, Department of Psychiatry, Leiden, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Walss-Bass</surname>
<given-names>Consuelo</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>UTHSCSH, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The corresponding author has read the journal's policy and the authors of this manuscript have the following competing interests: Spijker and Boschloo have received speaking fees and unrestricted research grants from Astra Zeneca. Hoencamp has received an unrestricted grant from Astra Zeneca and is currently supported by Parnassia Group. Penninx has received unrestricted grants from the Netherlands Organization for Health Research and Development. AS and EH received salaries from PsyQ Rijnmond. These competing interests do not alter the authors' adherence to PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. The other authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: KB ATS EH RAS BWJHP LB. Performed the experiments: LB RAS BWJHP. Analyzed the data: KB LB. Wrote the paper: KB ATS EH BWJHP RAS LB.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="econtrib001">
<p>‡ These authors also contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">k.becking@umcg.nl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>21</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e0133898</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>23</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>2</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Becking et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0133898" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Differentiating bipolar depression (BD) from unipolar depression (UD) is difficult in clinical practice and, consequently, accurate recognition of BD can take as long as nine years. Research has therefore focused on the discriminatory capacities of biomarkers, such as markers of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis or immunological activity. However, no previous study included assessments of both systems, which is problematic as they may influence each other. Therefore, this study aimed to explore whether cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers were a) independently associated with and/or b) showed effect modification in relation to a lifetime (hypo)manic episode in a large sample of depressed patients.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Data were derived from the Netherlands Study of Depression and Anxiety and comprised 764 patients with a DSM-IV depressive disorder at baseline, of which 124 (16.2%) had a lifetime (hypo)manic episode at the 2-year assessment, or a more recent episode at the 4-year or 6-year assessment. Baseline cortisol awakening response, evening cortisol and diurnal cortisol slope were considered as cortisol indicators, while baseline C-reactive Protein (CRP), Interleukin-6 (IL-6), and Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha (TNF-α) were included as inflammatory markers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>In depressed men and women, none of the cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers were (independently) associated with a (hypo)manic episode. However, effect modification was found of diurnal cortisol slope and CRP in relation to a (hypo)manic episode. Further analyses showed that depressed men with high levels of diurnal cortisol slope and CRP had an increased odds (OR=10.99, p=.001) of having a (hypo)manic episode. No significant differences were found in women.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Our findings suggest that the combination of high diurnal cortisol slope and high CRP may differentiate between UD and BD. This stresses the importance of considering HPA-axis and immunological activity simultaneously, but more research is needed to unravel their interrelatedness.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The infrastructure for the NESDA study (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nesda.nl" xlink:type="simple">www.nesda.nl</ext-link>) is funded through the Geestkracht program of the Netherlands Organization for Health Research and Development (Zon-Mw, grant number 10-000-1002) and is supported by participating universities and mental health care organizations (VU University Medical Center, GGZ inGeest, Arkin, Leiden University Medical Center, GGZ Rivierduinen, University Medical Center Groningen, Lentis, GGZ Friesland, GGZ Drenthe, Scientific Institute for Quality of Health Care (IQ Healthcare), Netherlands Institute for Health Services Research (Nivel) and the Netherlands Institute of Mental Health and Addiction (TRIMBOS)). Assaying of inflammatory markers was supported by the Neuroscience Campus Amsterdam and VIDI grant (Penninx). Statistical analyses were supported by an unrestricted research grant by Astra Zeneca Nederland (Spijker, Hoencamp, Boschloo). The Netherlands Organization for Health Research and Development had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. PsyQ Rijnmond provided support in the form of salaries for authors AS and EH, but did not have any additional role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. The specific roles of these authors are articulated in the ‘author contributions’ section. Astra Zeneca Nederland had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="0"/>
<table-count count="5"/>
<page-count count="14"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>Because of ethical and legal restrictions, our data are not freely available in the manuscript, supplemental files, or in a public repository. However, data is available upon request via NESDA Data Acces Committee (<email xlink:type="simple">datamanagement@ggzingeest.nl</email>).</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Accurate and timely recognition of bipolar disorder (BD) is very low, and receiving the correct diagnosis can take as long as 9 years [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Delayed recognition is associated with a more severe clinical course and substantial economic costs [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. BD is often misdiagnosed as unipolar depression (UD) at first [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]; around 40% of BD patients were initially diagnosed with a unipolar major depressive episode [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. This is because approximately half of BD patients present with a major depressive episode as their first mood episode [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], and patients often do not report their manic symptoms to their physicians [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Previous studies have identified some predictors of conversion from UD to BD, such as male gender, childhood trauma, severity of depressive symptoms and co-occurring manic symptoms during depression [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, in clinical practice depressive episodes in the course of a bipolar or unipolar disorder are almost identical and difficult to differentiate [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p>
<p>To elucidate underlying mechanisms involved in the differentiation of the mood episode in a unipolar or bipolar mood disorder, it may be of interest to examine whether biological markers found to be related to mood disorders can discriminate between UD and BD. Up to now, biological disturbances both in the regulation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis (HPA-axis) as well as immunological activity are believed to play a key role in UD [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and BD [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Previous studies have, for example, found higher cortisol levels and higher levels of inflammatory markers in BD patients [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], as well as UD patients [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] compared to healthy controls. Studies directly comparing unipolar and bipolar depression are scarce, but the few available studies suggest that HPA-axis disturbances [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and immune dysregulation [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] are more pronounced in bipolar depression. Furthermore, in the Netherlands Study of Depression and Anxiety (NESDA) various subtypes of unipolar and bipolar depression have been examined. For example, Jabben et al. showed that bipolar spectrum patients had a higher diurnal cortisol slope compared to patients with UD [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In a separate paper, Becking et al. recently showed that depressed patients with co-occurring manic symptoms did not significantly differ from depressed patients without manic symptoms in any of the inflammatory markers, but associations were found with the onset of manic symptoms after 2 years follow-up [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p>
<p>Most studies that focussed on the associations of these systems with mood disorders included only assessments of either HPA-axis or immunological activity [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Consequently, it was not possible to examine the interrelatedness of these systems. This might be problematic, as the systems influence each other. For example, hyperactivity of the HPA-axis, with an underlying glucocorticoid resistance, leads to an increased inflammatory response on a cellular level [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Similarly, increased pro-inflammatory cytokine levels can lead to inhibition of the glucocorticoid receptor function and directly activate the HPA-axis in the brain [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Although convincing evidence has demonstrated the interrelatedness of the systems, it is unclear as to how they influence each other in their relations with mood disorders [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p>
<p>Another complicating factor in identifying factors that could differentiate between unipolar and bipolar depression, is the influence of gender differences on phenomenology and biology of both mood disorders. Gender differences exist in prevalence [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], symptoms and treatment of mood disorders [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. For example, there is an increased prevalence of unipolar depression in women, which is associated with fluctuations in gonadal hormones [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This may point to differences in biological pathophysiological processes. Therefore, it has been advocated that gender should not merely be analyzed as a covariate, but men and women should be analyzed separately to really understand gender differences in the relation of the HPA-axis [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] as well as the immune system [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] with mood disorders.</p>
<p>To our knowledge, NESDA is the first study that assessed both cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers in a large sample of depressed men and women and would, thus, be suitable for examining the interrelatedness of the systems in relation to the presence of a lifetime (hypo)manic episode. Data were, therefore, derived from this study and we aimed to explore:
<list list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Whether cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers were independently associated with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Whether cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers showed effect modification in relation to a lifetime (hypo)manic episode</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>Because of reasons mentioned earlier, the results are shown for men and women separately. In addition, we were able to explore the role of potential confounders, such as sociodemographics, sampling and health factors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Study sample</title>
<p>Data were derived from the Netherlands Study of Depression and Anxiety (NESDA), an ongoing cohort study (N = 2981, age 18–65 years) including 2329 patients with a lifetime depressive and/or anxiety disorder as well as 652 healthy controls. Participants were recruited from the community (19%), general practice (54%), and specialized mental health care (27%). Participants with insufficient command of the Dutch language, or patients with a primary clinical diagnosis of bipolar disorder, obsessive-compulsive disorder, severe substance use disorder, or psychotic disorder were excluded from the study. The study protocol was approved centrally by the Ethical Review Board of the VU University Medical Centre and subsequently by the Ethical Review Boards of the other participating centers (Leiden University Medical Center and University Medical Center Groningen). Written informed consent was obtained from all participants (see [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] for a detailed description of NESDA). So far, NESDA included face-to-face assessments at baseline and 2-year (N = 2596, 87.1%), 4-year (N = 2402, 80.6%), and 6-year (N = 2256, 75.7%) follow-up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Unipolar versus bipolar depressive episodes</title>
<p>For the present study, we selected patients with a current DSM-IV depressive episode (N = 1158; &lt;6 months MDD or dysthymia) at baseline, as assessed with the Composite International Diagnostic Interview (CIDI, version 2.1) [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Unfortunately, the CIDI section on (hypo)manic episodes was not assessed at baseline, and consequently it was only possible to determine which patients met criteria for a DSM-IV (hypo)manic episode at follow-up assessments after 2 years (lifetime diagnosis), 4 years (diagnosis since the last interview) or 6 years (diagnosis since the last interview). Of our sample of 1158 depressed patients at baseline, 6 (0.5%) patients had missing information on cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers. Of these 1152 depressed patients, 388 (33.7%) did not have valid data at the 6-year follow-up assessment of a (hypo)manic episode and were therefore excluded for the current analyses. This resulted in a total sample of 764 depressed patients, of which 124 (16.2%) had, and 640 (83.8%) did not have a lifetime (hypo)manic episode at one of the follow-up assessments. The CIDI has proven to be highly reliable and valid for diagnosing unipolar depressive episodes as well as manic episodes [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and in a lesser extent for diagnosing hypomanic episodes [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. However, Regeer et al. showed that the validity of the CIDI was limited when compared with (hypo)manic episode diagnosis established with the the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM (SCID).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Cortisol indicators</title>
<p>Baseline cortisol was sampled through saliva using Salivettes (Starstedt AG, Numbrecht, Germany), which is a reliable and minimally intrusive way for assessing the active, unbound form of cortisol. Participants were instructed to collect saliva at seven time points on a regular working day (median time since the assessment of psychopathology and inflammation: 9 days). For the present study, we considered four cortisol indicators using six time points (T1-T6). Based on sampling points at awakening (T1) and 30 (T2), 45 (T3) and 60 (T4) minutes later, two indicators of the Cortisol Awakening Response (CAR) were calculated using a trapezoid formula [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The <italic>area under the curve with respect to the ground</italic> (AUCg) estimates the total cortisol exposure during the CAR and provides an indication of overall cortisol level throughout the day. The <italic>area under the curve with respect to the increase</italic> (AUCi) is a measure of the dynamic of the CAR and provides an indication of the sensitivity of the HPA-axis, emphasizing changes in cortisol exposure over time [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. <italic>Evening cortisol</italic> was based on the mean cortisol level at the sampling points of 10 pm (T5) and 11 pm (T6). In addition, the <italic>diurnal cortisol slope</italic> was calculated as a measure for the mean decline per hour ([cortisol T1 minus cortisol T6] / [time T6 minus time T1]). Detailed information on the assessment of the cortisol indicators in NESDA is provided elsewhere [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Inflammatory markers</title>
<p>Baseline inflammatory markers included <italic>C-reactive Protein</italic> (CRP), <italic>Interleukin-6</italic> (IL-6), and <italic>Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha</italic> (TNF-α). Fasting blood samples of the participants were obtained at approximately 8 a.m. at the day of the psychiatric interview and kept frozen at -80°C. CRP and IL-6 were assayed at the Clinical Chemistry department of the VU University Medical Center (Amsterdam, the Netherlands). High-sensitivity CRP plasma levels were measured in duplicate by an in-house ELISA based on purified protein and polyclonal anti-CRP antibodies (Dako, Glostrup, Denmark), while plasma IL-6 levels were measured in duplicate by a high-sensitivity enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (PeliKine Compact ELISA, Sanquin, Amsterdam, the Netherlands). Plasma TNF-α levels were assayed in duplicate at Good Biomarkers Science (Leiden, the Netherlands), using a high-sensitivity solid-phase ELISA (Quantikine HS Human TNF-α Immunoassay, R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA). Detailed information on the assessment of inflammatory markers in NESDA is provided elsewhere [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Potential confounders</title>
<p>Basic covariates (sociodemographics and sampling factors) and health factors were selected as potential confounders, as they have shown to be associated with the HPA-axis [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], the immune system [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], as well as BD [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. <italic>Sociodemographics</italic> included age, education (in years), and North-European ancestry. <italic>Sampling factors</italic> included awakening time, work status, type of day (weekday vs. weekend) and season (dark vs. light months) of the day of sampling. <italic>Health factors</italic> included smoking, alcohol use, physical activity, sleep, body mass index, cardiovascular disease, diabetes, other chronic diseases, statin use and anti-inflammatory medication use. Information on former or current smoking and alcohol use (no [&lt;1 drink per week], moderate [women: 1–14 drinks, men: 1–21 drinks per week] or heavy [women: &gt;14 drinks, men: &gt;21 drinks per week]) was obtained during the interview. Physical activity was measured with the International Physical Activity Questionnaire [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] in MET-minutes (metabolic equivalent; total effort expended in different activities over one week). Sleep duration was assessed with one item of the 5-item Women’s Health Initiative Insomnia Rating Scale (IRS) [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and dichotomized (sleep &lt;6 hours, yes or no). BMI was calculated as weight (in kg) divided by height squared (in m<sup>2</sup>). The presence of cardiovascular disease was assessed by self-report and appropriate medication use (Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical [ATC] codes: B01, N02BA01, N02BA15, C01DA, C02, C03, and C07-C10, see [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] for detailed description), while diabetes was considered to be present when the fasting plasma glucose level was &gt;7.0 mmol l<sup>-1</sup> or the patient used antidiabetic medication (ATC code: A10). Furthermore, we assessed self-reported chronic disease for which patients received treatment, including lung-disease, osteoarthritis or rheumatic disease, cancer, ulcer, intestinal problems, liver disease, epilepsy and thyroid gland disease. Medication included use of statins (ATC codes: C10AA and C10B) and anti-inflammatory medication (ATC codes: M01A, M01B, A07EB and A07EC).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>Data were analyzed with SPSS version 22.0 (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Evening cortisol, CRP, IL-6 and TNF-α were ln-transformed to normalize distributions and presented back-transformed in tables. First, characteristics (i.e., sociodemographics, sampling factors, and health factors) of depressed patients were compared across those without versus those with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode using T-tests for continuous variables and Pearson’s Chi-square tests for dichotomous and categorical variables. Second, Pearson’s correlations between all cortisol indicators and all inflammatory markers were calculated to explore their interrelatedness.</p>
<p>Then, separate logistic regression analyses were performed to explore whether each of the cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers were associated with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode in our sample of depressed patients. To determine the <italic>independent associations</italic> of cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode, multivariable analyses were conducted including those indicators and markers that had a p &lt;.10 in the previous analyses. To examine <italic>effect modification</italic> between HPA-axis activity and immunological activity in relation to a lifetime (hypo)manic episode, we tested the interaction terms between all cortisol indicators and all inflammatory markers. If significant (p &lt;.05), the nature of the effect modification was further explored by combining information on the level of the cortisol indicator and inflammatory marker (values in the highest tertile were considered high). Consequently, we could compare the presence of a lifetime (hypo)manic episode across depressed patients with a) high cortisol only, b) high inflammation only, and c) both high cortisol and inflammation, to d) depressed patients with low levels of cortisol and inflammation. All previous analyses were adjusted for basic covariates (sociodemographics and sampling factors). To examine whether significant associations could be explained by health factors, analyses were additionally adjusted for these factors.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>In our sample of depressed patients, 124 patients (16.2%) had a lifetime (hypo)manic episode. The mean age of onset of the (hypo)manic episode was 29 years. 7 patients (5.6%) had their last (hypo)manic episode before baseline measurement. Of the remaining patients, 67 (54.0%) had their last (hypo)manic episode 0–2 years after baseline measurement, 25 (20.2%) after 2–4 years and 25 (20.2%) after 4–6 years. <xref rid="pone.0133898.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the characteristics of our sample of depressed patients, comparing those with and without a lifetime (hypo)manic episode. In depressed men, a significant difference was found for years of education, but not any other factor. In women, no significant differences were found. <xref rid="pone.0133898.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the correlations across all cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers. Correlations between cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers were low in both depressed men (all r≤.17) and depressed women (all r≤.09), likely reflecting only partial biological overlap.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0133898.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Sample characteristics.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0133898.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Depressed men</th>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Depressed women</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No lifetime (hypo)manic episode (N = 209)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lifetime (hypo)manic episode (N = 56)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No lifetime (hypo)manic episode (N = 431)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lifetime (hypo)manic episode (N = 68)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sociodemographics</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years), mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9 (11.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7 (11.0)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4 (12.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3 (11.9)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education (years), mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (3.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 (3.0)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 (3.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 (3.4)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North-European ancestry, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203 (97.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (96.4)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">402 (93.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (92.6)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.85</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sampling factors</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time of awakening, mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:26 (0:59)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:34 (1:01)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:25 (1:02)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:34 (0:58)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.28</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working on day of sampling, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (70.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (73.2)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.73</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">274 (63.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (73.5)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling on weekday, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 (94.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (87.5)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400 (92.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (97.1)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling in month with more daylight, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (70.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (71.4)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">284 (65.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (76.5)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Health factors</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking status</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (26.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (21.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (30.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (33.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Former, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (32.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (30.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (32.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (20.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Current, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (40.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (48.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 (36.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (45.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol use</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.37</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (13.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (21.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (20.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (27.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 (75.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (71.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290 (67.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (60.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heavy, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (11.)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (12.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (11.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity (1000 MET-min/week), mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (3.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (3.5)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 (3.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (3.2)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.77</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep (&lt;6 hours)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122 (58.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (66.1)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239 (55.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (58.8)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body Mass Index, mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.05 (4.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.29 (5.1)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3 (5.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1 (5.8)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular disease, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (6.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.9)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (4.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.9)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (5.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.4)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (2.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.5)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of other chronic diseases, mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (1.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (1.1)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (1.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.2)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statin use, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (11.)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.9)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.65</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (4.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.9)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-inflammatory medication use, n (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (5.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7.1)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (5.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.9)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cortisol indicators</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCg (nmol/l/h), mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.19 (6.93)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.27 (6.96)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.66 (7.43)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.94 (7.79)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCi (nmol/l/h), mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68 (5.98)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (8.27)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.73</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04 (6.15)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 (6.95)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evening cortisol (nmol/l)<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref>, mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65 (1.79)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.75 (1.73)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.93 (1.75)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.93 (1.10)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diurnal cortisol slope (decline/h)<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref>, mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 (0.39)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.50)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.38)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.39)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.92</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Inflammatory markers</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (mg/l)<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref>, mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (5.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 (8.57)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (5.21)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (5.88)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.79</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-6 (pg/ml)<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref>, mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (4.65)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (6.41)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 (3.89)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (3.60)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-α (pg/ml)<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref>, mean (sd)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 (4.78)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (1.56)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 (3.82)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (3.88)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.16</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>Abbreviations: sd, standard deviation; AUCg, area under the curve with respect to the ground; AUCi area under the curve with respect to increase; CRP, C-reactive Protein; IL-6, Interleukin-6; TNF-α, Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Based on T-tests for continous variables and χ<sup>2</sup>-test for dichotomous and categorical variables.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> To normalize parameters, evening cortisol, CRP, IL-6 and TNF-α were ln-transformed, for interpretation means and standard deviations were back transformed.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0133898.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Pearson’s correlations between cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0133898.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Cortisol indicators</th>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Inflammatory markers</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Depressed men</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AUCg</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AUCi</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Even.</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Diurn.</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CRP</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IL-6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TNF-α</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cortisol indicators</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCg</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evening cortisol</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diurnal cortisol slope</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.45<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.08</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Inflammatory markers</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-α</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Depressed women</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AUCg</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AUCi</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Even.</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Diurn.</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CRP</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IL-6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TNF-α</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cortisol indicators</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCg</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evening cortisol</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diurnal cortisol slope</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.35<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.12<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Inflammatory markers</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.08</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-α</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>Abbreviations: even., evening cortisol; diurn., diurnal cortisol slope; AUCg, area under the curve with respect to the ground; AUCi area under the curve with respect to increase; CRP, C-reactive Protein; IL-6, Interleukin-6; TNF-α, Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p>* = p &lt;.05.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref rid="pone.0133898.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the results of logistic regression analyses separately relating each of the cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers to a lifetime (hypo)manic episode. None of the cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers was significantly associated with a lifetime (hyp)manic episode (i.e. all p≥.15 in depressed men, all p≥.15 in depressed women) and, consequently, analyses on <italic>independent associations</italic> were not further performed.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0133898.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Associations of cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0133898.t003g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Lifetime (hypo)manic episode Adjusted for basic covariates</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Depressed men</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold><xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cortisol indicators</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCg (nmol/l/h) (N = 168)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95–1.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCi (nmol/l/h) (N = 168)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93–1.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.86</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evening cortisol (nmol/l) (N = 200)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54–1.97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diurnal cortisol slope (decline/h) (N = 152)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60–5.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Inflammatory markers</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (mg/l) (N = 266)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87–1.25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.63</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-6 (pg/ml) (N = 266)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83–1.19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.95</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-α (pg/ml) (N = 266)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88–2.27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Depressed women</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold><xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cortisol indicators</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCg (nmol/l/h) (N = 325)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95–1.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCi (nmol/l/h) (N = 325)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91–1.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evening cortisol (nmol/l) (N = 381)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56–1.72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.98</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diurnal cortisol slope (decline/h) (N = 306)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32–2.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.89</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Inflammatory markers</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (mg/l) (N = 500)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83–1.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-6 (pg/ml) (N = 500)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89–1.40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-α (pg/ml) (N = 500)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93–1.61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.15</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>Abbreviations: OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval, AUCg, area under the curve with respect to the ground; AUCi area under the curve with respect to increase; CRP, C-reactive Protein; IL-6, Interleukin-6; TNF-α, Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Based on multivariable logistic regression analyses comparing depressed patients with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode to depressed patients without a lifetime (hypo)manic episode (reference), adjusted for basic covariates (sociodemographics, sampling factors).</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>To examine <italic>effect modification</italic> between HPA-axis activity and immunological activity in relation to a lifetime (hypo)manic episode, we first tested the interaction terms between all cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers (see <xref rid="pone.0133898.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Diurnal cortisol slope and CRP showed a significant interaction in depressed men (p = .005), whereas significant interactions were found for evening cortisol and IL-6 (p = .049) in depressed women. These significant interactions were further explored by combining information on the level (low versus high) of these specific cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers (see <xref rid="pone.0133898.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Compared to depressed men with low levels of diurnal cortisol slope and CRP, the odds of having a lifetime (hypo)manic episode was significantly increased in men with both high diurnal cortisol slope and CRP levels (OR = 5.23, p = .008, adjusted for basic covariates). After additional adjustment for health factors, these odds increased even more for men with high levels on both diurnal cortisol slope and CRP (OR = 10.99, p = .001). Although the direction and magnitude of the ORs showed some variation in depressed women, no significant differences were found between women with high evening values only (p = .19), high IL-6 levels only (p = .35) and both high evening cortisol and IL-6 levels (p = .50).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0133898.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Significance of interactions between cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers in relation to a lifetime (hypo)manic episode<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0133898.t004g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Inflammatory markers</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-6</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-α</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Depressed men</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cortisol indicators</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCg</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.77</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evening cortisol</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.62</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diurnal cortisol slope</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Depressed women</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cortisol indicators</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCg</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUCi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evening cortisol</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diurnal cortisol slope</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.81</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.90</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p>Abbreviations: AUCg, area under the curve with respect to the ground; AUCi area under the curve with respect to increase; CRP, C-reactive Protein; IL-6, Interleukin-6; TNF-α, Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Based on multivariable logistic regression analyses comparing depressed patients with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode to depressed patients without a lifetime (hypo)manic episode (reference), adjusted for basic covariates (sociodemographics, sampling factors).</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0133898.t005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t005</object-id>
<label>Table 5</label> <caption><title>Associations of combined cortisol and inflammatory groups with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0133898.t005g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0133898.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Lifetime (hypo)manic episode Adjusted for basic covariates<xref rid="t005fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Lifetime (hypo)manic episode Additionally adjusted for health factors<xref rid="t005fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Depressed men</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Slope*CRP</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low slope / low CRP (N = 63)</td>
<td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>Reference</italic></td>
<td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>Reference</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High slope/ low CRP (N = 33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14–2.31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09–2.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low slope / high CRP (N = 33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12–2.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10–2.72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High slope/ high CRP (N = 23)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55–17.62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52–47.91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Depressed women</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Evening*IL-6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low evening / low IL-6 (N = 145)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Reference</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High evening / low IL-6 (N = 95)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76–3.79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low evening / high IL-6 (N = 63)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62–3.86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High evening / high IL-6 (N = 34)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13–2.76</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t005fn001"><p>Abbreviations: OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval, AUCg, area under the curve with respect to the ground; AUCi area under the curve with respect to increase; CRP, C-reactive Protein; IL-6, Interleukin-6; TNF-α, Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha.</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Based on multivariable logistic regression analyses comparing depressed patients with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode to depressed patients without a lifetime (hypo)manic episode (reference), adjusted for basic covariates (sociodemographics, sampling factors).</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> Based on multivariable logistic regression analyses comparing depressed patients with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode to depressed patients without a lifetime (hypo)manic episode (reference), additionally adjusted for health factors.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>To our knowledge, this was the first study that considered the interrelatedness of the HPA-axis and immune system in a large sample of depressed patients with additional information on the presence of a lifetime (hypo)manic episode. Our study demonstrated that neither cortisol indicators nor inflammatory markers were (independently) associated with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode in the overall analyses in depressed men and women. When exploring possible effect modification, most of the analyses again yielded non-significant results. However, the association between diurnal cortisol slope and a lifetime (hypo)manic episode depended on CRP level, and vice versa, in depressed men. More specifically, depressed men with high levels of both diurnal cortisol slope and CRP had a 5-fold increased odds of having a lifetime (hypo)manic episode compared to men with low levels of both diurnal cortisol slope and CRP. Adjustment for the potentially confounding effects of health factors did even strengthen the association. No significant group differences were found in women.</p>
<p>An important strength of our study was the simultaneous assessment of multiple cortisol indicators and inflammatory markers and our findings, indeed, suggest that combining this information may help to distinguish patients with BD from those with UD. However, some limitations have to be recognized. First of all, we tested 24 interaction terms, and only found 2 significant results and 3 trends. Due to the small sample size of patients with BD, correcting for multiple testing with a standard conservative Bonferroni correction (p &lt;.002) would not have yielded any significant results, whereas a more lenient correction with a false discovery rate lower than 0.2 (p &lt;.008), such as advocated by Benjamini and Hochberg [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], would show that these results remain statistically significant. Although we also found a trend towards significance for the interaction between diurnal cortisol slope and IL-6 (p = .07) as well as AUCg and CRP (p = .06), power is limited. We, therefore, would like to encourage future studies to include larger numbers of patients in order to increase the reliability of findings.</p>
<p>Another important limitation of our study is that the CIDI section on (hypo)manic episodes was only conducted at the follow-up assessments after 2 years (lifetime diagnosis), 4 years (diagnosis since the last interview) or 6 years (diagnosis since the last interview). Information on the lifetime presence of a (hypo)manic episode was, thus, mainly based on retrospective data and may, therefore, be less accurate. Since we combined this information of three follow-up assessments, there is also great variation regarding the time since patients had their last (hypo)manic episode, which could influence our results. We therefore advise other studies to prospectively analyze the onset of (hypo)manic episodes in order to determine whether these biological markers can predict the onset of bipolar disorder. Third, cortisol sampling as well as inflammatory marker determination, took place on a single day, and therefore we could not take into account the day-to-day variability of cortisol secretion [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] or the circadian rhythm of cytokine secretion [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p>
<p>Finally, before translating our findings to the clinic, by for example combining assessment of inflammatory markers and cortisol indicators as a diagnostic tool is currently not appropriate. Due to practical limitations as well as the need for further data in this topic, we feel that it is far too early to state this could be the biomarker that can differentiate between unipolar and bipolar depression. However, we do think that our results show that researchers as well as clinicians involved in psychiatric biomarker research should always take into account the fact that these systems influence each.</p>
<p>Our study showed that depressed men with both high diurnal cortisol slope and high CRP levels have an increased odds of having a (hypo)manic episode compared to men with low levels of both measures. This was only evident in men, whereas in women this finding could not be replicated. This could be due to the fact that men seem to respond to stress with greater increase in cortisol compared to women [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Since inflammation represents a major stressor of the HPA-axis and vice versa [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], it could be that men are more sensitive to these interacting systems than women. Furthermore, this combination of an overactive HPA-axis and immune system may be characteristic of ‘allostatic overload’, a process in which the adaptive mechanisms of regulatory bodily systems become extreme or inefficient [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. This allostatic overload is often seen in mood disorders [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] and it has been hypothesized that the level of allostatic load reflects the severity of the disorder. As our findings demonstrated that the HPA-axis and immune system, as represented by the diurnal cortisol slope and CRP, are more severely dysregulated in BD patients than in UD patients, this may imply that BD is more severe than UD. This is in line with previous research showing that BD is associated with higher levels of impairments and disabilities compared to UD [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] and may be indirect support for the hypothesis that progression and worsening of outcomes in BD is caused by a higher allostatic load [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. One of the key mechanisms that are hypothesized to play an important role in the set point of the allostatic load, is the functioning of the Glucocorticoid Receptor (GR). That is, diminished functioning of the GR is thought to play a role in stress related diseases such as mood disorders [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Higher cortisol levels at night with a sharper decline during the day (reflected by a high diurnal slope) as well as a diminished inhibition of inflammatory activation (reflected by the general inflammatory marker CRP) could be consequences. Although our findings seem embedded in previous models, the risk of false positive findings cannot be ruled out, as for example it remains unclear how to interpret the lack of any association with IL-6 and TNF-α.</p>
<p>Another interesting observation was that neither cortisol indicators nor inflammatory markers were (independently) associated with a lifetime (hypo)manic episode in depressed men or women. This confirms findings from Su et al. [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], examining inflammation in bipolar depression, and from Becking et al. [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], using the same NESDA sample to examine inflammation in depressed patients with manic symptoms. Both studies did not find any differences in CRP, IL-6 and TNF-α level between depression subtypes. However, our results may partly contradict the findings of Jabben et al. [<xref rid="pone.0133898.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] who showed that high diurnal cortisol slope was associated with bipolar spectrum disorder in the same lNESDA sample. Our findings provide important additional information, as it showed that high diurnal cortisol slope was only associated with a (hypo)manic episode in depressed patients with high CRP levels.</p>
<p>In conclusion, our findings suggest that combining information on the HPA-axis and immune system may help to distinguish depressive episodes in the course of BD versus UD. That is, depressed men with high levels of diurnal cortisol slope as well as CRP had an increased odds of having a lifetime (hypo)manic episode, which may have resulted from a higher allostatic load. If these findings are replicated, this would underline the importance of considering HPA-axis and immunological activity simultaneously and we therefore want to encourage other researchers to include assessments on both systems in their future studies.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank the Netherlands Organization for Health Research and Development that funded the Study of Depression and Anxiety (NESDA), and all participating universities and mental health care organizations. Furthermore, we are grateful to all participants who gave their time and support to participate in the study.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaemi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boiman</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goodwin</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Diagnosing bipolar disorder and the effect of antidepressants: a naturalistic study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>804</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11078046</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Clinical consequences of under‐recognized bipolar spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>. <year>2003</year>;(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Fruyt</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demyttenaere</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bipolar (spectrum) disorder and mood stabilization: standing at the crossroads?</article-title> <source>Psychother Psychosom</source>. <year>2007</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17230048</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaemi</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sachs</surname> <given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>M. Chiou</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandurangi</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goodwin</surname> <given-names>FK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Is bipolar disorder still underdiagnosed? Are antidepressants overutilized?</article-title> <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>1999</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>1–3</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10357026</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tondo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lepri</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baldessarini</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Age at onset in 3014 Sardinian bipolar and major depressive disorder patients</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source>. <year>2010</year> <month>Jun</month>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>446</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0447.2009.01523.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1600-0447.2009.01523.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20040069</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berk</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallam</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasty</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Early intervention in bipolar disorders: opportunities and pitfalls</article-title>. <source>Med J Aust</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>187</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boschloo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spijker</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoencamp</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kupka</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nolen</surname> <given-names>W a</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoevers</surname> <given-names>R a</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Predictors of the onset of manic symptoms and a (hypo)manic episode in patients with major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2014</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e106871</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0106871" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0106871</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25259889</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname> <given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shim</surname> <given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>H-R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jun</surname> <given-names>T-Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bahk</surname> <given-names>W-M</given-names></name>. <article-title>A diagnosis of bipolar spectrum disorder predicts diagnostic conversion from unipolar depression to bipolar disorder: A 5-year retrospective study</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord. Elsevier</source>; <year>2015</year> <month>Mar</month>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benazzi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helmi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bland</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Agitated Depression: Unipolar? Bipolar? or Both?</article-title> <source>Ann Clin Psychiatry</source>. <year>2002</year> <month>Jun</month> <day>1</day>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12238740</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howren</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamkin</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suls</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Associations of depression with C-reactive protein, IL-1, and IL-6: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychosom Med</source>. <year>2009</year> <month>Feb</month>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/PSY.0b013e3181907c1b" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/PSY.0b013e3181907c1b</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19188531</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holsboer</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>The corticosteroid receptor hypothesis of depression</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>. <year>2000</year> <month>Nov</month>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11027914</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname> <given-names>BI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kemp</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soczynska</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inflammation and the phenomenology, pathophysiology, comorbidity, and treatment of bipolar disorder: a systematic review of the literature</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>. <year>2009</year> <month>Aug</month>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1078</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4088/JCP.08r04505" xlink:type="simple">10.4088/JCP.08r04505</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19497250</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daban</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieta</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackin</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis and bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Psych Clin N-Am</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cervantes</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gelber</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kin</surname> <given-names>FN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname> <given-names>VN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Circadian secretion of cortisol in bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>J psychiatry Neurosci</source>. <year>2001</year> <month>Nov</month>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11762208</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deshauer</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alda</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The cortisol awakening response in bipolar illness: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Can J psychiatry</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12971016</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myint</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>S-H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Imbalance between pro-inflammatory and anti-inflammatory cytokines in bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17434599</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leboyer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soreca</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frye</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamouza</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Can bipolar disorder be viewed as a multi-system inflammatory disease?</article-title> <source>J Affect Disord. Elsevier B.V</source>.; <year>2012</year> <month>Dec</month> <day>1</day>;<volume>141</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickerson</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stallings</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Origoni</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boronow</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yolken</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Elevated serum levels of C-reactive protein are associated with mania symptoms in outpatients with bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2007</year> <month>May</month> <day>9</day>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>952</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17391822</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhagwagar</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hafizi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cowen</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Increased salivary cortisol after waking in depression</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>. <year>2005</year> <month>Oct</month>;<volume>182</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vreeburg</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoogendijk</surname> <given-names>WJG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Pelt</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Derijk</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhagen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dyck</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Major Depressive Disorder and Hypothalamic-Pituitary-Adrenal Axis Activity</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>617</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2009.50" xlink:type="simple">10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2009.50</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19487626</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Häfner</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baghai</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eser</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schüle</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rupprecht</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bondy</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>C-reactive protein is associated with polymorphisms of the angiotensin-converting enzyme gene in major depressed patients</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Res</source>. <year>2008</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17391703</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehman</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiefe</surname> <given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seeman</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Relationship of Early Life Stress and Psychological Functioning to Adult C-Reactive Protein in the Coronary Artery Risk Development in Young Adults Study</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>819</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16712805</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bremmer</surname> <given-names>M a</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beekman</surname> <given-names>a TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deeg</surname> <given-names>DJH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penninx</surname> <given-names>BWJH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dik</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hack</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Inflammatory markers in late-life depression: results from a population-based study</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2008</year> <month>Mar</month>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17716746</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rybakowski</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Twardowska</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>The dexamethasone/corticotropin-releasing hormone test in depression in bipolar and unipolar affective illness</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Res</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10504004</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname> <given-names>Y-M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname> <given-names>T-P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>C-T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname> <given-names>S-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>M-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname> <given-names>P-C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Comparison of pro-inflammatory cytokines among patients with bipolar disorder and unipolar depression and normal controls</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>. <year>2014</year> <month>Sep</month> <day>25</day>;<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabben</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nolen</surname> <given-names>W A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smit</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vreeburg</surname> <given-names>S A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beekman</surname> <given-names>ATF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penninx</surname> <given-names>BWJH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Co-occurring manic symptomatology influences HPA axis alterations in depression</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Res. Elsevier Ltd</source>; <year>2011</year> <month>Sep</month>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1208</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becking</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boschloo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogelzangs</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haarman</surname> <given-names>BCM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riemersma-van der Lek</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penninx</surname> <given-names>BWJH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The association between immune activation and manic symptoms in patients with a depressive disorder</article-title>. <source>Transl Psychiatry. Nature Publishing Group</source>; <year>2013</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e314</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ritchey</surname> <given-names>A. K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chronic psychological stress and the regulation of pro-inflammatory cytokines: A glucocorticoid-resistance model</article-title>. <source>Heal Psychol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiecolt-Glaser</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Preacher</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacCallum</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malarkey</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glaser</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chronic stress and age-related increases in the proinflammatory cytokine IL-6</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2003</year> <month>Jul</month> <day>22</day>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>9090</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12840146</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zunszain</surname> <given-names>P A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anacker</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cattaneo</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname> <given-names>L A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pariante</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Glucocorticoids, cytokines and brain abnormalities in depression. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry</article-title>. <source>Elsevier Inc.</source>; <year>2011</year> <month>Apr</month> <day>29</day>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>722</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horowitz</surname> <given-names>M A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zunszain</surname> <given-names>P A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anacker</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Musaelyan</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pariante</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Glucocorticoids and Inflammation: A Double-Headed Sword in Depression? How Do Neuroendocrine and Inflammatory Pathways Interact during Stress to Contribute to the Pathogenesis of Depression?</article-title>. <source>Mod trends pharmacopsychiatry</source>. <year>2013</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuehner</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Review article Gender differences in unipolar depression: an update of epidemiological findings and possible explanations</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12890270</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sloan</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kornstein</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gender differences in depression and response to antidepressant treatment</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Clin North Am</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14563099</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vitonis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harlow</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Risk for New Onset of Depression During the Menopausal Transition</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16585467</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gobinath</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Influence of sex and stress exposure across the lifespan on endophenotypes of depression: focus on behavior, glucocorticoids and hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Front Neurosci</source>. <year>2014</year>;</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Penninx</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beekman</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smit</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zitman</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nolen</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spinhoven</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The Netherlands Study of Depression and Anxiety (NESDA): rationale, objectives and methods</article-title>. <source>Int J Methods Psychiatr Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/mpr.256" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/mpr.256</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18763692</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">American Psychiatric Association</collab>. <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</source>. <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>; <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wittchen</surname> <given-names>HU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robins</surname> <given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cottler</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sartorius</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Regier</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cross-cultural feasibility, reliability and sources of variance of the composite international diagnostic interview (CIDI)</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>159</volume>:<fpage>645</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1756340</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gander</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pfister</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>To what degree does the Composite International Diagnostic Interview (CIDI) correctly identify DSM‐IV disorders? Testing validity issues in a clinical sample</article-title>. <source>Int J Methods Psychiatr Res</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akiskal</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Angst</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guyer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschfeld</surname> <given-names>RM A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merikangas</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Validity of the assessment of bipolar spectrum disorders in the WHO CIDI 3.0</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16997383</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pruessner</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirschbaum</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meinlschmid</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellhammer</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Two formulas for computation of the area under the curve represent measures of total hormone concentration versus time-dependent change</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>. <year>2003</year> <month>Oct</month>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>916</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12892658</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clow</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hucklebridge</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Exploration of the awakening cortisol response in relation to diurnal cortisol secretory activity</article-title>. <source>Life Sci</source>. <year>2001</year> <month>Mar</month> <day>23</day>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>2093</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11324714</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogelzangs</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duivis</surname> <given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beekman</surname> <given-names>ATF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kluft</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neuteboom</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoogendijk</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Association of depressive disorders, depression characteristics and antidepressant medication with inflammation</article-title>. <source>Transl Psychiatry. Nature Publishing Group</source>; <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e79</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vreeburg</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kruijtzer</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Associations between sociodemographic, sampling and health factors and various salivary cortisol indicators in a large sample without psychopathology</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1109</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.04.024" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.04.024</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19515498</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Connor</surname> <given-names>M-F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bower</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Creswell</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitrov</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamby</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>To assess, to control, to exclude: effects of biobehavioral factors on circulating inflammatory markers</article-title>. <source>Brain Behav Immun. Elsevier Inc.</source>; <year>2009</year> <month>Oct</month>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>887</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kupfer</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The increasing medical burden in bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Jama</source>. <year>2005</year> <month>May</month> <day>25</day>;<volume>293</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2528</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15914754</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berk</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effects of physical activity in the acute treatment of bipolar disorder: A pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17182104</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berk</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>W V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tohen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lubman</surname> <given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieta</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Going up in smoke: tobacco smoking is associated with worse treatment outcomes in mania</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2008</year> <month>Sep</month>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2008.01.018" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jad.2008.01.018</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18280579</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sjöström</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bauman</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Booth</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ainsworth</surname> <given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>International physical activity questionnaire: 12-country reliability and validity</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>. <year>2003</year> <month>Aug</month>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1381</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12900694</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kripke</surname> <given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naughton</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Reliability and Validity of the Women’s Health Initiative Insomnia Rating Scale</article-title>. <source>Psychol Assess</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12847774</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogelzangs</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seldenrijk</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beekman</surname> <given-names>ATF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hout</surname> <given-names>HPJ Van</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jonge</surname> <given-names>P De</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penninx</surname> <given-names>BWJH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cardiovascular disease in persons with depressive and anxiety disorders</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord. Elsevier B.V</source>.; <year>2010</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>1–3</issue>):<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochberg</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamini</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>More powerful procedures for multiple significance testing</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>July 1988</issue>):<fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stalder</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hucklebridge</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clow</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use of a single case study design to examine state variation in the cortisol awakening response: Relationship with time of awakening</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.psyneuen.2008.10.023" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2008.10.023</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19059727</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uçeyler</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Häuser</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Systematic review with meta-analysis: cytokines in fibromyalgia syndrome. BMC Musculoskelet Disord</article-title>. <source>BioMed Central Ltd</source>; <year>2011</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>245</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kudielka</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirschbaum</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sex differences in HPA axis responses to stress: a review</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychol</source>. <year>2005</year> <month>Apr</month>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15740829</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anisman</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merali</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cytokines, stress and depressive illness: brain-immune interactions</article-title>. <source>Ann Med</source>. <year>2003</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12693607</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McEwen</surname> <given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Protection and damage from acute and chronic stress: allostasis and allostatic overload and relevance to the pathophysiology of psychiatric disorders</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>2004</year> <month>Dec</month>;<volume>1032</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15677391</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McEwen</surname> <given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mood disorders and allostatic load</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2003</year> <month>Aug</month>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12893096</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pini</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Queiroz</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagnin</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pezawas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Angst</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cassano</surname> <given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Prevalence and burden of bipolar disorders in European countries</article-title>. <source>Eur Neuropsychopharmacol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15935623</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grande</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magalhães</surname> <given-names>P V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunz</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieta</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kapczinski</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mediators of allostasis and systemic toxicity in bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Physiol Behav. Elsevier Inc.</source>; <year>2012</year> <month>Apr</month> <day>12</day>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname> <given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sternberg</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Glucocorticoid regulation of inflammation and its functional correlates: from HPA axis to glucocorticoid receptor dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>2012</year> <month>Jul</month>;<volume>1261</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-6632.2012.06633.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2012.06633.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22823394</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0133898.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname> <given-names>S-C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>M-T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname> <given-names>M-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>C-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y-C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname> <given-names>Y-J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Brain-Derived Neurotrophic Factor, Adiponectin, and Proinflammatory Markers in Various Subtypes of Depression in Young Men</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychiatry Med</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>