<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130758</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-10893</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Emergency Department Overcrowding and Ambulance Turnaround Time</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Emergency Department Overcrowding and Ambulance Turnaround Time</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Yu Jin</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>Sang Do</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Eui Jung</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>Jin Seong</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff004" ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cha</surname>
<given-names>Won Chul</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff005" ref-type="aff"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Emergency Medicine, Seoul National University Hospital, Seoul, Korea</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Laboratory of Emergency Medical Services, Seoul National University Hospital Biomedical Research Institute, Seoul, Korea</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, Inha University Graduate School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Department of Emergency Medicine, Gachon University Gil Hospital, Seoul, Korea</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>Department of Emergency Medicine, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lazzeri</surname>
<given-names>Chiara</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria Careggi, ITALY</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: WCC. Performed the experiments: SDS. Analyzed the data: EJL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JSC. Wrote the paper: YJL.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">docchaster@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>26</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e0130758</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>14</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>23</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Lee et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Objective</title>
<p>The aims of this study were to describe overcrowding in regional emergency departments in Seoul, Korea and evaluate the effect of crowdedness on ambulance turnaround time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>This study was conducted between January 2010 and December 2010. Patients who were transported by 119-responding ambulances to 28 emergency centers within Seoul were eligible for enrollment. Overcrowding was defined as the average occupancy rate, which was equal to the average number of patients staying in an emergency department (ED) for 4 hours divided by the number of beds in the ED. After selecting groups for final analysis, multi-level regression modeling (MLM) was performed with random-effects for EDs, to evaluate associations between occupancy rate and turnaround time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Between January 2010 and December 2010, 163,659 patients transported to 28 EDs were enrolled. The median occupancy rate was 0.42 (range: 0.10-1.94; interquartile range (IQR): 0.20-0.76). Overcrowded EDs were more likely to have older patients, those with normal mentality, and non-trauma patients. Overcrowded EDs were more likely to have longer turnaround intervals and traveling distances. The MLM analysis showed that an increase of 1% in occupancy rate was associated with 0.02-minute decrease in turnaround interval (95% CI: 0.01 to 0.03). In subgroup analyses limited to EDs with occupancy rates over 100%, we also observed a 0.03 minute decrease in turnaround interval per 1% increase in occupancy rate (95% CI: 0.01 to 0.05).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In this study, we found wide variation in emergency department crowding in a metropolitan Korean city. Our data indicate that ED overcrowding is negatively associated with turnaround interval with very small practical significance.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="3"/>
<table-count count="3"/>
<page-count count="9"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Emergency Department (ED) overcrowding has become a global health issue.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] ED overcrowding stems from multiple input, throughput, and output factors.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] It has been consistently reported that once overcrowded, an ED cannot function properly. Overcrowded EDs experience reduced performance quality as well as increased mortality and morbidity.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0130758.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</p>
<p>One of the most worrisome adverse effects of ED overcrowding is its effect on the prehospital system. Ambulances may be diverted from overcrowded EDs and rerouted to another facility, leading to additional transport time and increasing patient risks.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] In addition, ambulances must wait at EDs until they find appropriate beds to unload patients from their stretchers, known as offload time. This prolongs the turnaround time and decreases the availability of ambulances.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</p>
<p>Most published studies have been conducted in developed Western communities. No studies focusing on the association between the prehospital system and ED overcrowding have been conducted in developing countries. Considering the differences in the emergency medical service (EMS) among nations, investigation of the effects of ED overcrowding in these countries is warranted.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] The aim of this study was to describe the status of ED overcrowding in Seoul and evaluate the effect of overcrowding on ambulance turnaround time within this region.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Setting and participants</title>
<p>The study was conducted in Seoul, a large metropolitan city in Korea with a population of approximately 10 million people in an area of 605.2 km<sup>2</sup>. The population density of Seoul ranks among the highest for cities in the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD).[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] There are 31 designated emergency centers in the region that are capable of treating major trauma and critical patients.</p>
<p>The EMS system in Seoul is controlled by the National Emergency Management Agency (NEMA) with call number 119. Ambulances responding to 119 calls cover all prehospital transport, free of charge, including basic life support (BLS), intravenous (IV) access, and endotracheal intubation. At the time of this study, there were approximately 112 ambulances responding to 119 calls in service. It is by law, that ambulance crews have to hand—over patients to hospital staffs directly, which implies that they must wait to unload the patient on appropriate beds.</p>
<p>Patients were enrolled if they were transported by ambulance to 28 emergency centers between January 2010 and December 2010. Patients transported to other hospitals were excluded, as we did not have data on overcrowding status for those institutes.</p>
<p>Ethics approval was obtained from the Institutional Review Board (IRB) of Samsung Medical Center to conduct this study: IRB No: 2014-07-058. The requirement to obtain written informed consent from all study participants was waived by the IRB. Patient records were anonymized and de-identified prior to analysis</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Methods and measurements</title>
<p>We used the National Emergency Department Information System (NEDIS) to calculate ED overcrowding status for each ED in Seoul. We defined overcrowding status as the average occupancy rate, which was calculated by dividing the average number of patients staying in an ED for 4 hours by the number of beds in the ED. This index has been shown to be a reliable tool to quantify overcrowding status.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0130758.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</p>
<p>The 119 ambulance run database was used to analyze ambulance turnaround time. This database is based on ambulance run sheets, which records patients’ clinical status along with time stamps for the time the 119 call was placed, engine start time, field arrival, field departure, ED arrival, and the time the ambulance returned to base. We defined the turnaround time as the interval from the time of ED arrival to the time the ambulance returned to base.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>First, we calculated the overall average overcrowding status for each ED. Then, we analyzed associations between overcrowding and turnaround time for each group. Regression analysis was performed to predict the turnaround time for each individual, with adjustment for potential confounders, using a multi-level regression model (MLM) with random effects for EDs.</p>
<p>We also performed a subgroup analysis using only the patients who visited EDs with occupancy rates over 100%. This analysis was done because the association between overcrowding and turnaround time may not be linear when occupancy is not saturated (i.e., 100% occupied). We used Stata software (version 12.1, Stata Corporation, College Station, TX) for all analyses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Sensitivity analysis</title>
<p>Emergency departments differ in level of overcrowding. We performed sensitivity analysis with same regression analysis methods on three subgroups. (average occupancy ≤0.5, occupancy 0.5 ~ 1.0, and occupancy ≥1.0)</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>From January 2010 to December 2010, 28 EDs in Seoul sent data to NEDIS. The occupancy rates of these hospitals are shown in <xref rid="pone.0130758.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>. The median occupancy rate was 0.42 (interquartile range (IQR): 0.20–0.76), with a minimum of 0.10 and maximum of 1.94. Because of the wide range, we stratified EDs into 4 groups according to their occupancy rate (<xref rid="pone.0130758.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0130758.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Median occupancy rate of emergency departments in Seoul.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The 119 ambulance database from the same time period was used to enroll patients. During the study period, there were 277,214 ambulance transportations; 163,659 (59.0%) of these were transported to the 28 emergency centers evaluated in this study. The characteristics of the study population are shown in <xref rid="pone.0130758.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The mean age was 49.7 years (standard deviation (SD): 23.1). Of the patients, 91,060 (55.6%) were male. 24,368 (14.9%) presented with abnormal mentality as verbal response to coma. 60,805 (37.2%) were trauma patients. The average turnaround time was 31.5 min (SD: 24.0). The average distance between the ED and base was 3.13 km (SD: 2.80).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0130758.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Characteristics of the study population.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0130758.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Mean occupancy rate</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤0.5</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.5 to ≤1.0</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1.0</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of EDs<italic><xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87,487</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,211</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,961</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163,659</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, mean (SD) <italic><xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.1 (22.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.0 (23.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.6 (23.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.7 (23.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, N (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48,852 (55.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,167 (55.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,041 (55.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91,060 (55.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal mentality, N (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,460 (15.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,495 (14.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,413 (14.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,368 (14.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trauma, N (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36,460 (41.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,015 (36.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,330 (27.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60,805 (37.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turnaround interval, min (SD)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0 (22.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.5 (22.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1 (27.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5 (24.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED-base distance, km (SD)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.59 (2.10)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01 (2.30)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.48 (3.97)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12 (2.80)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>EDs were grouped based on their mean occupancy rate. <italic>*</italic></p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p><italic>* ED</italic>: <italic>emergency department</italic></p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p><italic>**SD</italic>: <italic>standard deviation</italic></p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The association between occupancy rate and turnaround time for ED level is shown in <xref rid="pone.0130758.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>. Occupancy rate and turnaround time were positively associated (Spearman’s rho = 0.58; P = 0.002). However, the relationship within each ED differed widely. Traveling distance was also different among EDs. The within ED variation of turn-around time and distance was displayed in <xref rid="pone.0130758.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>, and <xref rid="pone.0130758.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>. In <xref rid="pone.0130758.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, the circadian variation in turnaround time and occupancy rate is shown. Both turnaround time and occupancy rate increased during the daytime.</p>
<fig id="pone.0130758.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>demonstrates the association between the average turnaround time and occupancy rate at the emergency department level.</title>
<p>Spearman’s rho was 0.58 (P = 0.002). <italic>*95% CI</italic>: <italic>95% confidence interval</italic></p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pone.0130758.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Circadian variation in emergency department overcrowding and ambulance turnaround time.</title>
<p>During daytime, overcrowding and turnaround time increase together.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><xref rid="pone.0130758.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the results of the linear regression analysis and multi-level regression model with random effects for EDs. An increase in 1% of occupancy rate was associated with 0.02 minute (95% CI: 0.01 to 0.03) decrease in turnaround time. When limited to patients treated at EDs with an occupancy rate of 100% or greater, we observed a 0.03 minute (95% CI: 0.01 to 0.05) decrease in turnaround time per 1% increase in occupancy rate (<xref rid="pone.0130758.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0130758.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Linear regression analysis with a multi-level regression model.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0130758.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factors</th>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Multi-level analysis</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coef.</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(95% CI) <italic><xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></italic></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age group, yr</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>≥ 18</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">0.00 (Reference)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>19–65</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.88 to 1.59)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>66–110</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.50 to 2.28)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gender, male</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.02 to 0.44)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Abnormal mentality</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.81 to 3.70)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Trauma</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.19 to 1.63)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Time</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>00:00–04:00</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">0.00 (Reference)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>04:00–08:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.11 to 5.29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>08:00–12:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13.3 to 14.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>12:00–16:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15.3 to 16.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>16:00–20:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.1 to 11.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>20:00–24:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.12 to 7.25)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Day of the week</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>Sunday</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">0.00 (Reference)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>Monday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.59 to 2.87)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>Tuesday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.23 to 2.51)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>Wednesday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.90 to 2.18)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>Thursday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.41 to 2.69)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>Friday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.75 to 30.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    <bold>Saturday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.30 to 1.62)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Distance, km</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.44 to 3.60)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Occupancy rate, %</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.03 to -0.01)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Constant</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.8 to 13.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>Covariates were distance between ED and ambulance base, age, gender, mentality, trauma, and overcrowding group.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p><italic>*95% CI</italic>: <italic>95% confidence interval</italic></p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0130758.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Subgroup analysis of EDs with occupancy rate &gt; 1.0.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0130758.t003g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factors</th>
<th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Multi-level analysis</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coef.</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(95% CI) <italic><xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></italic></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age group, yr</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    ≥ 18</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">0.00 (Reference)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    19–65</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.76 to 3.31)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    66–110</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.97 to 3.63)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gender, male</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.15 to 1.09)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Abnormal mentality</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.21 to 5.56)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Trauma</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.08 to 2.15)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Time</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    00:00–04:00</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">0.00 (Reference)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    04:00–08:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.34 to 11.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    08:00–12:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.07 to 16.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    12:00–16:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(11.7 to 18.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    16:00–20:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.0 to 16.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    20:00–24:00</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.02 to 11.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Day of the week</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    Sunday</bold></td>
<td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">0.00 (Reference)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    Monday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.88 to 4.63)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    Tuesday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.79 to 5.61)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    Wednesday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.90 to 5.73)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    Thursday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.87 to 4.69)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    Friday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.53 to 6.35)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>    Saturday</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.07 to 3.85)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Distance, km</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.57 to 3.19)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Occupancy rate, %</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-0.05 to 0.01)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Constant</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8.95 to 16.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>Linear regression analysis with a multi-level regression model. Covariates were distance between ED and ambulance base, age, gender, mentality, trauma, and overcrowding group.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p><italic>*95% CI</italic>: <italic>95% confidence interval</italic></p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>A sensitivity analysis was performed. Emergency departments with average occupancy rate below 0.5 showed positive association between occupancy rate and turnaround time without statistical significance. (Coef. = 0.03 (95% CI: -0.00 to 0.06, p = 0.08) Emergency departments with average occupancy rate between 0.5 to 1.0 showed positive association between occupancy rate and turnaround time without statistical significance. (Coef. = 0.03 (95% CI: -0.01 to 0.07, p = 0.10) Emergency departments with average occupancy rate above 1.0 showed positive association between occupancy rate and turnaround time without statistical significance. (Coef. = -0.05 (95% CI: -0.08 to -0.02, p&lt;0.001)</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>ED overcrowding has become a major problem and is likely due to many causes, including increased complexity of clinical conditions, lack of hospital beds, and insufficient insurance programs. Overcrowded EDs function as gridlocks in the emergency health care system by diverting ambulances and increasing turnaround times. In this study, we described the overcrowding state among 28 major emergency centers in Seoul. However, the negative associations we observed between overcrowding and turnaround time were unexpected. Previous studies have demonstrated positive associations between ED overcrowding and turnaround time, while in this study, we observed a negative association. Similarly, subgroup analysis of EDs with occupancy rates greater than 1.0 also yielded a negative correlation</p>
<p>The discrepancy in outcome could be due to several different reasons. First, the cultures and policies of the EDs in this study may be different from those investigated in previous studies. ED staffs might have been more eager to find beds for 119 ambulance patients when the ED was overcrowded. The priority of getting vacant beds may be higher for 119 ambulances in the study settings though no national policy exists on priority of bed placement in ED. Though, the <xref rid="pone.0130758.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref> shows increasing turnaround time with occupancy rate which limits the potential influence of bed placement priority.</p>
<p>Second, ambulance patients could have been more likely to get up from stretchers in an overcrowded ED. Even though patients are transported by stretchers, it does not necessarily mean patients need beds for their stay in emergency departments. After the assessment by triage nurse and hand-over from 119 EMTs, many patients could sit up for chairs instead of beds. This may have facilitated the clearing process of 119 stretchers. However, we do not have data to show this process, which will be another limitation.</p>
<p>We observed a relative small effect size of a 0.02-minute decrease in turnaround time per 1% increase in occupancy rate, which is equivalent to a 2-minute decrease in turnaround time per 100% increase in occupancy rate. Although we had high statistical power due to the large sample size of this study, caution is needed in interpreting our findings.</p>
<p>ED overcrowding in developing countries has not been as widely discussed as in the developed countries. However, as the acute care system and EMS system of developing countries advance in size and performance, overcrowding may worsen. Since the healthcare system and basic characteristics of patients in these countries are distinct from those of the Western community, special attention is needed. Evidence-based policy and systematic evaluation of the “system disease” (overcrowding) will help us to mitigate this complex interwoven problem.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</p>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Limitation</title>
<p>This study has some major limitations. First, the definition of overcrowding was based on occupancy rate. Although the occupancy rate has been used as a surrogate marker for overcrowding in several studies and has been shown to be a reliable marker, there are other overcrowding indices, which may have altered our findings. For example, a substantial number of similar studies have used diversion status as a marker for overcrowding.</p>
<p>Second, the turnaround time could be biased by other factors. Though previous studies defined the turnaround interval as the period from ED arrival to the time the ambulance was back in service, this interval includes other processes, such as clearing and restocking ambulances, and completing paperwork.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0130758.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] Carter et al. have evaluated the validity of using turnaround time as a proxy for offload time, and concluded that turnaround time can be readily used with caution.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] The influence of traffic load is another critical confounder of the result. The decrease of turnaround time after office hour in the <xref rid="pone.0130758.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref> supports this relationship because the occupancy rate stays similar at the same time. However, we have adjusted for hour (with 4 hour interval) and day of week. Since the traffic has patterns of hours and days, the adjustment would have adjusted the potential confounding on some extent.</p>
<p>Third, the turnaround definition used in this article is different from previous studies, which defined turnaround time as the period from ED arrival to the time back in service.[<xref rid="pone.0130758.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0130758.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] Although the meaning of back in service can be vague, in many circumstances, it means that the ambulance is leaving the ED. In our study, ambulances returned to base for clearing and restocking, increasing the turnaround time longer due to the added travel time. We attempted to correct this potential bias by adjusting for the distance from EDs to base.</p>
<p>Finally, there could have been other variables not included in the regression model that may have acted as confounders or major effect modifiers, which could explain our unexpected outcome.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In this study, we found wide variation in emergency department crowding in a metropolitan city in a Southern Asian country. We also observed a significant negative association between ED crowding and ambulance turnaround time. However, the effect size was too small to have clinical and practical significance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0130758.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.s001" mimetype="application/zip" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Data</label>
<caption>
<title>The file S1_Data.csv is a file containing the data used in this study.</title>
<p>(ZIP)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0130758.s002" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Association between overcrowding state (occupancy rate) and turn-around time is described.</title>
<p>One can note a wide variation exit among emergency departments.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0130758.s003" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0130758.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Association between overcrowding state (occupancy rate) and travel distance is described.</title>
<p>Since the distance is associated with turn-around time and occupancy rate, it should be adjusted as a confounder of the regression model.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname> <given-names>FY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shyu</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>ED overcrowding in Taiwan: facts and strategies</article-title>. <source>The American journal of emergency medicine</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10102327</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">Institute of Medicine CotFoECitUSHS</collab>. <chapter-title>Hospital-based emergency care: at the breaking point</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><article-title>Access to acute care in the setting of emergency department overcrowding</article-title>. <source>Cjem</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17475096</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asplin</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magid</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhodes</surname> <given-names>KV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solberg</surname> <given-names>LI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lurie</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camargo</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></name>. <article-title>A conceptual model of emergency department crowding</article-title>. <source>Annals of emergency medicine</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12883504</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aronsky</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duseja</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Handel</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The effect of emergency department crowding on clinically oriented outcomes</article-title>. <source>Academic emergency medicine: official journal of the Society for Academic Emergency Medicine</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cha</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kwak</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name>. <article-title>The association between crowding and mortality in admitted pediatric patients from mixed adult-pediatric emergency departments in Korea</article-title>. <source>Pediatric emergency care</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1136</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/PEC.0b013e31823ab90b" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/PEC.0b013e31823ab90b</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22134231</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grierson</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of ambulance diversion on EMS resource availability</article-title>. <source>Prehospital emergency care: official journal of the National Association of EMS Physicians and the National Association of State EMS Directors</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neely</surname> <given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norton</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effect of hospital resource unavailability and ambulance diversions on the EMS system</article-title>. <source>Prehospital and disaster medicine</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>; discussion 7. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10155524</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ospina</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schull</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Innes</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blitz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Key indicators of overcrowding in Canadian emergency departments: a Delphi study</article-title>. <source>Cjem</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17935649</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olshaker</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rathlev</surname> <given-names>NK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emergency Department overcrowding and ambulance diversion: the impact and potential solutions of extended boarding of admitted patients in the Emergency Department</article-title>. <source>The Journal of emergency medicine</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16677993</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asplin</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emergency department crowding as a health policy issue: past development, future directions</article-title>. <source>Annals of emergency medicine</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12239493</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schull</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slaughter</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Redelmeier</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Urban emergency department overcrowding: defining the problem and eliminating misconceptions</article-title>. <source>Cjem</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17612424</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asplin</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emergency department crowding: old problem, new solutions</article-title>. <source>Emergency medicine clinics of North America</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>821</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16982341</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiuchi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alsakaf</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Comparison of emergency medical services systems across Pan-Asian countries: a Web-based survey</article-title>. <source>Prehospital emergency care: official journal of the National Association of EMS Physicians and the National Association of State EMS Directors</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Oecd Regions at a Glance 2013: Organization for Economic; 2013.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sills</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nick</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development of a novel measure of overcrowding in a pediatric emergency department</article-title>. <source>Pediatric emergency care</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17876254</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoot</surname> <given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aronsky</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Measuring and forecasting emergency department crowding in real time</article-title>. <source>Annals of emergency medicine</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>747</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17391809</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cone</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>. <article-title>A time-motion study of the emergency medical services turnaround interval</article-title>. <source>Annals of emergency medicine</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9472188</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Somma</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paladino</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lalle</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magrini</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magnanti</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Overcrowding in emergency department: an international issue</article-title>. <source>Intern Emerg Med</source> <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11739-014-1154-8" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11739-014-1154-8</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25446540</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Overton</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terashima</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cone</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Can emergency medical services use turnaround time as a proxy for measuring ambulance offload time?</article-title> <source>The Journal of emergency medicine</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jemermed.2013.08.109" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jemermed.2013.08.109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24373216</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spaite</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valenzuela</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meislin</surname> <given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Criss</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hinsberg</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prospective validation of a new model for evaluating emergency medical services systems by in-field observation of specific time intervals in prehospital care</article-title>. <source>Annals of emergency medicine</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>638</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8457088</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckstein</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effect of emergency department crowding on paramedic ambulance availability</article-title>. <source>Annals of emergency medicine</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14707948</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0130758.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schull</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lazier</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeulen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mawhinney</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emergency department contributors to ambulance diversion: a quantitative analysis</article-title>. <source>Annals of emergency medicine</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12658245</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>