<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-31075</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0055275</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Clinical immunology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Immune system</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Clinical research design</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Systematic reviews</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Diagnostic medicine</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Pathology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>General pathology</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Biomarkers</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Nutrition</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Vitamins</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Rheumatology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Systemic lupus erythematosus</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Immunology</subject>
          <subject>Pathology</subject>
          <subject>Rheumatology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Clinical Significance of Vitamin D in Systemic Lupus Erythematosus: A Systematic Review</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Vitamin D in SLE</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sakthiswary</surname>
            <given-names>Rajalingham</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Raymond</surname>
            <given-names>Azman Ali</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <addr-line>Department of Medicine, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia Medical Centre, Cheras, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Proost</surname>
            <given-names>Paul</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Leuven, Rega Institute, Belgium</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">sakthis5@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RS AAR. Performed the experiments: RS. Analyzed the data: AAR. Wrote the paper: RS AAR.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e55275</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Sakthiswary, Raymond</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Vitamin D deficiency is more prevalent among SLE patients than the general population. Over the past decade, many studies across the globe have been carried out to investigate the role of vitamin D in SLE from various clinical angles. Therefore, the aim of this systematic review is to summarise and evaluate the evidence from the published literature; focusing on the clinical significance of vitamin D in SLE.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>The following databases were searched: MEDLINE, Scopus, Web of Knowledge and CINAHL, using the terms “lupus”, “systemic lupus erythematosus”, “SLE and “vitamin D”. We included only adult human studies published in the English language between 2000 and 2012.The reference lists of included studies were thoroughly reviewed in search for other relevant studies.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>A total of 22 studies met the selection criteria. The majority of the studies were observational (95.5%) and cross sectional (90.9%). Out of the 15 studies which looked into the association between vitamin D and SLE disease activity, 10 studies (including the 3 largest studies in this series) revealed a statistically significant inverse relationship. For disease damage, on the other hand, 5 out of 6 studies failed to demonstrate any association with vitamin D levels. Cardiovascular risk factors such as insulin resistance, hypertension and hypercholesterolaemia were related to vitamin D deficiency, according to 3 of the studies.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>There is convincing evidence to support the association between vitamin D levels and SLE disease activity. There is paucity of data in other clinical aspects to make firm conclusions.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>The authors have no funding or support to report.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="6"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The link between vitamin D and systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) was first described in 1995 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Muller1">[1]</xref>. The discovery of vitamin D receptor expression by cells of the immune system has spurred more research on the immunomodulatory properties of vitamin D over the past decade. Both the innate and adaptive immune systems have a wide array of cells such as macrophages, dendritic cells, T cells, and B cells which express vitamin D receptors that may respond to the biologically active form of vitamin D (1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Adorini1">[2]</xref>. Several studies across the globe have reported that vitamin D deficiency is more prevalent among SLE patients than the general population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Kamen1">[3]</xref>. A possible explanation for this is the sun avoidance by SLE patients, which is an established trigger of lupus flares.</p>
      <p>To date, there are over a hundred studies on SLE and vitamin D. The investigators of these studies have tried to establish the prevalence of vitamin D deficiency and its significance in various clinical aspects such as disease activity, disease damage and laboratory parameters. A question which is yet to be answered is whether or not vitamin D deficiency truly alters the course and prognosis of SLE. The answer to this question has important clinical implications, as it may offer potential therapeutic possibilities with vitamin D supplementation. Therefore, the aim of this systematic review is to summarise and evaluate the evidence from published literature focusing on the clinical significance of vitamin D in SLE.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methodology</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Search Strategy</title>
        <p>We used the terms “lupus”, “systemic lupus erythematosus”, “SLE”, “vitamin D” and ‘SLE and vitamin D” to search the following databases: MEDLINE, Scopus, Web of Knowledge and CINAHL. Furthermore, the references of all retrieved articles were reviewed for relevant citations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Inclusion Criteria</title>
        <p>All adult human cohort and case-control studies written in English, which investigated the role and effects of vitamin D in SLE published between the years 2000 and 2012 were included.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Exclusion Criteria</title>
        <p>Studies in other languages apart from English, case reports, case series, animal studies letters to the editor and review articles were excluded. Regarding the justification for excluding paediatric studies; apart from the age factor, paediatric SLE runs a more aggressive clinical course than adult SLE with higher rates of organ involvement and the disease tends to be more severe at presentation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Brunner1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Pradhan1">[5]</xref>. Besides, studies on vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms were not selected. Most of the aforementioned studies lacked emphasis on and were not powered to investigate the correlation between measured vitamin D levels (25[OH]D) and its clinical significance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Abbasi1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Huang1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Huang2">[8]</xref>. Stringent selection criteria were applied in order to achieve a high level of homogeneity in the studies included in this systematic review.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Screening of Articles for Eligibility</title>
        <p>Retrieved articles were screened for eligibility based on titles and abstracts and were subsequently classified as ‘include’, ‘possible’ and ‘exclude’ categories. The ‘include’ and ‘possible’ categories comprised studies reporting (1) measured vitamin D levels and/or vitamin D supplementation, and (2) disease activity, disease damage, laboratory parameters and/or organ involvement in SLE. In the ‘possible’ category, there were uncertainties concerning the study design, sample population or objectives. For articles falling into the ‘include’ and ‘possible’ categories, where available, the full texts were obtained and assessed. Both authors participated in the selection of articles and only articles which were agreed upon by both were finally included in the review. Throughout the selection process, both authors reached consensus in every instance. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0055275-g001">Figure 1</xref> summarises the algorithm followed in the selection of studies.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0055275-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0055275.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The algorithm for selection of studies in this systematic review.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0055275.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Data Extraction</title>
        <p>The following data were extracted from the selected studies: study design; country; year; sample size; disease activity and damage scoring systems; organ involvement and findings. The relevant and particularly, significant statistical values were recorded (odds ratios [OR], p values, rho [r]).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>A total of 22 studies met the eligibility criteria. The vast majority of the studies were observational (95.5%) and cross-sectional (90.9%). Eight case-control studies and 14 cohort studies were included. The number of studies originating from each continent is as follows: 8 from America, 6 from Europe, 6 from Asia, 1 from Australia and 1 from Africa. Study sample sizes varied from 37 to 378 subjects. All studies used 25-hydroxyvitamin D to determine the vitamin D level. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0055275-t001">Table 1</xref> highlights the findings of the selected studies.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0055275-t001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0055275.t001</object-id>
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Summary of the selected studies.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0055275-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0055275.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study population</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Findings/Conclusions</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statistical findings</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Kamen2">[31]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectional Case-control</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 recently diagnosed SLE 240 controls</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower vitamin D levels is associated with a. presence of renal disease b. photosensitivity.</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR 13.3, p&lt;0.01 OR 12.9, p&lt;0.01</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza1">[9]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectional Cohort</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No relation was seen between vitamin D and disease duration, SLEDAI, SLICC-ACR or VAS indexes.</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Thudi1">[27]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectional Cohort</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 female SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin D deficiency was associated with a. lower global assessment scores, However, levels of dsDNA were higher in the group with levels of vitamin D that were greater than 47.7 nmol/L</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt; or  = 0.003p = 0.0069</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Toloza1">[32]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectional Cohort</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin D levels showed no correlation with bone mineral density</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.26</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Borba1">[15]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectional Case-control</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 SLE 26 controls</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin D level was associated witha. SLEDAI,b. osteocalcinc. bone-specific alkaline phosphatase.</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = −0.65, p&lt;0.001)r = 0.35r = −0.17,</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Wu1">[10]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCohort</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 female SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower vitamin D levels were significantly associated with highera. diastolic blood pressureb. low-density lipoprotein cholesterol,c. lipoprotein(a)d.fibrinogen levelse. self-reported hypertensionf. diabetes mellitusg. SLEDAIh. SLICC.With further adjustment for BMI, these associations were no longer significant.</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.034p = 0.013p = 0.024p = 0.000p = 0.016,OR 0.68p = 0.032, OR 0.49p = 0.001p = 0.003</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective cohort,those with low baseline vitamin D levels were supplemented with oral vitamin D(3)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inverse significant correlations between vitamin D levels and the VAS(fatigue)Changes in vitamin D levels correlated with changes in the VAS in patients with baseline vitamin D levels &lt;30 ng/mlNo significant correlationsbetween the vitamin D levels and:a. SLEDAIb. SDI</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.001p = 0.017p = 0.87p = 0.63</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Amital1">[16]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Israel</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCohort study</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">378 SLE(European and Israeli patients)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A significant negative correlation between the serum concentration of vitamin D and the SLEDAI-2K and ECLAM scales</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = −0.12,p = 0.018.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Hamza1">[17]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egypt</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCase-control</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 SLE60 controls</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum vitamin D levels were lower witha. increased SLEDAI score,b. frequency of photosensitivity</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 2.72,p = 0.002OR: 3.6,p&lt;0.01</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Bonakdar1">[18]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCohort study</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum vitamin D concentration was inversely correlated with the BILAG index score.Vitamin D deficiency was associated witha. higher concentrations of liver enzymes,b. lower serum albumin and hemoglobin concentrationsc. higher titers of antibodies to double-stranded DNA (ds-DNA).</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = −0.486,p = 0.001p&lt;0.05p&lt;0.05p&lt;0.001</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Ritterhouse1">[25]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCase-control</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 SLE32 controls</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin D deficiency was associated witha. higher B cell activationb. higher serum IFNalpha activity</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.009p = 0.02</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Kim1">[12]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCase-control</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 SLE49 controls</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The serum vitamin D levels, were positively correlated only witha. hemoglobinb. serum complement 3but not witha. SLEDAIb. SLICC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">beta = 0.256, p = 0.018beta = 0.365, p = 0.002beta = −0.04,p = 0.742beta  = −0.052,p = 0.62</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Szodoray1">[19]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hungary</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCohort</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced vitamin D levels were associated with :a. pericarditisb. neuropsychiatric diseasesc. deep vein thrombosisd. higher SLEDAI scoree. higher anti-double-stranded (ds)DNA autoantibody concentrations,f. higher anti-Smith antigen (anti-Sm) concentrationsg. lower C4 levelsh. higher immunoglobulin (Ig)G concentration</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.013p = 0.010p = 0.014p = 0.038p = 0.021p&lt;0.001p = 0.027p = 0.034</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Stockton1">[28]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCase-control</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 SLE21 controls</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue was not related to vitamin D status</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-MunozOrtego1">[13]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCohort study</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No correlation between vitamin D deficiency anda. SLEDAI scoreb. SLICC/ACR score</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.310p = 0.820</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok1">[14]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hong Kong</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCohort study</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin D correlated inversely and significantly witha. clinical SLE activityb. anti-C1qc. anti-dsDNA titers,d. but not with complement levels or damage scores.</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = −0.26;p&lt;0.001r = −0.14;p = 0.020r = −0.13;p = 0.020</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok2">[20]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hong Kong</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCohort</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levels of vitamin D correlated inversely witha. PGA,b. total SLEDAI scoresvitamin D deficiency had significantly highera. total/high-density lipoprotein(HDL) cholesterol ratiob. prevalence of antiphospholipid syndromeNo association could be demonstrated between vitamin D level and atherosclerosis</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">beta −0.20;p = 0.003beta −0.19;p = 0.003p = 0.02p = 0.007</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Yeap1">[21]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malaysia</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ProspectiveCohort</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38premenopausal SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">There was a significant negative correlation between SLEDAI scores and vitamin D levels.</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.033</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Bogaczewicz1">[26]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCase-control</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 SLE.49 controls</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin D deficiency was associated witha. renal diseaseb. leucopeniac. lower serum concentrations of IL-23)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.006p = 0.047p = 0.037</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Fragoso1">[23]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCase control</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 SLE64 controls</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No statistically significant association was observed between vitamin D deficiency and the following:a. disease activity (SLEDAI &gt;6)b. fatiguec. anti-DNA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.971p = 0.808p = 0.435</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Reynolds1">[22]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UnitedKingdom</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCohort</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with vitamin D deficiency had highera. BMIb. insulin resistance.c. SLEDAI-2KAortic stiffness was inversely associated with serum vitamin D independently of BMI, CVD risk factors and serum insulin.There was no association between vitamin D and carotid plaque and intima media thickness.</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.014p = 0.023p = 0.031beta = −0.0217p = 0.010</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Ravenell1">[29]</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UnitedStates</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross sectionalCohort</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 SLE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vitamin D levels inversely correlated with age-adjusted total plaque area.</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = –0.33,p = 0.018</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
      </table-wrap>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Vitamin D and its Association with SLE Disease Activity and Damage</title>
        <p>The disease activity was assessed in most studies with validated scoring systems such as SLEDAI (Systemic Lupus Erythematosus Disease Activity Index), BILAG (British Isles Lupus Activity Group), and ECLAM (European Consensus of Lupus Activity Measurement). In 6 of the studies, the disease damage was investigated with the Systemic Lupus International Collaborating Clinics Damage Index (SDI) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Wu1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Kim1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-MunozOrtego1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok1">[14]</xref>. Across the studies, the correlation between vitamin D levels and SLE disease activity has been rather inconsistent. Out of the 15 studies which looked into this aspect, two third of the studies (10/15) reported a significant inverse association between vitamin D and the measured disease activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Wu1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Borba1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Amital1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Hamza1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Bonakdar1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Szodoray1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok2">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Yeap1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Reynolds1">[22]</xref>. There were no significant methodological variations between the 10 studies showing an inverse relationship between vitamin D and the disease activity and the 5 studies that did not show such relationship. The outcome measurement used in all the 5 studies was SLEDAI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Kim1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-MunozOrtego1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Fragoso1">[23]</xref>. Similarly, 90% (9/10) of the studies which demonstrated a significant inverse relationship used SLEDAI. Of note, 3 out of the 5 negative studies in this regard were Spanish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-MunozOrtego1">[13]</xref>, and 2 of them were by the same authors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>.The damage scores, on the other hand, in 5 out of 6 studies failed to demonstrate a significant association with vitamin D levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Kim1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-MunozOrtego1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok1">[14]</xref>.</p>
        <p>In clinical practice, anti double stranded (ds) DNA and complement levels are simple, yet useful tools to monitor SLE disease activity. High titres of antidsDNA and low complement levels are associated with lupus flares <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Giles1">[24]</xref>.The majority of studies showed a significant inverse relationship between vitamin D levels and the former <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Bonakdar1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Szodoray1">[19]</xref> and a direct relationship with the latter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Kim1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Szodoray1">[19]</xref>. Along this line, Ritterhouse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Ritterhouse1">[25]</xref> found that that vitamin D deficiency was associated with significantly higher B cell activation and interferon alpha activity. Bogaczewicz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Bogaczewicz1">[26]</xref> had conflicting results in this regard with their finding of vitamin D deficiency being associated with lower concentrations of interleukin 23.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Vitamin D and VAS (Visual Analogue Score)</title>
        <p>The VAS was used to evaluate the patients’ global assessment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok2">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Thudi1">[27]</xref> and level of fatigue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Fragoso1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Stockton1">[28]</xref>. The findings of these studies showed no consistent pattern with respect to the relationship between the VAS and vitamin D levels. Only half of the studies found significant inverse correlation between these parameters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok2">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Thudi1">[27]</xref>. The remaining studies found no significant association.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Vitamin D and Cardiovascular Risk Factors</title>
        <p>There were 4 studies which investigated the relationship between vitamin D deficiency and cardiovascular risk factors such as hypercholesterolaemia, insulin resistance/diabetes mellitus and hypertension <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Wu1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok2">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Reynolds1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Ravenell1">[29]</xref>. Wu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Wu1">[10]</xref> found a significant association with insulin resistance which was consistent with the results of the study by Reynolds et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Reynolds1">[22]</xref>. Mok et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok2">[20]</xref> demonstrated a higher total/high density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol ratio in vitamin D deficient subjects supporting the findings of Wu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Wu1">[10]</xref> of higher low density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol with lower vitamin D levels. Reynolds et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Reynolds1">[22]</xref> and Ravenell et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Ravenell1">[29]</xref> had conflicting results on the correlation with carotid plaque. Ravenell et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Ravenell1">[29]</xref> discovered that vitamin D levels inversely correlated with age-adjusted total plaque area while Reynolds et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Reynolds1">[22]</xref> found the opposite. The latter, however demonstrated a significant increase in aortic stiffness with reducing levels of vitamin D.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The results of this systematic review indicate that there is substantial evidence to convince us of the association between vitamin D levels and SLE disease activity. However, one may argue that a few of the studies refute this finding and cast doubts on the aforementioned link. It is noteworthy that the 3 largest studies with sample sizes of 378,290 and 181 subjects, revealed strong inverse correlations between vitamin D levels and SLEDAI scores with p values of 0.018,&lt;0.001 and 0.001, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Wu1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Amital1">[16]</xref>. Mok et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok1">[14]</xref> concluded that vitamin D deficiency is a marker of SLE disease activity with comparable specificity to anti-C1q. The conflicting results of the few studies could be due to the diverse study populations, methodological variations and the power of several studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-MunozOrtego1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Fragoso1">[23]</xref> was probably too low to achieve statistical significance. While the results of these observational studies are helpful for generating hypotheses concerning the effects of vitamin D on the clinical course of SLE, it is unwise to make causal inferences from these studies.</p>
      <p>Lupus disease activity predicts the risk of subsequent organ damage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Lopez1">[30]</xref>. Intriguingly, the majority of studies consistently demonstrated that vitamin D level is not associated with organ damage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Kim1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-MunozOrtego1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0055275-Mok1">[14]</xref>. The authors are unable to provide any valid evidence-based explanation for this observation. This finding limits or perhaps, deters the use of vitamin D levels as a prognostication tool. Kamen et al. (4) and Bogaczewicz et al. (22) found an association between vitamin D levels and renal disease. Similarly, Reynolds et al. (24) and Ravenell et al. (25) pointed out a significant relationship with the cardiovascular system. These findings need to be tested rigorously by larger prospective studies to make firm conclusions. As these studies are too few in number, there is still profound lack of evidence to support the role of vitamin D in the management of the individual organ system. Nevertheless, this is an area worthy of further research due to the biologic plausibility of a link between vitamin D deficiency and especially, cardiovascular and renal disease in SLE.</p>
      <p>Our systematic review has limitations. We did not include articles in other languages which may have had valuable information or additional evidence related to this topic. It is reasonable to assume that some studies with negative or null results were simply not published; a well recognised publication bias. The cross sectional study design used in the majority of these studies does not give us a clear picture as to whether vitamin D deficiency confers a poorer outcome of SLE in the long term. Future research on vitamin D in SLE will hopefully address more practical concerns and provide answers to the following questions : the most appropriate phase of SLE to assess vitamin D (ie, at the time of diagnosis or while in remission); the cutoff value of ‘normal’ versus ‘insufficient’ vitamin D levels in lupus patients as compared to the general population; potential confounding factors such as medications, age, body size, geographic location, ethnicity, sun protective behaviours; and genetic variation in the metabolism of vitamin D.</p>
      <p>Much emphasis has been placed on vitamin D in SLE in recent years. Apart from its significant association with disease activity, based on the evidence highlighted in this systematic review, it is premature and would be fallacious to make any definitive claims for or against the role of vitamin D in other clinical aspects.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Muller1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kriegbaum</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baslund</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thymann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D3 metabolism in patients with rheumatic diseases: low serum levels of 25-hydroxyvitamin D3 in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Clinical rheumatology</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Adorini1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adorini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penna</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Control of autoimmune diseases by the vitamin D endocrine system</article-title>. <source>Nat Clin Pract Rheumatol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>404</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Kamen1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aranow</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The link between vitamin D deficiency and systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Curr Rheumatol Rep</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Brunner1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gladman</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibanez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urowitz</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Difference in disease features between childhood-onset and adult-onset systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Arthritis and rheumatism</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Pradhan1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pradhan V, Patwardhan M, Rajadhyaksha A, Ghosh K (2012) Clinical and Immunological Profile of Systemic Lupus Erythematosus. Indian pediatrics.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Abbasi1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rezaieyazdi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Afshari</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sahebari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Lack of association of vitamin D receptor gene BsmI polymorphisms in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology international</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1537</fpage>–<lpage>1539</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Huang1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>No association of vitamin D receptor gene start codon fok 1 polymorphisms in Chinese patients with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>The Journal of rheumatology</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1211</fpage>–<lpage>1213</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Huang2">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Association of vitamin D receptor gene BsmI polymorphisms in Chinese patients with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Irastorza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egurbide</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Berriotxoa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency in systemic lupus erythematosus: prevalence, predictors and clinical consequences</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>920</fpage>–<lpage>923</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Wu1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhew</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langman</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>25-hydroxyvitamin D and cardiovascular risk factors in women with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Arthritis &amp; Rheumatism: Arthritis Care &amp; Research</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1395</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-RuizIrastorza2">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Irastorza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egurbide</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Changes in vitamin D levels in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus: Effects on fatigue, disease activity, and damage</article-title>. <source>Arthritis care &amp; research</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1160</fpage>–<lpage>1165</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Kim1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D may not be a good marker of disease activity in Korean patients with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology international</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1189</fpage>–<lpage>1194</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-MunozOrtego1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Munoz-Ortego J, Torrente-Segarra V, Prieto-Alhambra D, Salman-Monte T, Carbonell-Abello J (2012) Prevalence and predictors of vitamin D deficiency in non-supplemented women with systemic lupus erythematosus in the Mediterranean region: a cohort study. Scandinavian journal of rheumatology.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Mok1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birmingham</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency as marker for disease activity and damage in systemic lupus erythematosus: a comparison with anti-dsDNA and anti-C1q</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Borba1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borba</surname><given-names>VZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kasamatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radominski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency in patients with active systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Osteoporosis international : a journal established as result of cooperation between the European Foundation for Osteoporosis and the National Osteoporosis Foundation of the USA</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Amital1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amital</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szekanecz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szucs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Serum concentrations of 25-OH vitamin D in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) are inversely related to disease activity: is it time to routinely supplement patients with SLE with vitamin D?</article-title> <source>Annals of the rheumatic diseases</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1155</fpage>–<lpage>1157</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Hamza1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamza</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Awwad</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Reduced serum concentrations of 25-hydroxy vitamin D in Egyptian patients with systemic lupus erythematosus: relation to disease activity</article-title>. <source>Medical science monitor : international medical journal of experimental and clinical research</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>CR711</fpage>–<lpage>718</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Bonakdar1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonakdar</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jahanshahifar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jahanshahifar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gholamrezaei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency and its association with disease activity in new cases of systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1155</fpage>–<lpage>1160</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Szodoray1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szodoray</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tarr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bazso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szegedi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The immunopathological role of vitamin D in patients with SLE: data from a single centre registry in Hungary</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian journal of rheumatology</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Mok2">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birmingham</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D levels in Chinese patients with systemic lupus erythematosus: relationship with disease activity, vascular risk factors and atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>652</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Yeap1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeap</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Othman</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zain</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D levels: its relationship to bone mineral density response and disease activity in premenopausal Malaysian systemic lupus erythematosus patients on corticosteroids</article-title>. <source>International journal of rheumatic diseases</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Reynolds1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pemberton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teh</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>25-Hydroxyvitamin D deficiency is associated with increased aortic stiffness in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>–<lpage>551</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Fragoso1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fragoso</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dantas</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha Junior</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>25-Hydroxyivitamin D3 levels in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus and its association with clinical parameters and laboratory tests</article-title>. <source>Revista brasileira de reumatologia</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Giles1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Giles BM, Boackle SA (2012) Linking complement and anti-dsDNA antibodies in the pathogenesis of systemic lupus erythematosus. Immunol Res.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Ritterhouse1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritterhouse</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niewold</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macwana</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency is associated with an increased autoimmune response in healthy individuals and in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Annals of the rheumatic diseases</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1569</fpage>–<lpage>1574</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Bogaczewicz1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogaczewicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sysa-Jedrzejowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arkuszewska</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zabek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kontny</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D status in systemic lupus erythematosus patients and its association with selected clinical and laboratory parameters</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>484</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Thudi1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thudi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wandstrat</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D levels and disease status in Texas patients with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>The American journal of the medical sciences</source> <volume>335</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Stockton1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stockton</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandiah</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paratz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bennell</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Fatigue, muscle strength and vitamin D status in women with systemic lupus erythematosus compared with healthy controls</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Ravenell1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravenell</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hollis</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Premature Atherosclerosis Is Associated With Hypovitaminosis D and Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme Inhibitor Non-use in Lupus Patients</article-title>. <source>The American journal of the medical sciences</source> <volume>344</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Lopez1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beeby</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isenberg</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Lupus disease activity and the risk of subsequent organ damage and mortality in a large lupus cohort</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology (Oxford)</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>498</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Kamen2">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouali</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaftman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hollis</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency in systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Autoimmunity reviews</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0055275-Toloza1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toloza</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gladman</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibanez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urowitz</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Vitamin D insufficiency in a large female SLE cohort</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>