<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
   <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
         <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
   <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PONE-RA-17832R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014758</article-id><article-categories>
         <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
            <subject>Research Article</subject>
         </subj-group>
         <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
<subject>Cell Biology/Gene Expression</subject>
<subject>Computational Biology/Genomics</subject>
<subject>Molecular Biology/Bioinformatics</subject>
<subject>Oncology/Hematological Malignancies</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> Activation and <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> Loss on Gene Expression in Murine Lymphoma</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Xpcl1</italic> and <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> in Lymphoma</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuppers</surname><given-names>Daniel A.</given-names></name>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>Harry C.</given-names></name>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¤a</sup></xref>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>Aimee L.</given-names></name>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>¤b</sup></xref>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Linsley</surname><given-names>Peter S.</given-names></name>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Clurman</surname><given-names>Bruce E.</given-names></name>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Fero</surname><given-names>Matthew L.</given-names></name>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
            <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Clinical Research Division, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, Washington, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Rosetta Inpharmatics, Seattle, Washington, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Kudla</surname><given-names>Grzegorz</given-names></name>
            <role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Edinburgh, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes>
         <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">mfero@fhcrc.org</email></corresp>
         <fn fn-type="con">
            <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: PSL MLF. Performed the experiments: DAK MLF. Analyzed the data: DAK ALJ MLF. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HCH ALJ PSL BEC MLF. Wrote the paper: MLF.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn1"><label>¤a</label><p>Current address: PhenoPath Laboratories, Seattle, Washington, United States of America</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn2"><label>¤b</label><p>Current address: Regulus Therapeutics, San Diego, California, United States of America</p>
         </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
         <p>Salary support in the form of research grants from the NIH and NCI was provided to M. Fero, H. Hwang, B. Clurman. Both Regulus Inc. and Rosetta Inpharmatics, Inc (a subsidiary of Merck Inc.) have approved or pending patents involving miRNA and microarray technology. The Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center holds patents on p27-deficient mouse models. All individuals received salary support from their host institutions. This does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
         <day>11</day>
         <month>3</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e14758</elocation-id><history>
         <date date-type="received">
            <day>9</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2010</year>
         </date>
         <date date-type="accepted">
            <day>14</day>
            <month>2</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kuppers et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
         <p>Mice lacking the <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> Cdk inhibitor (<italic>Cdkn1b</italic>) exhibit increased susceptibility to lymphomas from the Maloney murine leukemia virus (M-MuLV), and exhibit a high frequency of viral integrations at <italic>Xpcl1</italic> (<italic>Kis2</italic>), a locus on the X-chromosome. <italic>Xpcl1</italic> encodes miR-106a∼363, a cluster of microRNAs that are expressed in response to adjacent retroviral integrations. We report the first large-scale profile of microRNA expression in MuLV-induced lymphomas, in combination with microarray gene expression analysis. The source material was T-cell lymphomas induced by M-MuLV in <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> knockout mice and normal thymus. Surprisingly, the overall levels of miRNA expression were equivalent in lymphomas and normal thymus. Nonetheless, the expression of specific microRNAs was altered in tumors. The miR-106a∼363 miRNA were over-expressed in lymphomas, particularly those with viral integrations at the <italic>Xpcl1</italic> locus. In contrast, <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> deletion itself was associated with a different pattern of microRNA expression. Gene expression was dramatically altered in lymphomas, yet paralleled data from T-cell lymphomas induced by other mechanisms. Genes with altered expression in association with the <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null genotype were of similar functional classes to those associated with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration, but with the opposite pattern of expression. Thus, the effect of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> deletion may be to oppose an anti-oncogenic effect of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> rather than enhancing its oncogenic functions. A subset of miR-106a∼363 target genes was consistently reduced in lymphomas with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations, particularly genes with cell cycle and immune functions. We identify four predicted target genes of miR-106a∼363 miRNA, including <italic>N-Myc (Mycn)</italic>, and the TGF-beta receptor (<italic>Tgfbr2</italic>) using 3'UTR reporter assays. Still, bioinformatic miRNA target predictions were poor predictors of altered gene expression in lymphomas with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration. Confirmation of miR-106a∼363 gene targeting relevant to the tumor phenotype requires <italic>in vivo</italic> validation, because only a subset of predicted targets are consistently reduced in tumors that overexpress miR-106a∼363.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>National Cancer Institute R01CA100053 (MLF), R01CA084069 (BEC), K08HL073670 (HCH) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancer.gov/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cancer.gov/</ext-link>, Rosetta Inpharmatics, Inc. (PSL, ALJ) provided materials and technical support for microarray processing and miRNA QPCR. The funders had no role in data analysis, the decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
<page-count count="10"/>
</counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
   <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Mice lacking one or both copies of the <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> Cdk inhibitor are susceptible to developing a variety of tumor types when exposed to mutagenic agents. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Fero1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Gao1">[2]</xref> Several oncogenes and tumor suppressor genes have been shown to cooperate with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> loss, including PTEN and APC, in the induction of breast, colon and prostate cancers in mouse models. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Gao1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Petrocelli1">[4]</xref> We previously identified <italic>Xpcl1</italic> as a common viral integration site in T-cell lymphomas induced by Moloney murine leukemia virus (M-MuLV) infection. M-MuLV integrations targeted <italic>Xpcl1</italic> at a higher frequently in tumors induced in <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> knockout mice. This finding suggested that <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> deletion cooperates with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> activation in tumorigenesis, thus the region was referred to as the <italic>X-chromosome p27 cooperating locus</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Hwang1">[5]</xref> Expression of a non-coding RNA from this locus was increased in tumors with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations, and this was higher than levels expressed in normal thymic tissue. <italic>Xpcl1</italic> is not exclusively targeted by M-MuLV in mice with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> deletions; it has also been identified as a viral integration site in p27+/− and wildtype animals. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Hwang1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-GarrettEngele1">[6]</xref> Likewise, integrations of other retroviruses, RadLV and SL3-3, have been independently reported to map to the same X-chromosomal site in murine lymphomas. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Landais1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Lum1">[8]</xref> These integrations were associated with increased expression of a cluster of additional non-coding RNA splice variants, proximal to the viral integrations that were collectively referred to as <italic>Kis2</italic>. Mapping of microRNA sequences to the murine and human genomes identified the locus as the coding sequence for a cluster of five microRNAs, commonly referred to as miR-106a∼363, which span the proximal and distal EST clusters. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Tanzer1">[9]</xref> Thus the normal gene, herein referred to as <italic>Xpcl1</italic>, apparently produces a primary transcript that is cleaved to form component pre-miRNA hairpins, as well as the flanking ESTs. Indeed, the individual microRNA comprising miR-106a∼363 have been shown to be increased in tumors with viral integrations at the locus. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Lum1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Landais2">[10]</xref> Large scale viral mutagenesis screens identified increased cointegration of retroviruses at <italic>Xpcl1</italic> and cyclin D3 loci, which further suggests an interaction between the Rb pathway with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> in tumorigenesis. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Uren1">[11]</xref></p>
      <p>MicroRNAs are products of RNA precursors transcribed by RNA polymerase II and cleaved by the nuclear microprocessor complex, which is comprised of the RNAse III, Drosha, and DGCR8/Pasha, yielding 50−80 bp stem-loop pre-miRNA (reviewed by R. Shivdasani). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Shivdasani1">[12]</xref> Cytoplasmic Dicer further cleaves the hairpin structures off pre-miRNA producing double stranded RNA that includes the mature 20−22 bp microRNA product. Mature miRNA enter the RNA induced silencing complex (RISC), where recognition or target mRNA sequences may lead to translational silencing or degradation of mRNA targets. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Ambros1">[13]</xref> The miRBase database currently lists 600 microRNAs in the mouse genome. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-GriffithsJones1">[14]</xref> MicroRNA have been shown to impact a wide variety of physiological activities including developmental timing, cell proliferation, cell death, and hematopoiesis through a combination of direct effects on target gene expression and a cascade of secondary effects. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Carthew1">[15]</xref> The first oncogenic non-protein encoding RNA discovered was <italic>BIC</italic>, which lies at a common integration site of the avian leukosis virus, and encodes miR-155. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Clurman1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Tam1">[17]</xref> MiR-155 is overexpressed in a variety of human B-cell lymphomas, and <italic>BIC</italic> overexpression induced lymphomas in transgenic mice. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Costinean1">[18]</xref>– Human B-cell lymphomas have also been shown to harbor gene rearrangements involving the miR-17∼92 microRNA cluster, which is a paralog of miR-106a∼363. Overexpression of miR-17∼92 in transgenic mice increased the rate of Myc-induced lymphomas and was associated with reduced apoptosis, whereas cells lacking miR-17∼92 are prone to Myc induced apoptosis. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Mu1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-He1">[22]</xref></p>
      <p>It has been reported that tumor cells exhibit a global reduction in miRNA expression compared to normal tissues, and that impairment of the miRNA processing machinery is oncogenic. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Kumar1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Lu1">[24]</xref> Yet, little is known about the global patterns of miRNA or protein-coding gene expression in lymphomas induced by murine retroviruses. A hypothesis of the current work is that genetic alterations of M-MuLV induced lymphomas would result in characteristic phenotypic patterns of miRNA and protein-coding gene expression. Deletion of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> has been shown to be associated with more rapid M-MuLV-induced lymphoma development, with a higher frequency of viral integrations at <italic>Xpcl1</italic>. We therefore hypothesized that the gene expression phenotype associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> deletion in tumors would reflect an enhancement of the tumor phenotype, or an enhancement of the miRNA or gene expression profile specific to <italic>Xpcl1</italic>. The classes of genes associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> loss or <italic>Xpcl1</italic> activation may give clues to the altered functions associated with these mutations. Herein, we report the results of both a miRNA and a protein-coding gene expression analysis from M-MuLV induced T-cell lymphomas. We also validate the targeting of four genes by miRNA from the miR-106a∼363 cluster.</p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
         <title>Global miRNA expression in lymphomas vs. normal thymus</title>
         <p>Global assessments of microRNA expression have not been reported in MuLV-induced lymphomas. In this study, we used a qPCR platform (previously described) to assess expression of 188 microRNAs. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Jackson1">[25]</xref> The source material was T-cell lymphomas that had been induced by the M-MuLV infection of mice, with or without <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> knockout mutations, in F1 hybrid (C57BL/6J × 129S4) mice, as well as normal thymus controls. Retroviral integration sites were previously mapped in these samples, and integrations at the <italic>Xpcl1</italic> locus were identified in tumors from <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null animals, as well as in tumors arising in mice with one or more intact copies of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Hwang1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-GarrettEngele1">[6]</xref> (The complete dataset is given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s001">Table S1</xref>) We first compared the global miRNA expression profile of all tumors in comparison with normal murine thymus. The abundance of specific microRNAs varied over a wide range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). In keeping with what has been reported in human cancers, we found that the majority of microRNAs were reduced in lymphomas relative to total RNA input. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Lu1">[24]</xref> However, this approach does not consider the fact that lymphoma cells have a higher total RNA content than does normal thymocytes. We therefore measured the RNA and DNA content in each tumor and compared this to normal thymic tissue. On average, the lymphomas contained 1.9-fold more RNA relative to tissue mass, and relative to genomic DNA mass. Considering that M-MuLV tumors are near diploid, we conclude that there was nearly a two-fold increase in total RNA per cell in the lymphomas. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Vasmel1">[26]</xref> When adjusting for the total RNA content per cell, we find that the number of miRNAs significantly increased in lymphomas is comparable to the number that are decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). Likewise, the sum total quantity of miRNA in lymphomas was equivalent to normal tissue (Fold change = 1.08±0.05, tumor vs. normal, mean ± SE) when considered on a per cell basis.</p>
         <fig id="pone-0014758-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label>
            <caption>
               <title>Expression of miRNA in M-MuLV lymphomas.</title>
               <p>The overall abundance and distribution of expression of individual miRNA species in (A) lymphomas, compared to normal thymus, is similar but varies over a wide range. Concentration is expressed as copies per 10 pg or input RNA. Of the 62 miRNA with expression levels&gt;250 copies/cell (B) the majority show increased expression in tumors. (Levels displayed as the fold change of copies per tumor cell relative to copies per normal thymocyte, on a log2 scale). All 5 miRNA from the miR-106a∼363 cluster (green) are increased in tumors. The dashed red line shows magnitude of baseline shift resulting from a mean 1.9-fold increase in total RNA in tumors vs. normal thymus. Every miRNA value below this line is reduced relative to the increased total RNA content of tumor cells. Nine miRNA altered in association with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotype are shown in a heatmap (C) reflecting the relative abundance of each miRNA across tumor samples. Heatmap of five miRNA (D) with changes associated with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> viral integration status. All 5 are increased and are members of the miR-106a∼363 cluster.</p>
            </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
         <title>miRNA associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null genotype and <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations</title>
         <p>Amongst tumor samples, we compared the global microRNA expression profiles associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotype (<italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null vs. wildtype), as well as the status of viral integrations at <italic>Xpcl1</italic> (positive or negative). Unsupervised hierarchical clustering based on abundance of individual miRNA (not shown) did not strictly segregate tumor samples either by <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotype or by <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration. This indicates that, for the majority of miRNA, neither of these factors are the major determinant of variability. Nonetheless, some of the most striking changes in miRNA expression in lymphomas included the microRNA encoded by the miR-106a-363 cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). Using a supervised analysis algorithm (PAM), we tested the hypothesis that viral integrations at <italic>Xpcl1</italic> are associated with expression of a distinct set of miRNA. The median false positive discovery rate (FDR) was zero at up to 5 microRNAs but rose sharply at higher numbers. This indicates that there are only 5 microRNAs (miR-363, miR-92-2, miR-20b, miR-19b, and miR-106a) influenced by viral integration at <italic>Xpcl1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g001">Figure 1D</xref>). Sequence of a sixth microRNA, miR-18b, also lies in the cluster but it was not increased in <italic>Xpcl1</italic>+ tumors relative to <italic>Xpc1</italic>- tumors. Thus, the increased miR-18 levels noted in tumors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g001">Figure 1B</xref>), may be due to expression from paralogous miR-17∼92 cluster. One potential mechanism of cooperation would be if <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> deletion increased <italic>Xpcl1</italic> expression, e.g. by increasing expression following retroviral gene insertions or by increasing the miRNA stability. Therefore, we asked whether homozygous deletion of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> was associated with altered miRNA expression in tumor samples. A supervised analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g001">Figure 1C</xref>) suggests that 9 microRNAs were associated with the <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null genotype, with considerable variability (FDR 30%). However, this list of miRNAs does not include those from the miR-106a∼363 cluster. Likewise, limiting the analysis to tumors without <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations, also does not identify miR-106a∼363 microRNA associated with the absence of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> (not shown). Thus, <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> deletion does not appear to augment miR-106a∼363 expression in lymphomas, but it may induce increases in other miRNAs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
         <title>Gene expression in M-MuLV induced tumors</title>
         <p>Because gene expression profiles have not been reported for M-MuLV induced lymphomas, we compared the general pattern of gene expression in tumors compared to normal thymic tissue. Our analysis normalized expression values within samples, as a function of both expression intensities, and 2-dimensional feature locations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Wang1">[27]</xref> A supervised analysis (PAM) was used to identify genes differentially expressed in tumors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g002">Figure 2</xref>) compared to normal thymus. In addition, tumors showed more heterogeneity of expression compared to normal tissue. In order to determine whether the pattern of expression seen in M-MuLV tumors was similar to other T-cell lymphomas we compared our data to that previously reported for T-cell lymphomas arising in mice with a ß-catenin mutation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Guo1">[28]</xref> We observed a high degree of correlation across the two data sets, which is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g002">Figure 2B</xref>, a plot of expression rankings. The correlation is readily apparent as an increased density of points in the right upper and left lower quadrants (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.45, p&lt;2×10<sup>−16</sup> Pearson correlation). In a gene ontology assessment, the biological function terms for DNA and protein metabolism and the cell division cycle, were enriched amongst genes with high levels of expression in tumors on either platform. In contrast, T-cell function and intracellular signaling terms were enriched in the genes with reduced expression in lymphomas (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s002">Table S2</xref>). We refer to this altered pattern of gene expression as the lymphoma expression phenotype.</p>
         <fig id="pone-0014758-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label>
            <caption>
               <title>Patterns of mRNA expression in M-MuLV induced lymphomas.</title>
               <p>A heatmap (A) of the mRNA expression in 22 samples, showing both lymphomas (right) compared to normal thymus (left). The top 5000 genes (in terms of statistical significance) that display altered expression in tumors compared to normal thymus are shown. Expression levels are relative to gene-specific means, and are displayed log2 scale of microarray spot intensities (green  =  decreased, red  =  increased). A strong association of gene expression (B) in M-MuLV-induced lymphomas and ß-catenin-induced lymphomas is seen in a plot of expression rankings. The 9804 genes with the highest levels of expression are shown color coded by plot density (left lower quadrant  =  reduced gene expression in tumors on both platforms, right upper quadrant  =  increased expression). An even distribution of points across all four quadrants would be expected if there is no association in tumor gene expression between the two tumor types. A heatmap of 250 genes (C) whose expression is most strongly associated with tumors containing <italic>Xpcl1</italic> viral integration (+) vs. tumors without <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration (−). Gene names are given for selected <italic>Xpcl1</italic> predicted target genes.</p>
            </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
         <title>Gene expression profiles of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null and <italic>Xpcl1</italic>+ tumors</title>
         <p>To determine whether expression of specific classes of genes is associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotype, we compared the microarray expression profiles of lymphomas from <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null animals to tumors from mice with one or two copies of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic>. We ranked genes according to their PAM score, then tested for enrichment of gene ontology terms for the top 10% of genes altered in <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null tumors, using the Panther gene classification system. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Thomas1">[29]</xref> In this analysis, statistical significance is a function of both the relative enrichment of classification terms and the size of the gene class, so we displayed results in circle plots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g003">Figure 3A–C</xref>) showing all three parameters. Interestingly, the classes of genes enriched in <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null tumors were similar to those enriched in tumors in general (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g003">Figure 3A,B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s002">Table S2</xref>), suggesting that the <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null tumors had a more pronounced lymphoma expression phenotype. In a separate analysis, we compared the patterns of gene expression in tumors with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations vs. tumors without <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations, using an identical approach. There was partial overlap between <italic>Xpcl1</italic> and <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotypes, with 5 out of 8 <italic>Xpcl1</italic>+ tumors lacking <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic>, and 4 out of 9 <italic>Xpcl1</italic>- tumors lacking <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic>. For this reason, a slight resemblance between the classes of genes associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> loss and <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration might be expected. To the contrary, the functional classes associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null tumors showed the opposite pattern of expression in <italic>Xpcl1</italic>+ tumors. For example, the cell cycle term was enriched amongst genes with increased expression in <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null tumors, but it was also enriched amongst genes decreased in <italic>Xpcl1+</italic> tumors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g003">Figure 3B,C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s002">Table S2</xref>). The opposite was true for genes in the Immunity and Defense category. These differences were largely due to changes in non-overlapping genes, as highlighted in the Venn diagram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g003">Figure 3D</xref>), which further suggests that this observation is not simply due to the overlapping sample groups. To confirm the accuracy of the array results we verified, by qPCR, the RNA levels of 14 genes associated with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations. There was a strong correlation (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.91, p = 5×10<sup>−6</sup>, Pearson correlation) between mean expression levels determined by the microarrays and the qPCR assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g004">Figure 4A</xref>).</p>
         <fig id="pone-0014758-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label>
            <caption>
               <title>Gene expression associated with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration and <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null genotype.</title>
               <p>Biological function classes of the top 2500 genes associated with M-MuLV tumors vs. normal thymus (A) are shown in a circle plot with statistical significance plotted on the Y-axis and relative enrichment (observed/expected) plotted on the X-axis. Genes showing increased expression are shown (red) to the right and those with decreased expression (green) are plotted left of the Y-axis (P-values, binomial test). Circle diameters are proportional to the number of genes observed in each group. Within tumor samples, the functional classification of genes associated with (B) <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null genotype or (C) <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations are shown. A Venn diagram (D) shows limited overlap amongst genes exhibiting decreased expression in association with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration (<italic>Xpcl1</italic> Low) and simultaneously showing increased expression in <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null tumors (KO High) (n = 30). Likewise, there is little overlap between the <italic>Xpcl1</italic> High vs. KO Low sets (n = 37).</p>
            </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
         <fig id="pone-0014758-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label>
            <caption>
               <title>Effect of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> on target gene expression.</title>
               <p>(A) Differences in mRNA expression was measured by qPCR (mean -ΔΔCt) for 17 genes and plotted as the mean difference in PCR cycle number of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> positive vs. <italic>Xpcl1</italic> negative tumors. This correlated with the changes in genes expression noted on microarrays (mean M, log2(tumor/normal)). Genes with varying levels of change in association with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration are shown, some of which are predicted targets of miR-106a∼363 (red) and others which are not (blue). Comparison of luciferase activity (B) in reporter constructs containing 3'UTR sequences of miR-106a∼363 predicted target genes: <italic>Nfat5</italic>, <italic>N-myc</italic>, and <italic>Grsf1</italic>. Each 3'UTR reporter construct was cotransfected with either pCIG-<italic>Xpcl1</italic> or empty pCIG vector. <italic>Xpcl1</italic> was also transfected with reporter constructs with mutations in the seed region of the predicted miRNA target site (Δ3'UTR). <italic>Xpcl1</italic> expression reduces luciferase expression associated with the 3'UTR of <italic>Tgfbr2</italic> (C), and results in reduced <italic>Tgfbr2</italic> mRNA levels as measured by qPCR. <italic>Xpcl1</italic> reduces downstream signaling in response to TGF-beta (right panel C) as measured by activity of the 3T3-Lux reporter construct. (Barplots are means ± SE).</p>
            </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.g004" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
         <title><italic>Xpcl1</italic> target gene expression</title>
         <p>To test the hypothesis that miRNA expression was associated with reduced expression of predicted target genes we analyzed expression of genes that are predicted targets of microRNAs overexpressed in tumors with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> locus integrations, and microRNAs associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotype. Within tumors, a number of miR-106a∼363 target genes displayed reduced expression in association with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration. Of 500 <italic>Xpcl1</italic> predicted targets decreased in tumors with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> viral integrations there was relative enrichment for the terms Oncogenesis, and Cell Cycle (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0014758-t001">Table 1</xref>). We cloned the 3'UTR of four predicted target genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g004">Figure 4B,C</xref>), which showed varying levels of reduced expression in tumors, into a luciferase reporter constructs. This included two genes (<italic>N-myc</italic> and <italic>Grsf1</italic>) that were reduced in association with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> viral integration, and two genes (<italic>Tgfbr2</italic> and <italic>Nfat5</italic>) that were not. In each case, cotransfection of a genomic fragment of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> reduced expression of the 3'UTR reporter constructs. Mutation of miRNA binding site seed regions in the 3'UTR eliminated the effect of miR-106a∼363 on the expression of <italic>Nfat5</italic> and <italic>N-myc</italic>, but did not restore <italic>Grsf1</italic> expression. In the case of <italic>Tgfbr2</italic>, miR-106a∼363 decreased the expression level of the endogenous <italic>Tgfbr2</italic> mRNA and decreased TGF-beta signaling as measured by the p3TP-Lux reporter construct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g004">Figure 4D</xref>). Still, the majority of miR-106a∼363 predicted targets did not show a significant reduction at the RNA level in tumors with viral integration at <italic>Xpcl1</italic> (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g004">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s003">Table S3</xref>).</p>
         <table-wrap id="pone-0014758-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
               <title>Biological Process of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> targets with reduced mRNA expression.</title>
            </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0014758-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
               <colgroup span="1">
                  <col align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
               </colgroup>
               <thead>
                  <tr>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Xpcl1</italic> Targets</td>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Observed</td>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Expected</td>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P-value</td>
                  </tr>
               </thead>
               <tbody>
                  <tr>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oncogenesis</td>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2E-02</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell cycle</td>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td>
                     <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2E-02</td>
                  </tr>
               </tbody>
            </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
               <fn id="nt101">
                  <label/>
                  <p>Panther gene classification terms for the biological function of miR-106a∼363 predicted target genes (n = 500) that show reduced expression in tumors with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> viral integrations, relative to the superset of genes present on the microarray. (P-values, binomial test).</p>
               </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>A principal aim of this study was to determine the pattern of miRNA and protein coding gene expression associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> deletion or <italic>Xpcl1</italic> activation in M-MuLV lymphomas. Our initial hypothesis was that the two events would be associated with the activation of genes with similar functions, or in activities complementary for tumor development. Despite the extensive use of retroviral mutagenesis in mouse models, neither miRNA nor gene expression profiles have been previously reported. Thus, we felt it was imperative to observe the general patterns of gene expression in M-MuLV induced tumors compared to normal tissue, and determine whether this profile is comparable to T-cell lymphomas induced by other mechanisms. We found a global reduction in the miRNA/ total RNA ratio in tumors compared to normal thymic tissue, which is analogous to what has been described in human cancer. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Lu1">[24]</xref> However, it has long been recognized that proliferating cells, in general, and cancer cells, in particular, express higher levels of total RNA. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Mellors1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-VonBertalanffy1">[31]</xref> We therefore quantified the total RNA abundance in our M-MuLV lymphoma specimens, and found that the apparent change in global miRNA levels was entirely attributable to the increased total cellular RNA in tumors. Thus, it should not be assumed that reduced miRNA levels are a general characteristic of tumors, if the data is not adjusted to cell number. Still, in terms of biological impact, a decrease in the ratio of miRNA/total RNA may have the same implications as a drop in absolute miRNA abundance. The stoichiometry of miRNA compared to the expression of their target genes is likely a key determinant of miRNA effectiveness. In contrast to the lack of change of global miRNA levels, the pattern of individual microRNA expression was highly distinctive in tumors. A large numbers of microRNA were significantly changed (both up and down) compared to normal thymus.</p>
      <p>We found that, of the 188 miRNA queried, the only miRNAs significantly altered in association with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> are members of the miR-106a∼363 cluster. This reinforces observations reported for the radiation leukemia virus and SL3-3, which were also shown to be associated with increased miR-106a∼363 miRNA expression. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Lum1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Landais2">[10]</xref> Not all of the miR-106a∼363 miRNA sequences are unique. However, the fact that we see overexpression of miR-363 (which is unique to this cluster) shows that the cluster is overexpressed. Mir-18, in contrast, is also encoded by the paralogous <italic>miR-17∼92</italic> cluster. We observed increased expression of miR-18 in lymphomas, compared to normal thymic tissue. However, there was no further increase in miR-18 levels in tumors with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations, so this likely represents expression from the <italic>miR-17∼92</italic> paralog. The broad array of miRNAs sampled here indicates the specificity of the effect of Xpc1 integration on miR-106a∼363, and argues against a general effect on miRNA expression. Deletion of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> did not independently increase the expression of miR-106a∼363, but instead may have influenced expression of a separate group of miRNAs. This argues against the hypothesis that p27Kip1 cooperates with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> simply by enhancing the expression of its constituent miRNAs.</p>
      <p>In the case of protein coding genes, we observed a massive shift in the pattern of gene expression in M-MuLV induced T-cell lymphomas compared to normal thymic tissue. These changes are impressive when considered either on absolute terms (RNA per cell) or on relative terms (when adjusted to RNA abundance). On absolute terms, the overall abundance of RNA in tumors was 1.9× higher than in normal thymic tissue. Typically, expression data is normalized in ways that sets median gene expression values to a set value or, as in our case, sets the log ratios (sample vs. reference) to zero. Based on our raw (pre-normalized) data, 94% of all Entrez genes show significant increases in expression in tumors compared to normal thymic tissue (data not shown). Although this figure conveys the magnitude of shift in global RNA expression in tumor cells, it belies the shift in the pattern of gene expression exhibited by the tumors. In contrast, when expression data is subjected to conventional normalization (disregarding differences in RNA content per cell) we see that many genes exhibit relative decreases as well as increases in expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). The functional classification of genes showing reduced expression in the lymphomas was frequently related to T-cell immunity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g003">Figure 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s002">Table S2</xref>). This is consistent with lymphomas developing a de-differentiated phenotype. Alternatively, it may reflect a reduced likelihood of up-regulating genes not essential to tumor development. Despite differences in array platforms, we observed a high level of similarity in gene expression in our M-MuLV lymphomas compared to that previously reported for lymphomas with a stabilizing mutation of ß-catenin. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Guo1">[28]</xref> In both cases, genes involved with RNA and protein metabolism were up-regulated; whereas genes involved with immunity showed relatively reduced expression. We conclude that the massive alteration in gene expression in M-MuLV induced tumors is a common feature of murine T-cell lymphomas and is not a peculiarity of M-MuLV tumor induction.</p>
      <p>In comparison to other tumors, gene expression in <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null tumors showed further reduction in expression of genes involved with T-cell function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Thus, <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> loss was associated with both shortened survival and a further deviation from the normal T-cell expression phenotype. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Hwang1">[5]</xref> Interestingly, genes associated with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> retroviral integration showed the opposite pattern of expression, even though <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration frequently occurred in <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null animals. Our finding of a contrasting pattern of expression associated with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> genotype compared to <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotype does not support the hypothesis that loss of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> simply enhances <italic>Xpcl1</italic>'s expression phenotype. Because of sample number limitations, our assessment did not include a pair-wise comparison of all four subsets of tumor samples based on <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> and <italic>Xpcl1</italic> genotypes. Such an approach might better elucidate the extent to which coincident mutation of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> modifies gene expression changes by <italic>Xpcl1</italic>. Still, our data suggests that deletion of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> counters an anti-oncogenic pattern of gene expression induced by <italic>Xpcl1,</italic> rather than enhancing an oncogenic effect.</p>
      <p>According to the PicTar database 3,269 Entrez genes are predicted targets of at least one of the miR-106a∼363 miRNAs. Considering the large number of predicted targets, it is expected that miR-106a∼363 expression would induce a combination of oncogenic and anti-oncogenic effects. Others have demonstrated cellular activities by miR-106a∼363 (and its paralogous miRNA clusters) that are potentially pro-oncogenic. This includes the demonstration that anchorage independent growth is enhanced by miR-106a∼363 as well as direct targeting of <italic>Mylip</italic> and <italic>Rbp1-like</italic> gene expression. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Landais2">[10]</xref> Likewise, miR-106a∼363 and its paralogs have been shown to promote proliferation of cultured cells by targeting p21<sup>Cip1/Waf1</sup> and p63. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Ivanovska1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Manni1">[33]</xref> Thus it is somewhat surprising that our gene expression observations suggest that, in terms of its interaction with <italic>Xpcl1</italic>, the effect of <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> loss is to overcome an anti-tumor activity of <italic>Xpcl1</italic>, as opposed to enhancing <italic>Xpcl1</italic>'s oncogenic effect.</p>
      <p>In regards to the expression of miRNA target genes, we saw a high frequency of reduced gene expression (52%) amongst genes that are predicted targets of miR-106a∼363. However, we also observed a high frequency of reduced expression amongst miRNA target genes in general, regardless of the expression levels of their predicted effecter microRNAs. Thus, global reduction in miRNA target gene expression appears to be an incidental aspect of the tumor phenotype, although it might also result from secondary effects of a few overexpressed microRNAs. Two predicted targets of miR-106a∼363 miRNA are <italic>N-myc</italic> and <italic>Grsf1</italic>, both of which were decreased in <italic>Xpcl1</italic> positive vs. <italic>Xpcl1</italic> negative tumors. M-MuLV integrations were present at the <italic>N-Myc</italic> locus in 3 of the <italic>Xpcl1</italic> negative tumors that we assayed (not shown). This may partially explain the reduced levels of <italic>N-Myc</italic> that we observed in <italic>Xpcl1</italic> positive tumors. Additionally, forced expression of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> in cultured T-cells reduced expression of an <italic>N-Myc</italic> 3'UTR reporter construct. This effect by <italic>Xpcl1</italic> was eliminated by mutation of the predicted miRNA target site in the <italic>N-Myc</italic> 3'UTR, which indicates that the miRNAs directly target <italic>N-Myc</italic>. Reduced <italic>N-Myc</italic> expression would be expected to have an anti-proliferative effect, in part because <italic>N-Myc</italic> activates transcription of the Skp2 ubiquitin ligase, which in turn degrades <italic>p27Kip1</italic> protein. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Carrano1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Muth1">[35]</xref> Thus, the targeting of <italic>N-Myc</italic> by <italic>Xpcl1</italic> is one example of an anti-oncogenic effect that may be overcome by <italic>p27Kip1</italic> deletion.</p>
      <p>Not all of the predicted targets of miR-106a∼363 were consistently reduced in tumors with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integrations. For example, <italic>Tgfbr2</italic>, the TGF-ß cell surface receptor, is a predicted target of both miR-19b and miR-106a, but was not significantly changed in tumors with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration. Nonetheless, luciferase reporter assays indicate that the 3'UTR of <italic>Tgfbr2</italic> does confer sensitivity to <italic>Xpcl1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Likewise forced expression of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> in cultured cells reduced both <italic>Tgfbr2</italic> mRNA levels and reduced signaling downstream of TGF-ß. To an extent, the discrepancy between tumor RNA expression and the reporter assay data may reflect the ability of the luciferase assay to detect the combined effect of miRNA on both mRNA stability and protein translation. However, endogenous gene expression is also subject to secondary effects and compensatory changes, which might easily overwhelm the comparatively subtle impact of miRNA. Finally, the existence of cell-type or gene-specific modifiers of miRNA function remains a possibility; so cultured T-cells may not accurately reflect the situation in tumors. Our list of miR-106a∼363 predicted target genes, exhibiting reduced expression in association with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration, shortens the set of genes likely to mediate the effect of miR-106a∼363 on the tumor phenotype. The confirmation of the oncogenic potential of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> and the elucidation of its pathogenic mechanism would further benefit from the <italic>in vivo</italic> manipulation of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> expression in the absence of other M-MuLV integrations. Given the complexity of gene expression in tumors, and the subtle yet widespread effects of miRNA expression, overexpression of <italic>Xpcl1</italic> in primary cells will likewise be important for the confirmation of physiologically relevant miR-106a∼363 targets.</p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
         <title>Sample preparation and microRNA quantification</title>
         <p>This work involved frozen tumor samples previously taken from <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> knockout mice (p27−/−, p27+/−, and p27+/+) induced by neonatal Maloney Murine Leukemia Virus (M-MuLV) infection. These tumors were previously surveyed for the genomic integration sites of M-MuLV proviruses and are thus characterized with respect to the presence or absence of M-MuLV integrations at the <italic>Xpcl1</italic> locus (<italic>Xpcl1</italic> positive), and Myc family members. For this work tumor tissue was characterized as being p27null (−/−) vs. not null (+/− or +/+) and with respect to M-MuLV integration at the <italic>Xpcl1</italic> locus (positive or negative). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Hwang1">[5]</xref> The prior animal work was conducted according to national guidelines (OLAW) and approved by the IACUC of the Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center. Animals had been observed daily and were euthanized if they developed signs of morbidity, palpable tumors greater than 1 cm. diameter, or age &gt;1 year. These tumors were previously characterized for the presence of M-MuLV integrations at the <italic>Xpcl1</italic> locus. All animals were humanely euthanized with CO<sub>2</sub> or anesthetic inhalation. Frozen whole thymus from uninfected animals (on the same 129S4 × C57BL/6J F1 hybrid strain background) was used for comparisons. Tissues were divided, weighed and then extracted for either DNA or total RNA. RNA was prepared with Trizol (Invitrogen) using 1.5 volumes of isopropanol to increase the efficiency of miRNA precipitation. RNA and DNA were quantified using Ribogreen (Invitrogen) fluorescence. Expression of individual miRNAs were determined using a quantitative primer-extension PCR assay (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s001">Table S1</xref>), as previously described. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Raymond1">[36]</xref> Ct values were converted to copy numbers by interpolation on standard curves generated using single stranded mature miRNAs to calculate miRNA copies per 10 pg of input RNA, and are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s001">Table S1</xref>. The total RNA to DNA ratios of each tumor sample was determined by purifying total RNA and genomic DNA from weighed samples (&lt;5 mg) under non-saturating conditions on nucleic acid biding columns (RNeasy and DNeasy, QIAgen). Standard curves with 2-fold dilutions (0.625–10 mg) of starting material demonstrated a high degree of linearity with respect to the mass of starting material (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.985 for RNA, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.984 for DNA). The <italic>pamr</italic> software package for R (R-project.org, BioConductor.org) was used to identify miRNA associated with <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration (<italic>Xpcl1</italic>+ vs. <italic>Xpcl1</italic>−) and <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotype (null vs. +/− or +/+). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Tibshirani1">[37]</xref> The top miRNAs associated with <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotype and <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration are shown in heatmaps where quantities of individual miRNAs are displayed relative to the mean expression value of the same miRNAs across all samples. Hierarchical clustering was used to group samples post hoc using Cluster 3.0 software with Euclidean distance and complete linkage.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
         <title>Microarray analysis</title>
         <p>Trizol prepped total RNA was additionally treated with DNAseI (RNAse free, Roche) and purified with RNeasy mini columns (Qiagen). RNA was amplified and labeled with Cy5 and Cy3 as previously described. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Jackson1">[25]</xref> Labeled RNA pooled from 17 tumor samples and 3 normal thymuses formed a common reference and were co-hybridized vs. sample RNA in a two color format on duplicate custom murine oligonucleotide arrays (Agilent, GEO accession GPL8525) (n = 40 arrays. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s005">Table S5</xref> for complete sample descriptions). The genotypes of the tumor samples were balanced with roughly half of the samples (n = 9) being <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null, and half of the samples containing <italic>Xpcl1</italic> viral integrations (n = 8), 4 of which were both <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> null and <italic>Xpcl1</italic>+. (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s005">5</xref> for detailed sample descriptions). Log(2) ratios of fluorescence intensities (experimental sample vs. pooled reference) were normalized by intensity-dependent Loess followed by 2-dimensional location-dependent loess using the <italic>marray</italic> Bioconductor package without local background subtraction or scaling. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Wang1">[27]</xref> Missing (software flagged features) values were imputed by the K-nearest neighbor method, and genes associated with tumors vs. normal were determined with the PAM algorithm, using the <italic>pamr</italic> Bioconductor package. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Troyanskaya1">[38]</xref> We compared relative gene expression of tumors vs. normal, ranked by PAM-scores, to similarly processed raw data for ß-catenin induced tumors obtained from the GEO repository. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Guo1">[28]</xref> Both studies included normal thymus so we used this as a common reference. Platform specific bias was avoided by comparing ranks of expression data (expressed as log tumor/normal) and calculating the geometric means across multiple samples. This approach is equivalent to the Rank Product (RP) method, which was shown to be robust for comparing gene expression profiles. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Breitling1">[39]</xref> Likewise, we analyzed our M-MuLV tumor data for genes associated with either <italic>Xpcl1</italic> integration or <italic>p27<sup>Kip1</sup></italic> genotype (PAM-scores listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s003">Table S3</xref>). Data processing was streamlined with custom wrapper functions contained in the <italic>ArrayFun</italic> package (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://labs.fhcrc.org/fero/R/ArrayFun.html" xlink:type="simple">http://labs.fhcrc.org/fero/R/ArrayFun.html</ext-link>). This package includes functions, (<italic>array.getGEO, array.readGEO),</italic> that downloads data from these 40 microarrays, along with the sample description table, from the GEO FTP site directly into R. Both MIAME compliant raw and normalized data are available at the GEO data repository (accession GSE16005). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Edgar1">[40]</xref> An R script that outlines for obtaining raw data and recapitulates the data processing steps is included as a supporting data file (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s006">Table S6</xref>). We used the “compare gene list” tool of the Panther Classification System (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pantherdb.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pantherdb.org</ext-link>) In order to determine the enrichment of biological function terms in genes of interest. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Thomas1">[29]</xref> We input the top 2500 Entrez Gene IDs (ranked by PAM scores, above) and compared this to the entire set genes on the arrays. Terms over-represented in the genes of interest (p-values≤0.05, binomial test) are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014758-g003">Figure 3</xref> and are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s002">Table S2</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
         <title>MicroRNA target validation</title>
         <p>129S4 mouse genomic <italic>Xpcl1</italic> DNA was isolated from a phage library. A 1.5 kB fragment containing the entire miR-106a∼363 miRNA cluster was subcloned into pCIG (courtesy of Andy McMahon) with the chicken B-actin promoter, the pSM30 vector (courtesy of Muneesh Tewari) and the p1026x vector with the Lck promoter (courtesy of Brian Iritani). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Iritani1">[41]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Wu1">[43]</xref> Genomic 3'UTR DNA segments for putative target genes (<italic>N-Myc</italic>, <italic>Tgfbr2</italic>, <italic>Grsf1</italic>, and <italic>Nfat5</italic>) were PCR amplified from mouse 129S4 genomic DNA, cloned into pGL3-control (Promega), a luciferase reporter with the SV40 promoter, and verified by sequencing. Three or four bases of miRNA seed sequence, in the UTR of predicted target genes, were mutated using the QuickChange Mutagenesis Kit (Agilent, #210513) with oligonucleotides, listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014758.s004">Table S4</xref>. Wildtype and mutant 3'UTR reporter constructs were co-transfected (in triplicate) with pSM30-<italic>Xpcl1</italic> vs. empty vector and pRL-TK (Promega, renilla control) into 293T cells using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). <italic>Tgfbr2</italic> 3'UTR luciferase assays compared pCIG-Xpcl1 vs. empty vector. Luciferase activity was assayed at 48 hr. and adjusted by renilla activity. To quantify the effect on <italic>Tgfbr2</italic> mRNA expression and TGF-beta signaling, murine SV40-180 T-cells were transfected by electroporation with either p1026x–Xpcl1 or empty vector. RNA was isolated at 48 h and <italic>Tgfbr2</italic> qPCR was done, as described above. To measure TGF-beta signaling the p3TP-Lux reporter of TGF-beta signaling (courtesy of William Grady) was additionally transfected. The cells were treated with porcine TGF-beta 1 (5 ng/mL, R&amp;D Systems) starting at 24 hrs. post-transfection and luciferase activity was assayed at 48 h. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014758-Wrana1">[44]</xref> The transfection of each construct and its controls were performed in triplicate or quadruplicate.</p>
      </sec>
   </sec>
   <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0014758.s001" mimetype="application/x-excel" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>Table S1</label>
<caption><p>MicroRNA copy number per 10 pg input RNA.</p>
      <p>(0.07 MB XLS)</p></caption></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0014758.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>Table S2</label>
<caption><p>Biological Process of genes with altered expression in tumors.</p>
      <p>(0.10 MB PDF)</p></caption></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0014758.s003" mimetype="application/x-excel" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.s003" xlink:type="simple">
<label>Table S3</label>
<caption><p>Expression array Gene IDs and PAM significance scores.</p>
      <p>(0.96 MB XLS)</p></caption></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0014758.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.s004" xlink:type="simple">
<label>Table S4</label>
<caption><p>Oligonucleotide sequences used for mutagenesis of the 3'UTR of miR- 106a∼363 target genes.</p>
      <p>(0.07 MB PDF)</p></caption></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0014758.s005" mimetype="application/x-excel" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.s005" xlink:type="simple">
<label>Table S5</label>
<caption><p>Descriptions of RNA samples used for expression arrays.</p>
      <p>(0.02 MB XLS)</p></caption></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0014758.s006" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0014758.s006" xlink:type="simple">
<label>Table S6</label>
<caption><p>Instructions and R code for acquisition and analysis of expression array data.</p>
      <p>(0.00 MB TXT)</p></caption></supplementary-material>
   </sec>
</body>
<back>
   <ack>
      <p>We thank Jane Guo for assistance with sample preparation and Yanqun Wang at Merck, Inc. for assistance with raw data acquisition. We also thank William Grady and Muneesh Tewari for reporter plasmids.</p>
   </ack>
   <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Fero1">
         <label>1</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Fero</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Randel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Gurley</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>1998</year>
            <article-title>The murine gene p27Kip1 is haplo-insufficient for tumour suppression.</article-title>
            <source>Nature</source>
            <volume>396</volume>
            <fpage>177</fpage>
            <lpage>180</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Gao1">
         <label>2</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Banach-Petrosky</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Borowsky</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>A critical role for p27kip1 gene dosage in a mouse model of prostate carcinogenesis.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
            <volume>101</volume>
            <fpage>17204</fpage>
            <lpage>17209</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-DiCristofano1">
         <label>3</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Cristofano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>De Acetis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Koff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Cordon-Cardo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2001</year>
            <article-title>Pten and p27KIP1 cooperate in prostate cancer tumor suppression in the mouse.</article-title>
            <source>Nat Genet</source>
            <volume>27</volume>
            <fpage>222</fpage>
            <lpage>224</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Petrocelli1">
         <label>4</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Petrocelli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Slingerland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2001</year>
            <article-title>PTEN deficiency: a role in mammary carcinogenesis.</article-title>
            <source>Breast Cancer Res</source>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <fpage>356</fpage>
            <lpage>360</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Hwang1">
         <label>5</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Bronkhorst</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Randel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Berns</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>Identification of oncogenes collaborating with p27Kip1 loss by insertional mutagenesis and high-throughput insertion site analysis.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
            <volume>99</volume>
            <fpage>11293</fpage>
            <lpage>11298</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-GarrettEngele1">
         <label>6</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Garrett-Engele</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Tasch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Fero</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Perlmutter</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>A mechanism misregulating p27 in tumors discovered in a functional genomic screen.</article-title>
            <source>PLoS Genet</source>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <fpage>e219</fpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Landais1">
         <label>7</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Landais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Quantin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Rassart</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>Radiation leukemia virus common integration at the Kis2 locus: simultaneous overexpression of a novel noncoding RNA and of the proximal Phf6 gene.</article-title>
            <source>J Virol</source>
            <volume>79</volume>
            <fpage>11443</fpage>
            <lpage>11456</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Lum1">
         <label>8</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Lum</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Channa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartha</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Wabl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Retroviral activation of the mir-106a microRNA cistron in T lymphoma.</article-title>
            <source>Retrovirology</source>
            <volume>4</volume>
            <fpage>5</fpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Tanzer1">
         <label>9</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanzer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>Molecular evolution of a microRNA cluster.</article-title>
            <source>J Mol Biol</source>
            <volume>339</volume>
            <fpage>327</fpage>
            <lpage>335</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Landais2">
         <label>10</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Landais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Legault</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Rassart</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Oncogenic potential of the miR-106-363 cluster and its implication in human T-cell leukemia.</article-title>
            <source>Cancer Res</source>
            <volume>67</volume>
            <fpage>5699</fpage>
            <lpage>5707</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Uren1">
         <label>11</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Uren</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Kool</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Matentzoglu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattison</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Large-scale mutagenesis in p19(ARF)- and p53-deficient mice identifies cancer genes and their collaborative networks.</article-title>
            <source>Cell</source>
            <volume>133</volume>
            <fpage>727</fpage>
            <lpage>741</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Shivdasani1">
         <label>12</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Shivdasani</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2006</year>
            <article-title>MicroRNAs: regulators of gene expression and cell differentiation.</article-title>
            <source>Blood</source>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Ambros1">
         <label>13</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambros</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>The functions of animal microRNAs.</article-title>
            <source>Nature</source>
            <volume>431</volume>
            <fpage>350</fpage>
            <lpage>355</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-GriffithsJones1">
         <label>14</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>van Dongen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Enright</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>miRBase: tools for microRNA genomics.</article-title>
            <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
            <volume>36</volume>
            <fpage>D154</fpage>
            <lpage>D158</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Carthew1">
         <label>15</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Carthew</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Sontheimer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>Origins and Mechanisms of miRNAs and siRNAs.</article-title>
            <source>Cell</source>
            <volume>136</volume>
            <fpage>642</fpage>
            <lpage>655</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Clurman1">
         <label>16</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Clurman</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>1989</year>
            <article-title>Multiple proto-oncogene activations in avian leukosis virus-induced lymphomas: evidence for stage-specific events.</article-title>
            <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
            <volume>9</volume>
            <fpage>2657</fpage>
            <lpage>2664</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Tam1">
         <label>17</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Yehuda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>1997</year>
            <article-title>bic, a novel gene activated by proviral insertions in avian leukosis virus-induced lymphomas, is likely to function through its noncoding RNA.</article-title>
            <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
            <volume>17</volume>
            <fpage>1490</fpage>
            <lpage>1502</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Costinean1">
         <label>18</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Costinean</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Zanesi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Pekarsky</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Tili</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Volinia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2006</year>
            <article-title>Pre-B cell proliferation and lymphoblastic leukemia/high-grade lymphoma in E(mu)-miR155 transgenic mice.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
            <volume>103</volume>
            <fpage>7024</fpage>
            <lpage>7029</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Eis1">
         <label>19</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Eis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Chadburn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>Accumulation of miR-155 and BIC RNA in human B cell lymphomas.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
            <volume>102</volume>
            <fpage>3627</fpage>
            <lpage>3632</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Kluiver1">
         <label>20</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Kluiver</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Poppema</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Blokzijl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>BIC and miR-155 are highly expressed in Hodgkin, primary mediastinal and diffuse large B cell lymphomas.</article-title>
            <source>J Pathol</source>
            <volume>207</volume>
            <fpage>243</fpage>
            <lpage>249</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Mu1">
         <label>21</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Betel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Squatrito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>Genetic dissection of the miR-17∼92 cluster of microRNAs in Myc-induced B-cell lymphomas.</article-title>
            <source>Genes Dev</source>
            <volume>23</volume>
            <fpage>2806</fpage>
            <lpage>2811</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-He1">
         <label>22</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hemann</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hernando-Monge</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>A microRNA polycistron as a potential human oncogene.</article-title>
            <source>Nature</source>
            <volume>435</volume>
            <fpage>828</fpage>
            <lpage>833</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Kumar1">
         <label>23</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Impaired microRNA processing enhances cellular transformation and tumorigenesis.</article-title>
            <source>Nat Genet</source>
            <volume>39</volume>
            <fpage>673</fpage>
            <lpage>677</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Lu1">
         <label>24</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Miska</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez-Saavedra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>MicroRNA expression profiles classify human cancers.</article-title>
            <source>Nature</source>
            <volume>435</volume>
            <fpage>834</fpage>
            <lpage>838</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Jackson1">
         <label>25</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartz</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Schelter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Burchard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2003</year>
            <article-title>Expression profiling reveals off-target gene regulation by RNAi.</article-title>
            <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
            <volume>21</volume>
            <fpage>635</fpage>
            <lpage>637</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Vasmel1">
         <label>26</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Vasmel</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Gillis</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>1989</year>
            <article-title>Distinct chromosomal abnormalities in murine leukemia virus-induced T- and B-cell lymphomas.</article-title>
            <source>Int J Cancer</source>
            <volume>43</volume>
            <fpage>1112</fpage>
            <lpage>1119</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Wang1">
         <label>27</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Nygaard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith-Sorensen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hovig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Myklebost</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>MArray: analysing single, replicated or reversed microarray experiments.</article-title>
            <source>Bioinformatics</source>
            <volume>18</volume>
            <fpage>1139</fpage>
            <lpage>1140</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Guo1">
         <label>28</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Dose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Kovalovsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Beta-catenin stabilization stalls the transition from double-positive to single-positive stage and predisposes thymocytes to malignant transformation.</article-title>
            <source>Blood</source>
            <volume>109</volume>
            <fpage>5463</fpage>
            <lpage>5472</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Thomas1">
         <label>29</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Kejariwal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Karlak</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2003</year>
            <article-title>PANTHER: a library of protein families and subfamilies indexed by function.</article-title>
            <source>Genome Res</source>
            <volume>13</volume>
            <fpage>2129</fpage>
            <lpage>2141</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Mellors1">
         <label>30</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Mellors</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>1956</year>
            <article-title>Quantitative cytology and cytopathology: nucleic acids and proteins in the mitotic cycle of normal and neoplastic cells.</article-title>
            <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
            <volume>63</volume>
            <fpage>1177</fpage>
            <lpage>1201</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-VonBertalanffy1">
         <label>31</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Von Bertalanffy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Masin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Masin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>1957</year>
            <article-title>Detection of gynecological cancer; use of fluorescence microscopy to show nucleic acids in malignant growth.</article-title>
            <source>Calif Med</source>
            <volume>87</volume>
            <fpage>248</fpage>
            <lpage>251</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Ivanovska1">
         <label>32</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanovska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Magnus</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Kibukawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>MicroRNAs in the miR-106b family regulate p21/CDKN1A and promote cell cycle progression.</article-title>
            <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
            <volume>28</volume>
            <fpage>2167</fpage>
            <lpage>2174</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Manni1">
         <label>33</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Manni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Artuso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Careccia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Baserga</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>The microRNA miR-92 increases proliferation of myeloid cells and by targeting p63 modulates the abundance of its isoforms.</article-title>
            <source>FASEB J</source>
            <volume>23</volume>
            <fpage>3957</fpage>
            <lpage>3966</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Carrano1">
         <label>34</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Carrano</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Eytan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hershko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>1999</year>
            <article-title>SKP2 is required for ubiquitin-mediated degradation of the CDK inhibitor p27.</article-title>
            <source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
            <volume>1</volume>
            <fpage>193</fpage>
            <lpage>199</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Muth1">
         <label>35</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Muth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghazaryan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Eckerle</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Pöhler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2010</year>
            <article-title>Transcriptional repression of SKP2 is impaired in MYCN-amplified neuroblastoma.</article-title>
            <source>Cancer Res</source>
            <volume>70</volume>
            <fpage>3791</fpage>
            <lpage>3802</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Raymond1">
         <label>36</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Garrett-Engele</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>Simple, quantitative primer-extension PCR assay for direct monitoring of microRNAs and short-interfering RNAs.</article-title>
            <source>RNA</source>
            <volume>11</volume>
            <fpage>1737</fpage>
            <lpage>1744</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Tibshirani1">
         <label>37</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>Diagnosis of multiple cancer types by shrunken centroids of gene expression.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
            <volume>99</volume>
            <fpage>6567</fpage>
            <lpage>6572</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Troyanskaya1">
         <label>38</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Troyanskaya</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>2001</year>
            <article-title>Missing value estimation methods for DNA microarrays.</article-title>
            <source>Bioinformatics</source>
            <volume>17</volume>
            <fpage>520</fpage>
            <lpage>525</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Breitling1">
         <label>39</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Breitling</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Armengaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Amtmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Herzyk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>Rank products: a simple, yet powerful, new method to detect differentially regulated genes in replicated microarray experiments.</article-title>
            <source>FEBS Lett</source>
            <volume>573</volume>
            <fpage>83</fpage>
            <lpage>92</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Edgar1">
         <label>40</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Domrachev</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>Gene Expression Omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository.</article-title>
            <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
            <volume>30</volume>
            <fpage>207</fpage>
            <lpage>210</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Iritani1">
         <label>41</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Iritani</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Forbush</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Perlmutter</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>1997</year>
            <article-title>Control of B cell development by Ras-mediated activation of Raf.</article-title>
            <source>EMBO J</source>
            <volume>16</volume>
            <fpage>7019</fpage>
            <lpage>7031</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Megason1">
         <label>42</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Megason</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>A mitogen gradient of dorsal midline Wnts organizes growth in the CNS.</article-title>
            <source>Development</source>
            <volume>129</volume>
            <fpage>2087</fpage>
            <lpage>2098</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Wu1">
         <label>43</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonsra</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
            </person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>pSM155 and pSM30 vectors for miRNA and shRNA expression.</article-title>
            <source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source>
            <publisher-loc>United States</publisher-loc>
            <publisher-name>Springer Verlag</publisher-name>
            <fpage>205</fpage>
            <lpage>219</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0014758-Wrana1">
         <label>44</label>
         <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Wrana</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Attisano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Cárcamo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Zentella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
               <name name-style="western"><surname>Doody</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
               <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <year>1992</year>
            <article-title>TGF beta signals through a heteromeric protein kinase receptor complex.</article-title>
            <source>Cell</source>
            <volume>71</volume>
            <fpage>1003</fpage>
            <lpage>1014</lpage>
         </element-citation>
      </ref>
   </ref-list>
   
</back></article>