<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0178020</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-16-50802</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care providers</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical doctors</subject><subj-group><subject>Physicians</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Professions</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical doctors</subject><subj-group><subject>Physicians</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical locations</subject><subj-group><subject>Asia</subject><subj-group><subject>Japan</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care facilities</subject><subj-group><subject>Hospitals</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physics</subject><subj-group><subject>Nuclear physics</subject><subj-group><subject>Nuclear power</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research design</subject><subj-group><subject>Survey research</subject><subj-group><subject>Census</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Demography</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject><subj-group><subject>Dosimetry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physics</subject><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject><subj-group><subject>Dosimetry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Political geography</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Political science</subject><subj-group><subject>Political geography</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Have the tsunami and nuclear accident following the Great East Japan Earthquake affected the local distribution of hospital physicians?</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Physician outflow following a nuclear accident</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3401-8191</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kashima</surname>
<given-names>Saori</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>Kazuo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Matsumoto</surname>
<given-names>Masatoshi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Public Health and Health Policy, Graduate School of Biomedical and Health Sciences, Hiroshima University, Hiroshima, Japan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Department of Community Medicine, Chiba Medical Center, Teikyo University School of Medicine, Chiba, Japan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Community-Based Medical System, Graduate School of Biomedical and Health Sciences, Hiroshima University, Hiroshima, Japan</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Doi</surname>
<given-names>Hideyuki</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Hyogo, JAPAN</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p><list list-type="simple"> <list-item>
<p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> SK KI MM.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Data curation:</bold> SK KI.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> SK.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> KI.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Investigation:</bold> SK KI.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Methodology:</bold> SK KI.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Project administration:</bold> KI.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Resources:</bold> SK KI.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Software:</bold> SK.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Supervision:</bold> KI.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Validation:</bold> SK KI MM.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Visualization:</bold> SK.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> SK KI MM.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> SK KI MM.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">saori.ksm@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>25</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e0178020</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>23</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>7</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Kashima et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0178020"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Objective</title>
<p>The Great East Japan Earthquake occurred on 11 March 2011 near the northeast coast of the main island, ‘Honshu’, of Japan. It wreaked enormous damage in two main ways: a giant tsunami and an accident at the Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear Power Plant (FDNPP). This disaster may have affected the distribution of physicians in the region. Here, we evaluate the effect of the disaster on the distribution of hospital physicians in the three most severely affected prefectures (Iwate, Miyagi, and Fukushima).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>We obtained individual information about physicians from the Physician Census in 2010 (pre-disaster) and 2012 (post-disaster). We examined geographical distributions of physicians in two ways: (1) municipality-based analysis for demographic evaluation; and (2) hospital-based analysis for geographic evaluation. In each analysis, we calculated the rate of change in physician distributions between pre- and post-disaster years at various distances from the tsunami-affected coast, and from the restricted area due to the FDNPP accident.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The change in all, hospital, and clinic physicians were 0.2%, 0.7%, and −0.7%, respectively. In the municipality-based analysis, after taking account of the decreased population, physician numbers only decreased within the restricted area. In the hospital-based analysis, hospital physician numbers did not decrease at any distance from the tsunami-affected coast. In contrast, there was a 3.3% and 2.3% decrease in hospital physicians 0–25 km and 25–50 km from the restricted area surrounding the FDNPP, respectively. Additionally, decreases were larger and increases were smaller in areas close to the FDNPP than in areas further away.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Our results suggest that the tsunami did not affect the distribution of physicians in the affected regions. However, the FDNPP accident changed physician distribution in areas close to the power plant.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="award001">
<funding-source>
<institution-wrap>
<institution-id institution-id-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001691</institution-id>
<institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
<award-id>JP25516015</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>Kazuo</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<funding-statement>This research was supported by Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) KAKENHI Grant Number JP25516015 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jsps.go.jp/english/e-grants/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.jsps.go.jp/english/e-grants/index.html</ext-link>). The founder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="3"/>
<table-count count="3"/>
<page-count count="14"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data in this study are described in the manuscript. Data of Physician Census and Static Survey of Medical Institutions are available from the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare for researchers who meet their study purpose and the criteria for access to confidential data. The contact information is in the website of the Ministry (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei/sonota/chousahyo.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei/sonota/chousahyo.html</ext-link>).</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>On 11 March 2011, an extremely strong earthquake, recorded as 9.0 on the Richter scale, occurred offshore of the northeast Pacific coast, ‘Sanriku’, of the main island, ‘Honshu’, of Japan. This earthquake, referred to as the Great East Japan Earthquake, triggered a giant tsunami, which was 9.3 meters at its highest and caused catastrophic damage to the Tohoku region in northeast Japan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref001">1</xref>]. According to the report by the National Police Agency of Japan as of 9 December 2016, there had been 15,893 reported deaths in 12 prefectures and 2,556 missing persons in 6 prefectures attributed to the disaster [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref002">2</xref>]. Additionally, this disaster created one of the worst radiation leakage accidents, which was rated as the 7th (maximum) caution level on the International Nuclear Events Scale because of the high level of radioactive substances released from the Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear Power Plant (FDNPP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref003">3</xref>]. According to the report by the United Nations Scientific Committee on the Effects of Atomic Radiation (UNSCARE), iodine-131 and caesium-137, two major hazardous radionuclides, were released into the atmosphere in the ranges of 100 to 500 petabecquerels (PBq) and 6 to 20 PBq, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref004">4</xref>]. Such a massive and complex disaster inevitably has negative impacts on people’s health and daily life.</p>
<p>Long-term shortages of healthcare resources, as well as regional economic downturn or industry decline, are predictable following such events. Although physicians and medical staff will play an important role in reconstructing local health services in the area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref005">5</xref>], it is likely that securing adequate numbers of healthcare professionals may be difficult after such a large disaster. Furthermore, many of the areas affected by the earthquake were medically underserved even before the disaster because they are rural regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref007">7</xref>]. After the earthquake, according to the Japanese media, the situation was reportedly exacerbated, particularly in areas near the FDNPP, because of damage to infrastructure and radioactive contamination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref008">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref010">10</xref>]. Indeed, one recent study reported changes in the geographic distribution of secondary care nursing staff following the Great East Japan Earthquake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref011">11</xref>]. In addition, in our previous study, we evaluated physician’s characteristics susceptible to migration from the areas surrounding the nuclear power plant, and we found that less-aged physicians in the areas were more likely to decrease than other physicians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref012">12</xref>]. However, we have not studied the overall flow of physicians before and after the disaster. Particularly there is a lack of knowledge about the physicians' migration pattern not only from the areas of nuclear accident, but also from the tsunami-affected areas.</p>
<p>Therefore, we evaluated the effects of the Great East Japan Earthquake on the distribution of physicians within the most severely affected prefectures (Iwate, Miyagi, and Fukushima). Two major factors in this disaster may potentially impact physician distribution: the tsunami and the FDNPP accident. We analyzed changes in the number of hospital physicians at varying distances from the tsunami-affected area and from the FDNPP. Furthermore, we conducted an analysis based on two geographical units: municipality-based for demographic evaluation and hospital-based for geographic evaluation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Study area</title>
<p>We selected three prefectures (Iwate, Miyagi, and Fukushima) that were severely damaged by the Great East Japan Earthquake. Within the study area, the number of people killed was 15,826 (99.6% of the total killed), the number of people missing was 2,552 (99.8% of the total missing), and the number of people injured was 4,541 (73.8% of the total injured) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref002">2</xref>]. Miyagi Prefecture was the most severely affected (killed: 9,540; missing: 1,232; injured: 4,145), followed by Iwate (killed: 4,673; missing: 1,123; injured: 213), and Fukushima (killed: 1,613; missing 197; injured: 183). The number of casualties as a result of the tsunami was greater than 14,100 people (92.4% of deaths caused by the Great East Japan Earthquake), but no one was killed by direct effect of radiation. More than 80,000 people were forced to evacuate the region by an order from the government [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref001">1</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Physician data</title>
<p>Data regarding physicians were obtained from the Survey of Physicians, Dentists and Pharmacists compiled by the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref013">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref014">14</xref>]. Addresses of healthcare facilities were obtained from the Static Survey of Medical Institutions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref015">15</xref>]. In Japan, the Ministry conducts a complete census of physicians every 2 years. All licensed physicians must register for this census. Every 3 years, the Ministry conducts The Static Survey of Medical Institutions. By law, all clinics and hospitals in Japan must report their activities and resources in this survey. We obtained permission from the Ministry to use data from both censuses for research purposes.</p>
<p>Because the earthquake occurred in March 2011, we obtained individual information about physicians from the Physician Census in 2010 (pre-disaster) and 2012 (post-disaster). We also obtained information about individual hospitals and clinics from the Static Survey in 2008 (pre-disaster) and 2011 (post-disaster).</p>
<p>In the study area, there were 11,686 physicians at pre-disaster and 11,646 physicians at post-disaster. We recognized registered license holders as ‘physicians’ if their main job was recorded as practicing in hospitals (including university hospitals, hospital physician) or clinics (clinic physician). For demographic and geographic analysis, we analyzed only hospital physicians since such data were not available for clinics.</p>
<p>We excluded hospital physicians whose prefecture number, city code, type of work, or facility code or name data were missing or inconsistent in the record. To ensure comparability between data in the pre- and post-disaster years, we excluded hospital physicians whose hospital was relocated to another city or changed its function from a hospital to clinic after the disaster. In the post-disaster census, 18 hospital physicians were registered temporarily as practicing in a clinic. We treated these physicians as hospital physicians for the analysis.</p>
<p>To count the number of physicians and measure the distance from hospital or municipality to the disaster site, we linked the physician census and medical institution census using the code or name of each physician’s working facility.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Distance from disaster site</title>
<p>We measured distances from the disaster site to the physicians’ workplaces based on municipality (municipality-based analysis) and hospital (hospital-based analysis). We adopted these two methods for several reasons. In the municipality-based analysis, although the exact distance of each hospital from the disaster site cannot be calculated, the ratios of hospital physicians-to-population in each municipality can be. In contrast, hospital-based analysis enables the exact distance to be obtained, while physicians-to-population ratios cannot be calculated.</p>
<p>In the analyses, we accounted for two types of disaster: the tsunami-affected coast and radiation leakage from the FDNPP. To precisely locate the tsunami-inundated area, 100 meter × 100 meter grid cell data (updated on 18<sup>th</sup> April 2011) were obtained from the Geospatial Information Authority of Japan, Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref016">16</xref>]. For the distance from the tsunami-affected coast (tsunami-distance), we adopted a borderline at the point where the tsunami reached furthest inland. Distance to each healthcare facility was classified into three categories: ≤5 km, 5–10 km, and &gt;10 km. The area within 5 km included the inundated area. To measure the distance from the point of the FDNPP accident (FDNPP-distance), we used the distance from the radiation-polluted area because the straight distance to the power plant does not represent the extent of radioactive contamination because contamination levels depend on the wind direction. For the distance from the radiation-polluted area, we adopted a borderline of the area under evacuation order, which was designated by the government as of 22 April 2011 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g001">Fig 1</xref>). The area under evacuation order, which is designated by the government as the ‘restricted area’, contained ‘restricted areas with penalties’ (the area within 20 km) and ‘deliberate evacuation areas’ (in which the residents can enter without penalties, but they are not permitted to live) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref017">17</xref>]. The government ordered evacuation of the population from the radiation-polluted area based on air radiation dose rates, which were measured within 80 km of the FDNPP. The measurement was conducted as a part of the 4<sup>th</sup> Airborne Monitoring Survey on 5 November 2011 by the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology, Japan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref018">18</xref>]. The area under evacuation order remained a restricted area at the time of the physician census in December 2012. The distance from each healthcare facility to the restricted area due to the FDNPP accident was classified into five categories: 0 km (the zone including or within the area under evacuation order), 0–25 km, 25–50 km, 50–75 km, and 75–100 (inclusive)km. To account for both the tsunami and FDNPP accident simultaneously, we selected the areas within 5 km of the tsunami-affected coast and within 100 km of the restricted area surrounding the FDNPP, and conducted an analysis of these areas.</p>
<fig id="pone.0178020.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Map showing the geographical characteristics of disaster area and the change rate of physicians.</title>
<p>The size of the symbol for change rate represents the magnitude of the change. Air dose rate was measured within 80 km of the nuclear power plant and data were acquired from the Japan Atomic Energy Agency.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>In the municipality-based analysis, we classified the distance of municipalities from the disaster site based on whether a whole or any part of the municipality was included within the distance specified. For instance, if a municipality included any areas ≤5 km in tsunami-distance and &gt;0 and ≤ 25 km in FDNPP-distance, the municipality was placed in the category of ≤5 km in tsunami-distance and 0–25 km in FDNPP-distance. Administrative boundaries of municipalities for 2011 were obtained from the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport, and Tourism. In the hospital-based analysis, we used the address of each hospital to calculate the distance from the disaster site. The distance was measured using ArcGIS version 10.1 (ESRI Japan Inc.).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Population data</title>
<p>Population data for each municipality were obtained from the Survey on the Basic Register of Residents, conducted by the Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications, in 2009 (pre-disaster) and 2012 (post-disaster).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Because of data availability, we focused on hospital physicians. First, to evaluate overall trends, we investigated the demographic characteristics and information regarding medical resources for the entire study area. Next, we conducted a municipality-level analysis, in which we calculated the rate of change from pre- to post-disaster year in the number of hospital physicians, classified according to the tsunami-distance, the FDNPP-distance, and the FDNPP-distance within tsunami-affected area. Finally, we conducted a hospital-based analysis, in which we calculated the rate of change in the number of physicians classified according to the tsunami-distance, the FDNPP-distance, and the FDNPP-distance within tsunami-affected area. In addition, to evaluate variability in rates of change in the ratio of hospital physicians to total population, we calculated the median and interquartile range for each hospital. Furthermore, we treated the distance from the disaster site as a continuous variable, evaluating the rate of change in physicians against the distance using scatter plots with a cubic polynomial regression line.</p>
<p>To remove the potential effects of the FDNPP accident from our evaluation of tsunami-distance, seven municipalities located within the restricted area due to the FDNPP accident were excluded from the municipality-based analysis using tsunami-distance. We also excluded physicians at these hospitals from the hospital-based analysis using tsunami-distance. In addition, since areas further from the FDNPP were less affected by the accident, the analysis in FDNPP-distance was only evaluated within 100 km from the restricted area.</p>
<p>For context, we recorded the number of clinics and clinic physicians for the entire study area. We obtained data on the number of clinic physicians from the Static Survey of Medical Institutions because we could not obtain information on the working places of clinic physicians in the pre-disaster year from the Physician Census.</p>
<p>Descriptive statistical analysis was conducted in IBM SPSS Statistics version 22 (IBM Japan Inc., Tokyo, Japan) and graphical analysis was conducted with KaleidaGraph version 4.5 (HULINKS Inc. Tokyo, Japan).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Geography of the disaster area</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g001">Fig 1</xref> shows the pre-disaster hospital locations, the geographical characteristics of the tsunami-affected coast, and the post-disaster air radiation dose rate (8 months later). As shown, hospitals were located both in coastal and inland areas, which were populous. The tsunami-affected area spread along the coastline, and reached near-coastal inland areas (at maximum, about 11 km along a river from the coast). The rates of change in physicians at each hospital are also shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g001">Fig 1</xref>. The magnitude of decrease, represented by the size of the symbols, was larger in Fukushima than in the other prefectures. In addition, the largest decrease was observed in the area with an air radiation dose rate of over 1.1 μSv/h.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Total number of practicing physicians</title>
<p>Basic characteristics of the study area during pre- and post-disaster years are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0178020.t001">Table 1</xref>. At post-disaster, the total population within the study area decreased by 2.0%. During this period, nine hospitals were closed or stopped practicing, seven of which were located within 20 km of the FDNPP, i.e., the restricted area. The total number of practicing physicians increased slightly (0.2%) during this period. Specifically, hospital physicians increased, whereas clinic physicians decreased. However, there was a trend for lower rates of change in the study area than nationally (shown in parentheses) amongst both hospital and clinic physicians. The physicians-to-population ratios tended to increase in both physician categories, although that of clinic physicians increased less than that of hospital physicians.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0178020.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Demographic characteristics and number of hospitals and physicians in pre- and post-disaster year.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0178020.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="center">Pre-disaster, N</th>
<th align="center">Post-disaster, N</th>
<th align="center">Change rate, % (National change rate<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003"><sup>§</sup></xref>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Population</td>
<td align="center">5,725,977</td>
<td align="center">5,613,131</td>
<td align="center">-2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Hospital</td>
<td align="center">375</td>
<td align="center">366</td>
<td align="center">-2.4 (-0.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Clinic<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001"><sup>†</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">3,959</td>
<td align="center">3,854</td>
<td align="center">-2.7 (-0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">All physicians<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn002"><sup>‡</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">11,008</td>
<td align="center">11,026</td>
<td align="center">0.2 (3.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    at hospital</td>
<td align="center">7,063</td>
<td align="center">7,109</td>
<td align="center">0.7 (4.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    at clinic</td>
<td align="center">3,945</td>
<td align="center">3,917</td>
<td align="center">-0.7 (1.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Physicians per 100,000 population<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn002"><sup>‡</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">192</td>
<td align="center">196</td>
<td align="center">2.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    at hospital</td>
<td align="center">123</td>
<td align="center">127</td>
<td align="center">3.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    at clinic</td>
<td align="center">69</td>
<td align="center">70</td>
<td align="center">1.4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>† The number of clinics was obtained from the Static Survey of Medical Institutions, and included a special elderly nursing home.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p>‡ The physicians at the nursing home were not counted in this number.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p>§ The parentheses indicate the national changes.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Municipality-based analysis</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0178020.t002">Table 2</xref> shows the municipality-based analysis of number of hospitals and hospital physicians, classified according to tsunami-distance, FDNPP-distance, and FDNPP-distances within the tsunami-affected area. There was a slight decrease in hospital physicians in the area closest to tsunami-affected coast (≤5 km), but increases in other areas. Hospital physicians-to-population ratios increased slightly in all three areas, including the closest area (≤5 km). In contrast, hospital physicians decreased in areas 0 km, 0–25 km, and 25–50 km from the restricted area surrounding the FDNPP. There was also a decrease in hospital physicians-to-population ratios in areas 0 km from the restricted area. There were dramatic reductions in the number of physicians and physicians-to-population ratios in areas affected by both the tsunami and FDNPP accident.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0178020.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Population sizes and number of hospital physicians, classified according to the distance from the tsunami-affected coast and the nuclear power plant in 131 municipalities (municipality-based analysis).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0178020.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Municipality, N</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Hospital physicians, N</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Physicians per 100,00 population, N</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Pre- disaster</th>
<th align="center">Post- disaster</th>
<th align="center">Change rate (%)</th>
<th align="center">Pre- disaster</th>
<th align="center">Post- disaster</th>
<th align="center">Change rate (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="8"><bold>Tsunami-distance (T) (municipality N = 124)</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001"><sup>†</sup></xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km</td>
<td align="right">33</td>
<td align="right">1,800</td>
<td align="right">1,793</td>
<td align="right">-0.4</td>
<td align="right">96</td>
<td align="right">98</td>
<td align="right">2.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: 5–10 km</td>
<td align="right">13</td>
<td align="right">1,753</td>
<td align="right">1,842</td>
<td align="right">5.1</td>
<td align="right">190</td>
<td align="right">196</td>
<td align="right">2.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: &gt;10 km</td>
<td align="right">78</td>
<td align="right">3,411</td>
<td align="right">3,422</td>
<td align="right">0.3</td>
<td align="right">123</td>
<td align="right">126</td>
<td align="right">2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="8"><bold>Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear power plant (FDNPP) -distance (F) (municipality N = 92)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 0 km <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002"><sup>‡</sup></xref></td>
<td align="right">10</td>
<td align="right">191</td>
<td align="right">102</td>
<td align="right">-46.6</td>
<td align="right">117</td>
<td align="right">68</td>
<td align="right">-42.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 0–25 km</td>
<td align="right">18</td>
<td align="right">1,930</td>
<td align="right">1,874</td>
<td align="right">-2.9</td>
<td align="right">187</td>
<td align="right">189</td>
<td align="right">0.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 25–50 km</td>
<td align="right">23</td>
<td align="right">1,446</td>
<td align="right">1,414</td>
<td align="right">-2.2</td>
<td align="right">179</td>
<td align="right">179</td>
<td align="right">0.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 50–75 km</td>
<td align="right">24</td>
<td align="right">4,050</td>
<td align="right">4,169</td>
<td align="right">2.9</td>
<td align="right">252</td>
<td align="right">256</td>
<td align="right">1.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 75–100 km</td>
<td align="right">17</td>
<td align="right">694</td>
<td align="right">721</td>
<td align="right">3.9</td>
<td align="right">137</td>
<td align="right">148</td>
<td align="right">8.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="8"><bold>FDNPP-distance within tsunami-affected area (municipality N = 25)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 0 km<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002"><sup>‡</sup></xref></td>
<td align="right">6</td>
<td align="right">176</td>
<td align="right">89</td>
<td align="right">-49.4</td>
<td align="right">130</td>
<td align="right">71</td>
<td align="right">-44.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 0–25 km</td>
<td align="right">5</td>
<td align="right">627</td>
<td align="right">606</td>
<td align="right">-3.3</td>
<td align="right">150</td>
<td align="right">152</td>
<td align="right">1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 25–50 km</td>
<td align="right">3</td>
<td align="right">237</td>
<td align="right">242</td>
<td align="right">2.1</td>
<td align="right">156</td>
<td align="right">161</td>
<td align="right">3.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 50–75 km</td>
<td align="right">8</td>
<td align="right">1359</td>
<td align="right">1375</td>
<td align="right">1.2</td>
<td align="right">189</td>
<td align="right">190</td>
<td align="right">0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 75–100 km</td>
<td align="right">3</td>
<td align="right">326</td>
<td align="right">317</td>
<td align="right">-2.8</td>
<td align="right">150</td>
<td align="right">159</td>
<td align="right">5.9</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p><sup>†</sup> The seven municipalities located within the restricted area due to the nuclear accident were excluded from analysis.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p><sup>‡</sup> The area including the restricted area due to the nuclear accident. Information for this area is for reference, since it includes residential restriction areas and the restricted residence area.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Hospital-based analysis</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g002">Fig 2</xref> shows the distributions of distances of each hospital from the tsunami-affected coast (A) and the restricted area surrounding the FDNPP (B). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g002">Fig 2(A)</xref>, within the studied range of 0–120 km from the tsunami-affected coast, almost 40% of the hospitals are located within 5 km (30.9%) and 5–10 km (10.4%). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g002">Fig 2(B)</xref>, 7 hospitals (2.7%), 60 hospitals (22.8%), and 68 hospitals (25.9%) are located within 0 km, 0–25 km, and 25–50 km from the FDNPP, respectively.</p>
<fig id="pone.0178020.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Distributions of distance from disaster site to each hospital in the pre-disaster year (hospital-based analysis).</title>
<p>(A) Distance from the tsunami-affected coast and (B) from the restricted area surrounding Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear power plant (FDNPP). IQR, inter quartile range (25th percentile, 75th percentile); SD, standard deviation.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0178020.t003">Table 3</xref> shows the hospital-based analysis of number of hospitals and hospital physicians, classified according to the tsunami-distance, FDNPP-distance and FDNPP-distance within tsunami-affected area. In this analysis, there was no change in the number of hospital physicians in the area within 5 km, while there were increases in areas within 5–10 km and &gt;10 km of tsunami-distance. All seven hospitals closed or stopped practicing and all 45 hospital physicians left the designated restricted area. Hospital physicians decreased in areas ≤50 km and increased in areas over 50 km from the restricted area. The decrease in number was remarkable (-10.4%) at both the area affected both by the tsunami (≤5 km) and the FDNPP accident (0–25 km).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0178020.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Number of hospitals and physicians classified according to the distance from the tsunami-affected coast and the nuclear power plant in the pre- and post-disaster years (hospital-based analysis).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0178020.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Hospitals, N</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Hospital physicians, N</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="center">Pre- disaster</th>
<th align="center">Post- disaster</th>
<th align="center">Change rate (%)</th>
<th align="center">Pre- disaster</th>
<th align="center">Post- disaster</th>
<th align="center">Change rate (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Tsunami-distance (T) (hospital N = 368)</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001"><sup><bold>†</bold></sup></xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5km</td>
<td align="center">109</td>
<td align="center">107</td>
<td align="center">-1.8</td>
<td align="center">1,742</td>
<td align="center">1,742</td>
<td align="center">0.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: 5–10 km</td>
<td align="center">39</td>
<td align="center">39</td>
<td align="center">0.0</td>
<td align="center">1,491</td>
<td align="center">1,544</td>
<td align="center">3.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: &gt;10 km</td>
<td align="center">220</td>
<td align="center">220</td>
<td align="center">0.0</td>
<td align="center">3,785</td>
<td align="center">3,823</td>
<td align="center">1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear power plant (FDNPP)-distance (F) (hospital N = 263)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 0 km <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002"><sup>‡</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">7</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">-100.0</td>
<td align="center">45</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">-100.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 0–25 km</td>
<td align="center">60</td>
<td align="center">60</td>
<td align="center">0.0</td>
<td align="center">1,154</td>
<td align="center">1,116</td>
<td align="center">-3.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 25–50 km</td>
<td align="center">68</td>
<td align="center">68</td>
<td align="center">0.0</td>
<td align="center">1,009</td>
<td align="center">986</td>
<td align="center">-2.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 50–75 km</td>
<td align="center">92</td>
<td align="center">92</td>
<td align="center">0.0</td>
<td align="center">2,709</td>
<td align="center">2,778</td>
<td align="center">2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    F: 75–100 km</td>
<td align="center">36</td>
<td align="center">34</td>
<td align="center">-5.6</td>
<td align="center">419</td>
<td align="center">434</td>
<td align="center">3.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>FDNPP-distance within tsunami-affected area (hospital N = 93)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 0 km <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002"><sup>‡</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">7</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">-100.0</td>
<td align="center">45</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">-100.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 0–25 km</td>
<td align="center">15</td>
<td align="center">15</td>
<td align="center">0.0</td>
<td align="center">135</td>
<td align="center">121</td>
<td align="center">-10.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 25–50 km</td>
<td align="center">24</td>
<td align="center">24</td>
<td align="center">0.0</td>
<td align="center">232</td>
<td align="center">231</td>
<td align="center">-0.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 50–75 km</td>
<td align="center">35</td>
<td align="center">35</td>
<td align="center">0.0</td>
<td align="center">934</td>
<td align="center">943</td>
<td align="center">1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    T: ≤5 km &amp; F: 75–100 km</td>
<td align="center">12</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">-16.7</td>
<td align="center">199</td>
<td align="center">193</td>
<td align="center">-3.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p><sup><bold>†</bold></sup> The seven hospitals located within the restricted area due to the nuclear accident were excluded from the analysis.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p><sup>‡</sup> The area including the restricted area due to the nuclear accident. Information for this area is for reference, since it includes residential restriction areas and the restricted residence area.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g003">Fig 3</xref> shows the variability among hospitals in the rate of change of physicians-to-population ratios. Tsunami-distance (A) and FDNPP-distance (B) were treated as categorical variables in the boxplots (1) and as continuous variables in the scatter plots (2). The interquartile range of the rate of change did not change significantly with increased distance from the tsunami-affected coast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g003">Fig 3A-1</xref>). When we treated the tsunami-distance as a continuous variable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g003">Fig 3A-2</xref>), the cubic polynomial regression line was almost linear. Although variability in the rate of change was larger in closer areas than in more distant areas, variability was not significantly dependent on tsunami-distance. The interquartile range of the rate of change moved up slightly with increased FDNPP-distance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g003">Fig 3B-1</xref>). When we treated the FDNPP-distance as a continuous variable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g003">Fig 3B-2</xref>), the rate of increase was lower in the closest areas than other areas. Regardless, we excluded physicians at seven hospitals within the designated restricted area, following which the rate of increase was lowest in Fukushima (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g003">Fig 3B-2</xref>, gray circles) than in Miyagi Prefecture.</p>
<fig id="pone.0178020.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Boxplots and scatter plots showing hospital physicians-to-population ratios against distance from disaster site.</title>
<p>(A) Distance from the tsunami-affected coast and (B) from the restricted area surrounding Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear power plant (FDNPP) (hospital-based analysis). Municipality-based population data were used, while physician data were hospital-based. Seven hospitals located within the restricted area were excluded from the analysis with tsunami-distances. In Fig A-1 and B-1, the whiskers represent the 1.5 * inter quartile range ± the 25th and 75th percentile. The black diamond represents the mean of all of the data. IQR, inter quartile range (25th percentile, 75th percentile); SD, standard deviation.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0178020.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study, we evaluated changing distributions of physicians in the aftermath of the Great East Japan Earthquake. We analyzed the distributions at varying distances from the tsunami-affected coast and the restricted area due to the FDNPP accident. The number of physicians did not decrease in any subgroup of tsunami-distance, and actually increased when we adjusted for changes in the population. In contrast, the number of hospital physicians decreased within 50 km in FDNPP-distance. The decrease was most remarkable in areas 0–25 km away, except the area within the designated restricted area. In addition, a wider distribution of rates of change was observed in the area within 50 km of FDNPP-distance compared with more distant areas.</p>
<p>These results suggest the tsunami and nuclear leakage accident affected local areas differently. While a marked decrease was observed within the area affected by both the tsunami and FDNPP accident, the FDNPP potentially had a greater effect on the number of physicians than did the tsunami because the number of physicians was stable in tsunami-affected areas, excluding the influence of the FDNPP accident. Although the tsunami, a direct natural disaster, caused severe damage in coastal areas, communities were able to embark on reconstruction soon after the tsunami. In contrast, nuclear accidents, an artificial and secondary disaster, scatter radioactivity that may last years into surrounding areas, keeping people away from the area. Therefore, although both disasters originated from the same earthquake, the nuclear accident causes more serious and chronic influence in surrounding communities than the tsunami. Few studies have evaluated these differences.</p>
<p>In this study, we evaluated physician migration patterns in the areas affected by the tsunami and nuclear accident. The earthquake itself has also damaged the area, although the extent of the damage was far less than that of the tsunami. For example, 92.4% of deaths by the Great East Japan Earthquake were caused by drowning, 4.4% was by crush injuries, 1.1% was by burns, and 2.0% was by unspecified causes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref001">1</xref>]. Thus, the effects of the earthquake itself on the number of physicians are potentially small in this disaster situation.</p>
<p>It is noteworthy that the number of hospital physicians did not change in the area within 5 km of the tsunami-affected coast, even though two hospitals were closed or stopped practicing between the pre- and post-disaster years. In addition, the number of hospital physicians increased in areas 5–10 km from the tsunami-affected coast. The increased number is potentially influenced by temporarily placed physicians, who were dispatched to the affected area, particularly the tsunami-affected area, immediately after the disaster. According to official reports, 12,385 health professionals (2,720 teams) were dispatched to the area during the year after the disaster [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref019">19</xref>]. However, most of such temporarily placed physicians returned to their original facilities within several months. In addition, it was reported that the main activity of the dispatched medical teams terminated 4 months after the earthquake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref020">20</xref>]. Thus, the effect of such temporary physicians on present findings would be minimal by the end of 2012 when we obtained our post-disaster data.</p>
<p>On the other hand, decreased numbers of physicians were observed in the areas closest to the FDNPP. In the pre-disaster year, 45 physicians were working in seven hospitals within 20 km of the FDNPP, an area which was later designated as a restricted area by the government. Thus, they must have moved to areas further than 20 km from the FDNPP. However, a decrease in physicians was also observed in the areas 0–25 km away from the restricted area. These findings are consistent with a previous study that evaluated trends in nurse distributions after the same disaster [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref011">11</xref>]. The authors reported a decrease in nurses in the areas most affected by radiation. Fear of radiation might be even greater in physicians than the general population, discouraging them from practicing in the area.</p>
<p>There are a few studies that have reported changes in the number of physicians after similar catastrophic disasters. Following hurricane Katrina in the United States, total bed capacity decreased by about 80% approximately six months after the disaster [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref021">21</xref>]. Even after one year, the number of physicians in the affected parishes in New Orleans was 48% that of pre-disaster levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref022">22</xref>]. Previous studies suggest that economic concerns appeared to be a key factor in the failure of physicians to return to the Katrina-affected areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref022">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref023">23</xref>]. Although it may be differ between the situation of hurricane Katrina and the Great East Japan Earthquake, it is noteworthy that the number of physicians did not change in the tsunami-affected area after the earthquake. One possible explanation may be due to universal health insurance of Japan. In Japan, therefore, people may visit clinics and hospitals with being covered by a certain insurance, and clinics and hospitals may get fair reimbursement fee even at disaster areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref024">24</xref>]. In addition, the Japanese government exempted disaster victims from paying monthly premiums and out-of-pocket payments for medical care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref025">25</xref>]. Furthermore, the government provided financial support for medical institutions to restore damaged buildings, in accordance with the Special Reconstruction District Act [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref025">25</xref>]. This financial support might have potentially contributed to retaining physicians in affected areas.</p>
<p>We adopted two analysis methods to examine the influence of this earthquake. One was municipality-based and the other was hospital-based, both of which have their own advantages and disadvantages. The former enabled calculation of physician-to-population ratios, and the latter provided precise geographic analysis. The trends in physician distributions were, by and large, similar in the two methods. We used the detailed addresses of the hospitals where physicians were working. We measured the detailed distribution by calculating the means, medians, and interquartile ranges for each hospital, according to their distance from the tsunami-affected coast and the restricted area due to the FDNPP accident (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g003">Fig 3</xref>). We observed that the rate of change in the number of physicians before and after the disaster varied according to geographic FDNPP-distance. It is noteworthy that the rate of change was different among hospitals located at a similar FDNPP-distance. The standard deviations of the change rates at hospitals close to the restricted area surrounding FDNPP were larger than those further away (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g003">Fig 3B</xref>). This suggests that there was more variation in mean changes of physicians among closer hospitals than among more distant hospitals. Variability might be related to hospital characteristics, such as size and whether it is public or private. Further study is required that takes hospital characteristics into account to assess and avoid bias in the results.</p>
<p>All prefectures studied had already faced a shortage of physicians, even before the disaster, because of their rural location [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0178020.ref007">7</xref>]. The numbers of physicians per 100,000 people in 2010 (pre-disaster) were 193.7 in Iwate, 222.0 in Miyagi, and 191.2 in Fukushima. These were all under the national average (230.4). The pattern of changes in physician distributions differed among the prefectures. In Iwate, a decrease in physicians was observed regardless of the tsunami or FDNPP accident (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g001">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g003">3</xref>). In contrast, in Fukushima the decrease was particularly prominent in areas close to the nuclear power plant. Although the number of physicians increased in the surrounding area, hospitals located within 50 km of the restricted area surrounding the FDNPP, especially where the air dose rate was 1.1μSv/h, experienced decreases of more than 25% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0178020.g001">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
<p>In this study, we obtained population data from a survey on the basic register of residents for municipality-level analysis. Some residents have not changed their registration address even though they have moved to other cities after the disaster. This might be particularly true for areas within the restricted area surrounding the FDNPP. As such, the population size in the post-disaster year may be overestimated. This would mean that the rate of change in the number of physicians per unit population is smaller than estimated. However, we used the population data at municipality level, so if residents moved within the same municipality, bias would be minimal.</p>
<p>There are other limitations to this study. We were only able to obtain population data at municipality level. We could not obtain data in smaller geographic units, such as small census blocks. In the hospital-based analysis, because we used the population of the municipality in which the hospital was located, we could not directly calculate the number of hospital physicians per population in the hospital catchment area. Despite of these limitations, our findings are novel and tell how the two great disasters affect the distribution of human resource for health following the Great East Japan Earthquake. Our data would be a reference for other countries which are preparing for such disasters.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The differences in the distributions of the physicians before and after the tsunami were not substantial. Supportive action from other prefectures may have contributed to the lack of physicians in these areas. However, the number of hospital physicians in areas close to the restricted area surrounding the nuclear power plant decreased significantly, even after adjusting for population decreases. These results suggest a substantial difference in seriousness of the consequences of the two main disasters following the earthquake. Continuous observation is required in the affected areas, particularly near the nuclear power plant that caused radiation leakage.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Cabinet Office</collab>, <collab>Government of Japan</collab>. <source>White Paper on Disaster Management 2011 Executive Summary (Provisional Translation)</source>. <publisher-loc>Tokyo, Japan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cabinet Office, Government of Japan</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year> [April, 13. 2017]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bousai.go.jp/kaigirep/hakusho/pdf/WPDM2011_Summary.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.bousai.go.jp/kaigirep/hakusho/pdf/WPDM2011_Summary.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>National Police Agency of Japan</collab>. <source>Damage Situation and Police Countermeasures</source>. <publisher-loc>Tokyo, Japan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Police Agency of Japan</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year> [cited 2017 April 1st]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.npa.go.jp/archive/keibi/biki/higaijokyo_e.pdf" xlink:type="simple">https://www.npa.go.jp/archive/keibi/biki/higaijokyo_e.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>World Nuclear Association</collab>. <source>Fukushima Accident</source>. <publisher-loc>London, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Nuclear Association</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year> [cited 2016 Fev 1]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.world-nuclear.org/info/safety-and-security/safety-of-plants/fukushima-accident/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.world-nuclear.org/info/safety-and-security/safety-of-plants/fukushima-accident/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">UN. Sources, effects and risks of ionizing radiation, UNSCEAR 2013 report, part I: UN.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization, Public Health England, United Nations Office for Disaster Risk Reduction. Disaster risk management for health: overview. Geneva2011 [cited 2015 March 19]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/hac/events/drm_fact_sheet_child_health.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.who.int/hac/events/drm_fact_sheet_child_health.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Izumi M, Nakamura K, Kondo M. [Medical treatment and nursing in the affected areas -Current status and issues after the Great East Japan Earthquake-]2011 June 23, 2015; 713(2011. 6. 2):[1–12 pp.]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ndl.go.jp/jp/diet/publication/issue/pdf/0713.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ndl.go.jp/jp/diet/publication/issue/pdf/0713.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare, Japan. [Survey of Physicians, Dentists and Pharmacists 2010]. 2011 [cited 2015 21 June]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei/saikin/hw/ishi/10/dl/kekka_1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei/saikin/hw/ishi/10/dl/kekka_1.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Nikkei Medical</collab>. [<source>2012 March "special issue: Disaster medicine—a result and self-examination" reprint Vol.5"</source>]. <publisher-name>Nikkei Business Publications, Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year> [cited 2015 Sep. 29]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://medical.nikkeibp.co.jp/leaf/all/report/t169/201203/523931.html" xlink:type="simple">https://medical.nikkeibp.co.jp/leaf/all/report/t169/201203/523931.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Nikkei Medical</collab>. [<source>2012 March "special issue: Disaster medicine—a result and self-examination" reprint Vol.6"</source>]. <publisher-name>Nikkei Business Publications, Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year> [cited 2015 Sep. 29]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://medical.nikkeibp.co.jp/leaf/all/report/t169/201203/523947.html" xlink:type="simple">https://medical.nikkeibp.co.jp/leaf/all/report/t169/201203/523947.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Nikkei Medical</collab>. [<source>2012 March "special issue: Disaster medicine—a result and self-examination" reprint Vol.7"</source>]. <publisher-name>Nikkei Business Publications, Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year> [cited 2015 Sep. 29]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://medical.nikkeibp.co.jp/leaf/all/report/t169/201203/523948.html" xlink:type="simple">https://medical.nikkeibp.co.jp/leaf/all/report/t169/201203/523948.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morioka</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomio</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seto</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trends in the geographic distribution of nursing staff before and after the Great East Japan Earthquake: a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Hum Resour Health</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>70</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kashima</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characteristics of physician outflow from disaster areas following the Great East Japan Earthquake</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> (in press).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare, Japan. Survey of Physicians, Dentists and Pharmacists 2010. 2011 [cited 2015 23 March]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/english/database/db-hss/dl/spdp_2010.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mhlw.go.jp/english/database/db-hss/dl/spdp_2010.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare, Japan. [Survey of Physicians, Dentists and Pharmacists 2012]. 2013 [cited 2015 23 March]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei/saikin/hw/ishi/12/dl/gaikyo.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei/saikin/hw/ishi/12/dl/gaikyo.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare, Japan</collab>. <source>Summary of Static/Dynamic Surveys of Medical Institutions and Hospital Report, 2010</source>. <publisher-loc>Tokyo, Japan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year> [cited 2015 March 27]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/english/database/db-hss/smi.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mhlw.go.jp/english/database/db-hss/smi.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Geospatial Information Authority of Japan</collab>, <publisher-name>Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism</publisher-name>. [<source>The overview of Tsunami inundated area (1/100,000)</source>]. <publisher-name>Geospatial Information Authority of Japan, Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year> [updated April 18, 2011 cited 2015 March 24]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gsi.go.jp/chirijoho/chirijoho40022.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.gsi.go.jp/chirijoho/chirijoho40022.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Support Team for Residents Affected by Nuclear Incidents</collab>, <collab>Nuclear Emergency Response Headquarters</collab>, <collab>Cabinet Office, Japan</collab>. [<source>Review of the Areas under Evacuation Orders</source>]. <publisher-loc>Tokyo, Japan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cabinet Office, Japan</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year> [cited 2015 March 24]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.meti.go.jp/earthquake/nuclear/pdf/131009/131009_02a.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.meti.go.jp/earthquake/nuclear/pdf/131009/131009_02a.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ministry of education, culture, sports, science and technology, Japan;. Results of the Fourth Airborne Monitoring Survey by MEXT Tokyo, Japan: Ministry of education, culture, sports, science and technology, Japan 2011 [cited 2015 March 24]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://radioactivity.nsr.go.jp/en/contents/4000/3179/24/1270_1216.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://radioactivity.nsr.go.jp/en/contents/4000/3179/24/1270_1216.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare, Japan. The damage situation of and measures taken for the Great East Japan Earthquake 116th announcement (As of 14:00, March 23, 2012). 2012 [cited 2015 June 23]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/english/topics/2011eq/dl/23mar2012_damage.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mhlw.go.jp/english/topics/2011eq/dl/23mar2012_damage.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>[The role of JMAT as a response for a disaster of Japan Medical Association] (Special issue: Disaster medicine -The instructive and controversial through Great East Japan Earthquake and Tsunami Disasters)</article-title>. <source>The Journal of the Japan medical association</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>141</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">U.S. Government Accountability Office. Hurricane Katrina: Status of the Health Care System in New Orleans and Difficult Decisions Related to Efforts to Rebuild It Approximately 6 Months After Hurricane Katrina (GAO-06-576R). Washington, DC: U.S. Government Accountability Office; 2006 [cited 2015 June 23]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gao.gov/assets/100/94107.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.gao.gov/assets/100/94107.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madamala</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characteristics of physician relocation following Hurricane Katrina</article-title>. <source>Disaster Med Public Health Prep</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1097/DMP.0b013e3180679118" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/DMP.0b013e3180679118</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18388598</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffies</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health care infrastructure post-Katrina: disaster planning to return health care workers to their home communities</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1176/appi.ps.61.1.70" xlink:type="simple">10.1176/appi.ps.61.1.70</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20044421</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikegami</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname> <given-names>B-K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babazono</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Japanese universal health coverage: evolution, achievements, and challenges</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>378</volume>(<issue>9796</issue>):<fpage>1106</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0178020.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare, Japan. Response to the Great East Japan Earthquake By the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare, the Government of Japan 2012 [cited 2015 June 23]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/bunya/kokusaigyomu/asean/2012/dl/Introduction_Dr.Yamauchi.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mhlw.go.jp/bunya/kokusaigyomu/asean/2012/dl/Introduction_Dr.Yamauchi.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>