<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-11026</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052987</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Ecological environments</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Marine environments</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavioral ecology</subject>
              <subject>Marine ecology</subject>
              <subject>Spatial and landscape ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavioral ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Marine biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Marine ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Zoology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal behavior</subject>
              <subject>Mammalogy</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Marine and Aquatic Sciences</subject>
          <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Spatial and Social Sexual Segregation Patterns in Indo-Pacific Bottlenose Dolphins (<italic>Tursiops aduncus</italic>)</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Sexual Segregation by Dolphins in an Estuary</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Fury</surname>
            <given-names>Christine Ann</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ruckstuhl</surname>
            <given-names>Kathreen E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Harrison</surname>
            <given-names>Peter L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Southern Cross University Marine Ecology Research Centre, Southern Cross University, Lismore, New South Wales, Australia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Fenton</surname>
            <given-names>Brock</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Western Ontario, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">cfury10@gmail.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CF PH. Performed the experiments: CF. Analyzed the data: CF PH KR. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CF KR PH. Wrote the paper: CF PH KR.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>9</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e52987</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Fury et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sexual segregation seems to be common in bottlenose dolphins, whereby males and females live in different pods that mix mainly for mating. Male dolphins often use aggressive behaviour to mate with females, while females with calves may have different activity and dietary requirements to males and different susceptibility to predation. We investigated the degree of spatial and social sexual segregation in Indo-Pacific bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops aduncus</italic>) in a subtropical estuary in Australia. Based on surveys completed over three years, dolphin groups were mostly mixed-sex or female. Mixed-sex groups were found in larger groups in mostly deeper water, whereas, female groups were foraging across all water depths in smaller groups. Aggressive coercive behaviour by males towards females was high, occurring mainly in deeper water, at higher tides, and outside the breeding season. Habitat use by female dolphin groups suggests that shallow tributaries may provide a sanctuary from aggressive males, access to suitable prey items and density for mothers and their calves, or a combination of these factors.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was funded by Australian Geographic, Angourie Rainforest Resort, Project Aware and Southern Cross University Whale Research Centre. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sexual segregation for much of the year is a widespread phenomenon among social mammals including, ungulates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl1">[1]</xref>, bears <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Wielgus1">[2]</xref>, kangaroos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-MacFarlane1">[3]</xref>, seals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Kovacs1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Stewart1">[5]</xref> and cetaceans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Webster1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Martin1">[9]</xref>. Sexual segregation theory divides the categories of sexual segregation into social segregation where sexes live in separate groups outside of the breeding season, habitat segregation where sexes differ in habitat use, and spatial segregation where they occupy different areas within the same habitat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Conradt1">[10]</xref>. A number of different hypotheses have been proposed to explain sexual segregation including the activity budget, predation risk, forage selection and male-avoidance strategy hypotheses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Bon1">[11]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Weckerly1">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Little is known about the degree of spatial or sexual segregation in bottlenose dolphins or factors that could be driving these patterns. Our study thus aimed at quantifying the types of dolphin groups most commonly found throughout the different seasons, what types of habitat they use, and, if spatial or social sexual segregation occurs, which variables might explain these patterns. The main predators of bottlenose dolphins in the study site are bull sharks (<italic>Carcharhinus leucas</italic>) that are found mainly in the deeper estuary channels during the day; an area that dolphins and particularly females with young calves should avoid <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Heupel1">[14]</xref>. It has also been proposed that females with calves might avoid male harassment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Croft1">[15]</xref> and thus avoid areas frequented by males. It has further been proposed that females might avoid males due to direct or indirect effects on the frequencies of antagonistic interactions: females might avoid males of all age classes either because males engage in agonistic acts in the presence of females <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Bon1">[11]</xref> or because male presence causes an increase in female-female aggression as has been shown for Roosevelt elk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Cransac1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Weckerly1">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The social ecology of bottlenose dolphins is quite variable geographically, however, it has been described through several long-term studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Connor1">[16]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Wilson1">[18]</xref> to show a complex fission-fusion society whereby dolphins join and leave groups on a flexible basis, with interactions between individuals lasting for minutes to years. Sexual segregation is thought to be the basic framework of the society for some <italic>Tursiops</italic> spp. For dolphins that show sexual segregation it is strongest in the adults, where females with calves are a key element forming female groups, groups of males form strongly bonded alliances among 2–3 adult males, and juveniles form groups of mixed sexes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Parsons1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Wells1">[22]</xref>. Alliances are cooperating male dolphins working in pairs and triplets to seize and control the movements of females <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Connor1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Connor3">[23]</xref>. These alliance formations have been recorded in Port Stephens and Shark Bay, Australia and the Bahamas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Parsons1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Connor4">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Mller2">[26]</xref>. However, other studies also show that male alliances are not the predominant feature in all bottlenose dolphin populations and the degree of sexual segregation and the proportion of mixed-sex groups vary considerable geographically. For instance, common bottlenose dolphins (<italic>T. truncatus</italic>), such as those in Europe show no strong alliances between males and often dolphins occur in mixed-sex groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Wilson2">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Wilson3">[28]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The aim of this study was to describe the social system, seasonal and gender differences in habitat use and social segregation, and to investigate to what extent sexual segregation (spatial, habitat or social) occurs in a population of Indo-Pacific bottlenose dolphins (<italic>T. aduncus</italic>) in a subtropical estuary in eastern Australia. We predicted that female dolphins use different habitats than males, partly to avoid male aggression. Also, as small fish are more abundant in shallow estuarine waters, which makes it easier for calves to catch and consume small fish, we expected females with calves to be found in shallower waters compared to males. It was also expected that the dolphins would use different habitats during different tides and seasons according to prey availability, and that this would be independent of sex. It has been shown that differences in activity budgets between the sexes can lead to social segregation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl2">[29]</xref>. Furthermore, because of high energy demands due to lactation, we expected lactating females to show different activity budgets and specifically to spend more time foraging than adult males <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl3">[30]</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Study Site and Population</title>
        <p>The Clarence River estuary (CR) is located on the subtropical north coast of New South Wales (NSW) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g001">Figure 1</xref>). It is the largest coastal river in northern NSW <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-West1">[31]</xref> with a catchment area of approximately 22,446 km<sup>2</sup>, a waterway area of 89 km<sup>2</sup>, volume of 204.7×10<sup>6</sup> m<sup>3</sup> and a mean depth of 2.3 m. The approximate length of the river tidal influence is about 60 km from the mouth. The mean spring tidal range at the entrance is 1.34 m <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Walsh1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Eyre1">[33]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0052987-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Map of the study sites in northern New South Wales, Australia at the top and a detailed map of the Clarence River estuaries indicating the survey areas.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Dolphin population</title>
        <p>Results from the broader study on this dolphin population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury1">[34]</xref> concluded that the CR sustains a moderately sized, predominantly resident dolphin community. The abundance estimate from mark-recapture analyses were 71 (62–81 95% CI, CV = 0.07) dolphins utilizing the CR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury1">[34]</xref>. Site fidelity patterns of identified dolphins determined that 60% were residents, 26% were occasional visitors, and 14% were transients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury1">[34]</xref>. The dolphins were found to utilise the estuary all year-round and their spatial distribution was largest on high and flood tides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury2">[35]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Field Methods</title>
        <p>Boat-based surveys were completed in the Clarence River (CR) estuary over 3 years from October 2003 to September 2006 (4 to 12 surveys per calendar season). Surveys were conducted using small aluminium boats (∼4 m) powered by a 2-stroke engine. During the surveys the boat was kept at a steady speed of ∼6 knots and 1–3 observers maintained a constant visual search for dolphins. All surveys were done in calm conditions (i.e., Beaufort sea state ≤3) between 06:00 and 18:00 h. Generally, surveys were conducted to include all daylight hours, with morning surveys occurring from 7:00–13:00 and on other days afternoon surveys at 11:00–17:00 in most seasons, and with surveys starting earlier and finishing later when longer periods of daylight were available, particularly during summer. Different times of the day, tidal periods, weather conditions, months and all seasons were used for surveys to encompass all possible ranges and to avoid bias from only observing animals in the mornings or afternoons and potentially missing important behaviours that might only be displayed at certain other times of the day, only during ebb or flood tides, or only during certain months. The route for the surveys was randomized to ensure that surveys started and finished at different locations each survey, and travel occurred along different channels until the whole study area was covered. If dolphins were not located, surveys were still continued for the full survey time period to encompass multiple surveys of the full study area. Surveys ranged over a 16 km<sup>2</sup> area, which included surveys up to ∼28 km upstream from the river mouth. The study area began from 500 m landward of the estuary mouth. From 2005, if the dolphins were found in the study area and travelled upstream past the end of the designated study area they were followed up to a further 24 km. The surveys used a zigzag pattern in the wider areas of the estuary to maximize the chances of any encountering dolphins present, and the entire survey area was always covered during each survey period. A group of dolphins was defined as individuals being within a 100 m radius of one another and engaged in similar activities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Irvine1">[36]</xref>.</p>
        <sec id="s2c1">
          <title>Group composition</title>
          <p>65% of adult dolphins were individually identified by marks on their dorsal fins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury1">[34]</xref>. The group's gender classification was determined as males, females, mixed-sex, or unknown. Groups were classified as a mixed-sex group if at least one adult male and one adult female were present. Groups were considered female only groups if all adults, not juveniles, were known females. For female groups, a dolphin was classified as female by the consistent presence of a calf, sighted at least 6 times together, at any time in the 3 years of the study, or by observation of the genital slit. Males were classified by direct observation of their penis. Most often sex identification would involve post-fieldwork analysis of photographs where an erect penis was observed. If a gender category could not be established for the group, i.e. all adults could not be identified, it was classified as unknown (29%) and the data were not used in the analyses.</p>
          <p>Focal group follows were conducted during dolphin surveys where a focal group was followed to whatever extent possible during each sample period. Groups were followed from a distance of between 1–50 m, however, mostly at 30 m as prescribed by permit limits; however, sometimes dolphins came closer to the survey boat. An encounter with a group occurred until i) dolphins were no longer able to be observed, ii) the group split up or joined another group, or iii) the 3 hour limit had been reached as directed by the ethics permit. The survey then continued by searching for another group of dolphins. Instantaneous scan sampling involved an observer recording the group's current behaviour at pre-selected moments in time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Altmann1">[37]</xref>. For this study, behaviour was recorded every 3-mins on the minute throughout the observation period to determine the activity budget of the dolphins.</p>
          <p>A total of 87 boat-based surveys were completed during the 3-year study comprising of 468.5 h, with 142 dolphin groups and 2,452 dolphin GPS habitat use points for the full data set and 89 GPS habitat use points for the subset (only one data point per encounter). The median survey duration was 360 mins (range 120–510 mins). Lengths of focal follows of dolphins were between 12–180 mins. Survey effort (X<sup>2</sup><sub>3</sub> = 1.27, <italic>P</italic> = 0.74) and direct dolphin observation time (X<sup>2</sup><sub>3</sub> = 1.2, <italic>P</italic> = 0.753) were not significantly different among seasons (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0052987-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <table-wrap id="pone-0052987-t001" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.t001</object-id>
            <label>Table 1</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Boat-survey effort and direct dolphin observation (DDO) periods during each season.</title>
            </caption>
            <alternatives>
              <graphic id="pone-0052987-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
              <table>
                <colgroup span="1">
                  <col align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                </colgroup>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic>Study Sites</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <italic>Clarence River estuary</italic>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic>Season (year)</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic>Survey effort (h)</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic>DDO (h)</italic>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spring (2003–5)</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summer (2003–5)</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autumn (2004–6)</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winter (2004–6)</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.7</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (3 years)</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </alternatives>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2c2">
          <title>Spatial patterns and Activity Budget</title>
          <p>Upon sighting a group of dolphins, the group was slowly approached to minimize disturbance and the group position was determined using a hand-held global positioning system (GPS) (Garmin GPS 12), and the behavioural states were recorded. Behavioural states were foraging, travelling, social interactions and rest/milling. Social interactions were further categorized by the presence or absence of coercive behaviour by males if that was observed. Coercion is a form of aggressive behaviour used by males that occurs frequently among animals with promiscuous mating systems and often involves males using force to increase the chances that a female will mate with male/s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Smuts1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Muller1">[39]</xref>. In bottlenose dolphins, Connor <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Connor5">[25]</xref> observed that coercion often involves aggressive behaviour by males towards a female including biting, hitting with the tail, head-jerks or body slamming the female. The aggressive coercive behaviour observed in the CR was defined as 3–4 male dolphins flanking a female dolphin, often with all three males having erect penises and trying to force copulation with the female. There were often calves or juveniles accompanying the group, however, they were not herded by the males but remained within 10 m of the group.</p>
          <p>The GPS data points were downloaded using Waypoint + <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Hildebrand1">[40]</xref> and converted into GIS format using the program ArcView (ESRI, v.9.0). The group composition data were combined with the photographic identification data and sorted by groups, not individuals, and group composition by gender was determined for the adults in the group (not calves). A minimum of four GPS behavioural data points was required for the group to be considered in the analyses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Allen1">[41]</xref>, however, to avoid auto-correlation associated with the 3-min sampling method with differing encounter lengths, only one data point per encounter was used for the analyses of behaviour. The data point used was that recorded at the 12<sup>th</sup> minute mark (i.e. 4<sup>th</sup> data point); this data point was used because by this time any slight change in behaviour that might have occurred due to the presence of the boat had ceased <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury3">[42]</xref>.</p>
          <p>All data on groups of known composition were then analysed for each of the dolphin gender group categories (male, female or mixed-sex) for habitat utilization patterns, using the kernel density estimator (KDE) analysis with least squares cross validation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Seaman1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Hooge1">[44]</xref> in ArcView (ESRI, version 3.2) and Animal Movement Analyst Extension (AMAE) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Hooge1">[44]</xref>. The fixed kernel density estimator is regarded as the most appropriate method for estimating habitat utilization distribution (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Worton1">[45]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Silverman1">[47]</xref>), and uses probability density functions to identify areas of intense use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Seaman1">[43]</xref>. Many other methods have been developed since then, but the MCP and the kernel remain the most widely used and comparable approaches (see reviews in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-VanWinkle1">[48]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Worton2">[50]</xref>). We used least-squares cross-validation (LSCV) as it is the most commonly used method for automatically calculating the smoothing parameter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Worton1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Gubbins1">[46]</xref>. The LSCV method attempts to find a value for h that minimizes the mean integrated square error (MISE) by minimizing a score function CV(h) for the estimated error between the true density function and the kernel density estimate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Worton3">[51]</xref>. We used the fixed kernel approach that assumes the width of the standard bivariate normal kernel placed at each observation is the same throughout the plane of the utilization distribution.The 30% and 50% isopleths were used to investigate the core areas utilized by the dolphins, and the 75% isopleth shows the broader use of these areas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Worton1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Seminoff1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Hooge2">[53]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2c3">
          <title>Sexual differences in activity budget, spatial or habitat use</title>
          <p>The dependant variable was gender groups (male, female and mixed-sex). Each dolphin gender group encounter was classified into these predictor variables; duration of encounter (mins), year of survey (1, 2 or 3), time of day (1, 2, 3, and 4), behaviour (foraging, travelling,social interactions, and rest/milling), tidal phase (high, low, flood, ebb), tidal range (spring, neap), water depth (deeper, medium or shallow), group size and season (spring, summer, autumn, winter). Categories used for the variables were as follows. Year of survey categories were; Year 1 = spring 2003–winter 2004, Year 2 = spring 2004–winter 2005, Year 3 = spring 2005–winter 2006. Time of day categories were; 1 = 06:00–09:00 h, 2 = 09:00–12:00 h, 3 = 12:00–15:00 h, 4 = 15:00–18:00 h.</p>
          <p>The deeper water category occurred in the main channel where the average depth was 6–12 m, medium water depth was 4–5 m average depth with some sand banks present, and shallow water depth was 1–3 m average depth with many sand banks scattered throughout the area. Depth data and habitat type were determined from geomorphic habitat maps <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury3">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Dyall1">[54]</xref> and from records of water depth obtained using a Secchi disk as a weighted line to measure water depth at each survey location for associated research at these sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury3">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury4">[55]</xref>. Seasons were spring (September–November), summer (December–February), autumn (March–May) and winter (June–August).</p>
          <p>Tidal phase was divided into three-hour periods with high tide including the hour of high tide and the hour prior to and subsequent to it. Low tide included the hour of low tide and the hour prior to and subsequent. Flood tide included the 3 hours between the low tide and high tide periods, and ebb tide included the 3 hours between high tide and low tide periods. Tidal ranges included spring tides that were around the full moon and new moon period, and neap tides that were on the waning and waxing moon period and were of equal duration between categories.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2c4">
          <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
          <p>All of the predictor and dependent variables are categorical or nominal in nature. We therefore mostly used Chi-square analyses. Analyses were performed using the software package JMP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-JMP1">[56]</xref> and SPSS for windows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-SPSS1">[57]</xref>. Analyses were performed using either the full data set or a subset. In the subset data set we only used one data point per encounter with a particular group on a given day to avoid problems of pseudoreplication. To test for sexual differences in activity budgets we performed Chi-square tests on the full data set, with behavioural frequencies as the dependent and gender group categories as the predictor variable. To test for seasonal differences in the frequencies of female and mixed-sex groups we used a Mann-Whitney U-test on the subset data. To test whether the sexes use different habitats we compared seasonal habitat use for each gender group category using a Chi-square test with water depth category as the dependent and gender group category as the predictor variables. We also tested if the dolphins were using the different water depths (dependent variable) differently according to season and gender groups (predictor variables). Male-only groups were not included in any of the analyses because of insufficient data available for these groups. A Kruskal-Wallis test was used on the full dataset, separately, for each gender group to determine independence. We also wanted to identify environmental factors that could contribute to sexual segregation patterns, and thus tested for the effect of year of survey, time of day, behaviour, group size, duration of encounter, tidal phase, tidal range, water depth and season (predictor variables) on the occurrence of mixed-sex or female-only groups, using a nominal logistic model, with group type as the dependent variable.</p>
          <p>We also investigated whether different frequencies of coercive behaviour (dependent variable) were associated with different water depths, tides, and seasons (predictor variables) using Chi-square tests.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Gender group categories, Activity budgets and Group size</title>
        <p>The dolphin gender groups consisted of 1% males, 23% females, 47% mixed-sex, and 29% unknown (<italic>N</italic> = 2382 observations). Male only groups spent equal proportions of time foraging (50%) and travelling (50%) (<italic>N</italic> = 32); females in female groups spent more time foraging (62%) and resting (14%) (<italic>N</italic> = 539) than when in mixed-sex groups (39% and 5% respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g002">Figure 2</xref>). In mixed-sex groups females spent considerable time interacting with males (34%) (<italic>N</italic> = 1118). Significant differences were observed between the activity budgets of mixed-sex and female groups (X<sup>2</sup><sub>3</sub> = 181, df = 3, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g002">Figure 2</xref>). The mean female group size (excluding singletons) was 3.8 (SE 0.31, range 2–8) while the mean mixed-sex group size was 7.3 (SE 0.56, range 3–34).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0052987-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Frequency of dolphin behaviours for female (a), male (b), and mixed-sex (c) groups in the Clarence River estuary.</title>
            <p>* 76% of the total social interaction time (N = 442) of mixed-sex groups involved aggressive coercive behaviour.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Spatial patterns</title>
        <p>Groups of females occurred in all water depth categories, with 30% in deeper water, 34% in medium depths, and 35% in shallow water (X<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub> = 2.2, <italic>P</italic> = 0.35). However, there was a significant difference in the occurrence of mixed-sex groups with respect to depth categories; they were more often found in deeper water (71%) compared with medium (25%) or shallow (4%) water depths (X<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub> = 70.5, df = 2, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). The dolphin gender group sightings per season and water depth were significantly different between female (Kruskal-Wallis <italic>H</italic><sub>2</sub> = 91.7, df = 3, P&lt;0.001) and mixed-sex groups (Kruskal-Wallis <italic>H</italic><sub>2</sub> = 19.7, df = 3, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Female groups occurred in shallow water predominantly in winter, and in deeper water at similar frequencies among the seasons except in winter. They were not observed in shallow water during summer, which is the peak breeding season <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury3">[42]</xref>. Mixed-sex groups were predominantly observed in summer and spring in deeper water.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0052987-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Percentage of dolphin encounters in varying water depths for female and mixed-sex groups in the Clarence River estuary per season.</title>
            <p>The sum for the four seasons amounts to 100% for each water depth. Seasons are in order Spring, Summer, Autumn and Winter.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Coercive behaviour</title>
        <p>In the CR, 76% (<italic>N</italic> = 442) of the total social interaction time of mixed-sex groups involved aggressive coercive behaviour, which represents 14% (<italic>N</italic> = 336) of behaviours in the total behavioural budget recorded for all groups (<italic>N</italic> = 2382). The frequency of male coercive behaviour was significantly affected by water depth, with more occurring in deeper (52%) and medium (48%) depth than in shallow (2%) water (X<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub> = 44.2, df = 2, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001).</p>
        <p>The tidal phase had a significant effect on the occurrence of coercive behaviour with more coercive behaviour observed at high tide (36%) and at maximum flood (32%), with significantly less coercive behaviour at maximum ebb (24%) and at low (10%) tide (X<sup>2</sup><sub>3</sub> = 15.49, df = 3, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001). Significant seasonal differences were evident in the occurrence of coercive behaviour, with more occurring in winter (37%), autumn (32%), and spring (20%) and the least in summer (11%) (X<sup>2</sup><sub>3</sub> = 16.56, df = 3, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001). Mean dolphin group size (excluding singletons) during coercive behaviour was not significantly different (Mean 7.2, range 5–11) compared to periods when this behaviour did not occur (Mean = 5.8, range 2–34) (X<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub> = 1.225, <italic>P</italic> = 0.268).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Habitat use</title>
        <p>Analysis of habitat use using the fixed kernel density estimator analysis for different gender groups revealed that female gender groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g004">Figure 4</xref>) in the CR occupied a larger range of habitats than the mixed-sex groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Female groups utilized the small, shallow tributaries and travelled for longer distances up these smaller tributaries than the mixed-sex groups, which were concentrated more in the deeper main channel of the estuary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The core use areas for female groups included shallow areas of the channels near sand banks or breakwalls, whereas core use areas for mixed-sex groups were in deeper water in the main estuary channel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g004">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g005">5</xref>). Consequently, coercive behaviour was observed to be concentrated in the main estuary channel in deeper water and in an associated channel in medium water depth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g006">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0052987-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Female groups' kernel density estimator (KDE) for all behaviours from the Clarence River estuary (N = 539).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0052987-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Mixed-sex groups' kernel density estimates (KDE) for all behaviours from the Clarence River estuary (N = 1118).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0052987-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Mixed-sex groups' kernel density estimates (KDE) displaying aggressive coercive behaviour in the Clarence River estuary (N = 336).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052987.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Female and mixed-sex groups in the Clarence River estuary clearly have different distributions and habitat use patterns leading to social and spatial sexual segregation. Social and habitat segregation has also been found in sperm whales <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Whitehead1">[58]</xref>, beluga whales (<italic>Delphinapterus leucas</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Loseto1">[59]</xref>, and botos (<italic>Inia geoffrensis</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Martin1">[9]</xref>. Female bottlenose dolphins groups had a wider distribution and ventured into smaller, shallower channels of the estuary compared to mixed-sex groups, which predominantly used the deeper main estuary channel. Such spatial and habitat segregation and behavioural differences have also been reported in Northern elephant seals (<italic>Mirounga angustirostris</italic>) where females were predominantly foraging in deeper water on pelagic prey whereas males were closer to the coastline foraging mainly on benthic prey, and in Grey seals (<italic>Halichoerus grypus</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Breed1">[60]</xref>. In both of these seal species males are 1.5 to 10 times larger than females <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-LeBoeuf1">[61]</xref>, whereas bottlenose dolphins do not show a marked sexual dimorphism in size. It is not clear from our study whether behavioural and spatial differences are due to different energy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Main1">[62]</xref> and nutrient requirements due to lactation, or whether coercive behaviour by reproductively active males is contributing to spatial sexual segregation. The coercive behaviour used by male dolphins in our study is of particular interest, and its effect on the distribution of the female dolphin groups is discussed below, with respect to water depth and its relevance for mother and calf groups.</p>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Sexual segregation</title>
        <sec id="s4a1">
          <title>Grouping patterns and activity budgets</title>
          <p>Groups of female <italic>T. aduncus</italic> have been found to associate more with other females in a similar reproductive state than with females in different reproductive states <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Mller3">[63]</xref>. This was also observed in the CR, with females with calves tending to associate in a group with other females with calves (C. Fury, pers. obs.). Mixed-sex groups were found all year round, however, they were predominately found in the peak-breeding season of spring and summer (<italic>N</italic> = 19 and 17 respectively). CR female dolphins in female groups spent a greater proportion of their time foraging (CR: 62%), compared to when they were in a mixed-sex group (CR: 39%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052987-g002">Figure 2</xref>). A study on humpback whales (<italic>Megaptera novaeangliae</italic>) found that when female and calf pairs associated with multiple males they increased their time spent travelling and decreased their time at rest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Cartwright1">[64]</xref>, which would be energetically costly to both the mother and her calf. Hence, female dolphins might segregate from males because of different activity budgets.</p>
          <p>Differences in time spent feeding could however also be a reflection of higher food selectivity of females, less food availability in areas frequented by females and/or higher energetic demands during the period of offspring dependence. We are unable to identify the main causes of this behavioural difference. However, it has been proposed that sexual differences in activity budgets could cause social segregation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl2">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl3">[30]</xref>. To investigate whether sexual differences are large enough to lead to segregation, males in all male groups and mixed-sex groups should be compared to females in nursery groups and mixed-sex groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a2">
          <title>Predation risk</title>
          <p>Females with calves are likely to be more vulnerable to predation and should therefore use areas that are relatively safe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Michaud1">[65]</xref>. In Shark Bay, Western Australia, for example, tiger sharks (<italic>Galeocerdo cuvier</italic>) that are preying on calves, are found mostly in shallow water and their density is much greater in the warmer months (September–May) than during the cooler months (June–August) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Heithaus1">[66]</xref>. Studies on bottlenose dolphins and the effect of food availability and tiger shark predation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Heithaus1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Heithaus2">[67]</xref> found that when shark abundance was high, foraging dolphins greatly reduced their use of dangerous, but productive, shallow water patches and were found in relatively safer deep water areas. However the Shark Bay female dolphins' reproductive success was higher if they frequented the shallow water areas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Mann1">[68]</xref>. This suggests that the distributions of foraging dolphins may reflect a trade-off between predation risk and food availability.</p>
          <p>In the CR, the most common potential predators of dolphins would be bull sharks that are known to occur in estuaries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Heupel2">[69]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Matich1">[70]</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Last1">[71]</xref>, but most bull sharks that frequent estuaries are juveniles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Heupel1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Heupel2">[69]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Carlson1">[72]</xref>. In the CR, the female dolphins did not avoid any particular water depth and all of the estuary is &lt;20 m depth. Given that we do not know the distribution of adult bull sharks and their foraging patterns we do not now whether females with calves frequent estuaries to avoid attacks on their calves by adult bull sharks.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a3">
          <title>Prey selection</title>
          <p>The preferred prey items of CR dolphins are sea mullet (<italic>Mugil cephalus</italic>) and sand whiting (<italic>S. ciliata</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Fury2">[35]</xref>. Larger numbers of fish have been reported in shallow water compared to deep water in Australian estuaries. Specifically, a study in the Clarence River showed that the shallow vegetated habitats in the marine region have the greatest diversity and highest abundances of fish in the estuary <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-West2">[73]</xref>, therefore creating potentially more effective foraging habitats for mothers and calves. Female groups often frequented the Oyster Channel, a shallow tributary in the CR estuary where no mixed-sex groups were observed during surveys. Fish surveys in that channel have shown that the mean fish abundance peaks are in winter and spring <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-West1">[31]</xref>, when females, often with calves, were observed in the channel during surveys. Therefore, the use of these shallow water areas in the estuary by mothers and calves could be directly linked to the availability of prey species and may not be primarily driven by predator avoidance. In a monomorphic species, like <italic>T. aduncus</italic>, lactating females will have higher metabolic needs and might thus be expected to spend different proportions of their time feeding or select different prey items compared to males or non-reproducting females <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl4">[74]</xref>. Furthermore, calves need to learn to catch prey through their associations with mothers. Catching smaller prey, such as sand whiting (<italic>Sillago ciliata</italic>), is likely to be easier for calves in shallow compared to deep water. Calves begin to chase fish after a few months of age <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Mann2">[75]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Mann3">[76]</xref>. If fish are easier to catch and plentiful the question remains why male or mixed-sex groups do not seem to frequent these areas much. Breed <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Breed1">[60]</xref> found marked sexual segregation in grey seals and suggested that males and females might avoid scramble competition for food during important times of the year. Further investigation into diet preferences, scramble competition, and optimal foraging strategies by the different adult classes of dolphins is needed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a4">
          <title>Male Avoidance</title>
          <p>Male harrassment of females for breeding has been shown in various species, including but not limited to the boto (<italic>I. geoffrensis</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Martin1">[9]</xref>, dusky dolphins (<italic>Lagenorhynchus obscurus</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Weir1">[77]</xref>, Hector's Dolphin (<italic>Cephalorhynchus hectori</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Webster1">[6]</xref>, grizzly bears <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Wielgus2">[78]</xref>, polar bears <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Clark1">[79]</xref>, and ungulates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Bon1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Weckerly1">[13]</xref>. Male aggressive behaviour can drive females to alter their habitat use of an area, as was shown in a study on wild Trinidadian guppies (<italic>Poecilia reticulata</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Darden1">[80]</xref>. Male harassment and forced copulations are considered costly for females <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Hancox1">[81]</xref> as they and their calves can be injured or killed by males <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Martin1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Hancox1">[81]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Barnett1">[84]</xref>. Therefore, female bottlenose dolphins in the CR may be trying to avoid injury to themselves and their calves, especially during aggressive coercive behaviour, and thus segregate into shallow waters that are not frequented by these males.</p>
          <p>Most coercive behaviour recorded in the CR estuary occurred at high tide or flood tide in deeper water or medium depth water, while mixed-sex groups only occurred during low tide or ebb tide in deeper water. In shallower waters, the males might not be able to manoeuvre to mate effectively. The only times (N = 5) that herded females were observed escaping from the males was into shallower areas (C. Fury, unpublished obs.). Female dusky dolphins also have a lower likelihood of being harassed by males when occupying shallow waters and therefore shallow waters were considered to be a refuge from males <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052987-Weir1">[77]</xref>.</p>
          <p>Male coercive encounters in the CR often lasted for hours (range 18–159 mins, mean 68 mins). Our study showed that in winter (non-breeding season), when more coercive behaviour occurred, females and calves preferred shallow water, which may have been to avoid males. In contrast, in the summer peak-breeding season females were not observed in shallow water and occurred more often in the deeper water in mixed-sex groups, possibly to aid in mating and conception. Hence, females might segregate from males to avoid potential costs of associating with males in mixed-sex groups, while with a dependent calf.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Our study suggests that the bottlenose dolphins in the CR estuary are socially and spatially segregated. There are several factors that potentially contribute to the sexual segregation found in this species, including differences in activity budgets between males and females, the need for calves to learn to forage and capture prey in shallow waters, females with calves avoiding predation, and female avoidance of harrassment by males. Given the marked differences in activity budgets between female only and mixed-sex groups, it could be costly for females to frequent mixed-sex groups, except for reproduction. Habitat use by female dolphin groups in the CR estuary suggests that shallow areas of the estuary may provide a sanctuary from aggressive males, and access to suitable prey items and prey density for mothers and their calves, or a combination of these factors.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We are grateful assistance with fieldwork from Marjolijn van Stokkom, Kelly Toms and Kim Stewart. We thank Greg Luker for GIS advice and Dr Lyndon Brooks for statistical advice. Fieldwork was done under permit from the New South Wales Parks and Wildlife Service and ethics approval from Southern Cross University (NPWS S10404 and SCU no. 05/15).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruckstuhl</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Sexual segregation in ungulates: a comparative test of three hypotheses</article-title>. <source>Biological Reviews</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Wielgus1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wielgus</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bunnell</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Tests of hypotheses for sexual segregation in grizzly bears</article-title>. <source>Journal of Wildlife Management</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-MacFarlane1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacFarlane</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Boys will be boys: Social affinity among males drives social segregation in western grey kangaroos</article-title>. <source>Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Kovacs1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welke</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Sex and age segregation by <italic>Phoca vitulina</italic> concolor at haul-out sites during the breeding season in the Passamaquoddy Bay region, New Brunswick</article-title>. <source>Marine Mammal Science</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Stewart1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Ontogeny of differential migration and sexual segregation in northern elephant seals</article-title>. <source>Journal of Mammalogy</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>1101</fpage>–<lpage>1116</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Webster1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slooten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Evidence of Sex Segregation in Hector's Dolphin (<italic>Cephalorhynchus hectori</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Aquatic Mammals</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Laidre1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laidre</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heagerty</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heide Jorgensen</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Witting</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Sexual segregation of common minke whales (<italic>Balaenoptera acutorostrata</italic>) in Greenland, and the influence of sea temperature on the sex ratio of catches</article-title>. <source>ICES (International Council for the Exploration of the Sea) Journal of Marine Science</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>2253</fpage>–<lpage>2266</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Danilewicz1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danilewicz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Secchi</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bassoi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Habitat use patterns of franciscana dolphins (<italic>Pontoporia blainvillei</italic>) off southern Brazil in relation to water depth</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>943</fpage>–<lpage>949</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Martin1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>VMF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>River dolphins and flooded forest: seasonal habitat use and sexual segregation of botos (<italic>Inia geoffrensis</italic>) in an extreme cetacean environment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>263</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Conradt1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Conradt L (2005) Definitions, hypotheses, models and measures in the study of animal segregation. In: Ruckstuhl KE, Neuhaus P, editors. Sexual segregation in vertebrates: ecology of the two sexes. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. pp. 11–34.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Bon1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Unexplained sexual segregation in polygamous ungulates: a defence of an ontogenetic approach</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Processes</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Cransac1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cransac</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerard</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maublanc</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pepin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>An example of segregation between age and sex classes only weakly related to habitat use in mouflon sheep (<italic>Ovis gmelini</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>244</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Weckerly1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weckerly</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricca</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Sexual segregation in Roosevelt elk: cropping rates and aggression in mixed-sex groups</article-title>. <source>Journal of Mammalogy</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>825</fpage>–<lpage>835</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Heupel1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heupel</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeiser</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simpfendorfer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Long-term presence and movement patterns of juvenile bull sharks, <italic>Carcharhinus leucas</italic>, in an estuarine river system</article-title>. <source>Marine and Freshwater Research</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Croft1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piyapong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Predation risk as a driving force for sexual segregation: a cross-population comparison</article-title>. <source>American Naturalist</source> <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>867</fpage>–<lpage>878</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Connor1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smolker</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Two levels of alliance formation among male bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops</italic> sp.)</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Science USA</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Scott1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Scott MD, Wells RS, Irvine AB (1990) A long-term study of bottlenose dolphins on the west coast of Florida. In: Leatherwood S, Reeves RR, editors. The Bottlenose Dolphin. San Diego: Academic Press. pp. 235–244.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Wilson1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Habitat use by bottlenose dolphins: Seasonal distribution and stratified movement patterns in the Moray Firth, Scotland</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>1365</fpage>–<lpage>1374</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Parsons1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durban</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claridge</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balcomb</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Kinship as a basis for alliance formation between male bottlenose dolphins, <italic>Tursiops truncatus</italic>, in the Bahamas</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Connor2">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Connor RC, Wells R, Mann J, Read AJ (2000) The bottlenose dolphin: social relationships in a fission-fusion society. In: Mann J, Connor RC, Tyack PL, Whitehead H, editors. Cetacean Societies: Field Studies of Dolphins and Whales. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. pp. 91–126.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Mller1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Möller</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beheregaray</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harcourt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Association patterns and kinship in female Indo-Pacific bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops aduncus</italic>) of southeastern Australia</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Wells1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wells RS (2003) Dolphin social complexity: lessons from long-term study and life history. In: de Waal FBM, Tyack PL, editors. Animal Social Complexity: Intelligence, Culture, and Individualized Societies. Cambridge &amp; London: Harvard University Press. pp. 32–56.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Connor3">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson-Capps</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sherwin</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krützen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A new level of complexity in the male alliance networks of Indian Ocean bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops</italic> sp.)</article-title>. <source>Biology Letters</source></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Connor4">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heithaus</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barre</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Superalliance of bottlenose dolphins</article-title>. <source>Nature (London)</source> <volume>397</volume>: <fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Connor5">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Connor RC, Smolker RA, Richards AF (1992) Dolphin alliances and coalitions. In: Harcourt AH, de Waal FBM, editors. Coalitions and alliances in humans and other animals. Oxford, New York &amp; Tokyo: Oxford University Press. pp. 415–443.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Mller2">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Möller</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beheregaray</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harcourt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krützen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Alliance membership and kinship in wild male bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops aduncus</italic>) of southeastern Australia</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society Biological Sciences Series B</source> <volume>268</volume>: <fpage>1941</fpage>–<lpage>1947</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Wilson2">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The ecology of bottle-nosed dolphins, <italic>Tursiops truncatus</italic>, in the Moray Firth</article-title>. <source>European Research on Cetaceans</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Wilson3">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>An examination of the social structure of a resident group of bottle-nosed dolphins (<italic>Tursiops truncatus</italic>) in the Moray Firth, N.E. Scotland</article-title>. <source>European Research on Cetaceans</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl2">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruckstuhl</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kokko</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Modelling sexual segregation in ungulates: effects of group size, activity budgets and synchrony</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>909</fpage>–<lpage>914</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl3">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruckstuhl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Foraging behaviour and sexual segregation in bighorn sheep</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-West1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Comparison of fish and shrimp trawls for sampling deep-water estuarine fish in a large coastal river in eastern Australia</article-title>. <source>Fisheries Research</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>409</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Walsh1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Walsh S, Copeland C, Westlake M (2004) Major fish kills in the northern rivers of NSW in 2001: causes, impacts &amp; responses. Ballina: New South Wales Department of Primary Industries. 55 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Eyre1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eyre</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Regional evaluation of nutrient transformation and phytoplankton growth in nine river-dominated sub-tropical east Australian estuaries</article-title>. <source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source> <volume>205</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Fury1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fury</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Abundance, site fidelity and range patterns of Indo-Pacific bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops aduncus</italic>) in two Australian subtropical estuaries</article-title>. <source>Marine and Freshwater Research</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1015</fpage>–<lpage>1027</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Fury2">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fury</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Seasonal variation and tidal influences on estuarine use by bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops aduncus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Irvine1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Movements and activities of the Atlantic bottlenose dolphin, <italic>Tursiops truncatus</italic>, near Sarasota, Florida</article-title>. <source>Fishery Bulletin</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Altmann1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Observational study of behaviour: sampling methods</article-title>. <source>Behaviour</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Smuts1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smuts</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smuts</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Male aggression and sexual coercion of females in nonhuman primates and other mammals: evidence and theoretical implications</article-title>. <source>Advances in the Study of Behavior</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Muller1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahlenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emery Thompson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wrangham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Male coercion and the costs of promiscuous mating for female chimpanzees Proceedings of the Royal Society B:</article-title>. <source>Biological Sciences</source> <volume>274</volume>: <fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>1014</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Hildebrand1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hildebrand B (1997) Waypoint +. Version 1.8.03 ed.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Allen1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaudet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sayigh</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Fine-scale habitat selection of foraging bottlenose dolphins <italic>Tursiops truncatus</italic> near Clearwater, Florida</article-title>. <source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source> <volume>222</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Fury3">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fury CA (2009) Abundance, behaviour and habitat use patterns of Indo-Pacific bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops aduncus</italic>) in the Clarence and Richmond River estuaries in northern New South Wales, Australia [Ph.D. thesis]. Lismore: Southern Cross University. 212 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Seaman1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seaman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>An evaluation of the accuracy of kernel density estimators for home range analysis</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>2075</fpage>–<lpage>2085</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Hooge1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hooge PN, Eichenlaub B (2000) Animal Movement extension to ArcView. Version 2.0 ed. Anchorage, AK, USA: Alaska Science Center - Biological Science Office, U.S. Geological Survey.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Worton1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Worton</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Kernel methods for estimating the utilization distribution in home-range studies</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Gubbins1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gubbins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Use of home ranges by resident bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops truncatus</italic>) in a South Carolina estuary</article-title>. <source>Journal of Mammalogy</source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Silverman1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Silverman BW (1986) Density estimation for statistics and data analysis. London, UK: Chapman and Hall.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-VanWinkle1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Winkle</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Comparison of several probabilistic homerange models</article-title>. <source>Journal of Wildlife Management</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-White1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">White GC, Garrot RA (1990) Analysis of wildlife radio-tracking data. San Diego, USA: Academic Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Worton2">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Worton</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>A review of models of home range for animal movement</article-title>. <source>Ecological Modelling</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Worton3">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Worton</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Using Monte Carlo simulation to evaluate kernel-based home range estimators</article-title>. <source>Journal of Wildlife Management</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>794</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Seminoff1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seminoff</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Resendiz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Home range of green turtles Chelonia mydas at a coastal foraging area in the Gulf of California, Mexico</article-title>. <source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source> <volume>242</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Hooge2">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hooge P, Eichenlaub W, Solomon E (2001) Using GIS to analyze animal movements in the marine environment. In: Kruse G, Bez N, Booth A, Dorn M, Hills S, <etal>et al</etal>.., editors. Spatial processes and management of marine populations. Fairbanks: University of Alaska Sea Grant College. pp. 37–51.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Dyall1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Dyall A, Tobin G, Galinec V, Creasey J, Gallagher J, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2005) New South Wales coastal waterways geomorphic habitat mapping, version 2 (1∶100 000 scale digital data). Canberra: Geoscience Australia.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Fury4">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fury</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Impact of flood events on dolphin occupancy patterns</article-title>. <source>Marine Mammal Science</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>E185</fpage>–<lpage>E205</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-JMP1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">JMP Version 8 (2009) SAS Institute Inc. 8.0.2 ed. SAS Campus Drive, Cary, N.C.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-SPSS1">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">SPSS Version 17 (2008) SPSS for Windows. SPSS Inc. IBM Company Headquarters, Chicago, Illinois.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Whitehead1">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Whitehead H, Weilgart L (2000) The sperm whale: social females and roving males. In: Mann J, Connor RC, Tyack PL, Whitehead H, editors. Cetacean societies. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. pp. 154–172.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Loseto1">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loseto</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Segregation of Beaufort Sea beluga whales during the open-water season</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>1743</fpage>–<lpage>1751</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Breed1">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breed</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Sexual segregation of seasonal foraging habitats in a non-migratory marine mammal</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B</source> <volume>273</volume>: <fpage>2319</fpage>–<lpage>2326</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-LeBoeuf1">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Boeuf</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crocker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Foraging ecology of northern elephant seals</article-title>. <source>Ecological Monographs</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Main1">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Main</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Reconciling competing ecological explanations for sexual segregation in ungulates</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>704</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Mller3">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Möller</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harcourt</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Shared reproductive state enhances female associations in dolphins</article-title>. <source>Research Letters in Ecology</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Cartwright1">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Associations with multiple male groups increase the energy expenditure of humpback whale (<italic>Megaptera novaeangliae</italic>) female and calf pairs on the breeding grounds</article-title>. <source>Behaviour</source> <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>1573</fpage>–<lpage>1600</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Michaud1">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Michaud R (2005) Sociality and ecology of the odontocetes. In: Ruckstuhl KE, Neuhaus P, editors. Sexual segregation in Vertebrates: ecology of the two sexes. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. pp. 303–326.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Heithaus1">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heithaus</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Food availability and tiger shark predation risk influence bottlenose dolphin habitat use</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>480</fpage>–<lpage>491</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Heithaus2">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heithaus</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Does tiger shark predation risk influence foraging habitat use by bottlenose dolphins at multiple spatial scales?</article-title> <source>Oikos</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Mann1">
        <label>68</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barre</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heithaus</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Female reproductive success in bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops</italic> sp.): Life history, habitat, provisioning, and group-size effects</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Ecology</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Heupel2">
        <label>69</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heupel</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simpfendorfer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Estuarine nursery areas provide a low-mortality environment for young bull sharks <italic>Carcharhinus leucas</italic></article-title>. <source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source> <volume>433</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Matich1">
        <label>70</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heithaus</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Layman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Contrasting patterns of individual specialization and trophic coupling in two marine apex predators</article-title>. <source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Last1">
        <label>71</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Last PR, Stevens JD (1994) Sharks and Rays of Australia: CSIRO Australia. 513 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Carlson1">
        <label>72</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ribera</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conrath</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heupel</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Habitat use and movement patterns of bull sharks <italic>Carcharhinus leucas</italic> determined using pop-up satellite archival tags</article-title>. <source>Journal of Fish Biology</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>675</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-West2">
        <label>73</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Marine, brackish, and freshwater fish communities in the vegetated and bare shallows of an Australian coastal river</article-title>. <source>Estuaries</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Ruckstuhl4">
        <label>74</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ruckstuhl KE, Neuhaus P (2005) Sexual segregation in vertebrates: ecology of the two sexes. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 500 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Mann2">
        <label>75</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mann J, Sargeant B (2003) Like mother, like calf: the ontogeny of foraging traditions in wild Indian Ocean bottlenose dolphins (<italic>Tursiops</italic> sp.). In: Fragaszy DM, Perry S, editors. The Biology of Traditions: Models and Evidence. Cambridge, New York etc.: Cambridge University Press. pp. 236–266.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Mann3">
        <label>76</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smuts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Behavioral development in wild bottlenose dolphin newborns (<italic>Tursiops</italic> sp.)</article-title>. <source>Behaviour</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Weir1">
        <label>77</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duprey</surname><given-names>NMT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Würsig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dusky dolphin (<italic>Lagenorhynchus obscurus</italic>) subgroup distribution: are shallow waters a refuge for nursery groups?</article-title> <source>Canadian Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>1225</fpage>–<lpage>1234</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Wielgus2">
        <label>78</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wielgus</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bunnell</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Sexual segregation and female grizzly bear avoidance of males</article-title>. <source>Journal of Wildlife Management</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Clark1">
        <label>79</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stirling</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Habitat preferences of polar bears in the Hudson Bay lowlands during late summer and fall</article-title>. <source>Ursus</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Darden1">
        <label>80</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darden</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Male harassment drives females to alter habitat use and leads to segregation of the sexes</article-title>. <source>Biology Letters</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Hancox1">
        <label>81</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancox</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoskin</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Evening up the score: sexual selection favours both alternatives in the colour-polymorphic ornate rainbowfish</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>845</fpage>–<lpage>851</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Moquin1">
        <label>82</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moquin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruckstuhl</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Plasticity in the rumination behaviour of bighorn sheep: contrasting strategies between the sexes?</article-title> <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>1047</fpage>–<lpage>1053</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Milner1">
        <label>83</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>RNC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Booksmythe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jennions</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Backwell</surname><given-names>PRY</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The battle of the sexes? Territory acquisition and defence in male and female fiddler crabs</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>738</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052987-Barnett1">
        <label>84</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrantes</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Semmens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Site fidelity and sex-specific migration in a mobile apex predator: implications for conservation and ecosystem dynamics</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>1039</fpage>–<lpage>1048</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>