<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-18-35672</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Labor economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Employment</subject><subj-group><subject>Jobs</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical and statistical techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Metaanalysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Metaanalysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Education</subject><subj-group><subject>Educational attainment</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Labor economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Employment</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Database and informatics methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Database searching</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychological stress</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychological stress</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychological stress</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Just how miserable is work? A meta-analysis comparing work and non-work affect</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A meta-analysis comparing work and non-work affect</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Biskup</surname>
<given-names>Martin J.</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Project administration</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5976-6815</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>Seth</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Project administration</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bradley-Geist</surname>
<given-names>Jill C.</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="econtrib001"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Membere</surname>
<given-names>Ashley A.</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="econtrib001"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Psychology, George Mason University, Fairfax, VA, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>College of Business, University of Colorado, Colorado Springs, Colorado Springs, CO, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Stolarski</surname>
<given-names>Maciej</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Warsaw, POLAND</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="econtrib001">
<p>‡ These authors also contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">skaplan1@gmu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>5</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<elocation-id>e0212594</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>19</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>5</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Biskup et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594"/>
<abstract>
<p>Although we spend much of our waking hours working, the emotional experience of work, versus non-work, remains unclear. While the large literature on work stress suggests that work generally is aversive, some seminal theory and findings portray working as salubrious and perhaps as an escape from home life. Here, we examine the subjective experience of work (versus non-work) by conducting a quantitative review of 59 primary studies that assessed affect on working days. Meta-analyses of within-day studies indicated that there was no difference in positive affect (PA) between work versus non-work domains. Negative affect (NA) was higher for work than non-work, although the magnitude of difference was small (i.e., .22 <italic>SD</italic>, an effect size comparable to that of the difference in NA between different leisure activities like watching TV versus playing board games). Moderator analyses revealed that PA was relatively higher at work and NA relatively lower when affect was measured using “real-time” measurement (e.g., Experience Sampling Methodology) versus measured using the Day Reconstruction Method (i.e., real-time reports reveal a more favorable view of work as compared to recall/DRM reports). Additional findings from moderator analyses included significant differences in main effect sizes as a function of the specific affect, and, for PA, as a function of the age of the sample and the time of day when the non-work measurements were taken. Results for the other possible moderators including job complexity and affect intensity were not statistically significant.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>Publication of this article was funded in part by the George Mason University Libraries Open Access Publishing Fund. The authors received no other specific funding for this work.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="3"/>
<table-count count="6"/>
<page-count count="28"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the manuscript and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<disp-quote>
<p><italic>“This is the real secret of life -- to be completely engaged with what you are doing in the here and now</italic>. <italic>And instead of calling it work</italic>, <italic>realize it is play</italic>.<italic>”</italic> - Philosopher Alan W. Watts</p>
<p><italic>“Oh</italic>, <italic>you hate your job</italic>? <italic>Why didn’t you say so</italic>? <italic>There’s a support group for that</italic>. <italic>It’s called everybody</italic>, <italic>and they meet at the bar</italic>.<italic>”</italic> - Comedian Drew Carey</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>Paid work occupies a great deal of daily life for many people. On average, employed Americans work on about 60%-70% of their days and, on those days, spend about half their waking time working [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref001">1</xref>]. Given the amount of time we spend working, our well-being during that time is a matter of no small consequence, sometimes impacting decisions about whether, and how much, to work. The question of how the affective experience of work compares to that of non-work may be of increasing relevance today. This is due to the large numbers of baby-boomers reaching retirement age and making decisions as to whether/when to retire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref002">2</xref>] and in light of the current societal shift towards the “gig economy” of freelance and independent contracting work arrangements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref003">3</xref>]. The comparative experience of individuals’ well-being at work versus non-work also has potential implications for policy-makers who are interested in shaping strategies to promote societal well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref004">4</xref>].</p>
<p>So, just how do people feel in work versus in non-work activities and locations? Anecdotal evidence (see contrasting quotes above), theoretical perspectives, and empirical studies suggest very different conclusions about the emotional experience of work. At one extreme, classical economic theories regard work as “disutility” - being an inherently unpleasant activity that individuals engage in solely for instrumental financial purposes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref005">5</xref>]. Indeed, many definitions of “work” include the notion of <italic>obligation</italic> or “obligated time,” while “leisure” is characterized as the “antithesis of work, or “non-obligated time” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref006">6</xref>]. This characterization of work as the less desirable contrast to non-work is also a prominent feature of scientific management, piece-rate compensation schemes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref007">7</xref>], and popular accounts of work such as in Studs Terkel’s classic book “Working” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref008">8</xref>].</p>
<p>In contrast to the above, some psychologists and sociologists have offered a very different perspective – making claim to the possible well-being <italic>benefits</italic> of work(ing). For instance, Jahoda posited that work provides people with various non-financial benefits (e.g., time structure, social contact) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref009">9</xref>]. Hochschild presented data supporting the claim that in modern society, the workplace provides people with a sense of achievement and belonging, whereas home life has become increasingly stressful [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref010">10</xref>]. Similarly, Csikszentmihalyi and LeFevre noted “the paradoxical situation of people having many more positive feelings at work than in leisure” (p. 821) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref011">11</xref>]. Furthermore, eudaimonic perspectives such as Self-Determination Theory highlight the benefits that work can provide in the form of personal growth, meaning, and intrinsic motivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref012">12</xref>].</p>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>The primary study question and approach</title>
<p>In the current research, we examine the veracity of these different perspectives regarding the relative emotional experience of work versus non-work. To do so, we compare employees’ reported positive affect (PA) and negative affect (NA) regarding work versus non-work, both in terms of activity and location. Specifically, we conducted meta-analyses of within-person studies wherein people provide ratings of PA and/or NA <italic>both</italic> at, and away from, work. Using this strategy, mean levels in PA or NA would indicate differences in felt affect across domains. Additionally, we examine a number of moderators which allow for further insight into the puzzle behind the seemingly discrepant views outlined above on how people feel about/during/doing work. Indeed, a key impetus behind the current meta-analyses was that of testing for potential moderators which might explain <italic>when</italic>, <italic>why</italic>, and <italic>for whom</italic> affective experiences of work tend to be more (or less) favorable than non-work.</p>
<p>As such, we see this meta-analysis as making two primary contributions. First, it provides evidence about the relative role of work and non-work experiences with respect to psychological well-being. While a substantial body of work exists examining the interface of work and non-work domains and on affective spillover among those domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref013">13</xref>], few studies explicitly seek to directly compare the relative emotional experience of work versus non-work.</p>
<p>This oversight seems problematic as results regarding this issue can inform decision-making at various levels. At the individual level, results from the current study may guide decisions about how to spend one’s time (to the degree people have choice in doing so). As mentioned above, for an increasing number of people, work can be, in many ways, “optional” or discretionary, such as for some potential retirees [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref002">2</xref>]. Also, with a shift toward freelancing and other contingent (non-traditional) work arrangements comes increasing discretion with regard to what, when, where, and how people work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref003">3</xref>].</p>
<p>At the governmental level, the comparative experience of well-being at work versus non-work has implications for policy aimed at promoting societal well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref004">4</xref>]. To this point, discussions are underway by business and political leaders speculating as to the possible impacts of technological change and automation of work on the well-being of individuals and on the well-being of society. One possible policy-level approach to the much-feared mass displacement of workers by machines/automation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref014">14</xref>], is that of a “basic income” which would be received by members of a society “no strings attached” - no work required. The idea - which has received favor from leaders both past and present, including the likes of Elon Musk, Richard Branson, and Milton Friedman - is, in fact, currently being tested in Finland in a real-world “social experiment” of sorts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref014">14</xref>]. The Finnish government is providing a select number of residents with a basic income (amounting to approximately the equivalent of $16,000 annually) for two years and assessing the impact on recipients’ well-being and their decisions about how to spend their time if no longer “required” to earn money to live [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref014">14</xref>].</p>
<p>Beyond addressing the question of whether work is "better" or "worse" than non-work, a second intended contribution of the current study derives from its ability to explore moderators which speak to potentially important conceptual and methodological issues in the work and the affect literatures. For example, from a theoretical perspective, these findings can provide insight about the relative importance of different purported contributors to psychological benefits of work. For instance, one moderator we address is whether there are differences in work versus non-work affect when work is measured/recorded as a location (i.e., the workplace) versus as an activity (i.e., working). Findings that people feel relatively better (i.e., higher PA/lower NA) when work is an <italic>activity</italic> (as compared to work as <italic>location</italic>) would suggest that psychological benefits of work largely owe to task-related processes and phenomena such as cognitive busyness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref009">9</xref>] and goal progress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref015">15</xref>]. Conversely, the opposite finding would imply that non-task elements of work (e.g., socializing with colleagues or simply being away from home) are responsible for these benefits. We describe other examples in the following pages.</p>
<p>To investigate these questions, we incorporated studies that used methodologies seeking to capture/approximate experiential affect (as opposed to one-time recall/summary affect reports). Specifically, we included studies using one of two different methodologies - experience sampling methodology (ESM) or the day reconstruction method (DRM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref016">16</xref>]. In studies using real-time methods (ESM), employees report their current affect (e.g., <italic>how do you feel right now</italic>?) throughout the day [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref017">17</xref>]. In DRM studies, individuals reconstruct the previous day by listing the time and content of their activities and then reporting how they felt during each episode [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref016">16</xref>] These methodologies are now prevalent in psychology and management research, partly supplanting one-time affect assessments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref017">17</xref>].</p>
<p>An alternative approach to addressing the main questions would have been to compare one-time, overall assessments of how individuals feel “in general” about work and non-work. However, these assessments capture psychological constructions or overall evaluations of well-being (e.g., about domains) rather than the moment-to-moment affective experiences of interest here [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref018">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref019">19</xref>]. Owing to these differences in terms of construct representation and response process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref018">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref020">20</xref>], the relative reported favorability of a particular activity can vary dramatically using episodic versus one-time evaluative measurements. As an illustration of this phenomenon, individuals report “interacting with one’s children” as being very enjoyable <italic>in general</italic>, yet report <italic>specific episodes</italic> of interaction with one’s children as among the lowest/worst activities in terms of positive affect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref016">16</xref>]. As others have noted, no given method to assess well-being is unequivocally “superior” to other methods, <italic>per se</italic>; rather, the phenomenon/question of interest should guide the choice among them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref018">18</xref>]. Given the current focus on the real-time emotional phenomenology of these domains, including studies incorporating episodic measurements of affect seemed most appropriate.</p>
<p>Returning to the main research question as to whether and how affective experiences of work compare with non-work affective experience, the existing evidence seems to paint a somewhat mixed picture. Consistent with the notion that work provides various psychological benefits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref009">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref021">21</xref>] and represents a reprieve from home life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref010">10</xref>], some studies seem to cast work in a favorable light. For example, Snir and Zohar found positive affect at work to be at least as high as during leisure activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref022">22</xref>]. Another study showed that work was more “exciting” than leisure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref023">23</xref>]. Still other findings (many of which were not focused on the affective experience of work) indicate that work affect is more <italic>similar to</italic> - versus <italic>distinct/different from</italic> - affect in other life domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref024">24</xref>]. These findings call into question the notion that work is a less favorable affective experience than non-work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, several large-scale studies suggest a more decidedly negative role for work in terms affect. For example, several DRM studies have found that affective well-being at work is among the lowest of the various activities for which people reported their affect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref016">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref025">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref027">27</xref>]. Also, in a recent, very large ESM investigation of approximately 1.5 million observations from 20,000 individuals, the researchers reported that work ranked <italic>second lowest</italic> in happiness among 39 daily activities; the activity with the lowest happiness rating being “sick in bed” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref028">28</xref>]. Results such as these perhaps suggest that the studies noted above showing work as relatively more favorable are anomalies, possibly owing to smaller sample sizes or study-specific features. Indeed, what seemingly makes those findings and also ideas like Hochschild’s Time Bind [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref010">10</xref>] and the concept of “flow” at work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref011">11</xref>] intriguing is that they contradict the intuitive, common-wisdom notion of work as disutility. Taken together then, the available evidence is somewhat mixed (prompting this meta-analysis) but appears to favor the prediction that people tend to report higher PA and lower NA for non-work (versus work) contexts and activities.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1a</italic>: <italic>Mean-level PA will be higher away from work than at work</italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1b</italic>: Mean-level <italic>NA will be higher at work than away from work</italic>.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Study moderators</title>
<p>While we do offer main effect hypotheses, the mixed evidence above – along with intuition – suggest that there also is considerable variability in work versus non-work affective experiences. Thus, we also examined several moderators of the overall relationships. Specifically, we investigated moderators related to the measurement of affect and related to contextual (i.e., work or non-work) and demographic factors.</p>
<p>One set of moderators we considered involves the measurement of affect. Important to note is that, although we refer to these moderators as reflecting aspects of measurement, the proposed mechanisms underlying their potential effects refer to substantive theoretical phenomena or considerations. For example, for the ESM versus DRM moderator, we propose that the two measurement approaches may capture distinct evaluative processing involved in affective experiences (and in the <italic>reporting</italic> of affective experiences). As such, we regard the moderators (results) as speaking to theoretical questions/issues, rather than just reflecting measurement artifacts.</p>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Measurement method: ESM versus DRM</title>
<p>The first possible moderator we consider is whether affect is conceptualized and operationalized using 1) real-time measures capable of capturing moment-to-moment changes/differences (e.g., Experience Sampling Methodology (ESM); or 2) recall/summary measures of affect (i.e., the Day Reconstruction Method; DRM). Kahneman and colleagues developed the DRM as an alternative to ESM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref016">16</xref>]. Specifically, the DRM is mean to capture momentary affect in a manner that is less invasive and burdensome for participants than is ESM. In that seminal paper, the authors note strong correlations between data points collected using the two respective approaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref016">16</xref>]. However, the handful of other studies comparing the methods have not confirmed this equivalence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref029">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref030">30</xref>].</p>
<p>Noting these discrepancies, Diener and Tay called for more systematic investigations comparing these methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref031">31</xref>]. The present meta-analysis offers an opportunity to conduct such a large-scale comparison. More fundamentally, this analysis also can help yield insight into (potentially) distinct experiences of affect (as captured by the respective approaches). Although evidence is mixed, and explanations for potential differences are only speculative at this point [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref031">31</xref>], we ultimately concluded that there is sufficient evidence to offer a hypothesis here.</p>
<p>In particular, we hypothesize that ESM comparisons of work versus non-work will portray work more favorably compared to DRM comparisons. Answering Diener and Tay’s call to examine whether situational stereotypes may explain divergent findings from the methodologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref031">31</xref>], we propose that this effect results from the differential impact of such stereotypes in the two approaches. Specifically, we suggest that abstractions (i.e., prototypes/stereotypes) of work versus non-work will play a larger role in DRM ratings than in ESM ratings.</p>
<p>We base this argument on Construal Level Theory (CLT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref032">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref033">33</xref>]. According to CLT, people may construe of objects and events at differing levels of abstraction ranging from high-level construals (represented in terms of a few abstract features) to low-level construals (represented in terms of concrete and incidental details). The level of abstraction employed in a particular situation depends largely on the <italic>psychological distance</italic> associated with the object or event. In general, CLT proposes that greater psychological distance (whether temporal, spatial, etc.) is associated with higher-level (versus lower-level) construals. According to Trope and Liberman, these higher-level construals not only are more abstract than low-level construals, but they also tend to be simple, decontextualized, and “primary” or “core” in terms of containing the essential/prototypical elements of the object or event [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref033">33</xref>].</p>
<p>We present a brief illustration of the basic idea of CLT within the context of the current study. In thinking about work <italic>yesterday</italic>, the relative temporal ‘nearness’ should encourage low-level construals which incorporate particular details of one’s work day (e.g., a meeting scheduled with a particular person at a particular time on a particular topic). In contrast, when thinking about work <italic>last month</italic>, or about one’s job more <italic>generally</italic>, the relatively greater psychological/temporal distance should encourage high-level construals which incorporate abstractions and the core/primary elements of one’s work as opposed to very specific tasks and activities associated with a particular workday. Support for CLT comes from studies on a wide-range of topics, employing a wide range of methodologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref033">33</xref>].</p>
<p>Applying CLT here, this theory would seem to imply that, compared to DRM studies, investigations employing real-time methods (e.g., ESM) should encourage low-level construals. This is because the psychological/temporal distance between the participants’ rating is less (i.e., “nearer”) than when participants’ rating is separated in time from the actual experience - as in DRM. Because of the greater temporal distance between the <italic>lived experience</italic> of a work event and the <italic>re-lived experience</italic> of that event in DRM (versus in real-time studies), we expect a corresponding tendency for work to be thought about in more abstract terms here. In turn, we propose that individuals’ held <italic>schemas</italic> about work and working should have a greater influence on reports of affect in DRM studies than in real-time studies.</p>
<p>Thus, to the extent that held schemas about work(ing) tend to skew negative, results of DRM studies likewise should reflect this more negative schema of work. In contrast, because real-time studies should reduce psychological distance and foster lower-level construals, there should be less incorporation of generalized negative schemas about work. While we were not able to locate any theories or direct evidence suggesting that schemas about work(ing) are especially negative, there certainly are bountiful examples from outside the academic literature of work being portrayed as aversive (e.g. portrayals of work in music and in literature). Thus, while there obviously also are counter-examples of work being cast in positive terms, the notion that work more so is conceived in unfavorable terms seems reasonable.</p>
<p>Important to note is that, in making this prediction, we are not implying the superiority of one method over the other one [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref018">18</xref>]. Rather, we are suggesting the methods capture partly unique affective experiences - affect experienced in the moment (in ESM studies) versus reconstructed affect that incorporates previously held schemas along with reflection about the occurrence in question. As we elaborate upon in the Discussion section, theory and practical study considerations should dictate choice between these approaches.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>H2a</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean PA away from work versus at work (as proposed in</italic></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1a) will be smaller in real-time studies than in DRM studies</italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>H2b</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean NA at work versus away from work (as proposed in</italic></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1b) will be smaller in real-time studies than in DRM studies</italic>.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Operationalization of work: Work as an activity versus as a location</title>
<p>A second potential measurement-related moderator is the operationalization of “work(ing).” In some primary studies included here, work is conceptualized as an activity (i.e., people report that they are/were “working” at a given time). In other studies, work is conceptualized as a domain/location (i.e., people report being at their job location). We see two possibilities regarding the potential effects of this difference in wording.</p>
<p>Borrowing from CLT, one possibility is that reporting about work as an <italic>activity</italic> will result in more contextualized processing (i.e., lower-level construals that are more specific versus abstract generalizations). As such, when reporting about “working” or “doing work,” people’s reported affect should coincide more closely with, or rely on reference to, the actual activities they are completing as opposed to relying on more general abstractions about “work” in a broad, non-task-specific sense. In contrast, when reporting about work as a <italic>location</italic>, there may be a greater disconnect between reported affect and the behaviors or activities in which people are/were engaged. Rather, such reports may allow for a relatively greater influence of schematic thoughts about work versus non-work to color those reports. Again, insofar as there exists a schema of work being aversive, reports of affect between work and non-work should deviate more so in the latter case. As a result of these proposed processes, work should be reported as especially unpleasant relative to non-work when it represents a location.</p>
<p>An alternative notion - and, in turn, prediction - also seems plausible. When people report their affect “at work” (as a location), they may be referencing experiences/activities that are not actually “work” as defined by their job descriptions/roles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref034">34</xref>]. Instead, they also may be engaging in and reporting about activities that are perceived as discretionary and favorable, such as socializing with coworkers. As such, affect reports based on work-as-location may lead to relatively higher levels of PA and lower levels of NA as compared to affect reports based on work-as-activity, the latter of which should reflect only task-related activities. Clearly, both of these suggestions are speculative, owing in part to a lack of relevant data regarding how people <italic>think about their work</italic>. Given what we perceive as speculative and equally plausible alternative predictions, we offer competing hypotheses.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>H3a</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean PA away from work versus at work (as proposed in Hypothesis 1a) will be smaller in studies that operationalize work as an activity than in studies that define work as a location</italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>H3b</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean NA at work versus away from work (as proposed in Hypothesis 1b) will be smaller in studies that operationalize work as an activity than in studies that define work as a location</italic>. <italic>VERSUS</italic></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>H3c</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean PA away from work versus at work (as proposed in Hypothesis 1a) will be larger in studies that operationalize work as an activity than in studies that define work as a location</italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>H3d</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean NA at work versus away from work (as proposed in Hypothesis 1b) will be larger in studies that operationalize work as an activity than in studies that define work as a location</italic>.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Nature of affect</title>
<p>The primary focus of the meta-analysis is on potential differences in generalized PA and NA between work and non-work. In addition to valence, though, affect varies along a number of other dimensions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref035">35</xref>]. Thus, we also examine affect in two additional ways beyond valence. First, applying the conceptualization of affect varying along the dimensions of valence and intensity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref036">36</xref>], we explore whether affect intensity moderates the PA and NA findings. In addition to adopting the dimensional view of affect, we also applied the discrete view and examined potential differences between work and non-work affect for specific types of affect (e.g., anger versus anxiety). The decision to consider discrete forms of affect derived from the considerable research showing that even moods and emotions of the same valence and similar intensity are associated with different patterns of cognitive appraisal and action tendencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref037">37</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref038">38</xref>]. While one conceivably could bring theories to bear in making predictions for these two potential moderators, we opted to follow a more exploratory approach here. This was because theoretical predictions are seemingly not obvious for intensity and, while perhaps more possible regarding specific types of affect, were not always testable due to constraints in the number of primary studies assessing particular types.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Measurement day</title>
<p>Measurement day refers to whether estimates of non-work affect included only measurements made on workdays (e.g., after coming home from one’s job that day) or on both work and non-work days (e.g., weekends). This distinction is potentially meaningful given some research showing that mood is improved during the weekend relative to weekdays [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref039">39</xref>]. Ultimately, we determined that existing theory and evidence were not sufficient to allow for a formal hypothesis about this factor; moreover, the information reported in the constituent studies did not always allow for adequate/conclusive coding of whether (or to what extent) individuals’ affect reports were made on the weekend versus during the workweek.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Measurement schedule</title>
<p>Measurement schedule refers to the timing of the non-work measurements during the workday. In each study, employees reported their non-work affect before work, after work, or both before and after work. Evidence suggests that there are diurnal rhythms to both positive and negative affect. PA tends to increase during the day, perhaps leveling off in the afternoon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref040">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref041">41</xref>]. There also is evidence that NA tends to decrease during the day [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref040">40</xref>], but this pattern is less strong than the one for PA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref041">41</xref>]. This is because external events (that can occur at any time) seem to drive negative affect more so than do internal biological systems regulating diurnal rhythms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref041">41</xref>]. Still, findings imply that work should be rated as especially aversive when non-work affect (and especially PA) is measured later in the day. We do not offer specific hypotheses for time of day as a potential moderator, in part due to the speculative nature of the above reasoning, and in part owing to the fact that primary studies seldom report specific timings of measurements on the 24-hour clock (e.g., “after work” affect reports could occur at 5 pm or 10 pm, or any other number of times).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Job complexity</title>
<p>We also examined potential moderators reflecting the nature of one’s job and one’s non-work life/ demographic factors. The inclusion of these variable derives from the intuitive notion that the degree to which time spent at work is more or less pleasant than time spent elsewhere depends on the nature/characteristics of these two factors/domains.</p>
<p>Turning first to the nature of work, studies document that various job features are associated with salubrious psychological outcomes, including higher PA and lower NA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref042">42</xref>]. To capture the many characteristics that potentially lead to differences, we coded for job complexity. Borrowing from other theory and findings, we propose that more complex jobs offer psychological advantages including the opportunity to use and develop a greater amount of knowledge and skills and also more control over one’s work decisions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref043">43</xref>]. As such, work-related PA should be relatively higher and work-related NA relatively lower for employees with more complex jobs. This leads to the following predictions.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>H4a</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean PA away from work versus at work (as proposed in</italic></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1a) will be smaller for samples with higher job complexity</italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>H4b</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean NA away from work versus at work (as proposed in</italic></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1b) will be smaller for samples with higher job complexity</italic>.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Educational attainment</title>
<p>We also examined the educational level of the study participants as a potential moderator. We propose that work will be associated with relatively higher PA and lower NA (than non-work) for employees with greater educational attainment for two reasons. First, studies document that education level is positively correlated with various job characteristics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref044">44</xref>] that, in turn, predict greater well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref043">43</xref>]. Also, the higher incomes associated with more educational attainment can help reduce hassles and life events that can occur during non-work time (e.g., not being able to afford healthcare for oneself or one’s family) that negatively impact well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref016">16</xref>]. Thus, we propose the following hypotheses.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>H5a</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean PA away from work versus at work (as proposed in</italic></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1a) will be smaller for samples with higher educational attainment</italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>H5b</italic>: <italic>The difference between mean NA away from work versus at work (as proposed in</italic></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1b) will be smaller for samples with higher educational attainment</italic>.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Other non-work factors</title>
<p>We also reasoned that one’s circumstances and experiences outside of work could impact affect in that domain (e.g., at home) as well as affect at work (e.g., through family-to-work conflict). Thus, we examined multiple life-circumstance/ demographic variables as potential moderators – namely, the average age of the sample, the proportions of men and women in the sample, and the proportion of the sample that was cohabitating or married (versus living alone).</p>
<p>There is some indirect evidence suggesting directional propositions for these factors. For example, because some research demonstrates a positive relationship between age and job satisfaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref045">45</xref>], positive affect also reasonably should be relatively higher at work for older samples, while negative affect may be lower. Ultimately, though, we concluded that because the supportive evidence relates to attitudinal measures or overall well-being rather than to affect per se, operating in an exploratory manner here was appropriate.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Literature search</title>
<p>We conducted a broad search using the Science Direct databases (PsycInfo, PsycArticles) with the following search terms: “experience sampling,” “event* sampling,” “ESM,” “day reconstruction,” “DRM,” “ecological momentary,” “EMA,” “ambulatory assessment,” or “daily diary.” We also searched the Web of Science database using our initial search terms in combination with the following terms: “mood,” “emotion*,” affect,” or “well*being.” We did not specify start dates for any of the searches. The Science Direct databases contain comprehensive records dating back to the late 1800’s. The Web of Science database contains records dating back to 1900. The searches concluded in October, 2015. Also in October 2015, we conducted a targeted Google Scholar search for any additional datasets published by authors of existing usable datasets we previously had located.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Criteria for inclusion</title>
<p>Our inclusion criteria were the following: (1) sample of employed adults, excluding undergraduate student samples and clinical treatment groups, (2) use of real-time or short-term retrospective methods to measure affect during the current or previous day, (3) study included at least one emotion that could be categorized as either PA or NA, or included a measure of PA and/or NA, and (4) study design included measurement of affect during work and during non-work on the same day(s). Regarding the fourth requirement, we did include studies that measured affect on days when participants were not working (e.g., weekends) provided that both work and non-work also were assessed on the same day other day(s).</p>
<p>We identified approximately 350 studies that met these criteria. However, the majority of these studies did not report descriptive statistics separately for work and non-work affect as was required for the analyses. In those cases, we contacted the corresponding author via email (and, with a second message in cases of non-response) to request the necessary information. For approximately 10% of our requests, authors provided us with necessary information – either statistics or raw data – for the analyses.</p>
<p>For nineteen papers and two publically available data sets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref046">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref047">47</xref>], we computed the required statistics directly from raw data. We did so using the following method. First, we calculated average PA and NA associated with work and non-work, respectively, for each day for each participant. Next, we calculated person averages by aggregating across days for each participant. Finally, from these person averages we calculated sample averages and standard deviations for PA and NA that were in turn used for computing ESs.</p>
<p>The final database included 57 published papers or dissertations and the two publicly available datasets for which we were able to calculate relevant effects. Corresponding references are provided in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212594.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212594.g001">Fig 1</xref> is a flow diagram depicting the inclusion process for the final 57 studies. For PA, these studies provided 51 effect sizes based on a total sample of 37,472 participants and an estimated 1.6 million measurement occasions. For NA, these studies provided 53 effect sizes based on a total sample of 16,970 participants and an estimated 300,000 measurement occasions. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0212594.t001">Table 1</xref> provides additional sample characteristics. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212594.s002">S1 Table</xref> provides the full details from the primary studies.</p>
<fig id="pone.0212594.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>PRISMA flow diagram for studies included in and excluded from the meta-analysis.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pone.0212594.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Summary of included studies.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0212594.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Study Characteristics</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Positive Affect</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Negative Affect</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center"><italic>K</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>N</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>K</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>N</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement method</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Real-time</td>
<td align="center">37</td>
<td align="center">24,876</td>
<td align="center">39</td>
<td align="center">4,473</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    DRM</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center">12,011</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center">12,005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Operationalization of work</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Location</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">3,282</td>
<td align="center">37</td>
<td align="center">4,005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Activity</td>
<td align="center">18</td>
<td align="center">33,857</td>
<td align="center">13</td>
<td align="center">12,635</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement day</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Workdays only</td>
<td align="center">34</td>
<td align="center">7,763</td>
<td align="center">37</td>
<td align="center">8,050</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Workdays and weekends</td>
<td align="center">17</td>
<td align="center">29,709</td>
<td align="center">16</td>
<td align="center">8,920</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement schedule away from work</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Before work only</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">68</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">103</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    After work only</td>
<td align="center">11</td>
<td align="center">927</td>
<td align="center">11</td>
<td align="center">924</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Before and after work</td>
<td align="center">36</td>
<td align="center">36,343</td>
<td align="center">37</td>
<td align="center">15,809</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Total</td>
<td align="center">51</td>
<td align="center">37,472</td>
<td align="center">53</td>
<td align="center">16,970</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Coding of studies and operationalization of variables</title>
<p>All four authors were involved in coding studies. First, all authors coded a common subset of studies to ensure consistent interpretations and to allow for refinement of decision rules. Subsequently, two authors (the first author and one of the three other authors) coded each of the remaining studies.</p>
<p>Agreement between coders was generally strong. Most discrepancies reflected typos or mistakes in extracting information from papers or data sets. For more substantive discrepancies, the authors reached agreement through discussion of the study parameters and inclusion criteria. We calculated agreement between each pair of coders prior to resolution of the discrepancies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref048">48</xref>]. Initial agreement was 77.9% for affect categorization (i.e., whether an emotion was appropriately categorized as PA or NA) and averaged 80.2% for moderator variables (range across moderators = 72.1 – 88.5%).</p>
<p>For studies that reported discrete affect variables (e.g., happy, anxious), we categorized those variables as an aspect of either PA or NA based on the PANAS-X manual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref049">49</xref>]. A discrete emotion was categorized as PA if it was consistent with either the General Dimension Scale for PA or any of the Basic Positive Emotion Scales (i.e., Joviality, Self-Assurance, Attentiveness). Similarly, a discrete emotion was categorized as NA if it was consistent with the General Dimension Scale for NA or any of the Basic Negative Emotion Scales (i.e., Fear, Hostility, Guilt, Sadness). We also categorized stress as NA if the items composing the measure were consistent with Watson and Clark [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref049">49</xref>] or when the emotion was simply stated (e.g., “I feel stressed”). In addition to recording information necessary for calculating main effects, we also coded the following study-level variables as potential moderators: measurement method, operationalization of work, measurement day, measurement schedule, affect intensity, job complexity, educational attainment, age, gender, and relationship status.</p>
<p>We first describe the operationalizations of potential moderators related to the measurement of affect and then those related to contextual work and demographic factors. <italic>Measurement method</italic> refers to a binary variable denoting whether the study used 1) <italic>real-time</italic> measures of affect (e.g., ESM, ecological momentary assessment (EMA); or 2) the DRM. <italic>Operationalization of work</italic> is a binary variable referring to whether a given study defined and measured “work” in terms of 1) an <italic>activity</italic> (i.e., “working” or “doing” work) versus; 2) as a <italic>location</italic> (i.e., “at the office/workplace”). <italic>Measurement day</italic> is a binary variable created to distinguish between studies in which estimates of non-work affect included measurements on 1) <italic>workdays only</italic> (i.e., excluded any measurements from weekends and other non-working days) or; on 2) <italic>both</italic> work and non-work days (i.e., <italic>workdays and weekends</italic>). <italic>Measurement schedule</italic> pertains to the timing of the non-work measurements: 1) <italic>before work only</italic>; 2) <italic>after work only</italic>; or 3) <italic>before and after work</italic>. Last, <italic>intensity of affect</italic> refers to the overall level of activation or arousal associated with a measure of affect. For each study, we calculated the intensity of PA and/or NA as the average arousal of the measure’s items, utilizing arousal established norms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref050">50</xref>].</p>
<p>Turning to the work and non-work factors, we followed others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref051">51</xref>] in operationalizing <italic>job complexity</italic> using the O*NET “Job Zones” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref052">52</xref>]. A Job Zone is a group of occupations that are similar in how much overall experience, education, and on-the-job training people need to be able to do the work. There are five Job Zones, ranging from 1 (little or no preparation) to 5 (extensive preparation). Since most of the samples were mixed in terms of jobs, we calculated weighted averages when studies reported the information allowing us to do so (e.g., [% Zone 1]*[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref001">1</xref>] + [% Zone 2]*[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref002">2</xref>] + [% Zone 3]*[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref003">3</xref>] + [% Zone 4]*[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref004">4</xref>] + [% Zone 5]*[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref005">5</xref>]). However, the majority of studies in our sample did not provide enough information to calculate this composite score. Therefore, we contacted study authors and asked them to report the percentage of the sample that corresponded to each of the job zones. Some authors did send us raw data consisting of participants’ job titles. In these cases, two coders (the first author and one additional author) coded each of job titles using O*NET. Agreement between the composite scores created by the two coders was generally strong and did not lead to different analysis conclusions. Therefore, we report results for job complexity based on the average of the two coders’ ratings. In total, we were able to make assessments for 16 studies that covered a range of overall job complexity (<italic>M</italic> = 3.39; <italic>SD</italic> = 0.93).</p>
<p>Regarding the remaining potential moderators, we coded <italic>educational attainment</italic> as the percent of the sample with a bachelor’s degree or higher. <italic>Age</italic> refers to the average age of participants in the sample, and <italic>gender</italic> is the percent of the sample that was female. Last, <italic>relationship status</italic> was coded as the percent of the sample that was married or cohabitating.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Effect sizes</title>
<p>At the individual study level, effect sizes (ES) were calculated as the mean standardized difference between work PA/NA and non-work PA/NA, (<italic>M</italic><sub>work</sub> – <italic>M</italic><sub>non-work</sub>)/<italic>SD</italic><sub>pooled</sub>. Positive ESs indicated that affect (either PA or NA) was higher for work than non-work. A number of studies reported multiple estimates for either work or non-work affect. In these cases, we typically calculated simple averages within each domain before computing an ES. For example, if two time points were associated with work, one in the morning and one in the afternoon, we averaged the two time points for the overall analyses.</p>
<p>However, some studies reported additional information that allowed us to calculate weighted averages. Real-time studies sometimes reported N (i.e., the number of surveys completed) separately for each time point. For example, an article could mention that there were 1,000 assessments of affect “after work” but only 900 assessments of affect “before work” on a given day. In instances like this, we calculated a weighted average of non-work affect. In addition, DRM studies sometimes reported the average amount of time participants spent in the various activities for which they made affect ratings. In these cases, we time-weighted the activity estimates when computing overall averages for work and non-work affect.</p>
<p>This aggregation was necessary in order to maintain independent data points within the analysis. Thus, we effectively reduced the complexity of the data to a standardized mean gain where the same variable is measured on two occasions (i.e., work and non-work) for each sample [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref053">53</xref>]. For this within-subjects effect, <italic>SD</italic><sub>pooled</sub> is based upon the between-person standard deviations for both work and non-work. When studies did not report means and/or standard deviations, we attempted to calculate ESs using other statistics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref053">53</xref>]. For studies that reported F-statistics for one-way ANOVAs of two independent group means, we calculated ES using the following formula where <italic>n</italic> = sample size, ES = (2<italic>F</italic>/<italic>n</italic>)<sup>0.5</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref053">53</xref>]. In cases where t-statistics were reported, we used either the independent t-test conversion formula, ES = 2<italic>t</italic> / (2<italic>n</italic>)<sup>0.5</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref053">53</xref>] or the repeated measures formula, ES = <italic>t</italic>[2(1-<italic>r</italic>)/<italic>n</italic>]<sup>0.5</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref054">54</xref>] as appropriate. When only regression coefficients were reported, we made the following calculation, ES = <italic>B</italic> / <italic>SD</italic><sub>pooled</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref053">53</xref>].</p>
<p>Several studies reported multiple discrete emotions that were aspects of either PA or NA. In these cases, we combined these discrete emotions into a respective PA or NA composite for the comparisons involving generalized PA and NA. For example, estimates of happy, confident, and cheerful in one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref055">55</xref>] were combined to create an average for PA. Each effect size was subsequently corrected for unreliability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref056">56</xref>] and then weighted by its inverse variance using the following formula for repeated measures, 2n/[4(1-<italic>r</italic>) + ES<sup>2</sup>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref053">53</xref>]. In this formula, <italic>r</italic> is the person-level correlation between PA/NA associated with work and PA/NA associated with non-work. When reliability (alpha) or <italic>r</italic> was unavailable for a study, we used the average from other studies in the sample [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref056">56</xref>]. For studies with single-item measures, we assumed an estimated reliability of .70 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref057">57</xref>]. Main effects analyses conducted both with and without corrections for unreliability revealed consistency in the substantive findings; the results reported herein include both observed and corrected effects.</p>
<p>Overall ESs and associated heterogeneity were computed using random-effects models. Where the <italic>Q</italic> statistic for a main effect suggested variation in true ESs across studies, we also tested for the presence of moderators using mixed-effects modeling. Compared to fixed effects meta-analysis, the random effects models provided more realistic confidence intervals and allows for making make inferences extending beyond the studies in the present analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref058">58</xref>]. For each model, we identified influential outliers using features of the Metafor package for R (Version 1.9-8) and procedures outlined here [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref059">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref060">60</xref>]. An individual study ES qualified as an outlier if its studentized deleted residual exceeded ±1.96. Outlier ESs were then further evaluated using the <italic>influence</italic> function in R to examine the DFFITS value, Cook’s distance, leverage (hat value), and DFBETAS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref059">59</xref>]. When ESs were identified as both outliers and influential cases, we ran analyses both with and without those cases. For most models, we retained the influential outlier studies since their inclusion/exclusion did not impact conclusions. However, based on these criteria, a total of three studies were removed from the main effects models. One effect size was removed from the NA analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref061">61</xref>]; and two were removed from the PA analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref013">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref062">62</xref>].</p>
<p>Outlier diagnostics were run separately for the moderator analyses. In the univariate NA models, one of the studies noted above was removed from all moderator analyses for which it qualified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref061">61</xref>]. One study was removed from the measurement day model for the univariate NA model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref063">63</xref>]. Three of the NA models excluded two additional studies: the operationalization of work model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref063">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref064">64</xref>], the measurement schedule model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref064">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref065">65</xref>], and the gender model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref066">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref067">67</xref>].</p>
<p>In the univariate PA models, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref013">13</xref>] was again removed from all analyses for which it included moderator data. Two of the PA models excluded one additional study: the measurement method model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref027">27</xref>], and the age model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref062">62</xref>]. The PA model for measurement schedule excluded two additional studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref062">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref068">68</xref>] as did the model for measurement breadth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref068">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref069">69</xref>]. Finally, the PA model for operationalization of work excluded three additional studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref023">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref027">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref062">62</xref>].</p>
<p>In the multivariate moderator analyses, one study was removed from the NA model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref061">61</xref>]. No outliers were removed from the multivariate model for PA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref061">61</xref>]. All statistical analyses were conducted using the Metafor meta-analysis package for R (Version 1.9-8) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref059">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref060">60</xref>], except where otherwise indicated.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Main effects</title>
<p>One study was identified as an influential outlier for NA and two studies were identified as influential outliers for PA. However, there were no substantive reasons to exclude the studies so they were retained for the analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref070">70</xref>]. Moreover, the conclusions for the main effects remained the same, and the meta-analytic effect sizes changed only slightly when these effects were excluded (observed <italic>d</italic> for PA changed by .05 and for NA changed by .03).</p>
<p>An additional consideration was that several of the studies have substantially larger sample sizes compared to the remainder of the studies. In particular, one study had an especially large sample (<italic>N</italic> = 20,946) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref028">28</xref>] and three other studies had sample sizes exceeding 1,000 participants (total <italic>N</italic> = 10,531). In contrast, the remaining 56 studies had relatively more modest sample sizes (average <italic>N</italic> = 122; total <italic>N</italic> = 6,808). Since the four larger samples may be more influential and/or might differ systematically compared to the others (e.g., perhaps having more nationally representative samples), we conducted the analyses both with and without those studies included. Once again, the conclusions for the main effects remained unaltered, and the impact of the large studies on the meta-analytic effect sizes was small (observed <italic>d</italic> for PA changed by .04 and for NA changed by .01). Given this lack of impact, we retained the large studies in the analyses.</p>
<p>The individual study ESs and the meta-analytic average ES for PA and NA are shown in Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212594.g002">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212594.g003">3</xref>, respectively. The inverse variance weighted effect for PA was positive but not statistically significant (<italic>d</italic> = .07; δ = .09, 95% CI [-.04, .21], <italic>p</italic> =.160). In contrast, the inverse variance weighted effect for NA was positive and statistically significant (<italic>d</italic> = .18; δ = .22, 95% CI [.13, .30], <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). These results indicate that, on average, individuals do <italic>not</italic> report feeling more positive affect when away from work/not working than when at work/working. In contrast, reports of negative affect were significantly higher for work versus for non-work - although the magnitude of the difference was small. Notably, these conclusions were robust and not dependent on the exclusion of any individual study. Thus, Hypothesis 1a was not supported, whereas Hypothesis 1b was supported. In each case, heterogeneity analysis suggested a high degree of variability in individual study effect sizes after accounting for sampling error (<italic>Q</italic><sub>PA</sub> = 2140.42, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; <italic>Q</italic><sub>NA</sub> = 674.39, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). As such, we examined potential moderators.</p>
<fig id="pone.0212594.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Effect sizes (ESs) comparing work positive affect to non-work positive affect.</title>
<p>For each independent sample included in the meta-analysis, a corrected ES (square) and the associated 95% confidence interval (CI; line) is shown. On the bottom, the diamond shows the meta-analytically inverse variance weighted mean ES. The values associated with the ESs and CIs are located in the right column. Positive values for ES indicate greater positive affect during work versus non-work.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pone.0212594.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Effect sizes (ESs) comparing work negative affect to non-work negative affect.</title>
<p>For each independent sample included in the meta-analysis, a corrected ES (square) and the associated 95% confidence interval (CI; line) is shown. On the bottom, the diamond shows the meta-analytically inverse variance weighted mean ES. The values associated with the ESs and CIs are located in the right column. Positive values for ES indicate greater negative affect during work versus non-work.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>Moderators based on the measurement of affect</title>
<p>The results of the univariate moderator analyses for PA and NA are reported in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0212594.t002">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0212594.t003">3</xref>, respectively. In Hypothesis 2a and 2b, we predicted mean differences in affect as a function of “measurement method” – that is, whether the study used a real-time data collection method (e.g., ESM) or the day reconstruction method (DRM). For the univariate moderator analyses associated with these two hypotheses, outlier diagnostics identified one influential outlier study for PA and one (other) influential outlier study for NA. Although the magnitude of the meta-analytic effects was not substantially altered by the outliers, their exclusion changed the results of the moderator analyses from nonsignificant to statistically significant. The following results exclude the outlier studies and thus should be interpreted with a degree of caution. As seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0212594.t002">Table 2</xref>, measurement method was a significant moderator for PA (<italic>Q</italic><sub>between-groups</sub> = 10.84, <italic>p</italic> = .001). Work PA was slightly <italic>higher</italic> than non-work PA in real-time studies (δ = .09, 95% CI [-.01, .19], <italic>p</italic> = .078). In contrast, work PA was significantly <italic>lower</italic> than non-work PA in DRM studies (δ = -.33, 95% CI [-.56, -.10], <italic>p</italic> = .004). This finding supported H2a. The result for NA also was consistent with the relevant prediction in H2b (<italic>Q</italic><sub>between-groups</sub> = 11.80, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). Although work NA was higher than non-work NA for both types of studies, the difference was stronger in DRM studies (δ = .36, 95% CI [.26, .46], <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) than in ESM studies (δ = .16, 95% CI [.10, .21], <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). These findings support the idea that work is regarded as relatively more pleasant and less aversive when reports are made in real-time versus retrospectively.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0212594.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Univariate moderator analyses for positive affect: Work versus non-work.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0212594.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Moderator</th>
<th align="center"><italic>k</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>d</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>δ</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">95% CI</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">Moderator <italic>Q</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement method</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Real-time</td>
<td align="center">37</td>
<td align="center">0.08</td>
<td align="center">0.09</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">-.01, .19</td>
<td align="center">0.078</td>
<td align="center">10.84</td>
<td align="center">0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    DRM</td>
<td align="center">7</td>
<td align="center">-0.28</td>
<td align="center">-0.33</td>
<td align="center">0.11</td>
<td align="center">-.56, -.10</td>
<td align="center">0.004</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Operationalization of work</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Location</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">0.12</td>
<td align="center">0.13</td>
<td align="center">0.08</td>
<td align="center">-.03, .29</td>
<td align="center">0.123</td>
<td align="center">0.22</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Activity</td>
<td align="center">18</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">0.06</td>
<td align="center">0.11</td>
<td align="center">-.14, .28</td>
<td align="center">0.549</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement day</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Workdays only</td>
<td align="center">34</td>
<td align="center">0.14</td>
<td align="center">0.16</td>
<td align="center">0.07</td>
<td align="center">.01, .31</td>
<td align="center">0.027</td>
<td align="center">3.19</td>
<td align="center">0.074</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Workdays &amp; weekends</td>
<td align="center">17</td>
<td align="center">-0.05</td>
<td align="center">-0.06</td>
<td align="center">0.1</td>
<td align="center">-.27, .14</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement schedule<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    After work only</td>
<td align="center">11</td>
<td align="center">0.39</td>
<td align="center">0.43</td>
<td align="center">0.12</td>
<td align="center">.17, .68</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
<td align="center">8.91</td>
<td align="center">0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Before and after work</td>
<td align="center">36</td>
<td align="center">-0.01</td>
<td align="center">-0.009</td>
<td align="center">0.07</td>
<td align="center">-.14, .13</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center"><italic>k</italic></td>
<td align="center"><italic>B</italic></td>
<td align="center"><italic>B*</italic></td>
<td align="center"><italic>SE</italic></td>
<td align="center">95% CI</td>
<td align="center"><italic>p</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Affect intensity</td>
<td align="center">51</td>
<td align="center">0.037</td>
<td align="center">0.037</td>
<td align="center">0.11</td>
<td align="center">-.18, .25</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Job complexity</td>
<td align="center">12</td>
<td align="center">0.033</td>
<td align="center">0.034</td>
<td align="center">0.17</td>
<td align="center">-.31, .38</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Average age</td>
<td align="center">37</td>
<td align="center">0.021</td>
<td align="center">0.024</td>
<td align="center">0.01</td>
<td align="center">.004, .044</td>
<td align="center">0.015</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">% female</td>
<td align="center">39</td>
<td align="center">0.002</td>
<td align="center">0.002</td>
<td align="center">0.002</td>
<td align="center">-.003, .008</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Educational attainment</td>
<td align="center">18</td>
<td align="center">0.004</td>
<td align="center">0.004</td>
<td align="center">0.002</td>
<td align="center">-.000, .009</td>
<td align="center">0.069</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">% married/ cohabitating</td>
<td align="center">25</td>
<td align="center">-0.002</td>
<td align="center">-0.002</td>
<td align="center">0.004</td>
<td align="center">-.011, .007</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>Note: The first set of <italic>p</italic> values indicates whether the predicted estimate differs significantly from zero within moderator level. The second set of <italic>p</italic> values indicates whether the moderator accounts for a significant amount of heterogeneity (Q) in the mixed effects model. <italic>d</italic> = standardized mean difference; <italic>δ</italic> = corrected standardized mean difference; <italic>B</italic> = meta-regression coefficient; <italic>B*</italic> = corrected meta-regression coefficient.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p><sup>a</sup>“Before work only” measurement schedule for non-work affect was excluded from the analysis because it was utilized in only one study.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0212594.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Univariate moderator analyses for negative affect: Work versus non-work.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0212594.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Moderator</th>
<th align="center"><italic>k</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>d</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>δ</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">95% CI</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">Moderator <italic>Q</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement method</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Real-time</td>
<td align="center">38</td>
<td align="center">0.14</td>
<td align="center">0.16</td>
<td align="center">0.02</td>
<td align="center">.10, .21</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
<td align="center">11.80</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    DRM</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center">0.30</td>
<td align="center">0.36</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">.25, .46</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Operationalization of work</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Location</td>
<td align="center">37</td>
<td align="center">0.19</td>
<td align="center">0.21</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">.11, .31</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
<td align="center">0.04</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Activity</td>
<td align="center">13</td>
<td align="center">0.16</td>
<td align="center">0.19</td>
<td align="center">0.08</td>
<td align="center">.02, .36</td>
<td align="center">0.025</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement day</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Workdays only</td>
<td align="center">37</td>
<td align="center">0.16</td>
<td align="center">0.18</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">.08, .28</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
<td align="center">1.22</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Workdays &amp; weekends</td>
<td align="center">16</td>
<td align="center">0.25</td>
<td align="center">0.28</td>
<td align="center">0.07</td>
<td align="center">.13, .43</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement schedule</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Before work only</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">0.13</td>
<td align="center">0.13</td>
<td align="center">0.20</td>
<td align="center">-.26, .54</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center">1.79</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    After work only</td>
<td align="center">11</td>
<td align="center">0.12</td>
<td align="center">0.13</td>
<td align="center">0.09</td>
<td align="center">-.04, .31</td>
<td align="center">0.128</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">    Before and after work</td>
<td align="center">37</td>
<td align="center">0.23</td>
<td align="center">0.26</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">.17, .36</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center"><italic>k</italic></td>
<td align="center"><italic>B</italic></td>
<td align="center"><italic>B*</italic></td>
<td align="center"><italic>SE</italic></td>
<td align="center">95% CI</td>
<td align="center"><italic>p</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Affect intensity</td>
<td align="center">52</td>
<td align="center">0.029</td>
<td align="center">0.012</td>
<td align="center">0.12</td>
<td align="center">-.22, .25</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Job complexity</td>
<td align="center">14</td>
<td align="center">0.020</td>
<td align="center">0.022</td>
<td align="center">0.06</td>
<td align="center">-.10, .14</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Average age</td>
<td align="center">42</td>
<td align="center">-0.001</td>
<td align="center">-0.000</td>
<td align="center">0.010</td>
<td align="center">-.021, .019</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">% female</td>
<td align="center">42</td>
<td align="center">-0.000</td>
<td align="center">-0.000</td>
<td align="center">0.002</td>
<td align="center">-.005, .003</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Educational attainment</td>
<td align="center">21</td>
<td align="center">-0.001</td>
<td align="center">-0.001</td>
<td align="center">0.002</td>
<td align="center">-.006, .003</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">% married/ cohabitating</td>
<td align="center">22</td>
<td align="center">-0.003</td>
<td align="center">-0.004</td>
<td align="center">0.004</td>
<td align="center">-.012, .004</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>Note: The first set of <italic>p</italic> values indicates whether the predicted estimate differs significantly from zero within moderator level. The second set of <italic>p</italic> values indicates whether the moderator accounts for a significant amount of heterogeneity (Q) in the mixed effects model. <italic>d</italic> = standardized mean difference; <italic>δ</italic> = corrected standardized mean difference; <italic>B</italic> = meta-regression coefficient; <italic>B*</italic> = corrected meta-regression coefficient.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In Hypotheses 3a-3d, we offered competing predictions in regard to whether work was operationalized as a location versus an activity. Findings showed that this distinction was not significant for PA (<italic>Q</italic><sub>between-groups</sub> = .22, <italic>p</italic> = &gt;.25) or NA (<italic>Q</italic><sub>between-groups</sub> = .04, <italic>p</italic> &gt; .25). Thus, neither set of hypotheses was supported. The next moderators of interest pertained to the nature of affect. First, we investigated whether affect intensity (i.e., activation or arousal) impacted the difference in work- versus non-work PA and NA. Meta-regression results revealed that there was no effect of intensity of affect for either PA (<italic>B*</italic> = .03, <italic>p</italic> = &gt;.25) or NA (<italic>B*</italic> = .01, <italic>p</italic> = &gt;.25). Second, we also examined potential differences in work versus non-work experiences for specific types of affect. As seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0212594.t004">Table 4</xref>, we computed the meta-analytic effects for 23 discrete emotions where effect sizes could be calculated for 3 or more studies. Regarding positively valenced discrete emotions, alert (<italic>d</italic> = .37, <italic>p</italic> = .003), cheerful (<italic>d</italic> = .02, <italic>p</italic> = .025), and interested (<italic>d</italic> = .26, <italic>p</italic> = &lt;.001) were higher for work than for non-work, whereas enjoying (<italic>d</italic> = -.31, <italic>p</italic> = &lt;.001) and happy (<italic>d</italic> = -.19, <italic>p</italic> = .005) were lower for work than for non-work. Regarding negatively valenced discrete emotions, ten emotions were higher for work than for non-work: angry (<italic>d</italic> = .14, <italic>p</italic> = .008), depressed/blue (<italic>d</italic> = .05, <italic>p</italic> = .017), frustrated/annoyed (<italic>d</italic> = .39, <italic>p</italic> = &lt;.001), insecure (<italic>d</italic> = .13, <italic>p</italic> = .008), irritated (<italic>d</italic> = .08, <italic>p</italic> = .001), nervous (<italic>d</italic> = .22, <italic>p</italic> = &lt;.001), sad (<italic>d</italic> = .11, <italic>p</italic> = &lt;.001), stress (<italic>d</italic> = .35, <italic>p</italic> = &lt;.001), tense (<italic>d</italic> = .23, <italic>p</italic> = .013), and worried/anxious (<italic>d</italic> = .16, <italic>p</italic> = .007). Of note, these effect sizes generally were modest in magnitude as well (perhaps with the exceptions of frustrated/annoyed and stress). The effects for the other discrete emotions were not statistically significant. We expand on these results below.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0212594.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Discrete emotions during work and non-work.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0212594.t004g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Discrete Emotion</th>
<th align="center"><italic>k</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>N</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>d</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">95% CI</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Agitated</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">96</td>
<td align="center">0.16</td>
<td align="center">0.19</td>
<td align="center">-.20, .54</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Alert</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">182</td>
<td align="center">0.37</td>
<td align="center">0.12</td>
<td align="center">.12, .62</td>
<td align="center">0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Angry</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">1435</td>
<td align="center">0.14</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">.03, .25</td>
<td align="center">0.008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Cheerful</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">1464</td>
<td align="center">0.04</td>
<td align="center">0.01</td>
<td align="center">.00, .07</td>
<td align="center">0.025</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Depressed/Blue</td>
<td align="center">11</td>
<td align="center">8894</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">0.02</td>
<td align="center">.00, .09</td>
<td align="center">0.017</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Down/Downhearted</td>
<td align="center">9</td>
<td align="center">940</td>
<td align="center">-0.01</td>
<td align="center">0.02</td>
<td align="center">-.06, .02</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Enjoying</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">8260</td>
<td align="center">-0.31</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">-.42, -.20</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Enthusiastic</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">198</td>
<td align="center">0.15</td>
<td align="center">0.09</td>
<td align="center">-.03, .34</td>
<td align="center">0.117</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Excited/Energetic</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">293</td>
<td align="center">0.24</td>
<td align="center">0.14</td>
<td align="center">-.03, .53</td>
<td align="center">0.087</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Frustrated/Annoyed</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">1850</td>
<td align="center">0.39</td>
<td align="center">0.07</td>
<td align="center">.24, .54</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Guilty</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center">724</td>
<td align="center">-0.01</td>
<td align="center">0.06</td>
<td align="center">-.15, .11</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Happy</td>
<td align="center">16</td>
<td align="center">26137</td>
<td align="center">-0.19</td>
<td align="center">0.07</td>
<td align="center">-.33, -.05</td>
<td align="center">0.005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Insecure</td>
<td align="center">7</td>
<td align="center">691</td>
<td align="center">0.13</td>
<td align="center">0.04</td>
<td align="center">.03, .22</td>
<td align="center">0.008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Interested</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">279</td>
<td align="center">0.26</td>
<td align="center">0.04</td>
<td align="center">.17, .35</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Irritated</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">1492</td>
<td align="center">0.08</td>
<td align="center">0.02</td>
<td align="center">.03, .13</td>
<td align="center">0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Lonely</td>
<td align="center">9</td>
<td align="center">1297</td>
<td align="center">-0.02</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">-.12, .07</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Nervous</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
<td align="center">1323</td>
<td align="center">0.22</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">.12, .32</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Sad</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">3735</td>
<td align="center">0.11</td>
<td align="center">0.01</td>
<td align="center">.08, .14</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Satisfied</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center">724</td>
<td align="center">-0.08</td>
<td align="center">0.05</td>
<td align="center">-.18, .00</td>
<td align="center">0.076</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Stress</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">4611</td>
<td align="center">0.35</td>
<td align="center">0.07</td>
<td align="center">.21, .49</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Tense</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">219</td>
<td align="center">0.23</td>
<td align="center">0.09</td>
<td align="center">.04, .41</td>
<td align="center">0.013</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Vitality</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">191</td>
<td align="center">0.34</td>
<td align="center">0.39</td>
<td align="center">-.42, 1.10</td>
<td align="center">&gt;.250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Worried/Anxious</td>
<td align="center">18</td>
<td align="center">9964</td>
<td align="center">0.16</td>
<td align="center">0.06</td>
<td align="center">.04, .28</td>
<td align="center">0.007</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p>Note: <italic>d</italic> = standardized mean difference. The corrected standardized mean difference is not reported since the majority of measures consisted of single items.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Finally, we also investigated when measurements were made. For “measurement day”, results showed that whether or not the non-work measurements also occurred on weekends did not significantly moderate the results for PA (<italic>Q</italic><sub>between-groups</sub> = 3.19, <italic>p</italic> = .074) or NA (<italic>Q</italic><sub>between-groups</sub> = 1.22, <italic>p</italic> &gt; .25). Of note, though, the result for PA approached the <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 significance level, with work being rated as relatively more pleasant when non-work affect was only assessed on weekdays rather than on both weekdays and weekends. Additionally, the timing of the non-work measurements on workdays (i.e., measurement schedule) was a significant moderator for PA (<italic>Q</italic><sub>between-groups</sub> = 8.91, <italic>p</italic> &lt;.001). For studies with non-work measurements occurring both before and after work, there was no difference in PA between work and non-work (δ = -.01, 95% CI [-.14, .13], <italic>p</italic> &gt;.25), whereas for studies with non-work measurements occurring only after work, PA was greater during work (δ = .43, 95% CI [.17, .68], <italic>p</italic> = &lt; .001). There was no difference between the measurement schedules for NA (<italic>Q</italic><sub>between-groups</sub> = 1.79, <italic>p</italic> = &gt;.25).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>Moderators based on work and non-work factors</title>
<p>Turning to work and non-work factors (i.e., contextual and demographic factors), we first examined the potential influence of job complexity. Contrary to Hypotheses 4a and 4b, job complexity did not moderate the effect for either PA (<italic>B*</italic> = .03, <italic>p</italic> = &gt;.25) or NA (<italic>B*</italic> = .02, <italic>p</italic> = &gt;.25). Also, with regard to educational attainment, neither Hypothesis 5a nor Hypothesis 5b was supported. Of note, though, the effect for PA was significant at <italic>p</italic> = .069 (<italic>B*</italic> = .004) – lending support to the idea that individuals with more education experience relatively greater positive affect at work compared to away from work than do those with lower educational attainment.</p>
<p>With regard to the demographic factors we assessed in an exploratory manner, the average age of the sample was a significant moderator for PA (<italic>B*</italic> = .02, <italic>p</italic> = .015), but this significant effect only emerged once two influential outlier studies were removed from the analysis. Average age was not a significant moderator for NA <italic>(B*</italic> = -.000, <italic>p</italic> &gt; .25). Tentatively, older workers reported experiencing relatively higher PA, but not less NA, for work versus non-work than did younger employees. In contrast, neither the gender composition of the sample nor the proportion of the sample cohabitating/married (versus living alone) was a significant moderator for PA or NA (see results in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0212594.t002">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0212594.t003">3</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title>Multivariate moderator analyses</title>
<p>In order to assess potential confounding among the moderators, we conducted multiple regression analysis including the significant predictors. For PA, there were three significant moderators. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0212594.t005">Table 5</xref>, all three of the factors - measurement method (<italic>B*</italic> = -.31, <italic>p</italic> = .013), measurement schedule (<italic>B*</italic> = -.34, <italic>p</italic> = &lt;.001), and average age (<italic>B*</italic> = .02, <italic>p</italic> = .009) - still contributed to effect size variability in the multivariate model. However, the multivariate finding for age should be interpreted with caution since the significant effect only emerged after the removal of a single influential outlier study. For NA, multiple regression analysis was not required because there was only one significant univariate moderator (measurement method).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0212594.t005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t005</object-id>
<label>Table 5</label> <caption><title>Multivariate model for moderators of positive affect: Work versus non-work.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0212594.t005g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Moderator</th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>B*</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement method</td>
<td align="center">-0.27</td>
<td align="center">-0.31</td>
<td align="center">0.12</td>
<td align="center">0.013</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Measurement schedule</td>
<td align="center">-0.31</td>
<td align="center">-0.34</td>
<td align="center">0.09</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Average age</td>
<td align="center">0.02</td>
<td align="center">0.023</td>
<td align="center">0.009</td>
<td align="center">0.009</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"><italic>Q</italic></td>
<td align="center"><italic>p</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Model</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">26.60</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Residual</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">484.77</td>
<td align="center">&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t005fn001"><p>Note: <italic>k</italic> = 29. <italic>B</italic> = meta-regression coefficient; <italic>B*</italic> = corrected meta-regression coefficient.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec022">
<title>Supplemental analysis</title>
<p>As stated previously, the weighting formula for the ESs required the person-level correlation between work PA and non-work PA and between work NA and non-work NA. Thus the data collected for our primary meta-analysis can also be used to calculate meta-analytic estimates of the correlations among these four variables - work PA, work NA, non-work PA, and non-work NA - for a subset of 30 studies in our sample that assessed both positive affect and negative affect. These correlations were calculated using random-effects modeling within the RBNL meta-analysis program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref071">71</xref>] and are provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0212594.t006">Table 6</xref>. The results show that work and non-work PA were strongly correlated as were work and non-work NA (<italic>ρ</italic>s = .90, .95). In addition, PA was moderately and negatively correlated with NA within each domain (<italic>ρ</italic>s = -.40, -.47) whereas these relationships were somewhat less strong across domains (<italic>ρ</italic>s = -.26, -.30).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0212594.t006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t006</object-id>
<label>Table 6</label> <caption><title>Meta-Analytic correlations for PA and NA during work and non-work.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0212594.t006g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.t006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">80% CV</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">95% CI</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Constructs</th>
<th align="center"><italic>k</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>N</italic></th>
<th align="center"><inline-formula id="pone.0212594.e001"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0212594.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.e001" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M1"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></th>
<th align="center">P</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic><sub>ρ</sub></th>
<th align="center">% Var.</th>
<th align="center">L</th>
<th align="center">U</th>
<th align="center">L</th>
<th align="center">U</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">PAwork - NAwork</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">6,493</td>
<td align="center">-0.32</td>
<td align="center">-0.47</td>
<td align="center">0.17</td>
<td align="center">14.37</td>
<td align="center">-0.69</td>
<td align="center">-0.25</td>
<td align="center">-0.54</td>
<td align="center">-0.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PAnonwork -  NAnonwork</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">6,493</td>
<td align="center">-0.28</td>
<td align="center">-0.40</td>
<td align="center">0.15</td>
<td align="center">20.40</td>
<td align="center">-0.59</td>
<td align="center">-0.21</td>
<td align="center">-0.46</td>
<td align="center">-0.35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PAwork - NAnonwork</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">6,493</td>
<td align="center">-0.20</td>
<td align="center">-0.30</td>
<td align="center">0.13</td>
<td align="center">28.54</td>
<td align="center">-0.46</td>
<td align="center">-0.14</td>
<td align="center">-0.35</td>
<td align="center">-0.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PAnonwork - NAwork</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">6,493</td>
<td align="center">-0.17</td>
<td align="center">-0.26</td>
<td align="center">0.15</td>
<td align="center">22.67</td>
<td align="center">-0.45</td>
<td align="center">-0.07</td>
<td align="center">-0.32</td>
<td align="center">-0.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PAwork - PAnonwork </td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">6,493</td>
<td align="center">0.63</td>
<td align="center">0.90</td>
<td align="center">0.12</td>
<td align="center">10.01</td>
<td align="center">0.74</td>
<td align="center">1.00</td>
<td align="center">0.85</td>
<td align="center">0.94</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">NAwork - NAnonwork</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">6,493</td>
<td align="center">0.66</td>
<td align="center">0.95</td>
<td align="center">0.12</td>
<td align="center">9.38</td>
<td align="center">0.80</td>
<td align="center">1.00</td>
<td align="center">0.91</td>
<td align="center">1.00</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t006fn001"><p>Note: <inline-formula id="pone.0212594.e002"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0212594.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.e002" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M2"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> = sample-weighted mean correlation; ρ = estimate of population correlation corrected for unreliability; % Var. = percentage of variance explained by artifacts. Upper limits of 80% credibility value that exceeded 1 are reported as 1</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec023" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Classical economic theory suggests that work is a relatively distasteful experience. Indeed, Adam Smith, the father of modern economics, described work as “toil and trouble” requiring the sacrifice of one’s “ease, liberty, happiness” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref072">72</xref>]. Some prominent modern-day studies support this view, showing work to be among the least pleasant experiences of daily life 16, 28].</p>
<p>However, the current meta-analytic results partly refute this conclusion and instead show that affect at work is nearly on par with affect during the rest of daily life (non-work). Specifically, we found no significant difference between work and non-work positive affect. While work-related negative affect was higher than non-work negative affect, the magnitude of this difference was small, with an effect size of .22 <italic>SD</italic>. To put this effect size in context, other findings suggest that there is as much, if not more, variability in NA experienced during different leisure activities. For example, differences in NA between watching TV and playing board games and between socializing with friends and playing sports are very similar (<italic>d</italic> <sub>[television <italic>–</italic> games]</sub> = .19 <italic>SD</italic>; <italic>d</italic> <sub>[socializing <italic>–</italic> sports]</sub> = .20 <italic>SD</italic>) – computed here from the sample of full-time employees in the American Time Use data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref047">47</xref>]. This said, the results also showed that several discrete negative emotions were higher for work than non-work.</p>
<p>Below, we expand on this and the other findings. In this discussion, we also note potential directions for future research to more directly test the ideas implied by these results. Following that, we describe potential boundary conditions and limitations of this meta-analysis.</p>
<sec id="sec024">
<title>Interpreting the current findings</title>
<p>Given the variability among the primary study effect sizes, and the presence of at least some significant moderators, a reasonable question is whether the main effects are meaningful. In statistical parlance, “should one interpret the main effects given the significant interactions?” Based on the pattern of findings, we adopt a middle ground position here. On one hand, the heterogeneity in effect sizes and the presence of moderators indicate that the difference between work and non-work affect certainly depends on various factors. On the other hand, several findings <italic>collectively</italic> suggest that the main effect results also convey important information. These four findings are a) the non-significant main effect for PA, b) that work PA is actually slightly higher than non-work PA in studies using real-time methods, c) the relatively small overall effect size for NA, and d) the non-significant results for some of the more intuitive moderators (e.g., job complexity, whether or not weekend affect was taken into account).</p>
<p>With regard to what may explain these findings – especially vis-à-vis contradictory notions or understandings about the emotional experience of work – the moderator results offer some possible insights. Turning first to the method of measurement, work was rated as more pleasant and less unpleasant when studies used real-time methods versus the DRM. This difference was particularly notable for PA; real-time assessments suggested that work PA was slightly higher whereas DRM studies suggested that people felt better in non-work scenarios. Although the impact of work versus non-work on PA was not dramatic for either measurement method, the shifting direction of the effect supports the idea that DRM and ESM capture somewhat different realities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref073">73</xref>] as well as the idea that work is associated with different realities. This notion is consistent with Kahneman and Riis’s seminal piece on (measuring) psychological well-being, titled, “Living, and thinking about it: two perspectives on life” - a main thesis of which is that feeling in the moment and subsequent reflection about that moment reflect different realities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref074">74</xref>]. Applying this idea (and findings, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref075">75</xref>]) to the current results, neither the DRM nor real-time results is wrong. Both are valid reflections of people’s assessments of work; they simply reflect different working realities.</p>
<p>The DRM versus ESM results also seem to have implications with regard to researchers choosing one approach or the other for primary studies. While more work needs to be done, the current results paired with some other findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref018">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref073">73</xref>] suggest that real-time methods may be optimal when one is interested in emotion associated with relatively short events or activities (e.g., meetings, common work tasks) and, in particular, on the temporal unfolding of affect over the course of such events or activities. DRM may be less useful for these purposes because DRM produces only a single set of affect ratings if the event occurs during one period on the DRM form [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref073">73</xref>]. The issue of how people aggregate disparate levels or types of affect over a given experience remains unresolved. Beyond that consideration, though, DRM does not capture the diversity or change in affective experience over a given event.</p>
<p>In contrast, DRM appears more useful for measuring schematic representations of events (and the affect associated with them). To be clear, DRM ratings do capture within-day variability in affect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref040">40</xref>]. Thus, they clearly not only capture schemas or stereotypes about different contexts. But, the current findings provide further, albeit indirect, evidence suggesting that DRM ratings are more a function of such schemas than are ESM ratings. Again, choice among these methods, and also regarding the use of overall, one-time measures (or the decision to use multiple methods) should reflect theoretical and practical considerations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref073">73</xref>].</p>
<p>This idea that people’s recalled summary reports about work are less pleasant than their in-the-moment experiences of it also warrants separate mention. We are not aware of studies trying to assess schemas or stereotypes about the experience of working. But, assuming for the moment that future studies addressing this phenomenon are supportive, a reasonable query is, “now what?” Practically speaking, there is a question of whether organizations might develop interventions to reveal this disconnect and the notion that we sometimes “enjoy work more than we think we do.” We are not advocating such an intervention at this point but simply raise it as a possibility for future consideration and research.</p>
<p>The potential for this disconnect between experienced versus recalled affect also suggests value in trying to determine the features of work whose affective utility individuals may underestimate. Large-scale survey studies indicate that people believe extrinsic factors (e.g., pay, prestige, benefits) are especially strong contributors to job satisfaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref076">76</xref>]. Correlational studies among various factors and job satisfaction ratings, however, do not support the centrality of these extrinsic features for satisfaction. Rather, aspects of the job and the social environment consistently emerge as stronger predictors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref077">77</xref>]. The current findings may suggest that there is a tendency to focus on extrinsic factors when reporting job attitudes, perhaps more so than when reporting on momentary affect - when job features and social phenomena are more proximal.</p>
<p>We also would call for research exploring the affective value of some of the other latent factors Jahoda mentioned – such as time structure, social contact, and activity – using real-time assessments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref009">9</xref>]. Studies comparing employed and unemployed individuals support the role of these factors in explaining differences in psychological well-being, some of which even suggest the dominance of these factors relative to financial ones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref078">78</xref>]. However, ESM-type studies examining these factors are lacking. For instance, studies could try to capture factors like cognitive busyness and the degree to which one’s workday is structured on a recurring (e.g., daily or within-day) basis to examine which of these various factors may yield positive affect. Again, to the degree that there is a tendency to under-appreciate the potential emotional value of these everyday latent factors, people may hold more negative views of their jobs than the actual experience of work warrants. Also, thought-sampling studies in which employees actually report about what they are thinking during the work day could complement real-time affect reports to provide a fuller picture of the impact of work context and specific activities (or lack thereof) on employee subjective experience.</p>
<p>Additional moderator results that warrant discussion are those concerning the nature of affect. First, affect intensity did not impact the pattern of results. Thus, while negative affect is somewhat more common in work than non-work, it is not especially more intense in the workplace. To the degree that statements about contexts being more or less “emotional” connote the intensity of emotions, this finding has theoretical significance for the emotionality of work. Specifically, this null finding seems to refute any characterization of modern workplaces as bureaucratic “iron cages” devoid of emotion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref079">79</xref>] but also runs counter to the depiction of work as especially emotional. Rather, the intensity of emotions in the workplace and while working appears on par with emotional intensity in other contexts and activities.</p>
<p>In contrast to these null effects, the analyses yielded several differences among specific types of affect. In terms of positive affect, “happiness” and “enjoyment” were higher when people were not engaging in, or located at, work. These represent hedonic states and would seem to capture what is usually meant by “feeling good.” In contrast, “alert”, “interested”, and “cheerful” were higher for work than non-work. These latter findings generally seem consistent with the proposition that work is psychologically beneficial in part because it facilitates (mental) activity/engagement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref009">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref011">11</xref>]. Perhaps with the exception of the cheerfulness finding, the results also provide indirect support for the importance of work in fostering a sense of competence and meaningfulness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref012">12</xref>]. In general, then, work possibly fosters more eudaimonic well-being, while non-work fosters hedonic well-being. This conclusion partially may explain why, on average, individuals who work are happier than those who do not work, even after accounting for the financial benefits of work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref080">80</xref>]. Work and non-work experiences both can foster positive affect, but they provide different forms of it – this idea is consistent with our null finding for positive affect, more generally.</p>
<p>In contrast to the mixed findings for different types of PA, average levels of various specific types of NA generally were higher at work. The consistency across these many different negative moods and emotions implies that various workplace stressors and events are operative. That any one type of event could generate these somewhat heterogeneous forms of NA seems unlikely. Also, worth noting, though, is that these effect sizes - like those for generalized NA - generally were rather modest in magnitude.</p>
<p>In addition to these moderator results, a few other results from this study bear mention. One unexpected finding was that neither job complexity nor educational attainment impacted the effects. We certainly acknowledge that these results are tentative given methodological considerations. In particular, a limited number of studies provided data for us to calculate these two variables, thereby limiting the statistical power to detect a moderator effect. Moreover, in most cases, the samples were heterogenous on these factors, leading us to calculate average values for the sample. These caveats notwithstanding, the results do suggest that affective experiences may not vary as dramatically as other aspects of well-being between work and non-work domains. This may be due to affect largely being a result of discrete events rather than stable job characteristics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref081">81</xref>].</p>
<p>Other empirical support would seem to support this notion. For example, in a large-scale meta-analysis of job features, the relationship between Hackman and Oldham’s job characteristics and anxiety (an affective state) were non-significant and/or close to zero in all cases with the exception of that involving feedback from the job [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref082">82</xref>]. Moreover, although some individual studies do report significant correlations, as others have noted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref083">83</xref>], some of the most well-known studies linking job characteristics to affective states [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref042">42</xref>] have relied on self-reports of both constructs – thereby potentially yielding misleading results.</p>
<p>Rather than deriving from characteristics of the job, affect at work largely seems to result from particular events. Consistent with a main tenet of Affective Events Theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref081">81</xref>], studies link specific events to affective reactions, and especially interpersonal events (e.g., interactions with one’s manager, coworkers, clients; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref084">84</xref>]). Thus, insofar as the nature and/or quality of social relations and interactions do not vary much as a function job complexity, affect may not vary greatly either. Certainly, though, we acknowledge that this explanation is tentative and requires empirical investigation.</p>
<p>With regard to demographic characteristics, we explored whether age, gender, and marital status functioned as moderators. We did find that older samples reported higher relative PA at work, a result that seems to coincide with at least some other data showing that job satisfaction increases with age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref085">85</xref>]. But, with the exception of age, none of the factors altered the main effects. These results should be interpreted with caution since variance in the analyses was somewhat restricted by the use of study-level estimates for heterogeneous samples. Still, the pattern of weak and non-significant findings is suggestive that demographic factors generally are not strong determinants of differences in work versus non-work affect.</p>
<p>Finally, we also examined several methodological factors. Here, too, the results were mostly null, with only measurement schedule producing a significant effect. Specifically, for PA (but not NA), relative work affect was lower when non-work measurements were taken both before and after work compared to when non-work affect was assessed only after work. In contrast with previous studies on the diurnal rhythms of a working day [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref086">86</xref>], this result tentatively suggests that PA before work is greater than after work. While we only can conjecture about this finding, one possibility is that PA was measured later in the evening in studies where PA was measured only after work. Because PA may drop dramatically later in the evening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref041">41</xref>], those estimates may be somewhat lower than if PA was measured right after work - perhaps explaining these findings.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec025">
<title>Study limitations</title>
<p>While we have noted some limitations of this research in the discussion above, additional factors necessitate mention. First, we generally were not able to assess what people were actually <italic>doing</italic> either at work or away from work. Whether people are having lunch with colleagues versus interacting with angry customers almost certainly will tend to produce different affective reactions. Similarly, when away from work, engaging in a leisure activity with friends will tend to produce quite different emotional reactions than does engaging in housework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref016">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0212594.ref025">25</xref>]. Arguably, several of the variables we explored may have captured some of the goings-on generally taking place in the two environments (e.g., job complexity, whether people were married/cohabitating or living alone). However, these indirect attempts aside, the data in our sample largely precluded examination of the actual behaviors in which people were engaged in the work and non-work environments. We also were unable to explore specific locations or interaction partners because studies rarely reported that data, especially not within the work domain. Because of the potential insights that could be offered by such additional information, we encourage researchers to collect and report more detailed information about affective experiences, and particularly those occurring in different work contexts (e.g., meetings, email, teamwork, decision-making).</p>
<p>Also, some of the analyses were not based on terribly large sample sizes (or numbers of studies). Of note, we contacted over 20 additional “app” developers or companies whose app collected mood data, requesting them to share data for the project. For understandable legal reasons, however, they were not able to furnish the requested data. As described in the Method section, we also contacted hundreds of researchers, requesting data that we could have included in the analyses. Unfortunately, only about 10% of those researchers did provide such data. At the same time, we certainly wish to acknowledge and thank those who did so. As technologies continue emerging and greater quantities of data are collected, we are confident that larger data sets to further test ideas like the current ones will be available in the near future.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec026" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The current study sheds light on individuals’ emotional experiences of work as compared to non-work. The results suggest that mean-level positive and negative affect at work do not differ dramatically from the levels we experience outside of our jobs. We hope the current study serves to stimulate future efforts to tease out some of the ideas proposed here as well as other ideas that may help elucidate these meta-analytic findings.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec027">
<title>Supporting information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0212594.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Appendix</label>
<caption>
<title>References for the meta-analysis database.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0212594.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0212594.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Details on all primary studies included in the meta-analysis.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank the authors who provided data upon our requesting them.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Bureau of Labor Statistics</collab>. <source>Table 4. Employed persons working and time spent working on days worked by full- and part-time status and sex, jobholding status, educational attainment, and day of week, 2015 annual averages</source>. <year>2016</year>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bls.gov/news.release/pdf/atus.pdf" xlink:type="simple">https://www.bls.gov/news.release/pdf/atus.pdf</ext-link> Accessed 6.26.17.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawa</surname> <given-names>L.</given-names></name> <article-title>Older Americans are retiring in droves</article-title>. <source>Bloomberg Businessweek</source>. <volume>6</volume> <month>January</month> <year>2017</year>. Retrieved from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-01-06/older-americans-are-retiring-in-droves" xlink:type="simple">https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-01-06/older-americans-are-retiring-in-droves</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torpey</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hogan</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name> <source>Working in a gig economy</source>. <publisher-name>U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics</publisher-name>. <month>May</month> <year>2016</year>. Retrieved from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bls.gov/careeroutlook/2016/article/what-is-the-gig-economy.htm" xlink:type="simple">https://www.bls.gov/careeroutlook/2016/article/what-is-the-gig-economy.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diener</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oishi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname> <given-names>R. E</given-names></name>. <article-title>National accounts of subjective well-being</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <year>2015</year>; <volume>70</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0038899" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/a0038899</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25844649</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname> <given-names>D.</given-names></name> <source>The political economy of work</source>. <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>S.</given-names></name> <article-title>The integration of paid work and the rest of life. Is post‐industrial work the new leisure?</article-title> <source>Leisure Studies</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1080/02614360310001594131" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1080/02614360310001594131</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>FW</given-names></name>. <source>The principles of scientific management</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norton</publisher-name>; <year>1911</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terkel</surname> <given-names>S.</given-names></name> <source>Working: People talk about what they do all day and how they feel about it</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pantheon Books</publisher-name>; <year>1974</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahoda</surname> <given-names>M.</given-names></name> <source>Employment and unemployment: A social-psychological analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>1982</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochschild</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name> <source>The time bind: When work becomes home and home becomes work</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Metropolitan Books</publisher-name>; <year>1997</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Csikszentmihalyi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>LeFevre</surname> <given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Optimal experience in work and leisure</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>. <year>1989</year>; <volume>56</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>815</fpage>–<lpage>822</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.56.5.815" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.56.5.815</ext-link> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2724069</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deci</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olafsen</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Self-determination theory in work organizations: The state of a science</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Organizational Psychology and Organizational Behavior</source>. <year>2017</year>; <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnentag</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Binnewies</surname> <given-names>C.</given-names></name> <article-title>Daily affect spillover from work to home: Detachment from work and sleep as moderators</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Behavior</source>. 2013. <volume>83</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1016/j.jvb.2013.03.008" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1016/j.jvb.2013.03.008</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suddath</surname> <given-names>C.</given-names></name> <article-title>What if everyone got a monthly check from the government?</article-title> <source>Bloomberg Businessweek</source>. <day>10</day> <month>January</month> <year>2018</year>. Retrieved from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2018-01-11/what-if-everyone-got-a-monthly-check-from-the-government" xlink:type="simple">https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2018-01-11/what-if-everyone-got-a-monthly-check-from-the-government</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emmons</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Personal strivings: An approach to personality and subjective well-being</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>. <year>1986</year>; <volume>51</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1058</fpage>–<lpage>1068</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.51.5.1058" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/0022-3514.51.5.1058</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahneman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schkade</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>. <article-title>A survey method for characterizing daily life experience: The day reconstruction method</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>306</volume>(<issue>5702</issue>), <fpage>1776</fpage>–<lpage>1780</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1103572" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1103572</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15576620</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beal</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>ESM 2.0: State of the art and future potential of experience sampling methods in organizational research</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Organizational Psychology and Organizational Behavior</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-orgpsych-032414-111335" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-orgpsych-032414-111335</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diener</surname> <given-names>E.</given-names></name> <article-title>The metrics of societal happiness</article-title>. <source>Social Indicators Research</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>117</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>577</fpage>–<lpage>600</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Deconstructing job satisfaction: Separating evaluations, beliefs, and affective experiences</article-title>. <source>Human Resource Management Review</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clore</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Belief and feeling: Evidence for an accessibility model of emotional self-report</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>128</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>934</fpage>–<lpage>960</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.128.6.934" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.128.6.934</ext-link> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12405138</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname> <given-names>KI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Batinic</surname> <given-names>B.</given-names></name> <article-title>The need for work: Jahoda's latent functions of employment in a representative sample of the German population</article-title>. <source><italic>Journal of Organizational Behavior</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/job.622" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/job.622</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Snir</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zohar</surname> <given-names>D.</given-names></name> <article-title>Workaholism as discretionary time investment at work: An experience-sampling study</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychology</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1464-0597.2006.00270.x" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1464-0597.2006.00270.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myrtek</surname> <given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fichtler</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strittmatter</surname> <given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brügner</surname> <given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Stress and strain of blue and white collar workers during work and leisure time: Results of psychophysiological and behavioral monitoring</article-title>. <source><italic>Applied Ergonomics</italic></source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1016/S0003-6870" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1016/S0003-6870</ext-link>(98)00031-3 <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10416847</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilies</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwind</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeRue</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilgen</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>When can employees have a family life? The effects of daily workload and affect on work-family conflict and social behaviors at home</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>92</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1368</fpage>–<lpage>1379</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0021-9010.92.5.1368" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/0021-9010.92.5.1368</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17845091</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knabe</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rätzel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schöb</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weimann</surname> <given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Dissatisfied with life but having a good day: Time-use and well-being of the unemployed*</article-title>. <source>The Economic Journal</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>120</volume>(<issue>547</issue>), <fpage>867</fpage>–<lpage>889</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-0297.2009.02347.x" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-0297.2009.02347.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name>. <article-title>Time use, emotional well-being, and unemployment: Evidence from longitudinal data</article-title>. <source>American Economic Review</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>102</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>594</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1257/aer.102.3.594" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1257/aer.102.3.594</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dolan</surname> <given-names>P.</given-names></name> <article-title>Accounting for the richness of daily activities</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science (Wiley-Blackwell)</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>1000</fpage>–<lpage>1008</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2009.02392.x" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2009.02392.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacKerron</surname> <given-names>G.</given-names></name> <article-title>Are you happy while you work</article-title>? <source>The Economic Journal</source>. <year>2017</year>; <volume>127</volume>(<issue>599</issue>), <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bylsma</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor-Clift</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rottenberg</surname> <given-names>J.</given-names></name> <article-title>Emotional reactivity to daily events in major and minor depression</article-title>. <source>Journal of Abnormal Psychology</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>120</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0021662" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/a0021662</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21319928</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuchi</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname> <given-names>Y.</given-names></name> <article-title>Systematic comparison between ecological momentary assessment and day reconstruction method for fatigue and mood states in healthy adults</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Health Psychology</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/bjhp.12000" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/bjhp.12000</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23017062</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diener</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname> <given-names>L.</given-names></name> <article-title>Review of the Day Reconstruction Method (DRM)</article-title>. <source>Social Indicators Research</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>116</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-013-0279-x" xlink:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-013-0279-x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eng</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trope</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liberman</surname> <given-names>N.</given-names></name> <article-title>Spatial distance and mental construal of social events</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2006.01698.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1467-9280.2006.01698.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16623682</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trope</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liberman</surname> <given-names>N.</given-names></name> <article-title>Temporal construal</article-title>. <source>Psychological Review</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>110</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-295X.110.3.403" xlink:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-295X.110.3.403</ext-link> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12885109</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tourangeau</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rips</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rasinski</surname> <given-names>K.</given-names></name> <chapter-title>The psychology of survey response</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellsworth</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Patterns of cognitive appraisal in emotion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>. <year>1985</year>; <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>813</fpage>–<lpage>838</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3886875</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname> <given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Independence and bipolarity in the structure of current affect</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>967</fpage>–<lpage>984</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037//0022-3514.74.4.967" xlink:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.1037//0022-3514.74.4.967</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roseman</surname> <given-names>IJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Appraisal determinants of emotions: Constructing a more accurate and comprehensive theory</article-title>. <source>Cognition &amp; Emotion</source>. <year>1996</year>; <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/026999396380240" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/026999396380240</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keltner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Functional accounts of emotion</article-title>. <source>Cognition and Emotion</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/026999399379140" xlink:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.1080/026999399379140</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harter</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname> <given-names>R.</given-names></name> <article-title>Social time crucial to daily emotional well-being in the U.S</article-title>. <year>2008</year>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gallup.com/poll/107692/social-time-crucial-daily-emotional-wellbeing.aspx" xlink:type="simple">http://www.gallup.com/poll/107692/social-time-crucial-daily-emotional-wellbeing.aspx</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dockray</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahneman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wardle</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steptoe</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name> <article-title>A comparison of affect ratings obtained with ecological momentary assessment and the day reconstruction method</article-title>. <source>Social Indicators Research</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>99</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-010-9578-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11205-010-9578-7</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21113328</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname> <given-names>D.</given-names></name> <source>Mood and temperament</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saavedra</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <article-title>Kwun, SK. Affective states in job characteristic theory</article-title>. <source>Journal of Organizational Behavior</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)10991379(200003)21:2&lt;131::AID-JOB39&gt;3.0.CO;2-Q" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)10991379(200003)21:2&lt;131::AID-JOB39&gt;3.0.CO;2-Q</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgeson</surname> <given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Work Design Questionnaire (WDQ): Developing and validating a comprehensive measure for assessing job design and the nature of work</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>91</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1321</fpage>–<lpage>1339</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0021-9010.91.6.1321" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/0021-9010.91.6.1321</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17100487</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van den Broeck</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vansteenkiste</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Witte</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lens</surname> <given-names>W.</given-names></name> <article-title>Explaining the relationships between job characteristics, burnout, and engagement: The role of basic psychological need satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Work &amp; Stress</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilbur</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>. (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Age, education, job tenure, salary, job characteristics, and job satisfaction: A multivariate analysis</article-title>. <source><italic>Human Relations</italic></source>. 1985; <volume>38</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1177/001872678503800806" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1177/001872678503800806</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waite</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>B.</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title><italic>Contemporary families and experiences of work</italic>: <italic>A proposal for a New Alfred P</italic></article-title>. <article-title>Sloan Center of Working Families</article-title>. Proposal submitted to the Alfred P. Sloan Center.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bureau of Labor Statistics. American Time Use Survey 2010, 2012, and 2013 Multi-Year Well-Being Module Microdata Files [Data File]. 2014. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bls.gov/tus/wbdatafiles_1013.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.bls.gov/tus/wbdatafiles_1013.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borenstein</surname> <given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname> <given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>JPT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rothstein</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Introduction to meta-analysis</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>West Essex, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The PANAS-X: Manual for the positive and negative affect schedule- expanded form</chapter-title>. Unpublished manuscript, <publisher-name>Department of Psychology, University of Iowa</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Iowa City</publisher-loc>. <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warriner</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuperman</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brysbaert</surname> <given-names>M.</given-names></name> <article-title>Norms of valence, arousal, and dominance for 13,915 English lemmas</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research Methods</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1191</fpage>–<lpage>1207</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3758/s13428-012-0314-x" xlink:type="simple">10.3758/s13428-012-0314-x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23404613</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname> <given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ilies</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westrick</surname> <given-names>P.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Too much of a good thing: Curvilinear relationships between personality traits and job performance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>. 2011; <volume>96</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0021016" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/a0021016</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20939656</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oswald</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCloy</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivkin</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>P.</given-names></name> <article-title>Stratifying occupational units by specific vocational preparation</article-title>. <source>O*NET Consortium</source>. <year>1999</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipsey</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name>. <chapter-title><italic>Practical meta-analysis</italic> (Vol. ix)</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage Publications, Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlap</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cortina</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaslow</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of experiments with matched groups or repeated measures designs</article-title>. <source>Psychological Methods</source>. <year>1996</year>; <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoebi</surname> <given-names>D.</given-names></name> <article-title>Lean on me: Susceptibility to partner affect attenuates psychological distress over a 12-month period</article-title>. <source>Emotion</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/emo0000043" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/emo0000043</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25603137</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>FL</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Methods of meta-analysis: Correcting error and bias in research findings</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanous</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hudy</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Single-item reliability: A replication and extension</article-title>. <source>Organizational Research Methods</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1177/109442810144003" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1177/109442810144003</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erez</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloom</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Using random rather than fixed effects models in meta-analysis: Implications for situational specificity and validity generalization</article-title>. <source>Personnel Psychology</source>. <year>1996</year>; <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1744" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1744</ext-link> 6570.1996.tb01801.x</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viechtbauer</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname> <given-names>MWL</given-names></name>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Outlier and influence diagnostics for meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Research Synthesis Methods</source>. 2010; <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/jrsm.11" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/jrsm.11</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26061377</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viechtbauer</surname> <given-names>W.</given-names></name> <article-title>Metafor meta-analysis package for R, Version 1.9-8</article-title> [Computer software]. <year>2015</year>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=metafor" xlink:type="simple">http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=metafor</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juster</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moskowitz</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavoie</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D’Antono</surname> <given-names>B.</given-names></name> <article-title>Sex-specific interaction effects of age, occupational status, and workplace stress on psychiatric symptoms and allostatic load among healthy Montreal workers.</article-title> <source>Stress</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>616</fpage>–<lpage>629</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3109/10253890.2013.835395" xlink:type="simple">10.3109/10253890.2013.835395</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23952366</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houtveen</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Doornen</surname> <given-names>LJP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Negative affect and 24-hour ambulatory physiological recordings as predictors of spontaneous improvement of medically unexplained symptoms</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian Journal of Psychology</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>591</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9450.2008.00684.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1467-9450.2008.00684.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18771476</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bernstein, JH. Waiting for the weekend: The role of autonomy, relatedness, competence and work experiences in patterns of weekly well-being. Doctoral dissertation, University of Rochester. 2004. Available from ProQuest Dissertations and Theses database. (UMI No. 3142281).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fifield</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mcquillan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armeli</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tennen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reisine</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Affleck</surname> <given-names>G.</given-names></name> <article-title>Chronic strain, daily work stress and pain among workers with rheumatoid arthritis: Does job stress make a bad day worse?</article-title> <source>Work &amp; Stress</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1080/02678370412331324996" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1080/02678370412331324996</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>ZE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname> <given-names>XX</given-names></name>, &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname> <given-names>LL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effect of workplace incivility on end-of-work negative affect: Examining individual and organizational moderators in a daily diary study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Occupational Health Psychology</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0038167" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/a0038167</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25347686</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackowska</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dockray</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Endrighi</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrickx</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steptoe</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name> <article-title>Sleep problems and heart rate variability over the working day</article-title>. <source>Journal of Sleep Research</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2869.2012.00996.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2012.00996.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22309485</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salavecz</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simor</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Purebl</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bódizs</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dockray</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steptoe</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name> <article-title>Frequent nightmares are associated with blunted cortisol awakening response in women</article-title>. <source>Physiology &amp; Behavior</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>147</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1016/j.physbeh.2015.05.001" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1016/j.physbeh.2015.05.001</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Brinton, JE. Strain-based work-home conflict: Examining the relative contribution of exhaustion and negative affect in the association between work demands and home behaviors. Masters Thesis, Wake Forest University. 2014. Available from ProQuest Dissertations and Theses database. (UMI No. 1561744).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Auerbach, MA. The dynamic cycle of external, task interruptions: An ESM study of multiple role management. Doctoral dissertation, State University of New York at Albany. 2002. Available from ProQuest Dissertations and Theses database. (UMI No. 3053595).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cortina</surname> <given-names>J. M.</given-names></name> <article-title>Apples and oranges (and pears, oh my!): The search for moderators in meta-analysis.</article-title> <source>Organizational Research Methods</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname> <given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borrero</surname> <given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beal</surname> <given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Christian</surname> <given-names>M. S.</given-names></name> <source>RBNL Meta-analysis Program</source>. <year>2017</year>. New Orleans, Louisiana.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name> (1776). <source>An inquiry into the nature and causes of the wealth of nations</source> (R.H. Campbell &amp; A.S. Skinner, eds.). <publisher-loc>Indianapolis, IN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liberty Fund</publisher-name>, <year>1981</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diener</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname> <given-names>L.</given-names></name> <article-title>Review of the Day Reconstruction Method (DRM)</article-title>. <source>Social Indicators Research</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>116</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-013-0279-x" xlink:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-013-0279-x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahneman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riis</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Living, and thinking about it: two perspectives on life</article-title>. In <name name-style="western"><surname>Huppert</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baylis</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Keverne</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name> (editors), <source>The science of well-being</source>. <year>2005</year>. pp. <fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198567523.003.0011" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198567523.003.0011</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahneman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fredrickson</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Redeimeier</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <article-title>When more pain is preferred to less: Adding a better end</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science.</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.1993.tb00589.x" xlink:type="simple">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.1993.tb00589.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Society for Human Resource Management. Employee job satisfaction and engagement: Revitalizing a changing workforce. Alexandria, VA. 2016.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mottaz</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The relative importance of intrinsic and extrinsic rewards as determinants of work satisfaction.</article-title> <source>The Sociological Quarterly.</source> <year>1985</year>; <volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>385</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1533-8525.1985.tb00233.x" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1111/j.1533-8525.1985.tb00233.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname> <given-names>KI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geithner</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moser</surname> <given-names>K.</given-names></name> <article-title>Latent deprivation among people who are employed, unemployed, or out of the labor force</article-title>. <source>Journal of Psychology</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>143</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>491</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.3200/JRL.143.5.477-491" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.3200/JRL.143.5.477-491</ext-link> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19943399</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname> <given-names>M.</given-names></name> <chapter-title>Economy and society: An outline of interpretive sociology</chapter-title>. <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>. <year>1978</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname> <given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>, &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivers</surname> <given-names>C.</given-names></name> <chapter-title>She works/he works: How two-income families are happier, healthier and better off</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>; <year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cropanzano</surname> <given-names>R.</given-names></name> <chapter-title>Affective Events Theory: A theoretical discussion of the structure, causes and consequences of affective experiences at work</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Staw</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname> <given-names>LL</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Research in organizational behavior: An annual series of analytical essays and critical reviews</source>, Vol. <volume>18</volume> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>). <publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier Science/JAI Press</publisher-name>; <year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nahrgang</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morgeson</surname> <given-names>FP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Integrating motivational, social, and contextual work design features: A meta-analytic summary and theoretical extension of the work design literature</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>92</volume>, <fpage>1332</fpage>–<lpage>1356</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0021-9010.92.5.1332" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/0021-9010.92.5.1332</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17845089</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brief</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Organizational behavior: Affect in the workplace</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Psychology</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.psych.53.100901.135156" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.psych.53.100901.135156</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grandey</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brauburger</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Affective states and traits in the workplace: Diary and survey data from young workers</article-title>. <source>Motivation and Emotion</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1023/A:1015142124306" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1023/A:1015142124306</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendes</surname> <given-names>E. U.S.</given-names></name> <article-title>job satisfaction struggles to recover to 2008 levels. 2011</article-title>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gallup.com/poll/147833/job-satisfaction-struggles-recover-2008-levels.aspx" xlink:type="simple">http://www.gallup.com/poll/147833/job-satisfaction-struggles-recover-2008-levels.aspx</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0212594.ref086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schkade</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahneman</surname> <given-names>D.</given-names></name> <article-title>A population approach to the study of emotion: Diurnal rhythms of a working day examined with the day reconstruction method</article-title>. <source>Emotion</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/1528-3542.6.1.139" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/1528-3542.6.1.139</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16637757</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>