<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134485</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-13168</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Incremental Diagnostic Performance of Combined Parameters in the Detection of Severe Coronary Artery Disease Using Exercise Gated Myocardial Perfusion Imaging</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Values of Combined Treadmill and MPI Parameters in CAD</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Chia-Ju</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Yen-Wen</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff004" ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<xref rid="aff005" ref-type="aff"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>Kuan-Yin</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Yi-Chieh</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>Mei-Fang</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Yen</surname>
<given-names>Ruoh-Fang</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Tzen</surname>
<given-names>Kai-Yuan</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Nuclear Medicine, National Taiwan University Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Division of Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine, National Taiwan University Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Nuclear Medicine, Far-Eastern Memorial Hospital, New Taipei City, Taiwan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Cardiology Division of Cardiovascular Medical Center, Far-Eastern Memorial Hospital, New Taipei City, Taiwan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>National Yang-Ming University School of Medicine, Taipei, Taiwan</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zaragoza</surname>
<given-names>Carlos</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University Francisco de Vitoria School of Medicine, SPAIN</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CJL YWW. Performed the experiments: CJL YWW KYK YCC. Analyzed the data: CJL YWW KYK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CJL YWW KYK YCC MFC RFY KYT. Wrote the paper: CJL YWW.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">wuyw0502@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>31</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e0134485</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>27</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>10</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Liu et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0134485" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Purpose</title>
<p>Myocardial perfusion imaging (MPI) using gated single-photon emission tomography (gSPECT) may underestimate the severity of coronary artery disease (CAD). This study aimed to evaluate the significance of combined parameters derived from gSPECT, as well as treadmill stress test parameters, in the detection of severe CAD.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>A total of 211 consecutive patients referred for exercise MPI between June 2011 and June 2013 (who received invasive coronary angiography within six months after MPI) were retrospectively reviewed. Exercise MPI was performed with Bruce protocol and <sup>201</sup>Tl injected at peak exercise. Gated SPECT was performed using a cadmium-zinc-telluride camera and processed by QPS/QGS software. Perfusion defect abnormalities such as sum stress score (SSS); sum difference score, algorithm-derived total perfusion deficits, transient ischemic dilatation ratios of end-diastolic volumes and end-systolic volumes, post-stress changes in ejection fraction, and lung/heart ratio (LHR) were calculated. Treadmill parameters, including ST depression (STD) at the 1st and 3rd minutes of recovery stage (1’STD and 3’STD), maximal STD corrected by heart rate increment (ST/HR), heart rate decline in 1<sup>st</sup> and 3<sup>rd</sup> minutes of recovery stage, recovery heart rate ratio (HR ratio), systolic and mean blood pressure ratios (SBP ratio and MAP ratio) during recovery phase were recorded. Diagnostic performances of these parameters were analyzed with receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis and logistic regression for detection of left main (≥ 50%) or 3-vessel disease (all ≥ 70% luminal stenosis) on invasive angiography.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Among various MPI and treadmill parameters used for detection of severe CAD, SSS and ST/HR had the highest AUC (0.78, 0.73, <italic>p</italic> = NS) and best cut-off values (SSS &gt; 6, ST/HR &gt; 17.39 10<sup>-2</sup>mV/bpm), respectively. By univariate logistic regression, all parameters except 1’HRR, 3’HRR, SBP and MAP ratios increased the odds ratio of severe CAD. Only increased L/H ratio, 3’STD, and HR ratio remained significant after multivariate regression. The predicted values of combined MPI and treadmill parameters (LHR, 3’STD, and HR ratio) gave the best ROC (AUC: 0.91) than any individual parameter or parameter combination.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Of all treadmill and gSPECT parameters, the combination of MPI and treadmill parameters can offer better diagnostic performance for severe CAD.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>YWW. Grants MOST 100-2314-B-002-158 and 101-2314-B-418-012-MY3 from the Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.most.gov.tw/mp.aspx?mp=7" xlink:type="simple">http://www.most.gov.tw/mp.aspx?mp=7</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"/>
<table-count count="5"/>
<page-count count="13"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Myocardial perfusion imaging (MPI) using gated single-photon emission tomography (gSPECT) is a useful imaging modality for the detection and risk stratification of coronary artery disease (CAD). However, it is well known that MPI may underestimate the severity and extent of CAD due to its relative quantification of perfusion defects, particularly in cases of balanced ischemia [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Although the problem of balanced ischemia can be solved by calculating coronary flow reserve using dynamic positron emission tomography [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] or SPECT [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], additional costs and/or an acquisition algorithm are needed.</p>
<p>In addition to perfusion deficits, several stress-induced abnormalities [such as transient ischemic dilation (TID) and post-stress ejection fraction (EF)] can be derived from gSPECT [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and increased pulmonary uptake. These stress-induced abnormalities have shown diagnostic and prognostic importance in patients with suspected CAD [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Left ventricular TID ratio is known as a functional parameter which could increase the sensitivity of MPI for severe CAD [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and may be a specific prognostic marker for cardiovascular events [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Post-stress left ventricular stunning, in cases of decreased EF, is also an indicator of poor prognosis on gSPECT [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p>
<p>In addition, previous studies have shown that a number of variables obtained from the treadmill exercise test (TET) alone can be used to estimate prognosis in patients with suspected CAD. ST depression (STD) during the recovery stage [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], STD corrected by heart rate (HR) [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and post-exercise hemodynamic abnormalities, such as post-stress systolic blood pressure (SBP) [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and HR changes during the recovery stage [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], are associated with higher risk of cardiovascular events and mortality.</p>
<p>In this retrospective study, the diagnostic performance of combined parameters was compared with gSPECT and TET parameters. The aim of this study was to evaluate the significance of combined parameters derived from gSPECT using novel cadmium-zinc-telluride (CZT) detectors, as well as treadmill stress test parameters, in the detection of severe CAD.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Patients referred for exercise MPI between June 2011 and June 2013, who received invasive coronary angiography (CAG) within six months, were retrospectively reviewed. Patients were excluded if they had a history of myocardial infarction (MI), coronary artery bypass grafting, percutaneous coronary intervention, or documented congenital heart disease or severe valvular disease. The medical records (including demographics, cardiac risk factors, and medication) were reviewed for each patient. The pretest probability of CAD was evaluated using age, sex and angina typicality-based approach [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Ethical statement</title>
<p>This study was approved by the institutional review board of National Taiwan University Hospital. Patients’ written informed consent was waived due to the retrospective nature of the study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Treadmill MPI protocol</title>
<p>MPI gSPECT was performed using the one-day exercise stress-rest protocol with injection of 3 mCi (111 MBq) thallium-201 (<sup>201</sup>Tl). Treadmill exercise stress was applied using the standard Bruce protocol with a 4 minute recovery stage. Endpoints of treadmill stress included achievement of 85% of age-adjusted maximal heart rate, &gt;2 mm ST depression, systolic blood pressure (SBP) &gt;250 mmHg, typical angina, frequent ventricular ectopy, hemodynamically compromised arrhythmia, or physical limitation.</p>
<p>Imaging acquisition was performed using the Discovery NM530c SPECT gamma camera (GE Healthcare, Haifa, Israel), which was equipped with solid-state CZT detectors. Projections were recorded on 32 × 32 pixelated (2.46 × 2.46 mm<sup>2</sup>) CZT elements. Maximum likelihood expectation maximization was used with a reconstructed voxel size of 4.0 × 4.0 x 4.0 mm<sup>2</sup>. A Butterworth post-processing filter was applied (order 10, cut-off frequency, 0.37) to the reconstructed slices [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Treadmill parameters</title>
<p>Maximal ST depression (STD) and ST depression corrected by maximum HR (ST/HR) [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] were recorded. STDs at 1 min and 3 min of the recovery stage (1’STD, 3’STD) were also recorded. The SBP and HR dynamic changes during recovery stage were reviewed as post-stress hemodynamic changes. SBP at 3 min of recovery stage was divided by the SBP at 1 min of recovery stage to manifest the decline in SBP from target exercise level and was recorded as the SBP ratio [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The difference between heart rate at peak exercise and that at 1st min and 3rd min of recovery stage were also recorded (1’HRR and 3’HRR, respectively) [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. HR recovery ratio (HR ratio) was calculated as ratio of HR at 3rd min of recovery stage and that at 1st min of recovery stage.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>MPI parameters</title>
<p>Semiquantitative interpretation of 17 segments from the short axis, vertical long axis, and horizontal long axis of each gSPECT was performed by two experienced nuclear physicians. Each segment was visually scored using a 5-point scale: 0 = normal, 1 = equivocal or mild, 2 = moderate, 3 = severe reduction of radiotracer uptake, and 4 = absence of radiotracer uptake. The scores of all 17 segments for both stress and rest images were summed to produce summed stress scores (SSS) and summed rest scores (SRS), respectively. The difference between SSS and SRS was recorded as the summed difference score (SDS). For gSPECT functional parameters, automated algorithm quantitative perfusion SPECT, and quantitative gated SPECT (QPS/QGS, Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, LA, USA) were used. Patients were excluded for functional parameter analysis if significant arrhythmia compromised the ECG gating.</p>
<p>The extent and severity of pixel-based cardiac perfusion defects at rest (rTPD) and post-stress (sTPD) were also compared and expressed as continuous parameters of QPS/QGS [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The difference between sTPD and rTPD was recorded as dTPD. The left ventricular end-diastolic volume (EDV) and end-systolic volume (ESV) and the transient dilatation ratios (TIDs) of EDV and ESV were calculated at stress and rest. TID ratios derived from hearts less than 20 ml (i.e., small hearts) were excluded from analysis. Both stress and rest left ventricular EF ratios (EF ratio) and differences (EF change), retrieved from the QGS algorithm, were calculated as manifestations of post-stress EF changes.</p>
<p>The same 3 × 3 cm square region of interest (ROI) was placed on the anterior wall and lung region above the anterior wall at a distance equal to two ROIs using the anterior view of maximal intensity projection (MIP). Placement of ROIs on areas with hypoperfused myocardium was avoided. The ratio of total radioactivity recorded from the ROIs of lung and myocardium were calculated as the lung/heart ratio (LHR). The post-stress LHR (sLHR) and increment in LHR (dLHR) from rest to stress were used as parameters of increased pulmonary uptake after stress.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Coronary angiography results</title>
<p>CAG results performed within 6 months served as the gold standard. CAD was defined as more than 70% stenosis in any vessel. Severe CAD was defined as (1) left main arterial stenosis more than 50%, (2) three vessel disease with luminal stenosis of each major epicardial coronary artery more than 70%, and (3) two vessel disease including left anterior descending artery (LAD) with stenosis more than 70%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Continuous variables of patient groups were compared using the student <italic>t</italic>-test. Mann-Whitney test was used if normalcy of variables was rejected. Categorical variables were compared used Chi-square test. A <italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. The sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value (PPV), negative predictive value (NPV), and accuracy of each parameter were calculated and compared. The receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve was used to compare the diagnostic performance of parameters and to determine cut-off values for identification of severe CAD, primarily using Youden index (except for the TID ratio). The cut-off values of TID ratio were determined using the mean value + 2 standard deviations (SDs) in patients without stenotic coronary arteries, according to CAG results [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The cut-off criteria were also calculated to determine diagnostic performance using a combination of at least two different parameters, all of which had to be fulfilled simultaneously. The performance between cut-off values was compared using <italic>McNemar</italic> test or <italic>Cochran’s Q</italic> test.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>A total of 211 patients were included for analysis. Most patients included had intermediate to high pretest cardiovascular risk and MPI was performed for risk stratification. Two hundred and five patients (97%) had interpretable ECG. Four patients (1.9%) with left bundle branch block and another two patients (0.9%) with ventricular pacing rhythms were excluded for ST-T change interpretation. MPI results of five patients (2.4%) with atrial fibrillation were still included since no rapid ventricular response was noted on baseline ECG. The exercise duration of these five patients all reached stage 2 of Bruce protocol with average METS of 4.6. Other abnormal rhythm noted on baseline ECG included eighteen patients (8.5%) with right bundle branch block, eight patients (3.8%) with first degree atrioventricular block, and six patients (2.8%) with left ventricular hypertrophy. Fifty-two patients (24.6%) had positive treadmill stress test indicative myocardium ischemia.</p>
<p>Most patients had intermediate to high pretest CAD risk (high risk: 61 patients; intermediate risk: 146 patients; and low risk: 4 patients). Among all patients, 35 (20%) patients were diagnosed with severe CAD. The demographic comparisons between patients with and without severe CAD are listed in <xref rid="pone.0134485.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Patients with severe CAD had a higher prevalence of diabetes mellitus and hyperlipidemia, while no difference had been noticed regarding prescribed medication. Significant differences between the two groups were observed for SSS, SDS, TPD, EDV TID, dLHR, ST/HR, and recovery STD.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0134485.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>The comparison of demographic data between patient with and without severe CAD.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0134485.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No severe CAD</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe CAD</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients No.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59±10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59±9</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4±3.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.5±3.2</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">METS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2±1.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8±1.5</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HTN</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (71%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (71%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (25%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (49%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperlipidemia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (57%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (77%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (35%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (37%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Aspirin/Clopidogrel</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (49%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (60%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nitrate</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (19%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (34%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Beta-blocker</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (40%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (40%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ACEI/ARB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (39%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (49%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Statin/Fibrate</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (20%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (20%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPI parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SSS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2±5.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6±10.1</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SDS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1±4.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3±5.4</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> sTPD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5±7.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1±11.6</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> dTPD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2±6.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0±6.6</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ESV TID</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97±0.20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09±0.27</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> EDV TID</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0±0.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09±0.14</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> EF ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05±0.15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97±0.19</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> EF changes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9±6.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.8±13.2</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> sLH ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30±0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33±0.08</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> rLH ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32±0.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32±0.06</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> dLH ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.02±0.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01±0.05</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treadmill parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ST/HR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.28±14.97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.72±18.85</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1’ STD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34±0.53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78±0.72</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3’ STD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40±0.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92±0.73</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SBP ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92±0.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99±0.28</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MAP ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98±0.17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01±0.23</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1’HRR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1±9.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3±10.4</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3’HRR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7±12.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4±10.3</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HR ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81±0.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86±0.07</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>Abbreviation:</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p>BMI, body mass index; METS, metabolic equivalents; HTN, hypertension; DM, diabetes mellitus; ACEI, angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors; ARB, angiotensin receptor blocker; rLH ratio, the lung/heart ratio at rest.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The ROC analysis of TET and MPI parameters are displayed in <xref rid="pone.0134485.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0134485.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. SSS and ST/HR had the highest AUC among MPI and TET parameters (AUC = 0.781 and 0.730, respectively). The mean values of EDV TID and ESV TID in patients with patent coronary arteries on CAG were 0.99 ± 0.10 and 0.93 ± 0.17, respectively. The cut-off values of EDV TID and ESV TID were, therefore, set as 1.19 and 1.27, respectively, i.e., 2 SD above the mean values. Cut-off values of parameters other than TID are listed in <xref rid="pone.0134485.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Corresponding sensitivity, specificity, PPV, NPV and accuracy of each TET, MPI and combined parameters are also listed in <xref rid="pone.0134485.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone.0134485.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>The receiver operating curves of myocardial perfusion imaging (MPI) and treadmill parameters in detection of severe CAD.</title>
<p>The receiver operating curves of diagnostic performance of myocardial perfusion imaging (MPI) and treadmill parameters in detection of severe CAD were displayed on right and left panels. Summed stress score (SSS) and maximal ST depression corrected by maximum heart rate change (ST/HR) have highest area under the curve (AUC) among and treadmill parameters, respectively (AUC = 0.781 and 0.730).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pone.0134485.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>The ROC analysis of MPI and TET parameters.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0134485.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSS</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.781</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0436</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.720 to 0.835</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDS</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.763</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0450</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.700 to 0.819</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sTPD</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.731</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0458</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.666 to 0.789</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dTPD</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.727</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0456</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.662 to 0.786</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDV TID</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.707</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0526</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.622 to 0.782</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESV TID</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.621</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0670</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.532 to 0.703</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF ratio</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.608</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0696</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.520 to 0.691</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF change</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.604</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0691</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.516 to 0.688</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dLHR</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.673</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0492</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.605 to 0.736</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST/HR</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.730</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0441</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665 to 0.789</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1’STD</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.706</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0500</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.639 to 0.767</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3’STD</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.717</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0532</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649 to 0.778</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1’HRR</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0549</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.443 to 0.581</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3’HRR</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.590</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0487</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.519 to 0.657</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR ratio</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.650</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0500</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582 to 0.715</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP ratio</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.637</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0566</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.568 to 0.703</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP ratio</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.596</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0576</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.526 to 0.664</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0134485.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>The cutoff vales of MPI, TET and combined parameters and corresponding diagnostic performance.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0134485.t003g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treadmill parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut off values</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST/HR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;17.39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3’ STD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3HRR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STHR + SBP</td>
<td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STHR + 3HRR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STHR + SBP ratio + 3HRR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPI parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut off values</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sTPD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dTPD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDV TID</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1.19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESV TID</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1.27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;1.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF change</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sLHR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dLHR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;-0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSS + EDV TID</td>
<td rowspan="4" align="left" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSS + EF ratio</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSS + dLHR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSS + sLHR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">MPI + Treadmill parameters</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">SSS + ST/HR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">SSS + SBP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">SSS + 3HRR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">SSS + EDV + ST/HR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">SSS + ST/HR + SBP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">SSS + ST/HR + 3HRR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">SSS + dLH + ST/HR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Logistic predict values</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>*&gt;1mm with horizontal or downsloping ST depression, &gt;2mm with upsloping ST depression in consecutive multiple leads.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Among MPI and treadmill parameters, SSS and ST/HR had the highest AUCs (0.78 and 0.73, respectively) and best cut-off values (SSS &gt; 6 and ST/HR &gt; 17.39 10<sup>-2</sup>mV/bpm, respectively) in detection of severe CAD. SSS, as well as other perfusion deficit scores (SDS, sTPD, and dTPD) had fair sensitivity of up to 80%. EDV and ESV TID had extremely low sensitivity (both 20%) but high specificity (91%, 86%, respectively) for severe CAD.</p>
<p>Criteria using combined cut-off values of SSS or ST/HR, in addition to one or two other parameters, are shown in <xref rid="pone.0134485.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. These criteria had high specificity and accuracy in the detection of severe CAD, but sensitivity was inevitably compromised.</p>
<p>Upon univariate logistic regression (<xref rid="pone.0134485.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), all parameters significantly increased the odds ratio of severe CAD except 1’HRR, 3’HRR, and mean arterial pressure ratios in recovery stage (MAP ratio). However, only dLHR, 3’STD, and HR ratio remained significant on multivariate logistic regression (<xref rid="pone.0134485.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). The predicted probabilities generated from multivariate logistic regression had the highest AUC (0.91) and best detection of severe CAD (sensitivity 87%, specificity 90%, PPV 67%, NPV 97%, and accuracy 89%) of any other individual or combination of parameters mentioned above (p &lt; 0.01).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0134485.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>The univariate logistic regression analysis.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0134485.t004g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odds ratio</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSS</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1361</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0766 to 1.1989</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDS</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1873</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1004 to 1.2810</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sTPD</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0855</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0441 to 1.1284</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dTPD</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0997</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0440 to 1.1583</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDV TID<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0603</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0224 to 1.0995</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESV TID<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0255</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0060 to 1.0454</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF ratio</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0297</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0012 to 0.7579</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF change</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9389</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8852 to 0.9958</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dLHR<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1548</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0631 to 1.2544</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST/HR</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0400</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0189 to 1.0614</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1’STD</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8165</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6280 to 4.8728</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3’STD</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7164</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0303 to 6.8028</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1’HRR</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0122</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9758 to 1.0500</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3’HRR</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9770</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9478 to 1.0072</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR ratio<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0531</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0048 to 1.1036</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP ratio<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0235</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0037 to 1.0436</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP ratio<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0274</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9996 to 1.0560</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p>* Multiplied by 100 for unit correction.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0134485.t005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t005</object-id>
<label>Table 5</label> <caption><title>Multivariate logistic regression of MPI TET parameters.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0134485.t005g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0134485.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std. Error</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSS</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058750</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038571</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDV TID<xref rid="t005fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056826</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036858</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF_ratio</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79116</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29137</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dLHR<xref rid="t005fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26390</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088108</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST/HR</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.010108</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043857</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3’STD</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21776</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94335</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR ratio<xref rid="t005fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27037</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083471</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP ratio<xref rid="t005fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0083895</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021928</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-34.4571</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t005fn001"><p>*Multiplied by 100 for unit correction.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The identification of severe CAD based on abnormal MPI is important for referral physicians since management is critical in these patients. MPI is a useful imaging modality for the diagnosis of CAD. However, its limitation in severe extensive CAD, the so-called balanced ischemia, has been well documented. The perfusion defects visualized on MPI may underestimate the extent of coronary artery stenosis due to the lack of quantification of absolute coronary blood flow. Even using SSS &gt; 6 as the cut-off, below 8, the sensitivity was still only 77%.</p>
<p>Severe functional parameters on gSPECT MPI are associated with severe CAD. Prior studies have found that TID could be used to diagnose severe CAD in conjunction with perfusion defects. In the present study, the cut-off values for TID were similar to prior investigations [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], however, the sensitivity (20%) was lower than expected. Prior studies had suggested the superior performance of ESV TID over EDV TID [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], while only EDV TID remained significant in this study. Possible explanations for this discrepancy include differences in radioisotopes used (<sup>99m</sup>Tc tracers vs. <sup>201</sup>Tl), differences in stressors used (pharmacological vs. exercise), different imaging protocols, cameras, algorithms, methods of ratio calculation, or even differences in patients’ underlying disease such as diabetes or left ventricular hypertrophy [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The cut-off values of normalcy and the sensitivity of TID for severe CAD also varied in prior studies [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The significantly high prevalence of small heart size (79 patients, 37%) may have contributed to the differences in TID results. Small LV size is not uncommon in the Asian population, especially in women [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Other functional parameters, such as decreased EF or increased pulmonary uptake after stress, are associated with worse prognosis [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p>
<p>Recently introduced SPECT using solid state CZT cameras has shown better intrinsic performance compare with Anger cameras [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The significant reduction in acquisition time allows for rapid imaging before recovery of post-stress stunning [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. However, the differences in prognostic value between gated functional parameters derived from different camera systems have not yet be validated. Although ventricular volume and EF obtained from CZT cameras and Anger cameras have shown good agreement based on prior studies [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], the cut-off values for post-stress abnormalities may be different. For example, the upper limit of post-stress lung/heart ratio (0.41) of patients without CAD in our study was apparently lower than that previously reported [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Furthermore, gSPECT using <sup>201</sup>Tl is clinically feasible using CZT cameras because of higher sensitivity [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], but it could still contribute to differences in functional parameters on gSPECT [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].</p>
<p>The criteria of positive TET result using significant STD was not sensitive enough for the diagnosis of CAD. Using STD &gt;2 mm for severe CAD had poor sensitivity (46%) in this study. However, the HR corrected STD or STD in the recovery stage showed better performance than the uncorrected STD. In addition, abnormal hemodynamic changes after exercise have well established prognostic relevance regarding cardiovascular events and mortality. The delayed decline of SBP during the recovery stage of TET, the so-called paradoxical SBP elevation, was shown to be associated with severe CAD in prior studies [<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134485.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. However, like MPI parameters, none of TET parameters rendered acceptable cut-off values.</p>
<p>The majority of patients included in the current study had intermediate and high pre-test cardiovascular risk. However, estimating pre-test probability of angiographically significant CAD with traditional age, sex, and angina typicality-based approach sometimes overestimates the actual prevalence of disease[<xref rid="pone.0134485.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Therefore stress tests might provide incremental value of risk stratification. The possibility of severe CAD is increasing in patients with intermediate and high risk. The balanced ischemia on MPI might underestimate the disease severity, it is important to consider the risk factors, symptoms and prior treadmill exercise test results. The increment of diagnostic performance of combined MPI and treadmill parameters could be expected; however, previous studies mainly focused on validation of the diagnostic or prognostic significance of CAD of single test, and limited data validated the combination of treadmill ECG and MPI variables in patients with intermediate and high risk groups to our best knowledge. The majority (97%) of enrolled patients in this study had interpretable ECG and was feasible for analysis. The addition of TET to the gSPECT parameters offered better diagnostic accuracy than the individual test, primarily through an improvement in specificity. Using multivariate logistic regression, the probability of severe CAD could be predicted well by a combination of dLHR, 3’STD, and HR ratio. It is worth mentioning that LHR should be calculated despite the small field of view of the CZT camera considering its prognostic significance based on our results. Using the predicted probabilities as a cut-off had high sensitivity, specificity, and accuracy for diagnosis of severe CAD. For the few patients with non-evaluable ECG, as the other six patients (3%) in this study, the MPI parameters were still helpful with the acceptable accuracy.</p>
<p>The major limitations of this study included its retrospective nature and small sample size with heterogeneous characteristics. Only patients who underwent coronary angiography were included in the analysis which may have caused a selection bias. The frequency of coronary risk factors was high in the enrolled subjects, which might limit the generalization for clinical application.</p>
<p>In conclusion, although further prospective validation in a larger population is needed, our results encourage the wide use of treadmill as a stressor for MPI since these treadmill parameters could be easily retrieved from daily practice without additional cost or algorithm.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>This study was partially supported by grants MOST 100-2314-B-002-158 and 101-2314-B-418-012-MY3 from the Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tzen</surname> <given-names>KY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>YW</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Incremental value of coronary CT angiography added to myocardial perfusion imaging in patients with intermediate-to-high cardiovascular risk</article-title>. <source>Acta Cardiol Sin</source>. <year>2015</year>; In press.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jui</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tzen</surname> <given-names>KY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>PET assessment of myocardial perfusion reserve inversely correlates with intravascular ultrasound findings in angiographically normal cardiac transplant recipients</article-title>. <source>J Nucl Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>906</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2967/jnumed.109.073833" xlink:type="simple">10.2967/jnumed.109.073833</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20484427</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schindler</surname> <given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quercioli</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valenta</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrosio</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dilsizian</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantitative assessment of myocardial blood flow—clinical and research applications</article-title>. <source>Semin Nucl Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1053/j.semnuclmed.2014.04.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1053/j.semnuclmed.2014.04.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24948151</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname> <given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Quantitation of myocardial blood flow and myocardial flow reserve with 99mTc-sestamibi dynamic SPECT/CT to enhance detection of coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2294</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00259-014-2881-9" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00259-014-2881-9</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25143072</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharir</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Germano</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanagh</surname> <given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewin</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Incremental prognostic value of post-stress left ventricular ejection fraction and volume by gated myocardial perfusion single photon emission computed tomography</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1035</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10477527</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dona</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Massi</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Settimo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolini</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gianni</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pupi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Prognostic implications of post-stress ejection fraction decrease detected by gated SPECT in the absence of stress-induced perfusion abnormalities</article-title>. <source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00259-010-1643-6" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00259-010-1643-6</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21061121</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges-Neto</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Javaid</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname> <given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname> <given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagnanelli</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Poststress measurements of left ventricular function with gated perfusion SPECT: comparison with resting measurements by using a same-day perfusion-function protocol</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>215</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10796936</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thamilarasan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackstone</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Heart rate recovery immediately after treadmill exercise and left ventricular systolic dysfunction as predictors of mortality: the case of stress echocardiography</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1911</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11602493</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stress-induced abnormalities in myocardial perfusion imaging that are not related to perfusion but are of diagnostic and prognostic importance</article-title>. <source>European journal of nuclear medicine and molecular imaging</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17103165</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sangrigoli</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nkadi</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparison of pulmonary uptake with transient cavity dilation after exercise thallium-201 perfusion imaging</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1323</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10193734</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruddy</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newell</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finkelstein</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strauss</surname> <given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boucher</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prognostic importance of thallium uptake by the lungs during exercise in coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>317</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>1486</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3683484</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berman</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lew</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Potkin</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swan</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Transient ischemic dilation of the left ventricle on stress thallium-201 scintigraphy: a marker of severe and extensive coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>752</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3558976</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzanti</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Germano</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiat</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanagh</surname> <given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alexanderson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Identification of severe and extensive coronary artery disease by automatic measurement of transient ischemic dilation of the left ventricle in dual-isotope myocardial perfusion SPECT</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American College of Cardiology</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1612</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8636545</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abidov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bax</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishina</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoda</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Integration of automatically measured transient ischemic dilation ratio into interpretation of adenosine stress myocardial perfusion SPECT for detection of severe and extensive CAD</article-title>. <source>Journal of nuclear medicine: official publication, Society of Nuclear Medicine</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1999</fpage>–<lpage>2007</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arsanjani</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clond</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyun</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemley</surname> <given-names>M</given-names> <suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fish</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Transient ischemic dilation for coronary artery disease in quantitative analysis of same-day sestamibi myocardial perfusion SPECT</article-title>. <source>J Nucl Cardiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12350-012-9527-8" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s12350-012-9527-8</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22399366</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinoshita</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugihara</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adachi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azuma</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohno</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Assessment of transient left ventricular dilatation on rest and exercise on Tc-99m tetrofosmin myocardial SPECT</article-title>. <source>Clin Nucl Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11805482</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abidov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bax</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hachamovitch</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlach</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Transient ischemic dilation ratio of the left ventricle is a significant predictor of future cardiac events in patients with otherwise normal myocardial perfusion SPECT</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American College of Cardiology</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1818</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14642694</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Winter</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Velghe</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van de Veire</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Bondt</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Buyzere</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van De Wiele</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Incremental prognostic value of combined perfusion and function assessment during myocardial gated SPECT in patients aged 75 years or older</article-title>. <source>Journal of nuclear cardiology: official publication of the American Society of Nuclear Cardiology</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>662</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>uz Zaman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fatima</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samad</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishaq</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wali</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rehman</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Predictive and prognostic values of transient ischemic dilatation of left ventricular cavity for coronary artery disease and impact of various managements on clinical outcome using technetium-99m sestamibi gated myocardial perfusion imaging</article-title>. <source>Ann Nucl Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12149-011-0500-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s12149-011-0500-4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21629988</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rywik</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zink</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gittings</surname> <given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connor</surname> <given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Independent prognostic significance of ischemic ST-segment response limited to recovery from treadmill exercise in asymptomatic subjects</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2117</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9626171</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamasaki</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arima</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tahara</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamekou</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukumoto</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A new criterion combining ST/HR slope and deltaST/deltaHR index for detection of coronary artery disease in patients on digoxin therapy</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1100</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9605049</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimarino</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnabei</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madonna</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmieri</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radico</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatasciore</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A comparison of the diagnostic performance of the ST/HR hysteresis with cardiopulmonary stress testing parameters in detecting exercise-induced myocardial ischemia</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>168</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1274</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijcard.2012.12.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ijcard.2012.12.007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23260751</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Predictors for coronary artery disease in patients with paradoxical systolic blood pressure elevation during recovery after graded exercise</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>119</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17050013</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Usefulness of paradoxical systolic blood pressure increase after exercise as a predictor of cardiovascular mortality</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>518</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.amjcard.2008.04.027" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.amjcard.2008.04.027</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18721505</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cordeiro</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daida</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Squires</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gau</surname> <given-names>GT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prognostic significance of exercise-induced systemic hypertension in healthy subjects</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10072226</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okamoto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamagata</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamane</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuchioka</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Abnormal systolic blood pressure response during exercise recovery in patients with angina pectoris</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8354795</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otahal</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cleland</surname> <given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blizzard</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marwick</surname> <given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharman</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Exercise-induced hypertension, cardiovascular events, and mortality in patients undergoing exercise stress testing: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Hypertens</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/ajh/hps053" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/ajh/hps053</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23382486</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackstone</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pashkow</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snader</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Heart-rate recovery immediately after exercise as a predictor of mortality</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>341</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>1351</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10536127</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foody</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackstone</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Heart rate recovery after submaximal exercise testing as a predictor of mortality in a cardiovascularly healthy cohort</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10744592</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishime</surname> <given-names>EO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackstone</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pashkow</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Heart rate recovery and treadmill exercise score as predictors of mortality in patients referred for exercise ECG</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>284</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1392</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10989401</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vivekananthan</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackstone</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pothier</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Heart rate recovery after exercise is a predictor of mortality, independent of the angiographic severity of coronary disease</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>831</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12957428</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronan</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolk</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname> <given-names>JU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendel</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>ACCF/AHA/ASE/ASNC/HFSA/HRS/SCAI/SCCT/SCMR/STS 2013 multimodality appropriate use criteria for the detection and risk assessment of stable ischemic heart disease: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation Appropriate Use Criteria Task Force, American Heart Association, American Society of Echocardiography, American Society of Nuclear Cardiology, Heart Failure Society of America, Heart Rhythm Society, Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions, Society of Cardiovascular Computed Tomography, Society for Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance, and Society of Thoracic Surgeons</article-title>. <source>Journal of nuclear cardiology: official publication of the American Society of Nuclear Cardiology</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tzen</surname> <given-names>KY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Data-driven respiratory motion tracking and compensation in CZT cameras: a comprehensive analysis of phantom and human images</article-title>. <source>Journal of nuclear cardiology: official publication of the American Society of Nuclear Cardiology</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McHam</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marwick</surname> <given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pashkow</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Delayed systolic blood pressure recovery after graded exercise: an independent correlate of angiographic coronary disease</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>754</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10483957</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Germano</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanagh</surname> <given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slomka</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Kriekinge</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berman</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantitation in gated perfusion SPECT imaging: the Cedars-Sinai approach</article-title>. <source>J Nucl Cardiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17679052</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Afonso</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahajan</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Single-photon emission computed tomography myocardial perfusion imaging in the diagnosis of left main disease</article-title>. <source>Clin Cardiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>E11</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/clc.20534" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/clc.20534</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20014205</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heston</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sigg</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantifying transient ischemic dilation using gated SPECT</article-title>. <source>J Nucl Med</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1990</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16330561</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petretta</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Acampa</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daniele</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petretta</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nappi</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Assante</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Transient ischemic dilation in SPECT myocardial perfusion imaging for prediction of severe coronary artery disease in diabetic patients</article-title>. <source>Journal of nuclear cardiology: official publication of the American Society of Nuclear Cardiology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emmett</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magee</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Wall</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trieu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The role of left ventricular hypertrophy and diabetes in the presence of transient ischemic dilation of the left ventricle on myocardial perfusion SPECT images</article-title>. <source>Journal of nuclear medicine: official publication, Society of Nuclear Medicine</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1596</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ababneh</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sciacca</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergmann</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Normal limits for left ventricular ejection fraction and volumes estimated with gated myocardial perfusion imaging in patients with normal exercise test results: influence of tracer, gender, and acquisition camera</article-title>. <source>J Nucl Cardiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11144482</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kusuoka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashina</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Normal limits of ejection fraction and volumes determined by gated SPECT in clinically normal patients without cardiac events: a study based on the J-ACCESS database</article-title>. <source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17219133</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Normal values for nuclear cardiology: Japanese databases for myocardial perfusion, fatty acid and sympathetic imaging and left ventricular function</article-title>. <source>Ann Nucl Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12149-009-0337-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s12149-009-0337-2</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20108130</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romanens</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gradel</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saner</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pfisterer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparison of 99mTc-sestamibi lung/heart ratio, transient ischaemic dilation and perfusion defect size for the identification of severe and extensive coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source>Eur J Nucl Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>907</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504088</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name>. <article-title>A performance comparison of novel cadmium-zinc-telluride camera and conventional SPECT/CT using anthropomorphic torso phantom and water bags to simulate soft tissue and breast attenuation</article-title>. <source>Ann Nucl Med</source>. <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyagawa</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiyama</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishimura</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mochizuki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Performance of a semiconductor SPECT system: comparison with a conventional Anger-type SPECT instrument</article-title>. <source>Annals of nuclear medicine</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12149-012-0653-9" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s12149-012-0653-9</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22956363</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname> <given-names>FU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaidyanathan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bould</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trickett</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dodds</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Rapid-acquisition myocardial perfusion scintigraphy (MPS) on a novel gamma camera using multipinhole collimation and miniaturized cadmium-zinc-telluride (CZT) detectors: prognostic value and diagnostic accuracy in a 'real-world' nuclear cardiology service</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Imaging</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/ehjci/jet149" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/ehjci/jet149</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23975570</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buechel</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Husmann</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname> <given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pazhenkottil</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Treyer</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Ultrafast nuclear myocardial perfusion imaging on a new gamma camera with semiconductor detector technique: first clinical validation</article-title>. <source>European journal of nuclear medicine and molecular imaging</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>773</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00259-009-1375-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00259-009-1375-7</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20107783</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chikamori</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hida</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uchida</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Igarashi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoyama</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Comparison of myocardial perfusion imaging between the new high-speed gamma camera and the standard anger camera</article-title>. <source>Circulation journal: official journal of the Japanese Circulation Society</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparison of pulmonary uptake with transient cavity dilation after dipyridamole Tl-201 perfusion imaging</article-title>. <source>J Nucl Cardiol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11845129</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaminek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myslivecek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skvarilova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Husak</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koranda</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metelkova</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Increased prognostic value of combined myocardial perfusion SPECT imaging and the quantification of lung Tl-201 uptake</article-title>. <source>Clin Nucl Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11914664</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Songy</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lussato</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guernou</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Queneau</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geronazzo</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparison of myocardial perfusion imaging using thallium-201 between a new cadmium-zinc-telluride cardiac camera and a conventional SPECT camera</article-title>. <source>Clinical nuclear medicine</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>776</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/RLU.0b013e31821a294e" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/RLU.0b013e31821a294e</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21825848</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>YW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sex-specific normal limits of left ventricular ejection fraction and volumes estimated by gated myocardial perfusion imaging in adult patients in Taiwan: a comparison between two quantitative methods</article-title>. <source>Nucl Med Commun</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MNM.0b013e3283422838" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/MNM.0b013e3283422838</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21150486</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chien</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>YT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Myocardial perfusion image in asymptomatic postmenopausal women with physical inactivity and overweight</article-title>. <source>Obes Facts</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>372</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000333439" xlink:type="simple">10.1159/000333439</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22166757</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0134485.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>VY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berman</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rozanski</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunning</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Achenbach</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Mallah</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Performance of the traditional age, sex, and angina typicality-based approach for estimating pretest probability of angiographically significant coronary artery disease in patients undergoing coronary computed tomographic angiography: results from the multinational coronary CT angiography evaluation for clinical outcomes: an international multicenter registry (CONFIRM)</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>2423</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.039255" xlink:type="simple">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.039255</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025600</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>