<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-19575</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028258</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Clinical research design</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cross-sectional studies</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Epidemiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Infectious disease epidemiology</subject>
              <subject>Spatial epidemiology</subject>
              <subject>Survey methods</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Global health</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Infectious diseases</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Bacterial diseases</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Mycobacterium</subject>
                <subject>Tuberculosis</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Tropical diseases (non-neglected)</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Tuberculosis</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Infectious disease modeling</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Public health</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Disease ecology</subject>
              <subject>Preventive medicine</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Pulmonology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Respiratory infections</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject>
          <subject>Infectious Diseases</subject>
          <subject>Respiratory Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Two-Thirds of Smear-Positive Tuberculosis Cases in the Community Were Undiagnosed in Northwest Ethiopia: Population Based Cross-Sectional Study</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Undiagnosed Smear-Positive TB Cases at Dabat DHSS</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Tadesse</surname>
            <given-names>Takele</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Demissie</surname>
            <given-names>Meaza</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Berhane</surname>
            <given-names>Yemane</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kebede</surname>
            <given-names>Yigzaw</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Abebe</surname>
            <given-names>Markos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>School of Public Health, University of Gondar, Gondar, Ethiopia</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Addis Continental Institute of Public Health, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Armauer Hansen Research Institute, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Pai</surname>
            <given-names>Madhukar</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">McGill University, Canada</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">takele_tadesse@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: TT MD YB YK MA. Performed the experiments: TT MD YB YK MA. Analyzed the data: TT MD YB YK MA. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: TT MD YB YK MA. Wrote the paper: TT MD YB YK MA.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e28258</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tadesse et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Tuberculosis (TB) case detection rate remains low in Ethiopia. One of the underlying reasons is the emphasis on passive case finding strategy which may seriously underestimate the burden of the disease. Estimating the prevalence of smear-positive pulmonary TB through active case finding at population level can help assessing the degree to which passive case detection is successful.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods and findings</title>
          <p>This is population based cross-sectional study. The study population was all individuals aged ≥14 years. Interviews using a uniform questionnaire were done initially to identify individuals with chronic cough (≥15 days) and the two sputum (spot and morning) samples were gathered for standard smear microscopy. A total of 23,590 individuals aged ≥14 years were interviewed and 984 had a chronic cough for ≥15 days. Of 831 individuals who provided two sputum samples for acid fast bacilli (AFB), 41 had positive smears. A total of 22 smear-positive TB cases detected through passive case finding were on anti-TB treatment. The prevalence of new smear-positive TB was 174 per 100,000 in persons aged ≥14 years (95% CI: 121–227).The ratio of active to passive case finding was 2∶1. Higher rates of smear-positivity were observed among females [AOR: 3.28, 95% CI (1.54–6.77)], and in the age group ≥45 years [AOR: 2.26, 95% CI (1.12–4.59).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>The study revealed that about two-thirds of patients with active TB remain undiagnosed and thus untreated. This may indicate the need for strengthening case detection at the community level. Furthermore, the high burden of TB among females and in the age group ≥45 years warrants appropriate measures to control the disease.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Financial support was obtained from the University of Gondar, Armeaur Hansen Research Institute and the World Health Organization. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="6"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Tuberculosis (TB) remains one of the major causes of morbidity and mortality worldwide, while TB control strategy Directly Observed Treatment Short-course (DOTS) is one of the most cost-effective interventions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-World1">[1]</xref>. More than 81% of TB cases and deaths comes from developing countries; the TB situation in those countries is aggravated by high prevalence of human immunodeficiency virus, drug resistance, social inequalities, poor TB control efforts and inadequate health care spending <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-World2">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Dye1">[3]</xref>. However, very few population based TB prevalence studies were carried out in these countries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Mineab1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Norval1">[9]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Ethiopia ranked seventh among world's 22 high burden countries, with smear-positive TB case notification rate of 57 per 100,000 population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Federal2">[11]</xref> and 54 deaths per 100,000 population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-World1">[1]</xref>.The National Tuberculosis and Leprosy Control Program began to implement DOTS in 1994 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Federal1">[10]</xref>. In 2010, DOTS coverage is reportedly reached 100% and TB treatment is integrated into general health services. However, TB case detection rate remains very low in Ethiopia (36%) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Federal2">[11]</xref>. One of the underlying reasons is the emphasis only on passive case finding strategy, where TB patients self-report to health care facilities which are not equipped with the necessary diagnostic facilities and qualified health professionals. This strategy has the potential to seriously underestimate the burden of the disease and many TB cases remain undetected and thus untreated creating more chances for TB spread in the community <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Shargie1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-VanLeth1">[17]</xref>. Some interpreted the low detection rate as a sign of declining prevalence of TB rather than failure to detect cases. Population based studies can help to resolve such controversies. Therefore, this study aimed at estimating the prevalence of smear-positive TB through active case finding in Northwest Ethiopia.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Study setting and population</title>
        <p>The study was conducted at Dabat Health and Demographic Surveillance System (HDSS) hosted by the University of Gondar located at Dabat district in Northwest Ethiopia (see map, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028258-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Dabat district has an estimated population of 145,458 living in 27 rural and 3 urban Kebeles (the smallest administrative unit in Ethiopia). The local communities are largely depend on subsistence agriculture economy. The district has two health centers, three health stations, and twenty-nine health posts providing health services for the community. Only the two health centers provide DOTS for TB cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Central1">[18]</xref>. The Dabat HDSS covers ten randomly selected Kebeles with a total population of about 46,165, of which 23,590 (51%) were adults aged ≥14 years. Information on vital events like birth, death, and migration are collected quarterly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Tadesse1">[19]</xref>. Active TB surveillance was introduced at HDSS in collaboration with the district health office in October 2010.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0028258-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028258.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Map of the study area at Dabat district in Northwest Ethiopia.</title>
            <p>Area shaded with different colors-Dabat HDSS.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0028258.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Study design</title>
        <p>Population based cross-sectional study was conducted to estimate the prevalence of smear-positive TB at Dabat district from October to December 2010.</p>
        <sec id="s2b1">
          <title>Data collection</title>
          <p>Eighteen data collectors and three supervisors from Dabat HDSS were trained on pulmonary TB screening. They interviewed all individuals aged ≥14 years using pre-tested and structured symptom screening questionnaire to identify pulmonary TB suspected cases. Persistent cough for ≥15 days with or without other related symptoms was taken as a cardinal symptom for pulmonary TB. They also interviewed each individual whether he or she was on anti-TB treatment. Socio-demographic, geographical, and history of current and previous illnesses information were collected from each individual. After obtaining written informed consent, data collectors gathered two sputum samples (spot and morning) from every subject reported chronic cough with sputum using sputum cup labeled with unique individual identification number. The sputum samples were immediately placed in icebox which was maintained at temperature of 4 degrees Celsius and transported to either of the two-health centers located in the study area within 12 hours for microscopy examination. Poor specimens were replaced with an immediate spot collection. Registration forms were maintained for documentation of sputum transport details. Data collectors traced suspected individuals with positive interview screening to collect two sputum samples (spot and morning). Furthermore, we cross-checked TB registers at health centers to verify that those suspects who said they were taking anti-TB medication were actually on medication and evaluated thoroughly to ensure that individual new occurrences of TB had not been registered more than once.</p>
          <p>The diagnosis of TB was based on the national guideline <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Federal1">[10]</xref>. Sputum smears were prepared from each spot and morning samples. Smears were air dried, fixed and stained with Ziehl Neelsen (ZN) and examined by direct microscopy for AFB. Positive smears were quantified using International Union against Tuberculosis and Lung Disease (IUATLD) standards <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Ditah1">[20]</xref>. All positive slides and 10% of negative slides were re-confirmed by senior laboratory technician at the University of Gondar teaching hospital laboratory. The overall agreement between the two tests was 97%.</p>
          <p>A sputum smear-positive TB case was defined by two sputum smear-positive results for AFB or one positive smear result for AFB with radiographic abnormalities as determined by a clinician or one positive smear results for AFB in the case of HIV positive subjects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Federal1">[10]</xref>.</p>
          <p>The existing National Tuberculosis Control Programme algorithm was used for the diagnosis and treatment of pulmonary TB. Accordingly, all two smear-negative patients clinically investigated and treated by broad spectrum antibiotics for 7–10 day and followed for improvements within 2–4 weeks. Repeated examination of two sputum smears and clinical evaluation were done for individuals with one positive smear and one negative smear. Two sputum smears were repeated for 150 patients who had reported no improvement. All of the patients found negative for both slides and referred to the nearest district hospital for chest X-ray at the discretion of the health officer. Chest X-rays were evaluated by experienced radiologist and 17 patients were diagnosed as smear- negative pulmonary TB. All pulmonary TB cases identified during the survey were treated according to the national guidelines.</p>
          <p>Data were double entered using Visual Basic 6.0 (VB 6.0) and Microsoft Access 2003. Analysis was made using Stata/SE 11 for windows (Stata Corp, USA). Odds ratio with 95 percent confidence interval was calculated for some categorical variables in the study to assess the strength of association.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2b2">
          <title>Ethical considerations</title>
          <p>The study was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB) of the University of Gondar. Written informed consent was obtained from each participant. Informed written consent regarding eligible subjects below 18 years was obtained from parents or legal guardians. Individual records were coded and accessed only by research staff. Immediate referrals were arranged for those found smear-positive and all were started on anti-TB treatment at nearest health centers in the study area. Others found sick form non-TB causes were referred to the nearest health facility for further investigation and treatment.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Study population and TB suspects</title>
        <p>A total of 23,590 individuals aged ≥14 years were screened for pulmonary TB through symptom interviews. Of which 11,198 (47.5%) were males and 12,392 (52.5%) were females with male to female sex ratio of 0.9∶1. The mean age (± SD) of respondents was 34 (±17) years, ranging from 14 to 90 years. . About 63% of respondents had no formal schooling. Of the 984 (4.2%) individuals who had a chronic cough for ≥15 days, 831 provided two sputum samples for smear microscopy examination. Sputum samples were not collected and examined in 9.1% (83/914) individuals since they could not provided sputum samples at the time of data collection. Patients detected as smear- positive through active case finding had a mean delay of 13 weeks between having symptom (cough) and diagnosis following our screening. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028258-t001">Table 1</xref> shows socio-demographic characteristics of study population.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0028258-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028258.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Selected socio-demographic characteristics of respondents at Dabat district in Northwest Ethiopia, 2010 (n = 23,590).</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0028258-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0028258.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number (%)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P-value</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Sex</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11190(47.4 )</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.001</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12400(52.6)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Age group( in years)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14–29</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11384(48.3)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.001</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30–44</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6078(25.8)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥45</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6128(25.9)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Marital status</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Single</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7855(33.3)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.001</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Married</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12960 (54.9)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Divorced/Widowed</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2775(11.8)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Educational level</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No formal schooling</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14844(62.9)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.001</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4817(20.4)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Secondary</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3208(13.6)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">721(3.1)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Residence</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urban</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5027(21.3)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>0.001</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rural</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18563(78.7)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Prevalence of smear-positive TB</title>
        <p>From 984 individuals who reported cough, 150 reported taking anti-TB treatment during the survey. However, a review of TB registers revealed that only 22 smear-positive TB patients were on anti-TB treatment in the same period. Eight hundred and thirty one individuals including the 22 smear-positive TB gave two spot-morning sputum samples for examination. Forty one had new smear positive result, and none of those who were on anti-TB treatment was smear-positive. Thus, the prevalence of new sputum smear-positive TB was 174 per 100, 000 in persons aged ≥14 years (95% CI: 121–227). The ratio of smear-positive cases newly detected by active case finding to those detected through passive case finding was about 2∶1, indicating 2 undiagnosed TB cases in the community for every smear-positive TB case receiving treatment during the survey period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028258-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Higher rates of smear-positivity were observed among females [AOR: 3.28, 95% CI (1.54–6.77)], and in the age group ≥45 years [AOR: 2.26, 95% CI (1.12–4.59)] (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028258-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0028258-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028258.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Sex distribution of study population and TB patients identified at Dabat district in Northwest Ethiopia, 2010.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0028258.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0028258-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028258.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>Prevalence of smear-positive TB by selected socio-demographic characteristics of respondents at Dabat district in Northwest Ethiopia, 2010 (n = 23,590).</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0028258-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0028258.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interviewed</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Positive for AFB</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">COR(95% CI)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR(95% CI)</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Sex</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11190</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12400</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.21(1.53–6.73)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.28(1.54–6.77)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Age group(years)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14–29</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11384</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30–44</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6078</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.50(0.77–2.89)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29 (0.57–2.91)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥45</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6128</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.51(1.05–2.27)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.26 (1.12–4.59)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Marital status</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Single</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7855</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Married</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,960</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.67(0.74–3.75)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35(0.56–3.39)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Divorced/Widowed</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2775</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.90(1.57–9.72)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.85(0.64–5.68)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Residence</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urban</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5027</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rural</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18563</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.58(0.66–3.76)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.90 (0.96–3.99)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>AFB: Acid-fast bacillus; COR: Curd odds ratio; AOR: Adjusted odds ratio; CI: Confidence Interval;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>*: Statistically significant, P&lt;0.05.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This population based cross-sectional study identified TB as a significant health problem among individuals aged ≥14 years old. The study revealed that about two-thirds of the symptomatic sputum smear-positive TB cases in the community were undiagnosed and thus untreated. This suggested that for every confirmed pulmonary TB case on treatment there were about two undetected infectious TB cases in the communities.</p>
      <p>The prevalence of sputum smear-positive TB in this study is 174/100,000 persons aged ≥14 years. Other prevalence survey reported 78/100,000 in southern Ethiopia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Shargie1">[12]</xref>, 80/100,000 in northwest Ethiopia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Yimer1">[13]</xref> and 189/100000 in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Demissie1">[14]</xref>. The observed high prevalence of TB in our study in contrast to a very low prevalence documented in rural Ethiopia could be that in our study all sputum smear-negative TB patients were treated for free according to the national guideline <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Federal1">[10]</xref>, which might have increased the participation rate of symptomatic individuals. In addition, the low HIV prevalence in our rural sites, where 79% of our subjects were drawn, might have also contributed to higher frequency of symptomatic presentations with productive cough thus enhancing the chances for making pulmonary TB diagnosis. According to national figures, HIV prevalence is four times higher in urban (7.7%) than in rural (0.9%) areas, while in our study region the prevalence of HIV was six times higher in urban (9.9%) than in rural (1.5%) areas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Ministry1">[21]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Wide country variations in the prevalence of smear-positivity have been observed and direct comparison has been recognized to be difficult because of differences in sampling, data collection methods, study population, timing of the study, and related environmental and socioeconomic factors. For example, multistage cluster sampling technique was used in some studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Mineab1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Soemantri1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Anna1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Norval1">[9]</xref>, while others used random sampling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Horie1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Shargie1">[12]</xref> or included all samples <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Zaman1">[5]</xref>. The age groups studied were also different among studies and covered all age groups ≥15 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Mineab1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Zaman1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Yimer1">[13]</xref>, &gt;14 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Shargie1">[12]</xref> and ≥14 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Demissie1">[14]</xref>. Thus any comparison of prevalence data either within the country or among countries should be done with great caution.</p>
      <p>This study observed a significant delay in diagnosis; the mean delay between the onset of pulmonary TB symptoms (mainly cough) and treatment initiation following active detection by this study was 13 weeks. This finding is lower than a mean duration of symptoms of 28 weeks for those identified by active case finding in Bangladesh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Zaman1">[5]</xref> and higher than study report from Viet Nam (12 weeks) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Horie1">[7]</xref>. The reasons for this high patient delay could be lack of awareness on TB and its treatment, reliance on the non-modern healthcare providers, repeated visits to health care facilities without correct diagnosis, cost, distance and transport and cultural interpretations of disease might all surface as important barriers to care in this rural area of Ethiopia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Mengiste1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Tatek1">[23]</xref>. Interventions to improve the quality and accessibility at peripheral health services to facilitate early TB diagnosis and treatment remain very important.</p>
      <p>Routine reports based on passive case finding from health care facilities have repeatedly shown higher prevalence of TB for men than women <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-World1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Zaman1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Federal2">[11]</xref>. However, in our study the prevalence of smear-positive TB cases detected through active case finding was 3.3 times higher for females than males. This finding is consistent with data from rural areas of Vietnam <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Horie1">[7]</xref> and Southern Ethiopia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Shargie2">[24]</xref>. This could be due to the fact that, active case finding via household visits reduces the social inequity in accessing health services. Interventions to address gender inequalities are essential to increase TB case detection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Zaman1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Yimer1">[13]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Jianming1">[25]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Neyrolles1">[26]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Study from Guinea-Bissau and three West Africa countries reported that increase in age was significantly associated with TB infection (P&lt;0.0001) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Per1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Lienhardt1">[28]</xref>. Our study revealed that the prevalence of smear- positive TB was 2.3 times higher in older persons. It is known that the risks of TB acquisition, progression and reactivation increase as age increases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Donald1">[29]</xref>. Additionally, older persons may not visit health services because of long walking distance. In this survey we included individuals aged ≥14 years. Smear-positivity is infrequent in those &lt;14 years of age and collection of sputum samples is difficult; exclusion of this group will reduce workload but have only a small effect on the prevalence estimate for the total population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-VanderWerf1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-VanLeth1">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Smear-positive TB case detection rate is 36% in Ethiopia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Federal2">[11]</xref>. Lack of accurate and rapid diagnostics remains a major obstacle to progress in this regard. Health care facilities still heavily rely on sputum smear microscopy for the diagnosis of TB. This technique has low sensitivity and specificity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Karen1">[30]</xref>, however, efforts were made to ensure quality AFB diagnosis through appropriate instruction of symptomatic individuals on how to produce quality sputum sample from their lung. In the laboratory the macroscopic appearance of a sputum sample was checked and poor specimens were replaced with an immediate spot collection.</p>
      <p>The accurate denominator provided by the Dabat HDSS for this study is a unique strength for this study. Furthermore, Geographic Information System (GIS) based mapping is ongoing within Dabat HDSS to link disease patterns to geographic profiles which can generate hypotheses around host spots for TB transmission (such as hotspots for TB), and provide opportunities for targeted interventions such as intensified case-finding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Thomas1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Murray1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Tiwari1">[33]</xref>. This can be done through the innovative Health Extension Program (HEP) of the country that focuses on the prevention and control of communicable diseases in including TB diagnosis and treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Datiko1">[34]</xref>. Further, our estimate is robust as it used well trained data collectors using a simple and validated questionnaire contained selected high sensitive questions to pick suspects of pulmonary TB cases.</p>
      <p>One of the limitations to our study is not doing sputum culture. Ideally, in TB prevalence survey sputum smear and culture should be performed on all screened individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-World4">[35]</xref>. The prevalence of TB may be underestimated by 37% if only symptoms are used to identify TB suspects. Therefore, the strategy we applied cannot detect smear negative but culture-positive TB cases. The TB prevalence studies used sputum screening and sputum culture for confirmation, the chances of detecting smear positive TB cases were significantly greater <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028258-Horie1">[7]</xref>. However TB prevalence surveys in resource constrained countries need to take logistical and financial limitations to offset the criticism of spending the meager resources on research. Although our screening strategy has limitations with the possibility of underestimation, suggesting there are probably more TB cases in the surveyed communities than reported in this study. Furthermore, sputum samples were not collected and examined in 9.1% of the symptomatic individuals that may further aggravate the underestimation of the true TB prevalence in our study. With a better screening method and diagnostic facility, this prevalence could even be more than what is reported. However, one thing is very certain; the passive case detection approach currently implemented in Ethiopia leaves many undetected and thus untreated TB cases in the community perhaps favoring the continuous spread of the disease.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, about two-thirds of smear-positive TB cases remain undiagnosed and untreated creating a cluster of infectious cases in the community that maintain active TB transmission. Thus, the low case detection rate observed nationally can be improved by introducing enhanced case detection mechanisms and promoting favorable health seeking behaviors especially among females and older age groups at the community level using community based health infrastructure.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Addis Continental Institute of Public Health sponsored the primary investigator's doctoral training program. Authors gratefully acknowledge the study participants and health staff of Dabat and Woken health centers of Dabat district that were actively involved in laboratory, clinical and follow up activities.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-World1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization. Global tuberculosis control</collab>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Epidemiology, Strategy, Financing.</article-title>             <comment>WHO /HTM/TB/2010.7. WHO, Geneva, Switzerland</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-World2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization. Global tuberculosis control</collab>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Epidemiology, Strategy, Financing.</article-title>             <comment>WHO /HTM/TB/2009.426.WHO, Geneva, Switzerland</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Dye1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The population dynamics and control of tuberculosis.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>328</volume>             <fpage>856</fpage>             <lpage>861</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Mineab1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mineab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahlbi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuredin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tesfazion</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Determining the burden of tuberculosis in Eritrea: a new approach.</article-title>             <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>             <volume>85</volume>             <fpage>593</fpage>             <lpage>599</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Zaman1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaman</surname><given-names>k</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yunus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arifeen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baqui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Prevalence of sputum smear-positive tuberculosis in a rural area in Bangladesh.</article-title>             <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>             <volume>134</volume>             <fpage>1052</fpage>             <lpage>1059</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Soemantri1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soemantri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senewe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tjandrarini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Three-fold reduction in the prevalence of tuberculosis over 25 years in Indonesia.</article-title>             <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Disease</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>398</fpage>             <lpage>404</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Horie1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lien</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakurada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A survey of tuberculosis prevalence in Hanoi, Vietnam.</article-title>             <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Disease</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>562</fpage>             <lpage>566</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Anna1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kayla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>High Prevalence of Pulmonary Tuberculosis and Inadequate Case Finding in Rural Western Kenya.</article-title>             <source>American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine</source>             <volume>183</volume>             <fpage>1245</fpage>             <lpage>1253</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Norval1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Norval</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roustit</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>San</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>From tuberculin to prevalence survey in Cambodia.</article-title>             <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Disease</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>299</fpage>             <lpage>305</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Federal1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">Federal Ministry of Health Ethiopia</collab>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Tuberculosis, leprosy and TB/HIV prevention and control programme manual.</article-title>             <source>Fourth Edition</source>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Federal2">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">Federal Ministry of Health</collab>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Annual Health Service report.</article-title>             <comment>Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Shargie1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shargie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yassin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindtjorn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Prevalence of smear-positive pulmonary tuberculosis in a rural district of Ethiopia.</article-title>             <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Disease</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>87</fpage>             <lpage>92</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Yimer1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yimer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holm-Hansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yimaldu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjune</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Evaluating an active case-finding strategy to identify smear-positive tuberculosis in rural Ethiopia.</article-title>             <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Disease</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>1399</fpage>             <lpage>1404</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Demissie1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demissie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zenebere</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berhane</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindtjorn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>A rapid survey to determine the prevalence of smear-positive tuberculosis in Addis Ababa.</article-title>             <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Disease</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>580</fpage>             <lpage>584</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-World3">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization</collab>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>STOP TB Partnership and World Health Organisation.</article-title>             <comment>Global Plan to Stop TB 2006–2015. WHO, Geneva, Switzerland</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-VanderWerf1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Werf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgdorff</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>How to measure the prevalence of tuberculosis in a population.</article-title>             <source>Trop Med Int Health</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>475</fpage>             <lpage>484</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-VanLeth1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Leth</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Werf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgdorff</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Prevalence of tuberculosis infection and incidence of tuberculosis; a re-assessment of the symbol rule.</article-title>             <source>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>20</fpage>             <lpage>26</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Central1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">Central Statistical Authority</collab>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Population and Housing Census of Ethiopia: Results for Amhara Regional State.</article-title>             <comment>Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Tadesse1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Getachew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Admassu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amsalu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alemu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Demographic and Health Baseline Survey at Dabat District in Northwest Ethiopia, EJHBS; 15, special issue.</article-title>             <comment>In press</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Ditah1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ditah</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Monitoring tuberculosis treatment outcome: analysis of national surveillance data from a clinical perspective.</article-title>             <source>Thorax</source>             <volume>63</volume>             <fpage>440</fpage>             <lpage>446</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Ministry1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">Ministry of Health</collab>             <year>2007</year>             <source>Single-point HIV prevalence estimate</source>             <publisher-loc>Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>MOH</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Mengiste1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mengiste</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tesfay</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yohannes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witten</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Delays and care seeking behavior among tuberculosis patients in Tigray of northern Ethiopia.</article-title>             <source>Ethiop J Health Dev</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>7</fpage>             <lpage>12</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Tatek1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatek</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kifle</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wondwossen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sofonias</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Delay in initiating tuberculosis treatment and factors associated among pulmonary tuberculosis patients in East Wollega, Western Ethiopia.</article-title>             <source>Ethiop J Health Dev</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <issue>2</issue>             <fpage>148</fpage>             <lpage>156</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Shargie2">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shargie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Odd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindtjorn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Tuberculosis case-finding through a village outreach programme in a rural setting in southern Ethiopia: community randomized trial.</article-title>             <source>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</source>             <volume>84</volume>             <fpage>112</fpage>             <lpage>119</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Jianming1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jianming</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hongbing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Gender difference in knowledge of tuberculosis and associated health-care seeking behaviours: a cross-sectional study in a rural area of China.</article-title>             <source>BMC Public Health</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>7</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Neyrolles1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neyrolles</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quintana</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Sexual inequality in tuberculosis.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Med</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>e1000199</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Per1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Per</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Victor</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cesaltina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rémonie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Tuberculosis in Bissau: incidence and risk factors in an urban community in sub-Saharan Africa.</article-title>             <source>International Journal of Epidemiology</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>163</fpage>             <lpage>172</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Lienhardt1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lienhardt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sillah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bah</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Investigation of the risk factors for tuberculosis: a case–control study in three countries in West Africa.</article-title>             <source>International Journal of Epidemiology</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>914</fpage>             <lpage>923</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Donald1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Age and the epidemiology and pathogenesis of tuberculosis.</article-title>             <source>Lancet</source>             <volume>375</volume>             <fpage>1852</fpage>             <lpage>1854</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Karen1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Megan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vivienne</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philip</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Fluorescence versus conventional sputum smear microscopy for tuberculosis: a systematic review.</article-title>             <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>570</fpage>             <lpage>581</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Thomas1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matthew</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fellx</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Julia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Not just pretty pictures: geographical information system (GIS) in tuberculosis control-experience from Malawi.</article-title>             <source>Malawi Med Journal</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>33</fpage>             <lpage>35</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Murray1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mans</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beyers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayles</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>A multidisciplinary method to map potential tuberculosis transmission ‘hot spots’ in high-burden communities.</article-title>             <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Disease</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>767</fpage>             <lpage>774</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Tiwari1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>CMS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tewari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kandpal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Investigation of geo-spatial hotspots for the occurrence of tuberculosis in Almora district, India, using GIS and spatial scan statistic.</article-title>             <source>International Journal of Health Geographics</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>11</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-Datiko1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datiko</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindtjørn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Health Extension Workers Improve Tuberculosis Case Detection and Treatment Success in Southern Ethiopia: A Community Randomized Trial.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <issue>5</issue>             <fpage>e5443</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028258-World4">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization</collab>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Assessing tuberculosis prevalence through population-based surveys.</article-title>             <comment>Tuberculosis prevalence surveys: A handbook</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>