<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-11107</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108036</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Comparative anatomy</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Developmental biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary developmental biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleoecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Divergent evolution</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary systematics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleobiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleozoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Invertebrate paleontology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Taxonomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal taxonomy</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal behavior</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Horseshoe Crab of the Genus <italic>Limulus</italic>: Living Fossil or Stabilomorph?</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">The Genus <italic>Limulus</italic>: Past and Present</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" deceased="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kin</surname><given-names>Adrian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Błażejowski</surname><given-names>Błażej</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Society of Friends of Earth Sciences <italic>PHACOPS</italic>, Warsaw, Poland</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Institute of Paleobiology, Polish Academy of Sciences, Warsaw, Poland</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Alistair Robert</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Monash University, Australia</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">bblazej@twarda.pan.pl</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BB AK. Performed the experiments: BB AK. Analyzed the data: BB AK. Wrote the paper: BB AK.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<elocation-id>e108036</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Kin, Blazejowski</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A new horseshoe crab species, <italic>Limulus darwini</italic>, is described from the uppermost Jurassic (ca. 148 Ma) near-shore sediments of the Kcynia Formation, central Poland. The only extant species <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic> (Linnaeus) inhabits brackish-marine, shallow water environments of the east coast of the United States. Here it is shown that there are no important morphological differences between the Kcynia Formation specimens and extant juvenile representatives of the genus <italic>Limulus</italic>. The palaeoecological setting inhabited by the new species and the trophic relationships of extant horseshoe crabs are discussed in an attempt to determine the potential range of food items ingested by these Mesozoic xiphosurans. In this paper we propose the adoption of a new term stabilomorphism, this being: an effect of a specific formula of adaptative strategy among organisms whose taxonomic status does not exceed genus-level. A high effectiveness of adaptation significantly reduces the need for differentiated phenotypic variants in response to environmental changes and provides for long-term evolutionary success.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Polish National Science Centre (grant no. 2012/07/B/ST10/04175). The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Xiphosurida arthropods are amongst the rarest of macrofossils. Thus the discovery of new, three-dimensionally preserved Late Jurassic Xiphosurida material adds significantly to our understanding of a group, the stratigraphic range of which spans almost the entire Phanerozoic. The aim of this paper is to describe a new species, <italic>Limulus darwini</italic>, from the Late Tithonian Kcynia Formation at the Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry, near Tomaszów Mazowiecki in central Poland (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Limestones of this unit have yielded a total of eight well-preserved specimens, including one almost completely articulated exoskeleton. The other seven are incomplete; these are preserved as isolated fragments of the prosoma and opisthosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g002">Figure 2</xref>, for anatomy see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Specimens of <italic>L. darwini</italic> sp. nov. constitute the first Late Jurassic representatives of the order Xiphosurida to be recorded from Poland. So far, the sole limulid on record was a specimen of <italic>Limulitella</italic> cf. <italic>liasokeuperinus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Braun1">[1]</xref> from a brackish-marine horizon in the lower Pliensbachian Gielniów Formation at Skarżysko-Kamienna (i.e. south-central Poland – see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Samsonowicz1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Karaszewski1">[3]</xref>); however, this particular specimen was lost during World War II. Mesozoic specimens of horseshoe crabs were extremely rarely found in the fossil record. Previous studies of Xiphosurida of the families Paleolimulidae, Mesolimulidae, and Limulidae of the Limulacea (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Strmer1">[4]</xref>) have revealed mainly time-related, distinguishing features which have been based on often inconsistent phylogenetic and taxonomic criteria. Complicating matters further is the fact that extinct horseshoe crabs are extremely rare and that their remains are usually imperfectly preserved. Detailed analyses of the phylogenetic relationships between extinct and extant families and genera are therefore very difficult <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Sekiguchi1">[5]</xref>. A perusal of the literature reveals that, almost every new find is given the rank of a new genus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Feldmann1">[6]</xref>. Even the proposal by Riek and Gill <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Riek1">[7]</xref> to place the genus <italic>Mesolimulus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Strmer1">[4]</xref> in the family Limulidae thereby eliminating the family Mesolimulidae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Strmer1">[4]</xref> (considered here to be valid), does not significantly alter this situation.</p>
<fig id="pone-0108036-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Panoramic view of the highest level of exploitation in Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry (i.e. unit III and most fossiliferous ‘<italic>Corbulomima</italic> horizon’ occurring in the middle of the quarry wall) and locality map.</title>
<p>Key: 1, Marine sediments, not studied in detail. 2, Shallow water limestone. 3, Siliclastic, fine grained sediments.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0108036-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Three-dimensionally preserved representatives of Late Jurassic <italic>Limulus darwini</italic> that can be assigned to three major size classes.</title>
<p>(<bold>a</bold>) compressed and incomplete prosoma (ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 5); (<bold>b</bold>) Markedly incomplete prosoma (ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 4); (<bold>c</bold>) slightly incomplete opisthosoma (ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 6); (<bold>d</bold>) small, incomplete opisthosoma (ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 7); (<bold>e</bold>), (<bold>f</bold>) Positive (rock slab with imprint) and negative (external mould) of the holotype (ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 1), preserved as slightly compressed and juxtapositioned prosoma and opisthosoma; (<bold>g</bold>–<bold>i</bold>) least-deformed specimen (ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 2), preserved as a near-complete, medium-sized prosoma; (<bold>j</bold>–<bold>l</bold>) flattened, complete prosoma (ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 3), with exceptionally well-preserved right compound eye.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0108036-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Comparison of modern <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic> (left) and oldest known member of the genus <italic>Limulus darwini</italic> (right) from <italic>Corbulomima</italic> horizon of unit III from Late Jurassic (upper Tithonian = Middle Volgian) sedimentary sequence at Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry (central Poland).</title>
<p>(X), (Y) and (Z) - details emphasized, are most substantial morphological difference between both these forms. (cl) - cardiac lobe; (opr) – opisthosomal rim; (pa) – posterial area. Morphological elements of <italic>L. darwini</italic> exoskeleton not known from the fossil record (i.e. movable spines and telson) emphasized in grey.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>After a detailed analysis of three-dimensionally preserved Late Jurassic limulids from Owadów-Brzezinki, it should be explicitly stated that there are no significant morphological differences between these and extant juvenile individuals of the genus <italic>Limulus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Mller1">[8]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Without much doubt modern horseshoe crabs of that genus probably are even closer to Late Jurassic forms than previously thought <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Sekiguchi1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Riek1">[7]</xref>. The morphological features of the opisthosoma of these are very similar to the holotype of <italic>Limulus coffini</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Reeside1">[9]</xref>, a perfectly preserved, non-flattened opisthosoma from the Upper Cretaceous of Colorado, USA. Presumably both forms were closely related, while <italic>L. darwini</italic> most probably constitutes an early link both with <italic>L. coffini</italic> and the extant <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Mller1">[8]</xref>. This also means that the genus <italic>Limulus</italic> existed about 148 million years ago and has survived to the present day in an almost unchanged form. Accordingly, <italic>L. darwini</italic> is here regarded as the oldest known representative of the genus. However, the phylogenetic relationship of the new form with the Early Cretaceous <italic>Victalimulus mcqueeni</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Riek1">[7]</xref> of Australia and <italic>Crenatolimulus paluxyensis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Feldmann1">[6]</xref> of North America cannot be determined fully until more better preserved specimens of the latter are found.</p>
<sec id="s1a">
<title>Geological and palaeontological settings</title>
<p>The study area is located about 18 km southeast of Tomaszów Mazowiecki (central Poland; for details, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Salamon1">[10]</xref>). Here Late Tithonian ( = Middle Volgian) carbonate sediments are exposed in a small working quarry belonging to the Nordkalk Company (Sławno). At the moment, the Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry is the only place in extra-Carpathian Poland where the Upper Tithonian strata are available for study (the classic locality Brzostówka is now within the Tomaszów Mazowiecki town limits; quarries in Pomerania are flooded). The exposed carbonate sequence belongs to the Kcynia Formation, and can be divided into four successive units. Unit I is composed of indistinctly laminated massive fine-grained limestone (∼6.6 m total thickness) with <italic>Deltoideum delta</italic>, which forms a few beds of 40–80 cm thickness. The overlying unit II, c. 2 m thick, is represented by thinly-bedded, fine-grained limestones with occasional distinctive parallel lamination and mass occurrence of calcareous polychaete tubes in one horizon. Unit III, c. 15.6 m thick, is highly fossiliferous and has yielded the horseshoe crabs that are the subject of the research reported here. Unit IV, c. 2.3 m thick, the top of which is unexposed, is developed as organodetrital limestone rich in <italic>Nanogyra</italic> oysters, bryozoans and serpulids. They often form small bioherms. In general, units I, II and III probably represent a transition from an offshore to nearshore, perhaps lagoonal, setting, whereas Unit IV bears evidence of a return to more open marine conditions. Yellowish marls and marly clays of the Pałuki Formation occur lay below the Kcynia Formation.</p>
<p>The uppermost part of the unit (III) is highly fossiliferous, with a horizon of finely bedded fine-grained limestones at its base (also called the ‘<italic>Corbulomima</italic> horizon’), dominated by the small opportunistic bivalve <italic>Corbulomima obscura</italic> and somewhat less numerous <italic>Mesosaccella</italic> sp. It follows that the <italic>Corbulomima</italic> horizon in the higher portion of the section (i.e. unit III), from which all specimens of <italic>L. darwini</italic> originate, was laid down in a very shallow marine basin (perhaps lagoon), which had rather limited links with the open sea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Kin1">[11]</xref>. The constant proximity of the open sea is indicated by occasional finds of ammonites of the genus <italic>Zaraiskites</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Semenov1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>In the unit III representatives of the opportunistic soft-shelled bivalve genus <italic>Corbulomima</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Vokes1">[13]</xref>, disarticulated remnants of various marine and land arthropods (including decapods, beetles, dragonflies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Bechly1">[14]</xref> and grasshoppers) and moulds of ammonite shells are commonly associated with <italic>L. darwini</italic> sp. nov.</p>
<p>The vertebrate fauna comprises disarticulated fish remains (e.g. post-cranial skeleton of pycnodontiform fish), sphenodonts and a few skeletal remains of small indeterminate rhamphorhynchid pterosaurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Kin1">[11]</xref>.</p>
<p>Clearly there are many interesting parallels between the rocks of Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry and the classic Solnhofen lithographic limestone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Kin1">[11]</xref>. The fossils identified at both localities indicate a similar geological age and environment. Both marine and terrestrial organisms are very similar and allow comparative palaeontological studies at a previously unattainable level of taxonomic resolution. The recent identification of a new species of dragonfly (family Eumorbaeschnidae) and grasshopper (family Prophalangopsidae), families previously known only from the Solnhofen area, is an example. Clearly, the Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry may be regarded as a new ‘taphonomic window’ into the living world of the latest Jurassic and it represents the first near-contemporary palaeontological ‘supplement’ to Solnhofen (lower Tithonian) and Nussplingen (uppermost Kimmeridgian). The small palaeochronological distance (5–7 Ma) separating these three locations may enable us to trace lineages, with different stages of evolutionary advancement recorded by the fossils from these localities.</p>
</sec><sec id="s1b">
<title>Preservation of the studied horseshoe crabs</title>
<p>Limulid specimens in this study represent more or less three-dimensionally preserved elements of exuvia representing different age groups and occurring in three major size classes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108036-t001">Table 1</xref>). The holotype of <italic>L. darwini</italic> (ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 1; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g002">Figure 2e, f</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108036-t001">Table 1</xref>) is preserved as a slightly compressed and juxtapositioned complete prosoma and near-complete opisthosoma, but lacks opisthosomal spines. The absence of the telson can presumably be explained by exuvial disarticulation (i.e. stage 3 <italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Babcock1">[15]</xref>). One of the best preserved specimen, ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g002">Figure 2g–i</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108036-t001">Table 1</xref>), is a near-complete, medium-sized prosoma. Specimen ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g002">Figure 2j–l</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108036-t001">Table 1</xref>) is preserved as a slightly flattened, complete prosoma, with exceptionally well-preserved right compound eye. Another specimen (ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 5; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g002">Figure 2a</xref>), not included in the biometric analysis, is preserved as a flattened, incomplete prosoma, with an estimated length/width of c. 55 mm/82 mm. ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g002">Figure 2c</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108036-t001">Table 1</xref>) is a slightly incomplete opisthosoma. The two last-named specimens are parts of a single disarticulated moult (both specimens were found close to each other on the same surface stratum). Thus the maximum size of the new species must have been approximately 105 mm (without telson). Specimen ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g002">Figure 2b</xref>), also not included in the biometric analysis, is preserved as an incomplete prosoma (size, as preserved, 47 mm by 58 mm); its original length and width may be estimated at 53 mm and 80 mm, respectively. The two smallest specimens available are comparable in size, and are both preserved as incomplete opisthosomas: ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g002">Figure 2d</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108036-t001">Table 1</xref>) and ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 8 (not illustrated).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0108036-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Table of biometric measurements of selected specimens <italic>Limulus darwini</italic> sp. nov.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108036-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><italic>Limulus darwini</italic> sp. nov.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimens</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 7</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Prosomal length</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Prosomal width</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼52 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cardiac lobe length</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cardiac lobe width</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Interocular distance</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Opisthosomal length</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼16 mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Opisthosomal width</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼22 mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Axial width</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼19 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Last marginal spine length (anal angle)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼11 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Opisthosomal rim width</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼11 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼3.8 mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Posterial area length</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼7 mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Posterial area width</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼9 mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total length of prosoma &amp; opisthosoma</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.8 mm</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Systematic palaeontology</title>
<p>Phylum ARTHROPODA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Latreille1">[16]</xref></p>
<p>Order XIPHOSURIDA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Latreille2">[17]</xref></p>
<p>Family LIMULIDAE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Zittel1">[18]</xref></p>
<p>Genus <italic>Limulus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Mller1">[8]</xref></p>
<p><bold><italic>Type species</italic></bold><italic>. Limulus polyphemus</italic> Linnaeus, C. 1758. Systema Naturae. Ed. 10(1), 1–824. Salvii, Holmiae</p>
<p><italic>Limulus darwini</italic> sp. nov.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Diagnosis</italic></bold>.–Smaller than the type species, only up to 15% the size (although entirely represented by non-fully grown specimens, possible juveniles); absence of a median cardiac node (which is normally present in the type species); relatively long, narrow and moderately depressed shape of the occipital bands (instead of short, wide and shallow lobes in the type species); smaller size and more slender articular processes (instead of considerably larger and posteriorly expanded in the type species).</p>
<p><italic>Limulus darwini</italic> Kin &amp; Błażejowski 2014 sp. nov. urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FC04D675-4D90-4A32-8C1F-CC0FD04B0A19</p>
<p><bold><italic>Derivation of name</italic></bold>.–In honour of Charles Robert Darwin (1809–1882), for his invaluable contributions to our knowledge of evolution and natural history.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Type locality</italic></bold>.–Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry, close to Tomaszów Mazowiecki, central Poland, 51°22′34.53″N 20°08′07.86″E.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Holotype</italic></bold>.–ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g002">Figure 2 e, f</xref>), stored in the collections of the Institute of Paleobiology, Polish Academy of Science in Warsaw (ZPAL X.1/O-B).</p>
<p><bold><italic>Other material</italic></bold>.–Eight specimens (paratypes), ZPAL X.1/O-B/XA 2 to XA 9.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Stratigraphical range</italic></bold>.–<italic>Corbulomima</italic> horizon, Kcynia Formation, of Late Tithonian (Middle Volgian - <italic>Scythicus</italic> Zone, <italic>Zarajskensis</italic> Subzone and Horizon of Kutek <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Kutek1">[19]</xref>) age.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Geographical range</italic></bold>.–To date, known from the type locality only.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Measurements</italic></bold>.–See <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108036-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Description</italic>.–The holotype has a semicircular prosoma which is approximately 1.5 times wider than long. Its dorsal surface is delimited by a clear and uniformly narrow marginal rim. A single pair of relatively large compound eyes is situated on the well-developed ophthalmic ridges, posterior to the prosoma. The ophthalmic ridges terminate as two tubercles on the posterior part of the prosoma, and do not meet in front of the cardiac lobe. The interophthalmic region is bordered by two rows of poorly marked muscular impressions. The preophthalmic field is moderately wide, with a centrally positioned ocellus at its base. The sharply defined cardiac ridge forms a small median tubercle (in the posterior part) and becomes weaker halfway between the median tubercle and the ocelli. The genal spines are short; their outer margins almost parallel with the median axis of the body; the occipital bands are relatively narrow.</p>
<p>The opisthosoma is nearly hexagonal in outline and consists of a single sclerite with a poorly distinguished axis, without any transverse annulations or longitudinal ridge. The larger anterior part of opisthosoma consists of a small microtergite and six pairs of distinct apodomes ( = entapophyseal pits). The abdominal axis has two axial tubercles, the first halfway between the primary and secondary pairs of apodomes, the second slightly below the border (i.e. large muscle scars) with the posterior part of opisthosoma. The surface of the smaller posterior opisthosomal part, whose axis consists of two segments, forms a subhexagonal area and is separated by a posteriorly elongated and tapering area with three tubercles. The first is a centrally embedded posterior axial tubercle. The other two tubercles are much smaller and are symmetrical, on either side of the posterior axial tubercle. On the anterior ridges there are two symmetrically positioned tubercles. In the region of the first abdominal segment, closer to the axis, are two small articular processes. The moderately wide opisthosomal rim consists of six pairs of short and symmetrically arranged spines, and is terminated posteriorly by two large marginal spines. The structure of the venter (e.g. appendages, genital operculum, flabellum etc.) and construction of movable spines and telson are unknown.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Comparison of <italic>Limulus darwini</italic> with extinct and extant limulines</title>
<p>In broad terms, amongst all known extinct Mesozoic and Cenozoic horseshoe crabs (for details <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Strmer1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Feldmann1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Hauschke1">[20]</xref>) <italic>Limulus darwini</italic> shows general similarities almost identical with the well-known Late Jurassic limuline from Germany and two exceptionally preserved early Cretaceous limulines from USA (details below). This also means that other extinct post-Palaeozoic horseshoe crabs were not taken into account in comparison presented here <italic>inter alia</italic> because of lack of sufficiently well-preserved palaeontological materials (e.g. <italic>Victalimulus mcqueeni</italic> – see above) or recognizable morphological dissimilarity in relation with <italic>L. darwini</italic> (e.g. Middle Triassic <italic>Yunnanolimulus luopingensis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Zhang1">[21]</xref>). Xiphosurans have existed for some 480 Mya <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Lamsdell1">[22]</xref>, with the earliest unequivocal representatives found from the Upper Ordovician of Manitoba, Canada <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Rudkin1">[23]</xref>, followed by further Xiphosurida reports from the Lower Ordovician of Morocco <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-VanRoy1">[24]</xref>.</p>
<p>The new species described in this article shows some features in common with representatives of the genus <italic>Mesolimulus</italic>, in particular with <italic>M. walchi</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Desmarest1">[25]</xref> from the late Kimmeridgian pelitic limestones of Brunn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Rper1">[26]</xref> and Nusplingen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Fraas1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Schweigert1">[28]</xref>, and the early Tithonian lithographic limestones of Solnhofen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Mnster1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Frickhinger1">[30]</xref>. <italic>Limulus darwini</italic> differs from <italic>M. walchi</italic> mainly in having a narrower furrow along the inner margin of the genal angles on the prosoma and in the presence of short articular processes, plus the absence of distinct dorsal furrows on the opisthosoma. Among other features which distinguish these two species are the slender shape of the opisthosoma, the absence of a longitudinal ridge on the axis and the distinct separation of the posterior abdominal sclerite in the new species. Unfortunately, on the basis of material available from Germany, it cannot be determined unambiguously whether or not the last-mentioned differences are a function of the state of preservation of the <italic>L. darwini</italic> specimens, which are significantly less compressed.</p>
<p>The holotype of <italic>C. paluxyensis</italic>, from the Lower Crataceous (Albian) Glen Rose Formation in north-central Texas, has two special morphological features that distinguish it from all other post-Palaeozoic horseshoe crabs i.e. the beaded rims of the posterior region on the prosoma and flanks with two prominent ridges defining a tripartite surface on the opisthosoma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Feldmann1">[6]</xref>. The other exoskeleton features can be considered as generally similar to <italic>L. darwini</italic>, with the special exception of the proportionally much longer genal spines on the prosoma and clearly pronounced axial ridge on the opisthosoma. It is well understood that, during ontogenetic development, the modern horseshoe crabs follow the gradual change in proportions of the prosoma and opisthosoma as well as in dorsal sculpture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Barthel1">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Chiu1">[33]</xref>. Therefore, in our opinion, the significantly larger size of the holotype <italic>C. paluxyensis</italic> (length/wide diameters: 234 mm and 296 mm) precludes a detailed morphological comparison with relatively small exuvia belonging to the new species described herein (see above, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108036-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<p>Comparisons may be made with another extinct horseshoe crab <italic>Limulus coffini</italic>, which is preserved as a three-dimensionally complete opisthosoma (length c. 70 mm). This specimen shows similar morphological characteristics with the abdominal parts of <italic>L. darwini</italic>. Among the most important are six fixed spines terminated posteriorly by two large marginal spines occurring on both side of the relatively deep and wide posterior margin, six distinct apodomes on either side of the axis, and large muscle scars separating anterior and posterior opisthosomal parts. Among morphological features that distinguish <italic>L. darwini</italic> from <italic>L. coffini</italic> are: the lack of a pronounced axial ridge, the occurrence of three (not two) tubercles along the axial ridge and somewhat larger articular processes for the new species from Poland, although it should be noted that the spines on recent <italic>Limulus</italic> are quite variable even within a population.</p>
<p>In comparably sized individuals, i.e. juveniles, of <italic>L. polyphemus</italic> (compare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Babcock1">[15]</xref>), the separation of the larger anterior part and abdominal posterior part of the opisthosoma in <italic>L. darwini</italic> closely resembles the same opisthosomal area. Other morphological features of <italic>L. darwini</italic> also reveal a marked similarity to juvenile representatives of the genus <italic>Limulus</italic>; e.g. the degree of curvature and the general outline of the external margin of the genal lobe, the presence of moderately large lateral eyes placed posteriorly on the prosoma, cardiac lobes and cheek areas which have comparable shape and size proportions, the absence of a clearly marked opisthosomal axis, the presence of six pairs of distinct entapophyseal pits, the position of the first pair of marginal spines, the occurrence of three median tubercles along the axis of the opisthosoma, comparatively deep and wide posterior opisthosomal margin, and marginal spines with closely related outline and size. The similarities between <italic>L. darwini</italic> and <italic>L. polyphemus</italic> listed above, refer only to the dorsal part of their exoskeletons and, at the present time, it is only possible to carry out a limited comparison in this regard. However, a very high level of external parallels of the dorsal parts of both species (reaching about 85% of corresponding features - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g003">Figure 3</xref>) is highly suggestive of a relationship at genus level. The features noted distinguish the dorsal part of the exoskeletons of both forms, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g003">Figure 3</xref>. The most important of these are the presence of a median cardiac node (about halfway down the length of the cardiac rim, marked X) and the shape of the occipital bands (marked Y) on the prosoma, and also the size and shape of the articular processes (marked Z) on the opisthosoma.</p>
<p>Otherwise, with regard to similar sized (juvenile) horseshoe crabs belonging to the other two extant taxa – <italic>Tachypleus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Leach1">[34]</xref> and <italic>Carcinoscorpius</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Pocock1">[35]</xref> – <italic>L. darwini</italic> shows numerous important morphological differences. Among selected examples from both recent juvenile forms are: the compound eyes of <italic>L. darwini</italic> are positioned more anteriorly and their intraophthalmic distance is considerably smaller, the cheek area is much larger and more extensive (especially in the lateral and posterior direction), the cardiac lobes become narrower anteriorly and form a sub-triangle area with a more or less sharp outline, articular processes have different shapes and are directed entirely toward the outside (i.e. forming distinct angle with the opisthosomal axis).</p>
<p>Additionally, in <italic>Carcinoscorpius</italic> the genal spines are considerably broader and the shape of the opisthosoma is regularly hexagonal with a much wider opisthosomal rim. The general similarity of the dorsal part of the exoskeletons of the three above-mentioned genera achieves only about 55–65% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Chatterji1">[36]</xref>; however, this also seems to be a common similarity level between particular taxa of known (both extinct and extant) representatives of the family Limulidae (for details, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Feldmann1">[6]</xref>). A recent comparison of the modern American versus the Asiatic horseshoe crabs genera, based upon molecular patterns, shows that <italic>Limulus</italic> is a sister taxon to the other two genera <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Avise1">[37]</xref>.</p>
<p>In the presently recovered specimens, those of a size comparable to mature individuals of <italic>L. polyphemus</italic> are lacking, and the absence of fully-grown exoskeletons of late Jurassic horseshoe crabs from the fossil record remains enigmatic. According to preliminary assumptions made by Barthel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Barthel1">[31]</xref>, all specimens of <italic>M. walchi</italic> available were probably exoskeletons (moults) of young animals. Lending support to this observation are the finds of giant limulid trackways (i.e. <italic>Kouphichnium lithographicum</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Oppel1">[38]</xref> in the Upper Jurassic of Germany <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Frickhinger1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Kolb1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Schweigert2">[40]</xref> and France <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Gaillard1">[41]</xref>) which have been attributed to much larger (adult?) specimens. We suggest that the absence of large moults of <italic>M. walchi</italic> and <italic>L. darwini</italic> may, in part, have been caused by the much rarer moulting amongst subadult horseshoe crabs (usually once per year), in comparison to juveniles (up to several times), as has been documented for modern limulids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Barthel1">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Chiu1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Sekiguchi2">[42]</xref>.</p>
<p>Thus, it is possible that this was the same in <italic>L. darwini</italic>. The occurrence of moults of three age groups in <italic>L. darwini</italic> in the shallow-water sediments at Owadów-Brzezinki may thus be an example of a limulid nursery. In extant <italic>L. polyphemus</italic> and <italic>T. tridentatus</italic>, nursery grounds are found in shallow coastal zones, where young horseshoe crabs spend the first years rapidly increasing its size, prior to venturing out into deeper waters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Carmichael1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Chiu1">[33]</xref>.</p>
<p>The close morphological similarity between <italic>L. darwini</italic> and juvenile specimens of <italic>L. polyphemus</italic> is very apparent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g003">Figure 3</xref>). The prosomal width of small (juvenile) representatives of <italic>Limulus</italic> and <italic>Tachypleus</italic> usually does not exceed 29 mm; in older juveniles it is estimated to be between 29 mm and 168 mm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Carmichael1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Sekiguchi2">[42]</xref>. Based on these data, we contend that all specimens of <italic>L. darwini</italic> currently available pertain exclusively to moults of juveniles (compare <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108036-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<p>In this respect, the absence of epibionts on small to moderate large exoskeletons of extinct forms, such as Late Jurassic <italic>M. walchi</italic> and <italic>L. darwini</italic>, is also significant. Among extant adult horseshoe crabs a commonly observed phenomenon is the presence of differentiated epibiont associations (e.g. barnacles, bryozoan and slipper shell); these may cover large regions of the carapaces of some individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Tan1">[43]</xref>. Juveniles rarely have epibionts owing to their active burying in the sediment and the presence of mucus secretions on the dorsal parts, which allow them to remove from their exoskeletons any fouling organisms. However, it should be emphasized that adult horseshoe crabs only occasionally exhibit this (burrowing) type of behavior, replacing it by roaming on the surface and shallow digging <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Barthel1">[31]</xref>. Possibly a more important reason is that juvenile horseshoe crabs molt frequently and would therefore not be able to provide a suitable substrate for the epibionts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Key1">[44]</xref>. It seems to be important that the specimens collected so far from Owadów-Brzezinki locality have the potential for studying evolutional changes within the lineage in the timing of development (heterochrony) in which juvenile features are retained by the adult (paedomorphosis).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Palaeoecology of the <italic>Corbulomima</italic> horizon at Owadów-Brzezinki</title>
<p>Environmental interpretations of limestones of the <italic>Corbulomima</italic> horizon (unit III) are controversial. In the near-monotypic faunal assemblages (97 per cent <italic>Corbulomima</italic> sp. exhibiting internal mould preservation – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Kin1">[11]</xref>), organisms that would indicate a clearly brackish-water setting are missing; in addition, there is a total lack of sedimentological indicators of hypersalinity (e.g. authigenic gypsum crystals). Specimens of <italic>Corbulomima</italic> sp. from unit III are characterised by a slight variation in shell shape and ornament, resembling what is known from the extant euryhaline bivalve <italic>Potamocorbula amurensis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Schrenck1">[45]</xref> from the western Pacific <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Carlton1">[46]</xref>. Observations based on modern members of the family Corbulidae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Lamarck1">[47]</xref>, a group which first appeared in the Middle Jurassic and which includes about 35 nominal genera, 15 of them extant (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Yin1">[48]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Anderson1">[50]</xref>) have demonstrated a high degree of tolerance to salinity fluctuations. The maximum level has been recorded for <italic>Potamocorbula amurensis</italic> and <italic>Varicorbula gibba</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Olivi1">[51]</xref>, i.e. between 0 and 30 psu, and this remains almost constant at all growth stages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Carlton1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Nicolini1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Holmes1">[53]</xref>. Detailed studies of palaeoecological preferences of extinct corbulids have enabled similar conclusions to be reached <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Yin1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Lewy1">[54]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Wesselingh1">[57]</xref>. This means that at least some fossil corbulids must have been euryhaline and inhabited water of varying salinity. This, of course, limits their value for detailed palaeoecological analyses. Potentially, their mass occurrence might be suggestive only of episodic physical and/or chemical environmental stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Mandic1">[58]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Diet of recent limulids</title>
<p>The food intake of modern Atlantic <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic> is highly diverse and consists normally of bivalves, gastropods, polychaetes, crustaceans but also when available echinoids, campanularids, teleost fish, foraminifera and a small amount of plant material <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Smith1">[59]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Botton2">[61]</xref>. Similar dietary preferences have been identified in other extant species such as <italic>Tachypleus tridentatus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Leach1">[34]</xref>, <italic>Tachypleus gigas</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Mller1">[8]</xref> and <italic>Carcinoscorpius rotundicaudata</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Latreille2">[17]</xref>, as demonstrated by Chatterjee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Chatterjee1">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Chatterjee2">[63]</xref> and Zhou and Morton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Zhou1">[64]</xref>. A consistent element in the diet of all modern horseshoe crabs is organic detritus, consisting mainly of plant debris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Chatterjee2">[63]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Botton3">[65]</xref>. It is certainly the case that the diet composition of modern representatives varies at different growth stages and is strictly dependent on seasonal food availability which, in turn, reflects the food sources in the inhabited geographical area.</p>
<p>Juvenile and adult <italic>L. polyphemus</italic> prey mainly on invertebrates; for juveniles, this includes bivalves of the genera <italic>Mya</italic>, <italic>Ensis</italic>, <italic>Mulinia</italic>, <italic>Macoma</italic>, <italic>Spisula</italic>, <italic>Mytilus</italic>, <italic>Tellina</italic>, <italic>Gemma</italic> and <italic>Siliqua</italic>, the worms <italic>Nereis</italic> and <italic>Cerebratulus</italic>, and the gastropod genera <italic>Nassarius</italic>, <italic>Olivella</italic>, <italic>Polinices</italic>, <italic>Turbonilla</italic>, <italic>Odostomia</italic> and naticids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Botton1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Botton2">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Botton3">[65]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Walls1">[70]</xref>. Indo-Pacific forms (<italic>T. tridentatus</italic>, <italic>T. gigas</italic> and <italic>C. rotundicaudata</italic>) feed on bivalves of the genera <italic>Anadara</italic>, <italic>Dosinia</italic>, <italic>Placenta</italic>, <italic>Macoma</italic>, <italic>Solen</italic>, <italic>Neosolen</italic>, <italic>Teredo</italic>, a variety of worms (e.g. <italic>Gattyana</italic>, <italic>Phyllodoce</italic>, <italic>Nereis</italic>, <italic>Perinereis</italic>) and gastropods of the genera <italic>Cerithedia</italic>, <italic>Littorina</italic>, <italic>Assimenea</italic>, <italic>Nerita</italic>, <italic>Cassidula</italic> and <italic>Cymia</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Debnath1">[71]</xref>.</p>
<p>However, in terms of statistical representation, among all macrobenthic organisms the most favoured food items are plant debris and small, soft-shelled molluscs (i.e. bivalves and, to a lesser extent, snails). Furthermore, studies conducted on populations of modern <italic>L. polyphemus</italic>, which inhabits most of the eastern North American continental shelf (i.e. from Maine to Florida and parts of the Yucatan Peninsula in Mexico), have demonstrated that the dominant food component may almost exclusively be bivalves, which accounted for up to 87 per cent of total diet for horseshoe crabs examined <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Botton2">[61]</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Potential feeding habits of <italic>Limulus darwini</italic> sp. nov</title>
<p>Owing to a paucity of data, the potential importance of bivalves in the diet of Mesozoic horseshoe crabs cannot yet be fully assessed. The obvious reason for this is the rarity of finds of limuloids of this age and the fact that, in general, there is no conclusive evidence whether an investigated area formed the primary setting in which they lived, or represented merely the area of final burial. Based on available data, only an estimate of the percentage and environmental character of the bivalves in macrofossil assemblages that have yielded Mesozoic Xiphosurida can be made. For example, in the upper Kimmeridgian of Nusplingen (southern Germany), where <italic>Mesolimulus walchi</italic> is very rare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Schweigert1">[28]</xref>, bivalve fossils are uncommon and represent only an allochthonous element <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Scholz1">[72]</xref>. Thus, the Nusplingen area probably did not constitute an attractive feeding ground for <italic>M. walchi</italic>, but could have formed a potential trap for inexperienced or stressed individuals, as in the case of lethal lagoons of the Solnhofen and Cerin (France) areas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Barthel1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Gaillard1">[41]</xref>.</p>
<p>As discussed above, bivalves appear to be basic components of the diet of recent horseshoe crabs. These are represented by different taxonomic groups, among which the most important role is fulfilled by representatives of the order Myoida <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Stoliczka1">[73]</xref>, to which the family Corbulidae is assigned <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Anderson1">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Giribet1">[74]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Taylor1">[75]</xref>. Moreover, Botton and Ropes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Botton2">[61]</xref> demonstrated that bivalves of the genus <italic>Corbula</italic> formed part of the diet of <italic>L. polyphemus</italic>. It is therefore possible that the unusually high numbers of <italic>Corbulomima</italic> sp. at Owadów-Brzezinki may have constituted a kind of food attractor for <italic>L. darwini</italic> and as such, an important part of their diet. It is also important to realise that the majority of specimens of <italic>Corbulomima</italic> sp. are small (shell length between 3 and 12 mm), i.e. closely comparable with the size of bivalves preferred by the young and subadult representatives of extant horseshoe crabs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Botton1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Botton2">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Chatterjee2">[63]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Zhou1">[64]</xref>. This may indicate that the depositional area of unit III could have been both nursery ground and feeding zone for <italic>L. darwini</italic> sp. nov.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the areas inhabited by modern horseshoe crabs (for details, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Sekiguchi1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-SchusterCarl1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Walls1">[70]</xref>) largely coincide with three biogeographical regions of current expansion of the family Corbulidae (i.e. Panamic-Caribbean-western Atlantic; eastern Atlantic-Mediterranean; and Indo West Pacific-Japan-Australia; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Anderson1">[50]</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Wide feeding spectrum and euryhalinity as the key to evolutionary success</title>
<p>Evolutionary changes which are hardly noticeable or show a very slow pace over long geological periods are generally defined as bradytely <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Simpson1">[76]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Fisher1">[77]</xref>. The opposite process, i.e. the clearly evolutionary changes with very fast rate, is defined as tachytely. Simpson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Simpson1">[76]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Simpson2">[78]</xref> introduced the term bradytelic evolvers for groups that survived until today and show relatively little change since the very remote time when they first appeared in the fossil record. Moreover, Simpson established for each category a range centered around an average “lifetime” (for bradytelic species about 100 Ma). So defined, bradytely is nearly identical with the concept of “arrested evolution” proposed by Ruedemann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Ruedemann1">[79]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Ruedemann2">[80]</xref>, and hipobradytely pertains to the exceptionally low rate of evolutionary change exhibited by cyanobacterial taxa proposed by Schopf <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Shopf1">[81]</xref>. The terms and their interpretations presented below (i.e. stabilomorphism; variomorphism) should be construed as detailed explanation of both these evolutionary processes. Due to the nature of the issues discussed, the average rate of evolutionary changes (i.e. horotely) is not included in the discussion, and will be presented in details elsewhere.</p>
<p>Modern Limulacea are classified as opportunistic feeders, which are able to live and reproduce in exceptionally diverse environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Ehlinger1">[82]</xref>. Each of the three genera - <italic>Limulus</italic> (1), <italic>Tachypleus</italic> (2) and <italic>Carcinoscorpius</italic> (3), occurs in moderately deep or shallow water zones along the east coast of North America (1) and south-east coast of Asia (2, 3). All three genera (four species in total) exhibit a high tolerance to changes of salinity in inhabited areas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-SchusterCarl1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Walls1">[70]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Ehlinger1">[82]</xref>. The Asian species, <italic>C. rotundicaudata</italic> is also observed to migrate considerable distances from the mouth to the source area of Hooghly River (i.e. up to 150 kilometers - compare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Annandale1">[83]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Annandale2">[84]</xref>). Attempts at interpretation of the vital environment of Mesozoic Xiphosurida indicate the potential existence of substantial saline tolerance in various genera, which potentially could be closely related to the present-day Limulacea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Riek1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Hauschke1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Barthel1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Holland1">[85]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Pickett1">[87]</xref>.</p>
<p>Levels of polymorphism and heterozygosity for allozyme loci in <italic>Limulus</italic> are comparable to those found in much more rapidly evolving organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Selander1">[88]</xref>. Generally, genetic variation of intra- and interspecific-populations of extant Limulacea is generally considered to be similar to the mean estimates for many other animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Yang1">[89]</xref>. Intraspecific morphological variations are widely recognizable, but limited mainly to the size of exoskeletons and arising from this more or less noticeable differences in the proportions of the various morphological elements (compare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-SchusterCarl1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Chiu2">[67]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Sekiguchi3">[90]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Srijaya1">[94]</xref>). The latter observation may indicate that impact of phenotypic plasticity on morphological modifications amongst horseshoe crabs of the genus <italic>Limulus</italic> is low.</p>
<p>On this basis, it may be assumed that the relative evolutionary conservatism noticeable in <italic>Limulus</italic>, and presumably amongst all known representatives of Xiphosurida, may be related to a unique formula of adaptative strategy, which is a combination of wide feeding spectrum, euryhalinity and eurythermality (<italic>Limulus</italic> survives in the very cold waters of Maine to the very warm waters of the shallow water coasts in Florida and Mexico - approximately 1°C to 30°C). In the case of <italic>Limulus</italic>, the adaptive properties discussed here could potentially provide the exceptionally long-term evolutionary success without significant morphological modification in respect to periodic fluctuations of the environment.</p>
<p>In order to systematize this phenomenon, we propose the term <bold>stabilomorphism</bold>, which may be understood as: <italic>relative morphological stability of organisms in time and spatial distribution</italic>, <italic>the taxonomic status of which does not exceed genus level</italic>. The definition refers exclusively to genera that have survived at least one of the great mass extinctions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Raup1">[95]</xref>, or global biotic crises <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Walliser1">[96]</xref>, and occur in contemporary environments. This means that the morphological structure of the conceptual stabilomorph has been virtually unchanged for more than 65 million years (e.g. <italic>Limulus</italic>), or they are known from the fossil record over comparable period of time (e.g. ammonoid genus <italic>Phylloceras</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Suess1">[97]</xref>). The restricted applicability of this phenomenon may indicate, or even confirm, the multidimensionality of evolutionary processes of living organisms as well as their diversified pace, which presumably depend upon the type and quality of inherited adaptive strategy. It is also obvious that genetic factors, which may have an effect on the evolutionary success of known stabilomorphs, vary in individual cases.</p>
<p>This notion demands precise confirmation of evolutionary longevity to regard certain genera as stabilomorphs. In order to classify the effectiveness of their adaptive strategy a five-step scale has been proposed. It's scope is related with the ability to survive considerable biotic crises that coincide with the greatest mass extinctions in the history of life ( = Big Five <italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Raup1">[95]</xref> – <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0108036-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Graphical expression of the concept of stabilomorphism.</title>
<p>Evident (D–G) and potential (C and H) stabilomorphs (i.e. organisms not extending the genus level, with very slow rate of evolutionary speciation). The proposed degree of stabilomorphism (1–5) is consistent with a five-step scale of the greatest mass extinctions in the history of life (I–V) (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Raup1">[95]</xref>). Note that two genera (A and B), previously recognized as a model example of living fossils would thereby lose their present status (see explanations in text). Information about the stratigraphic ranges of stabilomorphs were taken from: (A) – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Forey1">[116]</xref>; (B) – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Sanders1">[117]</xref>; (C) – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Sepkoski1">[118]</xref>; (D) – data presented here; (E) – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Zhou2">[119]</xref>; (F) – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Stockey1">[120]</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Stockey2">[121]</xref>; (G) – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Luchetti1">[122]</xref>; (H) – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Emig1">[123]</xref>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108036.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Genera other than <italic>Limulus</italic>, persisting not less than the above proposed time limit (i.e. at least 65 million years), and well known both contemporarily and from the fossil record, are commonly referred as living fossils <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Darwin1">[98]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Gould1">[99]</xref>. These genera (e.g. <italic>Triops</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-SchrankFvon1">[100]</xref>, <italic>Araucaria</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Jussieu1">[101]</xref>, <italic>Ginkgo</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Linnaeus1">[102]</xref> and, probably, <italic>Lingula</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Bruguire1">[103]</xref> and <italic>Brachaelurus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Ogilby1">[104]</xref>) seemto fulfil the criteria of stabilomorphs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Finally, in strict scientific terms, we propose that the imprecise and unusually broad popular-science concept of living fossil should be replaced by the easy-to-define term <bold>stabilomorph</bold>. In view of the hypothesis adopted here, some genera previously recognized as a model examples of living fossils (e.g. <italic>Nautilus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Linnaeus2">[105]</xref>, <italic>Latimeria</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Smith2">[106]</xref> – <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108036-g004">Figure 4</xref>) lose their present status.</p>
<p>A variability of lesser features within a population, and, perhaps more visibly between populations over a period of time is a fundamental feature of all living organisms; this is the basis for acceptance of evolution as a process. The most important clue derived from a comparison of recent and fossil late-Jurassic <italic>Limulus</italic> species is that their level of adaptation, the quality of their adaptive strategy is so high (so effective), that small changes which had to continually occur over several millions years (in the case of <italic>L. darwini</italic>, at least 148 Ma) did not result in any significant morphology variations. In applying this concept to other supposed stabilomorphs, it implies that their adaptation reached such a point in their development, that they (as a group) could afford to “reject” any further changes.</p>
<p>One still open question is of primary or secondary origin of the unique features of hemolymph of recent Limulacea (for discuss, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Iwanaga1">[107]</xref>), i.e. the violent amebocyte reaction to the presence of pirogenic endotoxins (i.e. lipopolysaccharides) produced by bacteria. This property is used, <italic>inter alia</italic>, in the medical industry, i.e. in the LAL test ( = Limulus Amebocyte Lysate) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Norvitsky1">[108]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Walls2">[110]</xref>. Presumably this feature increases the quality of the adaptive strategy within extant horseshoe crabs and, in consequence, affects the increased survival rate in subsequent populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Mikkelsen1">[111]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Leibovitz1">[112]</xref>. Naturally, issues of occurrences of this unique hemolymph feature among extinct Limulacea are highly problematic and it is regrettable that there is no opportunity to confirm this phenomenon within the fossil record.</p>
<p>Interestingly, specific counterparts of antibacterial properties of recent horseshoe crab hemolymph (e.g. anti-bacterial skin glands secretions) have also been recognized among representatives of other animal groups, characterized by strong evolutionary conservatism (e.g. frogs, crocodiles, sharks; for details, see – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Zasloff1">[113]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108036-Merchant1">[115]</xref>).</p>
<p>However, it is important to recognise in the Author's hypothesis adopted here, some organisms with adaptive abilities opposite to stabilomorphs, exhibiting deficiency of morphological stability, featuring a number of phenotypic variants in response to environmental changes. They would have fossil record rather short in the evolutionary time scale. Organisms exhibiting these characteristics might be specified as <bold>variomorphs</bold>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>The studied fossils of <italic>Limulus darwini</italic> were collected by authors during fieldwork in the Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry (lat. 51.374238°, lon. 20.136343°) in 2009–2013 (permission number: 1/2007/227, issued by Robert Siuda, Managing Director of Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry of the Nordkalk Company - branch in Poland). The collected material (both holotype and paratypes) are housed at the Institute of Paleobiology, Polish Academy of Science in Warsaw (ZPAL X.1/O-B). All studied specimens were on loan to the authors for the entire scientific study period. Fossils were measured using vernier callipers with an accuracy of 0.05 mm. All specimens have been prepared manually at the Museum of Association of Friends of Geosciences in Łódź and Institute of Paleobiology, Polish Academy of Science in Warsaw. The photography was carried out both in Łódź (Museum of Association of Friends of Geosciences) and Warsaw (Institute of Paleobiology, Polish Academy of Science). Photographs were taken using a Canon EOS 400D Digital Camera. All figures have subsequently been edited with Adobe Photoshop CS3 imaging software.</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Nomenclatural Act</title>
<p>The electronic edition of this article conforms to the requirements of the amended International Code of Zoological Nomenclature, and hence the new names contained herein are available under that Code from the electronic edition of this article. This published work and the nomenclatural acts it contains have been registered in ZooBank, the online registration system for the ICZN. The ZooBank LSIDs (Life Science Identifiers) can be resolved and the associated information viewed through any standard web browser by appending the LSID to the prefix “<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zoobank.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://zoobank.org/</ext-link>”. The LSID for this publication is: urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 8BB366FF-7999-4768-A0A5-72521D9606CB. The electronic edition of this work was published in a journal with an ISSN, and has been archived and is available from the following digital repositories: PubMed Central, LOCKSS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lockss.org" xlink:type="simple">www.lockss.org</ext-link>).</p>
</sec></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>Adrian Kin passed away before the submission of the final version of this manuscript. Błażej Błażejowski accepts responsibility for the integrity and validity of the data collected and analyzed. We would like to sincerely thank Adrian's wife Kasia Kin for assistance and support during fieldwork over many years. We thank Peter Walsh (University of Silesia), Rodney M. Feldmann (Kent State University) and John W. M. Jagt (Natuurhistorisch Museum Maastricht) for many useful suggestion and correction of English. We also appreciate the help provided in the field of Robert Siuda and Cezary Błaszczyk (both from Owadów-Brzezinki Quarry, Nordkalk Company). We express our thank to Jennifer H. Mattei (Sacred Heart University) and H. Jane Brockmann (University of Florida) for many helpful suggestions related to living horseshoe crabs during the early phase of this investigation. And last but not least, we wish to acknowledge David Rudkin (Royal Ontario Museum) for his critical review and very helpful comments that improved the manuscript, and two anonymous reviewers.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Braun1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Braun CF (1860) Die Thiere in den Pflanzenschiefern der Gegend von Bayreuth. 1771, Zool. Fundamenta.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Samsonowicz1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Samsonowicz J (1952) Era mezozoiczna w Polsce. <italic>in</italic> MKsiążkiewicz and JSamsonowicz, Zarys geologii Polski. 90–130. [in Polish]</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Karaszewski1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karaszewski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Obecność rzadkiej skamieniałości – limulusa w liasie świętokrzyskim</article-title>. <source>Przegląd Geol</source> <volume>23</volume><supplement>(10)</supplement>: <fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage> [in Polish].</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Strmer1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Størmer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1952</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny and taxonomy of fossil horseshoe crabs</article-title>. <source>J Paleon</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>630</fpage>–<lpage>640</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Sekiguchi1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Sekiguchi K, Shuster CN Jr. (2009) Limits on the global distribution of horseshoe crab (Limulacea): Lessons learned from two lifetimes of observations: Asia and America. <italic>in</italic> Tanacredi JT, Botton ML and Smith DR (eds.). Biology and Conservation of Horseshoe Crabs. Springer, New York, 5–24.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Feldmann1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schweitzer</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dattilo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farlow</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Remarkable preservation of a new genus and species of limuline horseshoe crab from the Cretaceous of Texas, USA</article-title>. <source>Palaeontology</source> <volume>54</volume> <supplement>(6)</supplement>: <fpage>1337</fpage>–<lpage>1346</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Riek1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riek</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>A new xiphosuran genus from Lower Cretaceous freshwater sediments at Koonwarra, Victoria, Australia</article-title>. <source>Paleontology</source> <volume>14</volume> <supplement>(2)</supplement>: <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Mller1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name> (<year>1785</year>) <article-title>Entomostraca seu Insecta Testacea</article-title>. <source>Lipsiae et Hafniae</source> <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Reeside1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeside</surname><given-names>JB</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name> (<year>1952</year>) <article-title>A Cretaceous horseshoe crab from Colorado</article-title>. <source>J Wash Acad Sci</source> <volume>42</volume> <supplement>(6)</supplement>: <fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Salamon1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salamon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zatoń</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gajerski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Tithonian (Upper Jurassic) crinoids from Central Poland</article-title>. <source>Paläontologie, Stratigraphie, Fazies (14), Freiberger Forsch C</source> <volume>511</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage> Freiberg.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Kin1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruszczyński</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Błażejowski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The paleoenvironment and taphonomy of a Late Jurassic (Late Tithonian) Lagerstädtte from central Poland</article-title>. <source>Lethaia</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Semenov1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Semenov VP (1898) Opyt prilozhenija statisticheskovo metoda k izucheniju raspredelenija ammonitov v russkoj jure. Ježeg Geol Miner Rossii 2, Varšava – Novo-Aleksandria.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Vokes1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vokes</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name> (<year>1945</year>) <article-title>Supraspecific groups of the pelecypod family Corbulidae</article-title>. <source>Bull Amer Mus Nat Hist</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Bechly1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>First record of the fossil dragonfly family Eumorbaeschnidae from the Upper Jurassic of Poland</article-title>. <source>Acta Pal Polonica</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Babcock1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Babcock</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title><italic>Paleolimulus</italic>, an early limuline (Xiphosurida), from Pennsylvanian—Permian Lagerstatten of Kansas and taphonomic comparison with modern <italic>Limulus</italic></article-title>. <source>Lethaia</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Latreille1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Latreille PA (1829) Le Règne animal. (Ed. Cuvier, C.L.C.F.D.). 2nd ed., vol. 4. Crustacés, arachnides et partie des insectes. Paris, Déterville, 1584.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Latreille2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Latreille PA (1802) Histoire Naturelle Generale et particuliere des Cristaces et Insectes. Dufact, Paris, 1–467.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Zittel1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zittel</surname><given-names>K von</given-names></name> (<year>1881–85</year>) <article-title>Handbuch d. Palaeontologie</article-title>. <source>Palaeozool</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>640</fpage>–<lpage>645</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Kutek1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kutek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Scythicus</italic> Zone (Middle Volgian) in Poland: its ammonites and biostratigraphic subdivisions</article-title>. <source>Acta Geol Polonica</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Hauschke1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauschke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Zur Verbreitung und Okologiemesozoischer Limuliden</article-title>. <source>Neues Jahr Geol Paläon Abh</source> <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Zhang1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lü</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>First occurrence of horseshoe crab (Arthropoda) fossils from China</article-title>. <source>Prog Nat Sci</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1090</fpage>–<lpage>1093</lpage> [In Chinese].</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Lamsdell1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamsdell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Revised systematics of Palaeozoic ‘horseshoe crabs’ and the myth of monophyletic Xiphosura</article-title>. <source>Zool Jour Linnean Soc</source> <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Rudkin1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nowlan</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The oldest horseshoe crab: a new xiphosurid from late Ordovician konservat-lagerstätten deposits, Manitoba, Canada</article-title>. <source>Palaeontology</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-VanRoy1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Roy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botting</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vinther</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ordovician faunas of Burgess Shale type</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>465</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Desmarest1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Desmarest AG (1822) Les Crustacés prominent dits. <italic>in</italic> ABrongniart and A. GDesmarest, Historie naturelle des crustacés, sous les rapports zoologiques, 67–142.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Rper1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Röper M, Rothgaenger M, Rothgaenger K (1996) Die Plattenkalke von Brunn (Landkreis Regensburg). Eichendorf (Eichendorf Verlag), 1–102.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Fraas1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1855</year>) <article-title>Beiträge zum obersten weissen Jura in Schwaben</article-title>. <source>Jh Ver vaterl Naturkde Württemberg</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Schweigert1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweigert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Miscellanea aus dem Nusplinger Plattenkalk (Ober-Kimmeridgian, Schwäbische Alb), 4</article-title>. <source>Limuliden Jber Mitt oberrhein Geol Ver NF</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Mnster1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Münster G (1840) Über die fossilen Arten <italic>Limulus</italic> in den lithographischen Schiefern von Bayern. <italic>in</italic> Münster, G. Graf zu (ed.) Beiträge zur Petrefacten-Kunde 3: 26–27.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Frickhinger1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Frickhinger KA (1994) The fossils of Solnhofen. Korb Goldschneck-Verlag 1–336.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Barthel1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barthel</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title><italic>Limulus</italic>: a living fossil. Horseshoe crabs and interpretation of an. Upper Jurassic environment (Solnhofen)</article-title>. <source>Naturwissenshaften</source> <volume>61</volume> <supplement>(10)</supplement>: <fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Carmichael1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rutecki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valiela</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Abundance and population structure of the Atlantic horseshoe crab <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic> in Pleasant Bay, Cape Cod</article-title>. <source>Mar Ecol Prog Ser</source> <volume>246</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Chiu1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>HMC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The Behaviour of Juvenile Horseshoe Crabs, <italic>Tachypleus tridentatus</italic> (Xiphosura), on a Nursery Beach at Shui Hau Wan, Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>Hydrobiologia</source> <volume>523</volume> <supplement>(1–3)</supplement>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Leach1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1819</year>) <article-title>Dictionnaire des Science Naturelle</article-title>. <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Pocock1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name> (<year>1902</year>) <article-title>The taxonomy of recent species of <italic>Limulus</italic></article-title>. <source>Mag Nat Hist</source> <volume>9</volume> <supplement>(7)</supplement>: <fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Chatterji1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Chatterji A (1994) The Horseshoe Crab—A Living Fossil (Orissa, India: A Project Swarajya Publication), 157 pp.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Avise1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avise</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>A speciational history of “living fossils”: molecular evolutionary patterns in horseshoe crabs</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1986</fpage>–<lpage>2001</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Oppel1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oppel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1862</year>) <article-title>Ueber Fährten lithographischen Schiefer (<italic>Ichnites lithographicus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Paläeontologische Mitteilungen aus dem Museum des Koeniglich Bayerischen Staates</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Kolb1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>Riesige <italic>Limulus</italic>-Fährte aus den lithographischen Schiefern bei Pfalzpaint</article-title>. <source>Geol Blätter Nordost-Bayern</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Schweigert2"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweigert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Die Spurenfauna des Nusplinger Plattenkalks (Oberjura, Schwäbische Alb)</article-title>. <source>Stutt Beitr Natur B</source> <volume>262</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Gaillard1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A giant limulid trackway (<italic>Kouphichnium lithographicum</italic>) from the lithographic limestones of Cerin (Late Kimmeridgian, France): ethological and environmental implications</article-title>. <source>Swiss J Geosci</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Sekiguchi2"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seshimo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Post-Embryonic Development of the Horseshoe Crab</article-title>. <source>Biol Bull</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Tan1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christianus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul Satar</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Epibiont Infestation on Horseshoe Crab <italic>Tachypleus gigas</italic> (Müller) at Pantai Balok in Peninsular Malaysia</article-title>. <source>Our Nature</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Key1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Key MM Jr, Jeffries WB, Voris HK, Yang CM (1996) Epizoic bryozoans and mobile ephemeral host substrata. Reprinted from Gordon DP, Smith AM, Grant-Mackie JA. Bryozoans in space and time. Proceedings of the 10th International Bryozoology Conference, Wellington, New Zealand; 1995. National Institute of Water and Atmospheric Research Ltd, Wellington, 1–442.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Schrenck1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Schrenck L (1867) Mollusken des Amur-Landes und des Nordjapanischen Meeres. Reisen und Forschungen im Amur-Lande In den Jahren 1854–1856, Vol. 2. Kaiserliche Akademie der Wlssenschaften. St Petersburg, 259–974.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Carlton1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlton</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schemel</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Remarkable invasion of San Francisco Bay (California, USA) by the Asian clam <italic>Potamocorbula amurensis</italic>. I. Introduction and dispersal</article-title>. <source>Mar Ecol Prog Ser</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Lamarck1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamarck</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>1818</year>) <article-title>Histoire Naturelle des Animaux sans Vertebres</article-title>. <source>Paris</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>612</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Yin1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fürsich</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>An endemic brackish water faunule from the Middle Jurassic of southern Qinghai Province, China</article-title>. <source>Paläon Zeitsch</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Harper1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The Middle Jurassic bivalve ‘<italic>Cuspidaria</italic>’ <italic>ibbetsoni</italic>: a corbulid not a septibranch</article-title>. <source>Palaeontology</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>759</fpage>–<lpage>769</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Anderson1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roopnarine</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Evolution and Phylogenetic Relationships of Neogene Corbulidae (Bivalvia, Myoidea) of Tropical America</article-title>. <source>J Paleon</source> <volume>77</volume> <supplement>(6)</supplement>: <fpage>1086</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Olivi1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Olivi G (1792) Zoologia adriatica ossia catalogo ragionato degli animali del golfo e delle lagune di venezia. Bassano, Venecia, 1–334.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Nicolini1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolini</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penry</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Spawning, fertilization, and larval development of <italic>Potamocorbula amurensis</italic> (Mollusca: Bivalvia) from San Francisco Bay, California</article-title>. <source>Pac Sci</source> <volume>54</volume> <supplement>(3)</supplement>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Holmes1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Aspects of the ecology and population genetics of the bivalve <italic>Corbula gibba</italic></article-title>. <source>Mar Ecol Prog Ser</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Lewy1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewy</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samtleben</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Functional morphology and palaeontological significance of the conchiolin layers in corbulid pelecypods</article-title>. <source>Lethaia</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Yin2"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>An isotopic study of paleosalinity with Jurassic fossil shells</article-title>. <source>Earth Science (Ch Univ Geosci)</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>553</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage> [in Chinese with English abstract].</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Yin3"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Brackish water bivalve fauna in Jurassic Yanshiping Group of southern Qinghai and its paleosalinity analysis</article-title>. <source>Acta Pal Sin</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>434</lpage> Beijing. [in Chinese with English Sumary].</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Wesselingh1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wesselingh</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>A Pliocene freshwater molluscan faunule from Guatemala, with implications for Neogene neotropical molluscan dispersal</article-title>. <source>Doc Nat</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Mandic1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandic</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harzhauser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spezzaferri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zuschin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The paleoenvironment of an early Middle Miocene Paratethys sequence in NE Austria with special emphasis on paleoecology of mollusks and foraminifera</article-title>. <source>Geobios</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Smith1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>OR</given-names></name> (<year>1953</year>) <article-title>Notes on the ability of the horseshoe crab <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic> to locate soft-shell clams <italic>Mya arenaria</italic></article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>636</fpage>–<lpage>637</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Botton1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Importance of predation by horseshoe crabs, <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic>, to an intertidal sand flat community</article-title>. <source>J Mar Res</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Botton2"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ropes</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Feeding ecology of horseshoe crabs on the continental shelf, New Jersey to North Carolina</article-title>. <source>Bull Mar Sci</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Chatterjee1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar R</surname><given-names>Vijay</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parulekar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Growth and morphometric characteristic in the horseshoe crab, <italic>Carcinoscorpius rotundicauda</italic> (Latreille) from Canning (WestBengal), India</article-title>. <source>Pak J Sci Ind Res</source> <volume>31</volume> <supplement>(5)</supplement>: <fpage>352</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Chatterjee2"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parulekar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Feeding behaviour and food selection in the horseshoe crab, <italic>Tachypleus gigas</italic> (Müller)</article-title>. <source>Hydrobiologia</source> <volume>246</volume> <supplement>(1)</supplement>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Zhou1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The diets of juvenile horseshoe crabs, <italic>Tachypleus tridentatus</italic> and <italic>Carcinoscorpius rotundicauda</italic> (Xiphosura), from nursery beaches proposed for conservation in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>J Nat Hist</source> <volume>38</volume> <supplement>(15)</supplement>: <fpage>1915</fpage>–<lpage>1925</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Botton3"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Diet and food preferences of the adult horseshoe crab, <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic>, in Delaware Bay, New Jersey, USA</article-title>. <source>Mar Biol</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-SchusterCarl1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Schuster Carl N Jr. (1982) A pictorial review of the natural history and ecology of the horseshoe crab, <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic>, with reference to other Limulidae. <italic>in</italic> Alan RLiss (ed.), Physiology and Biology of Horseshoe Crabs: Studies on Normal and Environmentally Stressed Animals, New York, 1–167.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Chiu2"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The morphology differentiation of two horseshoe crabs, <italic>Tachypleus tridentatus</italic> and <italic>Carcinoscorpius rotundicaudata</italic> (Xiphosura), in Hong Kong with a regional Asian comparison</article-title>. <source>J Nat Hist</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>2369</fpage>–<lpage>2382</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Manton1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Manton SM (1977) The Arthropoda: habits, functional morphology, and evolution. Clarendon Press, 1–527.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Botton4"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haskin</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Distribution and feeding of the horseshoe crab, <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic>, on the continental shelf off New Jersey</article-title>. <source>Fish Bull</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Walls1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berkson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The horseshoe crab, <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic>: 200 million years of existence, 100 years of study</article-title>. <source>Rev Fish Sci</source> <volume>10</volume> <supplement>(1)</supplement>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Debnath1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Debnath R (1992) Studies on Indian horseshoe crabs (Merostomata: Xiphosura) with special reference to its feeding behaviour. Unpublished PhD dissertation. Department of Marine Science, University of Calcutta, Calcutta, India, 1–158.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Scholz1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schweigert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bivalves from the Nusplingen Lithographic Limestone (Jurassic, Upper Kimmeridgian, Southern Germany)</article-title>. <source>Palaeodiversity</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Stoliczka1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoliczka</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1870–1871</year>) <article-title>Cretaceous fauna of southern India; III. The Pelecypoda, with a review of all known genera of this class, fossil and Recent. Palaeontologia Indica, Mem</article-title>. <source>Geol Soc India</source> <volume>6</volume> <supplement>(3)</supplement>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Giribet1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Giribet G, Distel D (2003) Bivalve phylogeny and molecular data. <italic>in</italic> CLydeard and D. RLindberg (eds.), Molecular Systematics and Phylogeography of Mollusks, 45–90. Smithsonian, Washington.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Taylor1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dyal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A molecular phylogeny of heterodont bivalves (Mollusca: Bivalvia: Heterodonta): new analyses of 18S and 28S rRNA genes</article-title>. <source>Zool Scri</source> <volume>36</volume> <supplement>(6)</supplement>: <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Simpson1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Simpson GG (1944) Tempo and Mode in Evolution. New York: Columbia Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Fisher1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Fisher, D. 1984. The Xiphosurida: archetypes of bradytely?, p. 196–213. <italic>In</italic> NEldredge and S. MStanley (eds.), Living Fossils. Springer-Verlag, New York.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Simpson2"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Simpson GG (1953) The major features of evolution. Columbia Univ. Press, New York, 1–434.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Ruedemann1"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruedemann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1922a</year>) <article-title>Additional studies of arrested evolution</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>8</volume> <supplement>(3)</supplement>: <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Ruedemann2"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruedemann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1922b</year>) <article-title>Further notes on the paleontology of arrested evolution</article-title>. <source>Amer Natur</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Shopf1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shopf</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>“Hypobradytely”: Comparison of rates of Precambrian and Phanerozoic evolution</article-title>. <source>J Vert Pale</source> <volume>7</volume> <supplement>(3)</supplement>: <fpage>25</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Ehlinger1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Ehlinger GS, Tankersley RA (2009) Ecology of Horseshoe Crabs in Microtidal Lagoons. <italic>In</italic> Biology and Conservation of Horseshoe Crabs (eds. Tanacredi JT, Botton ML, Smith DR). Springer, New York, 149–162.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Annandale1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Annandale</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1909</year>) <article-title>The habits of Indian king crabs</article-title>. <source>Rec Ind Mus</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Annandale2"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Annandale</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1922</year>) <article-title>The marine element in the fauna of Ganges</article-title>. <source>Bijdr Dierk Amsterdam</source> <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Holland1"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Holland FD, Erickson JM Jr., O'Brien DE (1975) <italic>Casterolimulus</italic>: a new Late Cretaceous link in limulid lineage. <italic>in</italic> Pojeta J Jr., Pope JK (eds.), Stud Paleo Strat 67: 235–249.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Boada1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boada</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villalta</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cerdá</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Paleontología y palcoecologia de los yacimientos fosiliferos del Muschelkalk superior entre Aleover y Montral (Montañas de Prades. Provincia de Tarragona)</article-title>. <source>Cuade Geol Ibér</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Pickett1"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>A new freshwater limuloid from the middle Triassic of New South Wales</article-title>. <source>Palaeontology</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>609</fpage>–<lpage>621</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Selander1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Selander</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewontin</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>Genetic variation in the horseshoe crab (<italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic>), a phylogenetic “relic”</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Yang1"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Yang MC, Chen CP, Hsieh HL, Huang H, Chen CA (2009) Phylogeography, Demographic History, and Reserves Network of Horseshoe Crab, <italic>Tachypleus tridentatus</italic>, in the South and East China Seaboards. <italic>in</italic> Tanacredi JT, Botton ML, Smith DR (eds.), Biology and Conservation of Horseshoe Crabs. Springer, New York, 163–181.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Sekiguchi3"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Morphological variation and distribution of a horseshoe crab, <italic>Tachypleus gigas</italic>, from the Bay of Bengal and the Gulf of Siam</article-title>. <source>Proc Japan Soc Zool</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Sokoloff1"><label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokoloff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Observations on populations of the horseshoe crab <italic>Limulus</italic> ( = Xiphosura) <italic>polyphemus</italic></article-title>. <source>Res Popul Ecol (Kyoto)</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Riska1"><label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Morphological variation in the horseshoe crab <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic></article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>35</volume> <supplement>(4)</supplement>: <fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>658</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Yamasaki1"><label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Yamasaki T, Makioka T, Saito J (1988) Morphology. <italic>in</italic> Sekiguchi K (ed.) Biology of Horseshoe Crabs. Sci House, Tokyo, 69–132.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Srijaya1"><label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srijaya</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pradeep</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mithun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan AShahoram</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A New Record on the Morphometric Variations in the Populations of Horseshoe Crab (<italic>Carcinoscorpius rotundicauda</italic> Latreille) Obtained from Two Different Ecological Habitats of Peninsular Malaysia</article-title>. <source>Our Nature</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>2011</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Raup1"><label>95</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raup</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sepkoski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Mass extinctions in the marine fossil record</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>215</volume>: <fpage>1501</fpage>–<lpage>1503</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Walliser1"><label>96</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Walliser OH (1996) Global events in the Devonian and Carboniferous. <italic>in</italic> O. HWalliser (ed.), Global Events and Event Stratigraphy in the Phanerozoic, 225–250. Springer Verlag, Berlin.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Suess1"><label>97</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suess</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1866</year>) <article-title>Über Ammoniten. Sitzungberichte der Akademie der Wissenshaft</article-title>. <source>Wien. 52 (for 1865), Abteilung</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage> Wien.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Darwin1"><label>98</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Darwin C (1859) On the origin of species by means of natural selection. Or the preservation of favoured races in the struggle for life. London, John Murray, 1–502.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Gould1"><label>99</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Through a lens, darkly: do species change by random molecular shifts or natural selection?</article-title>. <source>Nat His</source> <fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-SchrankFvon1"><label>100</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrank F von</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1803</year>) <article-title>Fauna Boica</article-title>. <source>Durchgedachte Geschichte der in Baiern einheimischen und zahmen Tiere</source> <volume>3</volume> <supplement>(1)</supplement>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage> Landshut.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Jussieu1"><label>101</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jussieu</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name> (<year>1789</year>) <article-title>Genera Plantarum secundum ordines naturales disposita</article-title>. <source>Herissant and Barrois</source> <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>498</lpage> Paris.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Linnaeus1"><label>102</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Linnaeus C (1771) Mantissa plantarum altera generuj editionis VI. &amp; specierum editionis II. 1–588, Laurentii salvii, Stockholm.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Bruguire1"><label>103</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Bruguière M (1791) Tableau encyclopèdique et mèthodique des trios règnes de la nature. 96–189. Agasse, Paris.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Ogilby1"><label>104</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogilby</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>1907</year>) <article-title>Notes on exhibits</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Queensland</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Linnaeus2"><label>105</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linnaeus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1758</year>) <article-title>Systema Naturae. Ed</article-title>. <volume>10</volume> <supplement>(1)</supplement>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>824</lpage> Salvii, Holmiae.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Smith2"><label>106</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JLB</given-names></name> (<year>1939</year>) <article-title>A surviving fish of the Order Actinistia</article-title>. <source>Trans R Soc South Afr</source> <volume>27</volume> <supplement>(1)</supplement>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Iwanaga1"><label>107</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Evolution and phylogeny of defense molecules associated with innate immunity in horseshoe crab</article-title>. <source>Front Biosci</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>973</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Norvitsky1"><label>108</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Norvitsky</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Discovery to commercialization: the blood of the horseshoe crab</article-title>. <source>Oceanus</source> <volume>27</volume> <supplement>(1)</supplement>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Huovinen1"><label>109</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huovinen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nummela</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koppinen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Detection of endotoxins with limulus amoebocyte lysates of <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic> and <italic>Tachypleus tridentatus</italic> origin</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Methods</source> <volume>11</volume> <supplement>(2)</supplement>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Walls2"><label>110</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berkson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Effects of Blood Extraction on the Mortality of the Horseshoe Crab, <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic></article-title>. <source>Va J Sci</source> <volume>51</volume> <supplement>(3)</supplement>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Mikkelsen1"><label>111</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Mikkelsen T (1988) The Secret in the Blue Blood. Sci. Press, Beijing China 1–125.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Leibovitz1"><label>112</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Leibovitz L, Lewbart GA (2003) Diseases and symbionts: vulnerability despite tough shells. <italic>in</italic> Shuster CN, Barlow RB Jr., Brockmann HJ (ed.), The American horseshoe crab, 245–275. Cambridge, Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Zasloff1"><label>113</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zasloff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Magainins, a class of antimicrobial peptides from <italic>Xenopus</italic> skin: isolation, characterisation of two active forms, and partial cDNA sequence of a precursor</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>5449</fpage>–<lpage>5453</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Moore1"><label>114</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wehrli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>JN</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Squalamine: An aminosterol antibiotic from the shark</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>1354</fpage>–<lpage>1358</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Merchant1"><label>115</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jerkins</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pallansch</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Broad spectrum antimicrobial activity of leukocyte extracts from the American alligator (<italic>Alligator mississippiensis</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Veter Imm &amp; Immunopathology</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Forey1"><label>116</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Forey PL (1998) History of the coelacanth fishes. Chapman and Hall, New York, 1–419.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Sanders1"><label>117</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Sanders WB, Landman NH (2010) Nautilus: The Biology and Paleobiology of a Living Fossil. Springer, 1–632.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Sepkoski1"><label>118</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sepkoski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A compendium of fossil marine animal genera</article-title>. <source>Bull Amer Paleon</source> <volume>363</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Zhou2"><label>119</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The rise of Ginkgoalean plants in the early Mesozoic: a data analysis</article-title>. <source>Geol J</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Stockey1"><label>120</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stockey</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>The Araucariaceae: an evolutionary perspective</article-title>. <source>Rev Paleon Palyn</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Stockey2"><label>121</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stockey</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Mesozoic Araucariaceae: morphology and systematics relationships</article-title>. <source>J Plant Res</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>502</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Luchetti1"><label>122</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luchetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scanabissi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of ribosomal intergenic spacer in the tadpole shrimp <italic>Triops cancriformis</italic> (Crustacea, Branchiopoda, Notostraca)</article-title>. <source>Genome</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>888</fpage>–<lpage>893</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108036-Emig1"><label>123</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emig</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Proof that <italic>Lingula</italic> (Brachiopoda) is not a living-fossil, and emended diagnoses of the Family Lingulidae</article-title>. <source>Car de Géol</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>