<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-31975</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056603</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Physiological processes</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Homeostasis</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Chemical biology</subject>
              <subject>Small molecules</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Molecular cell biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cellular structures</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Subcellular organelles</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cell death</subject>
              <subject>Cellular stress responses</subject>
              <subject>Cellular types</subject>
              <subject>Membranes and sorting</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Chemistry</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Organic chemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Organic compounds</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Small molecules</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Drugs and devices</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Drug research and development</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Chemistry</subject>
          <subject>Physiology</subject>
          <subject>Cell Biology</subject>
          <subject>Pharmacology</subject>
          <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Endoplasmic Reticulum Membrane Reorganization Is Regulated by Ionic Homeostasis</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Ionic Homeostasis Regulates ER Reorganization</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Varadarajan</surname>
            <given-names>Shankar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Tanaka</surname>
            <given-names>Kayoko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Smalley</surname>
            <given-names>Joshua L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bampton</surname>
            <given-names>Edward T. W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Pellecchia</surname>
            <given-names>Maurizio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Dinsdale</surname>
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Willars</surname>
            <given-names>Gary B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cohen</surname>
            <given-names>Gerald M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>MRC Toxicology Unit, University of Leicester, Leicester, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Biochemistry, University of Leicester, Leicester, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Cell Physiology and Pharmacology, University of Leicester, Leicester, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Sanford-Burnham Institute, La Jolla, California, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Holowka</surname>
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Cornell University, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">gmc2@le.ac.uk</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SV KT ETWB GBW GMC. Performed the experiments: SV KT JLS ETWB DD. Analyzed the data: SV KT JLS ETWB DD GBW GMC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MP JLS DD. Wrote the paper: SV KT MP DD GBW GMC. Provided cells: CT. Provided technical assistance: JMW TS.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <elocation-id>e56603</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Varadarajan et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recently we described a new, evolutionarily conserved cellular stress response characterized by a reversible reorganization of endoplasmic reticulum (ER) membranes that is distinct from canonical ER stress and the unfolded protein response (UPR). Apogossypol, a putative broad spectrum BCL-2 family antagonist, was the prototype compound used to induce this ER membrane reorganization. Following microarray analysis of cells treated with apogossypol, we used connectivity mapping to identify a wide range of structurally diverse chemicals from different pharmacological classes and established their ability to induce ER membrane reorganization. Such structural diversity suggests that the mechanisms initiating ER membrane reorganization are also diverse and a major objective of the present study was to identify potentially common features of these mechanisms. In order to explore this, we used hierarchical clustering of transcription profiles for a number of chemicals that induce membrane reorganization and discovered two distinct clusters. One cluster contained chemicals with known effects on Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis. Support for this was provided by the findings that ER membrane reorganization was induced by agents that either deplete ER Ca<sup>2+</sup> (thapsigargin) or cause an alteration in cellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> handling (calmodulin antagonists). Furthermore, overexpression of the ER luminal Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensor, STIM1, also evoked ER membrane reorganization. Although perturbation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis was clearly one mechanism by which some agents induced ER membrane reorganization, influx of extracellular Na<sup>+</sup> but not Ca<sup>2+</sup> was required for ER membrane reorganization induced by apogossypol and the related BCL-2 family antagonist, TW37, in both human and yeast cells. Not only is this novel, non-canonical ER stress response evolutionary conserved but so also are aspects of the mechanism of formation of ER membrane aggregates. Thus perturbation of ionic homeostasis is important in the regulation of ER membrane reorganization.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>The study was supported by the Medical Research Council. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling is involved in the regulation of many cellular functions including those associated with growth, differentiation and apoptosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Berridge1">[1]</xref>. Sources of Ca<sup>2+</sup> involved in regulating the cytoplasmic [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>) include the extracellular fluid and the Ca<sup>2+</sup> store in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). This ER store is tightly controlled by a range of influx and efflux mechanisms, including the sarco/endoplasmic reticulum Ca<sup>2+</sup> ATPase (SERCA), which is responsible for transferring Ca<sup>2+</sup> into the ER lumen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Berridge2">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Sammels1">[3]</xref>. Inhibitors of SERCA activity, such as thapsigargin (THG), prevent this transfer and deplete the store thereby elevating [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>, as a consequence of a flux through leak channels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Treiman1">[4]</xref>. The stimulated release of ER Ca<sup>2+</sup> is brought about primarily by activation of the specific ER-resident channel proteins, the inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (IP<sub>3</sub>) receptors and ryanodine receptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Berridge2">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Sammels1">[3]</xref>. Depletion of ER Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores triggers an influx of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> to provide a source for their replenishment. This store operated calcium entry (SOCE) is mediated by ER membrane proteins, such as STIM1 and STIM2, that detect reduced ER luminal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] and interact with plasma membrane channel proteins, including ORAI and TRPC family members to mediate Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Gees1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Prakriya1">[8]</xref>. In addition to SOCE, other mechanisms of Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry into the cell, including ARC (arachidonic acid regulated Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry) have been identified <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Shuttleworth1">[9]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Defects in intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis are a common occurrence in different stress conditions, where the functioning of the ER is disrupted. As a result, cells accumulate unfolded and misfolded proteins in the ER lumen. This causes ER stress, resulting in the activation of a coordinated intracellular signaling cascade called the unfolded protein response (UPR), in an effort to restore cellular homeostasis and integrity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Ron1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Schroder1">[11]</xref>. The UPR causes a temporary arrest in global protein synthesis, while generating chaperones to deal with the unfolded proteins. However, when the extent of stress is overwhelming, the UPR signals the cell to undergo apoptosis by a number of mechanisms including up-regulation of proapoptotic BCL-2 family members and also by transferring Ca<sup>2+</sup> to the mitochondria, which then orchestrates the intrinsic apoptotic pathway, eventually leading to the elimination of the stressed cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Shore1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Tabas1">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Recently we described a novel cellular stress response characterized by a striking, but reversible, reorganization of ER membranes distinct from canonical ER stress and the UPR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. This ER membrane reorganization results in a dramatic redistribution and clustering of ER membrane proteins together with impaired ER transport and function. In our previous study, apogossypol, a putative broad spectrum BCL-2 family antagonist, was used as the prototype compound to induce ER membrane reorganization. Using connectivity mapping, we further established the widespread occurrence of this stress response identifying a wide range of structurally diverse chemicals from different pharmacological classes, including antihistamines, antimalarials, antiparasitics and antipsychotics that induce ER membrane reorganization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. Thus, ER membrane reorganization is a feature of a newly identified cellular stress pathway with potentially important consequences affecting the functioning of the ER.</p>
      <p>In this study, we used hierarchical clustering to identify a group of ER membrane aggregating compounds that may act by perturbation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis. This was supported by the induction of ER membrane reorganization by calmodulin antagonists, SERCA inhibitors or over-expression of STIM1. However, induction of ER membrane reorganization by apogossypol required an influx of extracellular Na<sup>+</sup>, confirming the importance of ionic homeostasis in regulating ER membrane reorganization.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Cell culture</title>
        <p>HeLa cells from ATCC (Middlesex, UK) were cultured in DMEM supplemented with 5 mM L-glutamine and 10% fetal calf serum (FCS) (all from Life Technologies, Paisley, UK). DT40 B cells, both IP<sub>3</sub>R (IP<sub>3</sub> receptor) KO and IP<sub>3</sub>R1 reconstituted, from Prof. C. Taylor (University of Cambridge, UK) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Dellis1">[15]</xref>, were cultured in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 10% FCS and 1% heat inactivated chicken serum (Biosera Ltd., East Sussex, UK). <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> cells harbouring <italic>rtn1-GFP</italic> allele (KT4007 : <italic>h<sup>90</sup> ade6.M216 leu1.32rtn1-GFP-2×FLAG::Kan<sup>R</sup></italic>) were cultured either in rich YE medium or in minimal medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Alfa1">[16]</xref> supplemented with adenine and leucine.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Reagents and plasmids</title>
        <p>STIM1-YFP (Addgene plasmid 19754), ORAI1-YFP (Addgene plasmid 19756) and ORAI3-Myc (Addgene plasmid 16370) were from Dr. A. Rao (La Jolla Institute for Allergy and Immunology, La Jolla, CA, USA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Prakriya1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Gwack1">[17]</xref>. ORAI2-Myc was generated from a cDNA obtained by RT-PCR from total RNA of HeLa cells (using fwd: <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GAATTCATGAGTGC TGAGCTTAA-3′</named-content>; rev: <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CTCGAGCAAGACCTGCAGGCTGCGCT-3′</named-content>) and cloned into the <italic>Eco</italic>RI-<italic>Xho</italic>I sites of pcDNA3.1-Myc-His (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). BAP31 antibody was from Abcam (Cambridge, UK). <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> (specific activity 32 mCi mg<sup>−1</sup>; 54 mCi mL<sup>−1</sup>) and scintillation fluid were from Perkin-Elmer Inc. (Cambridge, UK). The oil mixture used for collecting cells in the <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> uptake and release experiments was from Dow Corning (Seneffe, Belgium). Apogossypol was synthesized as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Becattini1">[18]</xref>. TW37 was from Selleck Chemicals LLC (Houston, TX, USA). Calmidazolium, thapsigargin (THG), (N-(10-aminodecyl)-5-chloro-1-naphthalenesulfonamide hydrochloride) (A-7), 2-aminoethoxydiphenyl borate (2-APB) and LOE-908 were from Tocris Bioscience (Bristol, UK). Benzamil and all other reagents, unless mentioned otherwise, were from Sigma-Aldrich Co. (St. Louis, MO, USA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Transient overexpression, genomic tagging and siRNA knockdowns</title>
        <p>For transient transfections, cells were transfected using TransIT-LT-1 transfection reagent (Mirus Bio LLC, WI, USA) and left for 48 h, according to the manufacturer's instructions. For siRNA knockdowns, cells were reverse-transfected with oligoduplexes (Life Technologies), using Interferin Reagent (Polyplus Transfection Inc, NY, USA), according to the manufacturer's protocol and processed 72 h after transfection. Cells were reverse-transfected with 10 nM of STIM1 (ID# S13563), ORAI1 (ID# S39560) or ORAI3 (ID# S41090). To visualize ER membrane aggregates in fission yeast, the <italic>rtn1</italic> gene (also known as <italic>cwl1</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Godoy1">[19]</xref>), which encodes a reticulon-like-domain-containing protein Rtn1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Gonzalez1">[20]</xref>, was chromosomally tagged with GFP-2×FLAG as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Funaya1">[21]</xref> to generate the strain, KT4007 : <italic>h<sup>90</sup> ade6.M216 leu1.32 rtn1-GFP-2×FLAG::Kan<sup>R</sup></italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title><sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> uptake and release experiments</title>
        <p><sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> uptake and release experiments were carried out based on previously described methods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Wilcox1">[22]</xref>. Briefly, cells grown to confluence in one or more 175 cm<sup>2</sup> flasks were washed and collected with a cell lifting buffer (0.9% (w/v) NaCl, 0.1% (w/v) EDTA and 10 mM HEPES, pH 7.4) and centrifuged at 1500 rpm for 3 minutes in a bench-top microfuge. The cells were washed twice with 3 mL of intracellular-like buffer (ICB), containing 120 mM KCl, 2 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 5 mM (NaH<sub>2</sub>COONa)<sub>2.</sub>6H<sub>2</sub>O, 2.4 mM MgCl<sub>2.</sub>6H<sub>2</sub>O, 20 mM HEPES, 5 mM ATP, pH 6.9 and enough EGTA to arrive at a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] of 70–150 nM, as determined using fura-2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Grynkiewicz1">[23]</xref>. The cells were then permeabilized in 2 mL of ICB containing 0.1 mg mL<sup>−1</sup> of saponin for 1 minute, followed by centrifugation at 1500 rpm for 2 minutes. For the <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> uptake experiments, as an index of SERCA activity, the permeabilized cells were then resuspended in ICB with the appropriate concentrations of DMSO, apogossypol or THG, followed by the addition of 2.3 µCi mL<sup>−1</sup> of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup>. The resuspended cells were then aliquoted and collected at the indicated time points by centrifugation at 14000 rpm for 1 minute. The cell pellets were rapidly resuspended in 0.5 mL of oil (1∶1 mixture of Dow Corning 556 Cosmetic Grade Fluid and Dow Corning 550 Fluid) and centrifuged for a further 1 minute at 14000 rpm. The sample tubes were then inverted to drain and air-dried at room temperature for 30 minutes. Finally, the pellets were dissolved in 1.1 mL of scintillant and associated <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> determined by liquid scintillation counting. To determine Ca<sup>2+</sup> release, cells were permeabilized as above with saponin and following collection, the intracellular stores were loaded by 20 minutes incubation with 2.3 µCi mL<sup>−1</sup> of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup>. The release of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> was then determined by treatment of the cells with test reagents for the times indicated before collection of the cells and determination of the remaining associated <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> exactly as described above.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Ca<sup>2+</sup> imaging</title>
        <p>HeLa cells grown on coverslips were loaded with 2 µM fura-2 AM (Life Technologies) in extracellular medium (ECM), containing 121 mM NaCl, 5.4 mM KCl, 1.6 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.8 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 6 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 9 mM glucose, 25 mM HEPES, pH 7.4, in the dark at room temperature for 30 minutes. Cells were then washed and coverslips mounted on a Zeiss axiovert inverted microscope and maintained at 37°C in ECM. Epifluorescent images were collected with alternating excitation at 340 and 380 nm and emissions collected above 510 nm using a digital CCD camera (Orca ER, Hamamatsu, Hamamatsu City, Japan). Drugs were added at indicated time points. For measurement of SOCE, cells were incubated in nominally Ca<sup>2+</sup> free ECM and treated as indicated, followed by addition of CaCl<sub>2</sub> to the ECM to a final concentration of 1.8 mM to allow SOCE. For all experiments, changes in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> were measured in 20 individual cells in each of at least three separate experiments, unless otherwise specified.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Elimination media experiments in yeast</title>
        <p>To investigate the role of cationic influx in ER membrane reorganization, <italic>S. pombe</italic> cells, harbouring <italic>rtn1-GFP</italic> at its own chromosomal locus were exposed to the different chemicals with modifications of the minimal media <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Alfa1">[16]</xref>. Briefly, yeast cells cultured in rich yeast extract medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Alfa1">[16]</xref> to a density of 1×10<sup>7</sup> cells mL<sup>−1</sup> at 30°C were extensively washed and diluted with either low Ca<sup>2+</sup> medium (minimal media minus the CaCl<sub>2</sub> and supplemented with 20 mM EGTA), low K<sup>+</sup> medium (minimal media minus KCl and potassium hydrogen phthalate), low Mg<sup>2+</sup> medium (minimal media minus the MgCl<sub>2</sub>) or low Na<sup>+</sup> medium (minimal media minus Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> and Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) to a density of 2×10<sup>6</sup> cells mL<sup>−1</sup>. They were then exposed to drugs for 2 h, followed by image acquisition.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Microarray analysis and hierarchical clustering</title>
        <p>We previously identified a subset of chemicals that induce ER membrane reorganization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. To tease apart potential functional differences between chemicals that induce ER membrane reorganization, we performed hierarchical clustering analysis using gene-expression data for ER membrane aggregating chemicals following a 6-hour exposure in MCF-7 cells. We utilized both in-house generated microarray data and Connectivity Map datasets for this application. For generating the in-house microarray data, total RNA extracted from MCF-7 cells exposed to different agents was used to make biotin-labeled cRNA using the Illumina TotalPrep RNA amplification kit, hybridized to an Illumina HumanHT-12 BeadChip array, Cy3 labeled and scanned using an Illumina BeadArray Reader (all from Illumina, Hayward, CA, USA). Microarray data normalization and analyses were carried out using ArrayTrack software (NCTR/FDA, Jefferson, AR, USA), and the data sets were compared by Welch's t-test. Microarray data were normalized using a quantile normalization method and filtered to remove genes with low mean channel intensities (&lt;250). The top 50 most differentially expressed genes across all datasets were used for hierarchical clustering, using a Pearson correlation metric and average link clustering.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Microscopy</title>
        <p>For immunofluorescent staining, cells grown on coverslips were fixed with 4% (w/v) paraformaldehyde, permeabilized with 0.5% (v/v) Triton X-100 in PBS and followed by incubations with primary antibodies, the appropriate fluorophore-conjugated secondary antibodies, mounted on glass slides and subjected to confocal microscopy on a Zeiss LSM510 (Cambridge, UK). Imaging of the yeast cells was conducted at 30°C using a Leica SP5 laser scanning confocal microscope. Cells were immobilized on glass bottom dishes (MatTek Corporation, Ashland, MA, USA) coated with lectin from <italic>Bandeiraea simplicifolia</italic> (Sigma-Aldrich Co.) and incubated with appropriate media. Images along the Z axis were taken every 0.5–0.6 µm to fully cover the thickness of the cell. Obtained images were processed by Huygens Essential (Scientific Volume Imaging, Hilversum, Holland), a deconvolution software, and maximum Z-projection images were generated by Image J (NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA). For electron microscopy, cells were fixed and processed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. Electron micrographs were recorded using an ES1000W CCD camera and Digital Micrograph software (Gatan, Abingdon, UK) with a Zeiss 902A electron microscope or with a Megaview 3 digital camera and iTEM software (Olympus Soft Imaging Solutions GmbH, Münster, Germany) in a Jeol 100-CXII electron microscope (Jeol UK Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, UK).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Hierarchical clustering reveals a possible role for altered Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis in ER membrane reorganization</title>
        <p>Using microarray analysis and connectivity mapping, we previously identified a diverse range of chemicals that induce ER membrane reorganization thereby demonstrating the widespread occurrence of this novel cellular response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. To identify a possible common mechanism shared by these chemicals in the induction of ER membrane aggregates, we further analyzed the connectivity map microarray datasets for these chemicals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Lamb1">[24]</xref>. Using hierarchical clustering, we identified two distinct chemical groups, potentially indicating functional chemical differences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Apogossypol clustered with several chemicals, including THG, ivermectin and chlorpromazine, all of which disrupt Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis, suggesting a possible role for this in ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0056603-t001">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, we have previously observed that preventing the reuptake of released Ca<sup>2+</sup> by exposing cells to several SERCA inhibitors, including THG, 2,5-di-<italic>t</italic>-butyl-1,4-benzohydroquinone (BHQ) and cyclopiazonic acid (CPA) resulted in ER membrane reorganization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. In this regard, several ER membrane reorganizing compounds previously identified by connectivity mapping, including several antipsychotic phenothiazines, are also known to inhibit SERCA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0056603-t001">Table 1</xref>), thus potentially linking ER membrane reorganization to the inhibition of SERCA activity and altered Ca<sup>2+</sup> handling.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0056603-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Hierarchical clustering reveals a possible role for Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis in ER membrane reorganization.</title>
            <p>Heat map analysis comparing the top 50 differentially expressed genes following the indicated drug treatments as available in the connectivity map reference database. Yellow and blue indicate up or down regulation, respectively. Hierarchical clustering was used to analyze microarray data for chemicals known to induce ER membrane reorganization. The microarray data were normalized, compared with the equivalent control samples, and filtered by mean channel intensity (&lt;250) and mean log<sub>2</sub> fold changes across all the data sets (&lt;1.8). Trends in the resulting gene expression matrix were analyzed, using a Pearson correlation metric and average link clustering. Based on transcriptional trends, two distinct groups of chemicals were identified. Apogossypol clustered with a number of chemicals that are known to disrupt Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis (shaded in blue box).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0056603-t001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Perturbation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis by compounds clustered with apogossypol.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0056603-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compounds clustered with apogossypol</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Activity</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extent of ER membrane reorganization</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effects on Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivermectin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiparasitic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERCA inhibitor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Bilmen1">[47]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clotrimazole</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimyotic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERCA inhibitor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Bartolommei1">[48]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niclosamide</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antihelminthic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not known</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyrvinium</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antihelminthic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effects Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Kucherenko1">[49]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dequalinium</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimalarial/Antiseptic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibits intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> uptake</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Kuum1">[50]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gossypol</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antifertility/Antimalarial</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca<sup>2+</sup> release from rat liver mitochondria</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Martinez1">[51]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valinomycin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibits intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> uptake</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Eleno1">[52]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thapsigargin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sesquiterpene lactone</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERCA inhibitor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Treiman1">[4]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorpromazine</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antipsychotic phenothiazine</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibits SOCE</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Choi1">[53]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trifluoperazine</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antipsychotic phenothiazine</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calmodulin and SERCA inhibitor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Khan1">[54]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Vandonselaar1">[55]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDGA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antioxidant</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERCA inhibitor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Barata1">[56]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>Listing of the eleven compounds that clustered with apogossypol in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g001">Figure 1</xref> and their pharmacological activities. HeLa cells after 4 h exposure to ivermectin (20 µM), clotrimazole (50 µM), niclosamide (50 µM), pyrvinium (20 µM), dequalinium (10 µM), gossypol (10 µM), valinomycin (20 µM), thapsigargin (10 µM), chlorpromazine (20 µM), trifluoperazine (20 µM) or NDGA (50 µM) exhibited varying levels of ER membrane reorganization, from minimal (<bold>+</bold>) to extensive reorganization (<bold>+++</bold>). Ten of the eleven compounds have been described to perturb cellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis by different mechanisms.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Apogossypol-mediated release of intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> is not directly linked to ER membrane reorganization</title>
        <p>To assess if inhibition of SERCA activity was critical for ER membrane reorganization, we monitored the extent of uptake of radiolabeled Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup>) into the intracellular stores of HeLa cells, following exposure to different agents. THG blocked Ca<sup>2+</sup> uptake, in agreement with its known activity as an irreversible inhibitor of SERCA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Treiman1">[4]</xref>. However, apogossypol did not block Ca<sup>2+</sup> uptake, suggesting that apogossypol induced ER membrane reorganization independent of reduced SERCA activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Nevertheless, both apogossypol and THG caused a marked stimulation of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> efflux from intracellular stores similar to that induced by IP<sub>3</sub>, while ionomycin (used as a positive control) caused a complete release (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). Since the extent of apogossypol-mediated <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> efflux was very similar to that mediated by IP<sub>3</sub>, we speculated that apogossypol-mediated Ca<sup>2+</sup> release may also occur <italic>via</italic> the IP<sub>3</sub> receptors. To explore this possibility, we used either chicken DT40 B lymphocytes that lack all three isoforms of the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor (DT40-KO) or cells that were reconstituted with IP<sub>3</sub> receptor isoform 1 (DT40-IP<sub>3</sub>R1) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Dellis1">[15]</xref>. Both apogossypol and IP<sub>3</sub> induced extensive release of intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> (∼85%) in permeabilzed DT-40-IP<sub>3</sub>R1 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g002">Figure 2C</xref>, top panel), whereas in the absence of IP<sub>3</sub> receptors the IP<sub>3</sub>-mediated Ca<sup>2+</sup> efflux was essentially reduced to control levels, and the release mediated by apogossypol was somewhat reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g002">Figure 2C</xref>, bottom panel). Moreover, neither caffeine nor ryanodine caused any efflux of intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>, thus excluding any involvement of ryanodine receptors (data not shown). These results suggest that apogossypol-stimulated Ca<sup>2+</sup> efflux from the ER is partially mediated by IP<sub>3</sub> receptors. Nevertheless, apogossypol induced a similar degree of ER membrane reorganization in both DT40KO and IP<sub>3</sub>R1 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g002">Figure 2D</xref>), suggesting that the release of ER Ca<sup>2+</sup> <italic>via</italic> IP<sub>3</sub>Rs is not responsible for apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0056603-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization is not due to depletion of intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores.</title>
            <p>(A) Permeabilized HeLa cells, exposed to DMSO (control), apogossypol (10 µM), or THG (10 µM), were labelled with <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> and samples collected at the indicated times to assess <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> uptake. (B) Permeabilized HeLa cells labelled with <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> for 20 minutes, were exposed to DMSO (control), apogossypol (10 µM), THG (10 µM), IP<sub>3</sub> (3 µM) or ionomycin (1 µM) for the indicated times and samples collected and assessed for the extent of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup> release. (C) Experiments were carried out as in (B) except using DT40 cells, that either lack all 3 isoforms of IP<sub>3</sub> receptors (DT40 KO) or were reconstituted with IP<sub>3</sub>R1 (DT40-IP<sub>3</sub>R1). (D) Extensive ER membrane reorganization, as assessed by electron microscopy (scale bar, 1 µm) was observed in DT40- IP<sub>3</sub>R1 and DT40 KO cells, exposed to apogossypol (10 µM) for 4 h. Error bars shown in A–C represent the standard error of the mean.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>ER membrane reorganization is associated with an altered handling of Ca<sup>2+</sup></title>
        <p>When cells were treated with THG in the absence of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>, re-addition of Ca<sup>2+</sup> to the outside of the cells resulted in a marked increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3A</xref>), consistent with store depletion and stimulation of SOCE. Apogossypol also evoked a similar increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> under these experimental conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). However, this occurred in the absence of an initial apogossypol-mediated increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> implying Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx <italic>via</italic> either a non-SOCE pathway or alternatively SOCE following store depletion in the absence of a detectable increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>. Nevertheless, ER membrane reorganization mediated by both apogossypol and THG was associated with Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx. We therefore investigated if enhanced Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx mediated by other agents would result in ER membrane reorganization. Several calmodulin antagonists, including calmidazolium, A-7 and trifluoperazine, reported to induce Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx or alter Ca<sup>2+</sup> handling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Itoh1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Peppiatt1">[26]</xref>, also resulted in extensive ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3B</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. Moreover, 2-APB, an inhibitor of SOCE and potentially IP<sub>3</sub> receptors, abolished apogossypol induced ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3C</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Bootman1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Maruyama1">[28]</xref>. To further understand if ER membrane reorganization could result from enhanced SOCE, we overexpressed STIM1 and ORAI 1–3 proteins, which are critical for the induction of SOCE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Hogan1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Liou1">[7]</xref>. Overexpression of STIM1-YFP resulted in excessive clustering of ER membranes in &gt;60% of the transfected cells, which co-localized with the BAP31-positive ER membrane aggregates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). In contrast, overexpressed ORAI 1 and 2 localized to the plasma membrane and did not result in ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). ORAI3 localized to and caused minor clustering of ER membranes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). The excessive clustering of STIM1-YFP positive ER aggregates was most likely a result of overexpression, as cells expressing very low levels of STIM1-YFP failed to produce similar aggregates and maintained normal ER ultrastructure (data not shown), in agreement with previous reports <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Liou1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Smyth1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Hewavitharana1">[30]</xref>. However we cannot completely exclude the possibility that expression of YFP may in some way facilitate aggregation of STIM1. Furthermore, ER membrane reorganization was not observed following overexpression of other ER resident proteins, including SEC22-CFP, KDEL-RFP and SEC61-GFP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref> and data not shown), implying that the marked ER ultrastructural change following STIM1 transfection was probably not an overexpression artifact but was more likely due to a functional activity of the overexpressed STIM1 protein, suggesting a potential involvement of STIM1 and/or SOCE in ER membrane reorganization.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0056603-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>ER membrane reorganization may be due to enhanced Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry.</title>
            <p>(A) Fura-2-loaded HeLa cells were exposed to either apogossypol (10 µM) or THG (10 µM) in Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free media. This was followed by addition of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Changes in fura-2 fluorescence were measured throughout as an index of changes in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>. The graph represents the mean from 3 independent experiments with 20 cells recorded in each experiment. (B) Extensive ER membrane reorganization, assessed by BAP31 staining, was observed in HeLa cells exposed for 4 h to the calmodulin inhibitors, calmidazolium (10 µM) and A-7 (20 µM) (scale bar, 20 µm). (C) Apogossypol-mediated ER membrane reorganization was abolished when HeLa cells were pretreated for 1 h with 2-APB (10 µM) (scale bar, 20 µm). (D) Transient overexpression of YFP, STIM1-YFP, ORAI1-YFP, ORAI2-Myc or ORAI3-Myc and immunostaining with BAP31 antibody, revealed that STIM1-YFP caused extensive ER membrane reorganization, similar to that observed following apogossypol (scale bar, 10 µm). (E) Ultrastructure of STIM1-YFP expressing HeLa cells showing STIM1-mediated reorganization of ER membranes (lower two panels). The bottom panel (scale bar, 5 µm) shows a detail of one of two regions of pronounced ER membrane organizations (indicated by black arrows in the middle panel). It also shows a clear continuity of membranes with the rest of the ER (white arrows). The upper panel shows a comparable area of control transfected HeLa cell (the scale bar in the top 2 panels is 2 µm).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To further exclude the possibility that ER membrane reorganization following STIM1-YFP overexpression was a consequence of the nonspecific aggregation of the YFP-fused protein, resulting in OSER (organized smooth ER) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Snapp1">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Takei1">[33]</xref>, we examined the ultrastructure of these cells. The STIM1-YFP positive ER aggregates clearly resembled the patches of disorganized ER membranes induced by apogossypol (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3E</xref>) and were clearly distinct from OSER induced by over-expression of ER resident proteins, including the IP<sub>3</sub> receptor and hydroxyl-methylglutaryl (HMG)-CoA reductase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Snapp1">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Takei1">[33]</xref>. We therefore wished to test the possibility raised by these data that apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization may be due to an enhanced store mediated influx of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, although we cannot exclude the involvement of a non-SOCE Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>SOCE is not essential for ER membrane reorganization</title>
        <p>To ascertain the potential role of this Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx, we silenced the genes required for SOCE and assessed apogossypol- and THG-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx and ER membrane reorganization. Down-regulation of STIM1 and ORAI1 almost totally abolished THG-mediated SOCE but had little inhibitory effect on apogossypol-mediated Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). However, it should be noted that following STIM1 or ORAI1 knockdown, cells exposed to apogossypol behaved inconsistently, exhibiting a variety of patterns of single and multiple peaks, making it difficult to assess the extent of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx, although this was clearly not blocked. Down regulation of ORAI3 did not block THG-mediated SOCE and again resulted in multiple and variable spikes in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> following exposure to apogossypol (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g004">Figure 4A</xref>, bottom right panel). Despite these changes in the extent and pattern of THG- or apogossypol-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> elevations, silencing either STIM1, ORAI1 or ORAI3 genes had no inhibitory effect on apogossypol- or THG-mediated ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g004">Figure 4B</xref>), which implied that these proteins are not involved in either apogossypol- or THG-induced ER membrane reorganization. Importantly, ER membrane reorganization was apparent even in cells exposed to apogossypol or THG in Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free conditions, further supporting the suggestion that an influx of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> is not critical for the ER changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g004">Figure 4C</xref>). To confirm these observations, we exploited the evolutionary conserved nature of this phenomenon, and used fission yeast. Similar to the effects observed in mammalian cells, apogossypol induced ER membrane reorganization in fission yeast both in minimal media and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free media (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g004">Figure 4D</xref>), confirming that an enhanced Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx is not important for the induction of ER membrane reorganization in either human or yeast cells.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0056603-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Enhanced Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx is not critical for apogossypol-mediated ER membrane reorganization.</title>
            <p>(A) Down-regulation of STIM1, ORAI1 or ORAI3, using RNA interference for 72 h, had no significant inhibitory effects on apogossypol-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry, as measured by the maximal ratio change in fura-2 fluorescence in Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free conditions followed by addition of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>. In contrast, THG-mediated SOCE was dramatically reduced following STIM1 and ORAI1 siRNA but not with ORAI3 siRNA. The graph for THG represents the mean from 3 independent experiments with 20 cells recorded in each experiment. Following apogossypol, the effects were not uniform (the cells behaving inconsistently, often exhibiting multiple peaks) and the graph represents data from a single cell in one of three independent experiments. (B) HeLa cells, transfected for 72 h with siRNA against STIM1, ORAI1 or ORAI3, were exposed to apogossypol (10 µM) for 4 h and immunostained with BAP31 antibody to assess ER membrane reorganization (scale bar, 20 µm). (C) HeLa cells, exposed to apogossypol (1 µM) or THG (5 µM) for 1 h, in serum-free normal DMEM or in serum- and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free DMEM, were immunostained with BAP31 antibody to assess ER membrane reorganization (scale bar, 20 µm). (D) <italic>S. pombe</italic>, harboring <italic>rtn1-GFP</italic> at its endogenous <italic>rtn1</italic> locus to visualize the ER membranes, were grown for 2 h in minimal media or Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free media (supplemented with 20 mM EDTA), in the presence or absence of apogossypol (10 µM) (scale bar, 10 µm).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Influx of Na<sup>+</sup> is critical for apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization</title>
        <p>Although apogossypol induced extensive ER membrane reorganization in Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free conditions, LOE-908, a broad spectrum cation channel inhibitor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Miwa1">[34]</xref>, completely blocked apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization in fission yeast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g005">Figure 5A</xref>), which suggested a requirement of a cation influx other than Ca<sup>2+</sup>. A series of elimination experiments revealed that removal of extracellular Na<sup>+</sup>, but not K<sup>+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup> or Ca<sup>2+</sup>, markedly decreased apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g005">Figure 5A</xref> and data not shown). This was further supported by the observation that benzamil, a potent Na<sup>+</sup>-channel blocker <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Kleyman1">[35]</xref>, also abolished the ability of apogossypol to induce ER membrane aggregates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). LOE-908 and benzamil also inhibited apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization in HeLa cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g005">Figure 5B</xref>), suggesting an evolutionary conserved requirement for Na<sup>+</sup> influx in the induction of ER membrane aggregates. Furthermore, both these compounds inhibited TW37- but not THG-induced ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). Like apogossypol, TW37 is also a broad spectrum BCL-2 family antagonist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Vogler1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Wang1">[37]</xref>. Taken together these results demonstrate that ER membrane reorganization induced by broad spectrum BCL-2 family inhibitors is primarily initiated by perturbation of Na<sup>+</sup> homeostasis.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0056603-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Apogossypol induces ER membrane reorganization <italic>via</italic> an enhanced influx of Na<sup>+</sup>.</title>
            <p>(A) <italic>S. pombe</italic> cells, harbouring <italic>rtn1-GFP</italic>, exhibited extensive ER membrane reorganization following exposure for 2 h to apogossypol (10 µM), when grown in minimal media, or minimal media lacking K<sup>+</sup>. Apogossypol-mediated ER membrane reorganization was abolished when cells were suspended in Na<sup>+</sup>-free media or exposed to either LOE-908 (10 µM) or benzamil (100 µM) 30 minutes before exposure to apogossypol (scale bar, 10 µm). (B) Influx of Na<sup>+</sup> is required for ER membrane reorganization induced by some but not all agents in HeLa cells. Thus, LOE-908 (10 µM) or benzamil (100 µM) abolished apogossypol- (10 µM) and TW37- (50 µM)-induced membrane aggregates but not those induced by THG (10 µM) (scale bar, 20 µm). (C) Scheme summarizing the formation, regulation and consequences of ER membrane reorganization. Exposure to stress conditions, such as inhibition of the BCL-2 family (apogossypol, TW37) or SERCA (THG) induced ER membrane reorganization (right hand panel). Multiple mechanisms, including an influx of Na<sup>+</sup>, through LOE-908- and benzamil-sensitive Na<sup>+</sup> channels, and ER Ca<sup>2+</sup> depletion or altered Ca<sup>2+</sup> handling regulate ER membrane reorganization. These membrane aggregates are reversible and occur independent of canonical ER stress, as tunicamycin (Tunic) and brefeldin A (BFA), two inducers of canonical ER stress, do not result in ER membrane reorganization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. However, at later times, the extensive ER membrane reorganization may eventually lead to canonical ER stress and the UPR, thus placing ER membrane reorganization upstream and/or independent of the UPR.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In our previous study we characterized a novel cellular stress response, involving a rapid reorganization of ER membranes that is distinct from the canonical ER stress response and the UPR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. Using microarray analysis and connectivity mapping, we also demonstrated that this is a common cellular response to a wide range of structurally diverse chemicals from different pharmacological classes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. Here, further investigation revealed that many of these agents may perturb Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0056603-t001">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, ER network formation is accompanied by changes in Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Sprocati1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Voeltz1">[39]</xref>, which occurs due to either enhanced influx of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>, inhibition of the reuptake of cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> into ER stores or pronounced release from intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores. In the experiments showing that three structurally distinct SERCA inhibitors induced ER membrane reorganization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>, a concentration of THG was used (5–10 µM) that was higher than that generally used to inhibit SERCA (e.g., 2 µM), which raised the possibility that other properties of these molecules in addition to SERCA inhibition may be required for them to induce these ultrastructural changes. Nevertheless, experimental support for a role for Ca<sup>2+</sup> in ER membrane reorganization was provided by our findings that exposure to inhibitors of calmodulin or over-expression of STIM 1, an ER resident Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensor essential for SOCE, induced ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Furthermore, 2-APB, an inhibitor of SOCE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Bootman1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Maruyama1">[28]</xref>, blocked apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g003">Figure 3</xref>), thereby implicating SOCE as a mediator of the ER changes. However, THG caused a profound induction of ER membrane reorganization even when SOCE was inhibited by down-regulation of either STIM1 or ORAI1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g004">Figure 4</xref>). In addition, removal of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> had no impact on ER membrane reorganization in response to any of the inducers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g004">Figure 4C</xref> and data not shown), suggesting that Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx across the plasma membrane is not required. It is possible, therefore, that effects of 2-APB on aspects other than SOCE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Bootman1">[27]</xref> may underlie its inhibitory action on apogossypol-induced changes. Further, as 2-APB did not inhibit ER membrane reorganization in response to other agents, including THG, this suggests that such structural changes may be mediated by multiple mechanisms or alternatively, 2-APB is unable to block later steps in the pathway that are triggered by these agents.</p>
      <p>Previously we had shown that this novel form of non-canonical ER stress was evolutionary conserved as ER membrane reorganization was observed in human, mouse and Chinese hamster cells as well as in the fission yeast, <italic>S. pombe</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">[14]</xref>. We have extended this aspect of our previous study to show that ER membrane reorganization also occurs in chicken cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). More importantly, not only is the phenomenon of ER membrane reorganization evolutionary conserved, but some aspects of the mechanism of the formation of ER membrane aggregates are also conserved between man and fission yeast. This was most clearly illustrated by our finding that apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization required an influx of extracellular Na<sup>+</sup> both in a human tumor cell line (HeLa) and in fission yeast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056603-g005">Figure 5</xref>). A similar requirement for extracellular Na<sup>+</sup> influx was also observed with TW37, a related broad spectrum BCL-2 family antagonist, but not for THG. Taken together these results demonstrate that ER membrane reorganization induced by broad spectrum BCL-2 family inhibitors is primarily regulated by perturbation of Na<sup>+</sup> homeostasis, although other mechanisms including altered ER Ca<sup>2+</sup> handling may also be important and may even be a common thread underlying ER membrane reorganization. In this respect it is interesting to note that the BCL-2 family proteins have been proposed to regulate ER Ca<sup>2+</sup>, although there is little agreement on the precise mechanism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Distelhorst1">[40]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Scorrano1">[43]</xref>. It is possible that there may be some relationship between the BCl-2 family, Ca<sup>2+</sup>and Na<sup>+</sup> homeostasis.</p>
      <p>Inhibitors of apogossypol-induced ER membrane reorganization, including 2-APB and LOE 908, could be exerting their activity by blocking the Na<sup>+</sup> influx <italic>via</italic> TRP and other Na<sup>+</sup> channels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Bootman1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Hu1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Xu1">[45]</xref>, which could explain why these inhibitors failed to abolish the effects of THG, which may be mediated directly at the level of the ER. This would also suggest that apogossypol enhances extracellular Na<sup>+</sup> influx and we therefore attempted to characterize the mechanism of such influx in fission yeast. This was seen as a more tractable model than mammalian cells, as Na<sup>+</sup> influx in mammalian cells is complex and is carried out by several mechanisms, including Na<sup>+</sup>/Ca<sup>2+</sup> exchangers, Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> exchangers and several other symporters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0056603-Garty1">[46]</xref>. In <italic>S. pombe</italic>, only three such genes, <italic>sod2</italic> (SPAC977.10), SPAC15A10.06 and SPAC3A12.06c, can be identified in PomBase, a comprehensive database for fission yeast (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pombase.org" xlink:type="simple">www.pombase.org</ext-link>). However, single deletion mutants of these genes had no apparent inhibitory effects on apogossypol-mediated ER membrane reorganization (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0056603.s001">Figure S1</xref>), thereby preventing a conclusive demonstration of the most important channels. Moreover, THG failed to induce ER membrane reorganization in fission yeast (data not shown), most likely due to the lack of SERCA in <italic>S. pombe</italic>.</p>
      <p>In summary we have extended our previous study on this novel form of ER stress and demonstrated that some features of the mechanism of formation of ER membrane reorganization are also evolutionary conserved between man and yeast. We now show that an altered cellular ion homeostasis is associated with the ability of a range of chemicals to induce ER membrane reorganization. Given the structural diversity of these chemicals, it is unlikely that they precipitate ER membrane reorganization through identical mechanisms. Indeed here we show that the broad-spectrum BCL-2 family inhibitors, apogossypol and TW37, mediate ER membrane reorganization by a mechanism dependent on the influx of extracellular Na<sup>2+</sup> through benzamil- and LOE-908-sensitive channels. In contrast, inhibition of SERCA by THG and altered cellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis by the calmodulin inhibitors A-7 and calmidazolium resulted in ER membrane reorganization that at least for THG was independent of extracellular Na<sup>+</sup> influx. Although these data suggest that different mechanisms precipitate the events responsible for ER membrane reorganization, they do not rule out a common final pathway. It is conceivable, for example, that altered concentrations of Na<sup>+</sup> in the sub-plasmalemmal region or immediately adjacent to the ER are able to perturb cellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> handling, particularly by the ER, and it is this that drives the ER membrane reorganization.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0056603.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0056603.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Deletion of sodium channels in fission yeast did not inhibit apogossypol-mediated ER membrane reorganization.</bold> Fission yeast strain KT4007 (<italic>h<sup>90</sup> ade6.M216 leu1 rtn1-GFP-2×FLAG::Kan<sup>R</sup></italic>) carrying GFP-2×FLAG tagged <italic>rtn1</italic> gene and subjected to chromosomal gene deletion of either SPAC977.10 (<italic>sod2</italic>), SPAC15A10.06 or SPAC3A12.06c, still exhibited extensive ER membrane reorganization with apogossypol. (scale bar, 10 µm). Some sort of change in cell morphology (overall larger cells) was noticeable upon deletion of SPAC15A10.06.</p>
          <p>(TIFF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Professor C. Taylor (University of Cambridge, UK) for both IP<sub>3</sub>R KO and IP<sub>3</sub>R1 reconstituted DT40 B cells. We also thank Judy McWilliam and Tim Smith for technical assistance.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Berridge1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bootman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roderick</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Calcium signalling: dynamics, homeostasis and remodelling</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Berridge2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The endoplasmic reticulum: a multifunctional signaling organelle</article-title>. <source>Cell Calcium</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Sammels1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sammels</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parys</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Missiaen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Smedt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bultynck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Intracellular Ca2+ storage in health and disease: a dynamic equilibrium</article-title>. <source>Cell Calcium</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Treiman1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Treiman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caspersen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A tool coming of age: thapsigargin as an inhibitor of sarco-endoplasmic reticulum Ca(2+)-ATPases</article-title>. <source>Trends Pharmacol Sci</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Gees1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gees</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colsoul</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nilius</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The role of transient receptor potential cation channels in Ca2+ signaling</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>a003962</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Hogan1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular basis of calcium signaling in lymphocytes: STIM and ORAI</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Immunol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>533</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Liou1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>STIM is a Ca2+ sensor essential for Ca2+-store-depletion-triggered Ca2+ influx</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1235</fpage>–<lpage>1241</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Prakriya1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prakriya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feske</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gwack</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srikanth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Orai1 is an essential pore subunit of the CRAC channel</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>443</volume>: <fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Shuttleworth1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuttleworth</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Arachidonic acid, ARC channels, and Orai proteins</article-title>. <source>Cell Calcium</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Ron1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Signal integration in the endoplasmic reticulum unfolded protein response</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Schroder1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schroder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The mammalian unfolded protein response</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>789</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Shore1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oakes</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Signaling cell death from the endoplasmic reticulum stress response</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Tabas1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Integrating the mechanisms of apoptosis induced by endoplasmic reticulum stress</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Varadarajan1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varadarajan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bampton</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smalley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caves</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A novel cellular stress response characterised by a rapid reorganisation of membranes of the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1896</fpage>–<lpage>1907</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Dellis1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dellis</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dedos</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tovey</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taufiq Ur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubel</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Ca2+ entry through plasma membrane IP3 receptors</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>313</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Alfa1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Alfa C, Fantes P, Hyams J, McLeod M, Warbrick E (1993) Experiments with Fission Yeast: A Laboratory Course Manual: Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Gwack1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gwack</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srikanth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feske</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Guilloty</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oh-hora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Biochemical and functional characterization of Orai proteins</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>282</volume>: <fpage>16232</fpage>–<lpage>16243</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Becattini1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becattini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monosov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Rational design and real time, in-cell detection of the proapoptotic activity of a novel compound targeting Bcl-X(L)</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Godoy1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Godoy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arellano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Characterization of cwl1+, a gene from Schizosaccharomyces pombe whose overexpression causes cell lysis</article-title>. <source>Yeast</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>983</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Gonzalez1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meerbrey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torii</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Padte</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Nuclear shape, growth and integrity in the closed mitosis of fission yeast depend on the Ran-GTPase system, the spindle pole body and the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>2464</fpage>–<lpage>2472</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Funaya1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Funaya</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samarasinghe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pruggnaller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Transient structure associated with the spindle pole body directs meiotic microtubule reorganization in S. pombe</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>562</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Wilcox1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Challiss</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nahorski</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Inositol-1,3,4,5-tetrakisphosphate induces calcium mobilization via the inositol-1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor in SH-SY5Y neuroblastoma cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharmacol</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>810</fpage>–<lpage>817</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Grynkiewicz1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grynkiewicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poenie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>A new generation of Ca2+ indicators with greatly improved fluorescence properties</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>260</volume>: <fpage>3440</fpage>–<lpage>3450</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Lamb1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Modell</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blat</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The Connectivity Map: using gene-expression signatures to connect small molecules, genes, and disease</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>313</volume>: <fpage>1929</fpage>–<lpage>1935</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Itoh1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hidaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Direct interaction of calmodulin antagonists with Ca2+/calmodulin-dependent cyclic nucleotide phosphodiesterase</article-title>. <source>J Biochem</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>1721</fpage>–<lpage>1726</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Peppiatt1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peppiatt</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bootman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Calmidazolium and arachidonate activate a calcium entry pathway that is distinct from store-operated calcium influx in HeLa cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>381</volume>: <fpage>929</fpage>–<lpage>939</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Bootman1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bootman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roderick</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>2-aminoethoxydiphenyl borate (2-APB) is a reliable blocker of store-operated Ca2+ entry but an inconsistent inhibitor of InsP3-induced Ca2+ release</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1145</fpage>–<lpage>1150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Maruyama1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanaji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakade</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikoshiba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>2APB, 2-aminoethoxydiphenyl borate, a membrane-penetrable modulator of Ins(1,4,5)P3-induced Ca2+ release</article-title>. <source>J Biochem</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>498</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Smyth1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beg</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Putney</surname><given-names>JW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rusan</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Phosphoregulation of STIM1 leads to exclusion of the endoplasmic reticulum from the mitotic spindle</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1487</fpage>–<lpage>1493</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Hewavitharana1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewavitharana</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Girish</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Location and function of STIM1 in the activation of Ca2+ entry signals</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>26252</fpage>–<lpage>26262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Snapp1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Snapp</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Francolini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lombardo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Formation of stacked ER cisternae by low affinity protein interactions</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>163</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Borgese1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgese</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Francolini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snapp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Endoplasmic reticulum architecture: structures in flux</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>358</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Takei1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mignery</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mugnaini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sudhof</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Camilli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor causes formation of ER cisternal stacks in transfected fibroblasts and in cerebellar Purkinje cells</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Miwa1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iwamuro</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>LOE 908: A specific blocker of nonselective cation channel</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Drug Rev</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Kleyman1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleyman</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cragoe</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Amiloride and its analogs as tools in the study of ion transport</article-title>. <source>J Membr Biol</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Vogler1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dinsdale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Bcl-2 inhibitors: small molecules with a big impact on cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>360</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Wang1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolovska-Coleska</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Structure-based design of potent small-molecule inhibitors of anti-apoptotic Bcl-2 proteins</article-title>. <source>J Med Chem</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>6139</fpage>–<lpage>6142</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Sprocati1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprocati</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raimondi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Francolini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borgese</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Dynamic and reversible restructuring of the ER induced by PDMP in cultured cells</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>3249</fpage>–<lpage>3260</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Voeltz1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voeltz</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prinz</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rist</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A class of membrane proteins shaping the tubular endoplasmic reticulum</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Distelhorst1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Distelhorst</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Bcl-2 and calcium: controversy beneath the surface</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2875</fpage>–<lpage>2880</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Pinton1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzuto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Bcl-2 and Ca2+ homeostasis in the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1409</fpage>–<lpage>1418</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Rong1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Distelhorst</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bcl-2 protein family members: versatile regulators of calcium signaling in cell survival and apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Physiol</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Scorrano1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scorrano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oakes</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Opferman</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sorcinelli</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>BAX and BAK regulation of endoplasmic reticulum Ca2+: a control point for apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>300</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Hu1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colton</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>2-aminoethoxydiphenyl borate is a common activator of TRPV1, TRPV2, and TRPV3</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>35741</fpage>–<lpage>357488</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Xu1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boulay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harteneck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Block of TRPC5 channels by 2-aminoethoxydiphenyl borate: a differential, extracellular and voltage-dependent effect</article-title>. <source>Br J Pharmacol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Garty1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garty</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Epithelial sodium channels: function, structure, and regulation</article-title>. <source>Physiol Rev</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Bilmen1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilmen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wootton</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michelangeli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The inhibition of the sarcoplasmic/endoplasmic reticulum Ca2+-ATPase by macrocyclic lactones and cyclosporin A</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>366</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Bartolommei1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolommei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tadini-Buoninsegni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moncelli</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inesi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Clotrimazole inhibits the Ca2+-ATPase (SERCA) by interfering with Ca2+ binding and favoring the E2 conformation</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>9547</fpage>–<lpage>9551</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Kucherenko1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kucherenko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zelenak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eberhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qadri</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Effect of casein kinase 1alpha activator pyrvinium pamoate on erythrocyte ion channels</article-title>. <source>Cell Physiol Biochem</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Kuum1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veksler</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liiv</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura-Clapier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaasik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Endoplasmic reticulum potassium-hydrogen exchanger and small conductance calcium-activated potassium channel activities are essential for ER calcium uptake in neurons and cardiomyocytes</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>633</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Martinez1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Espinosa-Garcia</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The antifertility agent, gossypol, releases calcium from rat liver mitochondria</article-title>. <source>Comp Biochem Physiol C</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Eleno1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eleno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botana</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Espinosa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Valinomycin, a degranulating agent in rat mast cells which inhibits calcium-uptake</article-title>. <source>Agents Actions</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Choi1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Chlorpromazine inhibits store-operated calcium entry and subsequent noradrenaline secretion in PC12 cells</article-title>. <source>Br J Pharmacol</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Khan1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longland</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michelangeli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The effects of phenothiazines and other calmodulin antagonists on the sarcoplasmic and endoplasmic reticulum Ca(2+) pumps</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1797</fpage>–<lpage>1806</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Vandonselaar1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandonselaar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hickie</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delbaere</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Trifluoperazine-induced conformational change in Ca(2+)-calmodulin</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Biol</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0056603-Barata1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolosker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Meis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Modulation of the low affinity Ca2+-binding sites of skeletal muscle and blood platelets Ca2+-ATPase by nordihydroguaiaretic acid</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biochem</source> <volume>195</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>