<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132345</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-03475</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Next-Generation Sequencing Techniques Reveal that Genomic Imprinting Is Absent in Day-Old <italic>Gallus gallus domesticus</italic> Brains</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Genomic Imprinting Absent in Chicken</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Qiong</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Kaiyang</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Daixi</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Junying</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Guiyun</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>Jiangxia</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Ning</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>Lujiang</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Department of Animal Genetics and Breeding, National Engineering Laboratory for Animal Breeding, College of Animal Science and Technology, China Agricultural University, Beijing, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wade</surname>
<given-names>Claire</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Sydney, AUSTRALIA</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LQ. Performed the experiments: QW KL DZ. Analyzed the data: QW JZ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JL GX. Wrote the paper: QW NY LQ.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">quluj@cau.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>10</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e0132345</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>16</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>14</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Wang et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<p>Genomic imprinting is a phenomenon characterized by parent-of-origin-specific gene expression. While widely documented in viviparous mammals and plants, imprinting in oviparous birds remains controversial. Because genomic imprinting is temporal- and tissue-specific, we investigated this phenomenon only in the brain tissues of 1-day-old chickens (<italic>Gallus gallus</italic>). We used next-generation sequencing technology to compare four transcriptomes pooled from 11 chickens, generated from reciprocally crossed families, to the DNA sequences of their parents. Candidate imprinted genes were then selected from these sequence alignments and subjected to verification experiments that excluded all but one SNP. Subsequent experiments performed with two new sets of reciprocally crossed families resulted in the exclusion of that candidate SNP as well. Attempts to find evidence of genomic imprinting from long non-coding RNAs yielded negative results. We therefore conclude that genomic imprinting is absent in the brains of 1-day-old chickens. However, due to the temporal and tissue specificity of imprinting, our results cannot be extended to all growth stages and tissue types.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>Beijing innovation team attached to poultry industry technology system (CARS-PSTP) and National Scientific Supporting Projects of China (2011BAD28B03）received by LQ support the sequencing and data analysis; National Scientific Supporting Projects of China (2012BAD39B04)received by LQ play role in verification experiment and preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="4"/>
<table-count count="2"/>
<page-count count="13"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Genomic imprinting is an epigenetic phenomenon in which certain genes are expressed in a parent-of-origin-specific manner [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In other words, genes exhibit monoallelic or preferential allelic expression: maternal imprinting silences alleles from the mother, resulting in the predominant expression of paternal alleles, while paternal imprinting is the reverse, where maternal alleles are expressed predominantly.</p>
<p>The parental conflict hypothesis is one of the most plausible explanations for genomic imprinting, offering an evolutionary advantage for this epigenetic mechanism. Sexual conflict between the parents results in the biased expression of genes that affect maternal resource allocation. Specifically, maternal genes are selected to conserve sufficient resources for both the mother and her progeny, while paternal genes are selected to use resources in a way that maximizes offspring growth at the expense of the mother [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Under the logic of this hypothesis, there is little selective pressure for genomic imprinting in oviparous animals such as birds, because their embryos grow and develop in eggs. Thus, resource allocation to offspring is more equalized between mothers and fathers, resulting in less sexual conflict.</p>
<p>Genomic imprinting is very well documented in mammals and plants [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], although equivocal in insect models such as <italic>Drosophila</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Notably, some indirect evidence for imprinting has been found in birds, specifically chickens, suggesting that the parental conflict hypothesis may not fully explain this phenomenon. Previous studies on chickens have found parent-of-origin-specific quantitative trait loci (QTL) that either correspond to orthologous imprinted regions in human and mouse genomes, or are connected with economically important, typically imprinted traits in mammals [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. As yet, however, researchers have been unable to determine whether these parent-specific QTL are actually dependent on imprinting, or whether other mechanisms are involved.</p>
<p>The recent advances in next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies, including transcriptome sequencing (RNA-seq), now make answering such questions possible [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In fact, a recent study using NGS reported the lack of genomic imprinting in chicken embryos at 4.5 days [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, because the analysis was performed using whole embryos, and genomic imprinting is both temporally and tissue-specific [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], such results do not fully exclude the possibility of imprinting in chickens. Conflicting parent allele-specific expression between different tissues, for example, may cancel each other out when measuring gene expression in the entire embryo.</p>
<p>Gene imprinting is a special case of allele-specific expression [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and previously, we verified the tissue specificity of allele-specific expression in the chicken [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In this study, we chose to use brain tissue from 1-day-old chickens to investigate whether genomic imprinting is present in an oviparous animal. Brain tissue is ideal for our study because numerous genes are expressed in the brain [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and it is commonly used for similar research. Additionally, imprinted genes have been implicated in neurodevelopment [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Coupled with our sample collection from the developmentally important 1-day-old stage, we believe our study will contribute to a further understanding of neurological ontogeny in the brain.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p>Animal experiments were approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of the China Agricultural University (Approval ID: XXCB-20090209). Animals were fed and handled according to the regulations and guidelines established by this committee, and all efforts were made to minimize suffering.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Reciprocal design</title>
<p>To determine whether genomic imprinting exists in 1-day-old chicken brains, we compared the allelic-bias of four transcriptome libraries pooled from 11 chickens, descended from two reciprocally crossed families, to the DNA sequences of their parents.</p>
<p>Two inbred strains (<italic>Cornish</italic>: Cor and <italic>White Leghorn</italic>: WL) were chosen as the reciprocally crossed parents (cross I: female Cor × male WL, cross II: female WL × male Cor) (<xref rid="pone.0132345.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). Eleven 1-day-old chickens were euthanized with carbon dioxide and their brains collected (three females and three males in cross I, two females and three males in cross II because only two females were available). Total RNA was extracted from the brain tissue and all same-sex samples of the same family were pooled to establish an RNA-seq library. The pools of each family (that is, the female and the male pool) were used as two biological replicates of that family. DNA samples of four parents from each family were used for whole-genome re-sequencing.</p>
<fig id="pone.0132345.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Reciprocal design.</title>
<p>We reciprocally crossed two inbred strains, <italic>Cornish</italic> (Cor) and <italic>White Leghorn</italic> (WL), to generate progenies. For each cross, the brains of 1-day-old chickens from each sex were collected and total RNA was extracted from the tissue samples. Same-sex RNA samples from the same family were pooled to establish an RNA-seq library. The male and female pools within the same family were regarded as biological replicates. DNA samples of four parents from each family were used for whole-genome re-sequencing.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Data acquisition and analysis</title>
<p>Whole-genome sequencing of parent genomes and RNA-seq of offspring genomes were performed using an Illumina HiSeq 2500 sequencer. Library construction and sequencing were performed following manufacturer protocols (TruSeq DNA Sample Prep Kit, TruSeq RNA Sample Prep Kit, TruSeq PE Cluster Kit v3-cBot, and TruSeq SBS Kit v3). Paired-end reads of 100 bps were produced. The insert sizes of the re-sequencing and RNA-seq libraries were 300 bps and 330 bps, respectively.</p>
<p>Using our re-sequenced genome and the Galgal4 reference genome (from the Ensembl Genome Browser), we simulated Cor and WL genomes. We then used two programs, the Burrows-Wheeler Aligner’s Smith-Waterman Alignment tool [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and the Genome Analysis Toolkit [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], to align the two simulated genomes and look for homozygous SNPs. Specifically, we verified that SNPs at a particular locus were the same within the two parent strains and different between them. We adopted two standards for filtering homozygous SNPs between the parent strains: a loose standard of higher than 2× sequencing depth and a general standard of higher than 10× depth. The loose standard was implemented first, to avoid missing any potential imprinted genes. Under both standards, reads should be the same at every homozygous SNP locus across the two sets of parental re-sequencing data.</p>
<p>Next, we identified SNPs exhibiting parent-of-origin allelic expression in the reciprocal crosses with TopHat software [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], which allows us to align RNA-seq reads to the simulated parent genomes. Each SNP locus was required to have at least 10 reads aligned to the parental alleles in the transcriptome pool, thus deviating from a 1:1 ratio. We used a chi-square test, with an adjusted (via Bonferroni correction) P-value set at 0.05, to look for a significant deviation. Additionally, the cut-off for number of SNPs was set at less than two per 10 bases. We considered an SNP to be potentially imprinted if the percentage of reads including those SNPs is more than 75% aligned to either the maternal or the paternal allele in both reciprocal crosses. Further, the allelic ratio of the SNP was expected to be inverted between the two crosses.</p>
<p>To annotate the candidate SNPs and predict their function, we used the SnpEFF program [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], which categorizes genomic variants based on their locations. For SNPs that are located in or near genes, the high alignment percentage roughly reflects the expression levels of those genes. Thus, SNPs that appear to be imprinted may also indicate the presence of potentially imprinted genes. We quality-checked our reads using the FastQC tools in the StatsDB package [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p>
<p>Finally, we identified any long non-coding RNAs that potentially exhibit imprinting. We assembled transcripts from our simulated genomes using the Cufflinks program [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. We found new, previously unannotated transcripts by comparing the assembly results to known transcripts. We excluded any new transcripts that lacked at least one exon and was less than 200 bps in size. We screened for candidate non-coding RNAs using the Coding Potential Calculator [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The resultant transcripts were further filtered through the NCBI-nr database [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] to ensure accuracy. Candidate imprinted SNPs were then mapped to long non-coding RNAs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Verification experiments</title>
<p>NGS techniques may occasionally provide false positives [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Thus, to validate the sequences and expression patterns of candidate imprinted genes, and to verify SNP homozygosity across our parental samples, we performed the following verification experiments.</p>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Restriction endonuclease analysis</title>
<p>We obtained cDNA from the RNA pools of offspring using reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). We then amplified any candidate genes of the offspring and parents that contained a potentially imprinted SNP. We generally used CAPS (cleaved amplified polymorphic sequences) assays for our analyses. However, in cases where the SNPs were not located at cleavage sites, we designed primers to introduce restriction enzyme sites and ran dCAPS (derived cleaved amplified polymorphic sequences) assays [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Amplified PCR products were separated with gel electrophoresis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Direct Sanger sequencing</title>
<p>Next, we genotyped our amplified cDNA and DNA products using Sanger sequencing, to exclude the possibility of incomplete digestion.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Pyrosequencing</title>
<p>We aimed to detect imbalanced allelic expression in the offspring of our reciprocal crosses, through the use of pyrosequencing with Pyromark Q96 (Qiagen). One candidate SNP in particular warranted more detailed investigation, due to its unusual properties (apparently sex-specific imprinting; described in the Results and Discussion section, under the subsection of “Verification experiments excluded all potential imprinted genes”). For this SNP, we analyzed brain cDNA samples (obtained from PT-PCR), and extracted RNA from the liver, heart, and pectorals of each offspring separately. We also verified the SNP on two other reciprocally crossed families (cross III and cross IV), where the four parents’ genotypes are homozygous at that SNP locus. Similar to the previous four crosses, these parent genotypes were confirmed using Sanger sequencing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Monoclonal sequencing</title>
<p>Since some candidate SNPs are located in regions that are difficult to amplify and sequence directly, we performed monoclonal sequencing of the two candidate genes in which those SNPs are located. We connected a pMD19-T Vector to the target segment containing the candidate SNP. The vector was then transformed into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> for amplification and sequencing of the target DNA segments.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Identification of candidate imprinted genes</title>
<p>We obtained a total of 412,605,954 reads (82.5 Gb) in the re-sequenced genome and 237,006,676 reads (47.4 Gb) in RNA-seq. The four RNA-seq libraries contained 10.2 Gb, 11.3 Gb, 11.8 Gb, and 14.1 Gb of reads. All libraries passed our quality control checks, and the base quality was very high, even at the end of reads (Fig A and B in <xref rid="pone.0132345.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 File</xref>).</p>
<p>Using the re-sequencing and RNA-seq data, we were able to identify many allele-specific expressed SNPs. Of the 825,211,908 reads in the re-sequencing data, 812,227,808 (98.43%) reads could be mapped to the Galgal4 reference genome. The mean sequence depth was 19.5×. We identified 726,884 SNPs and 422,693 SNPs under the loose and general standards, respectively. Under the general standard, SNPs that occurred between the two strains covered 4,960 genes, relative to a total of 17,108 genes in the reference genome.</p>
<p>Of these SNPs, we found several that potentially exhibited parent-of-origin effects. The proportion of reads aligned to the maternal genome was 0.5 at most SNP loci (chi-square test, p &lt; 0.05. Fig C in <xref rid="pone.0132345.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 File</xref>). Under the general standard, we were only able to isolate one SNP in males, located on the autosomes. This SNP was also included under the looser standard, where we were able to select 1,478 SNPs in females (two from autosomes, 1,470 from the Z chromosome, and six unmapped to any chromosome) and 12 SNPs in males (eight from autosomes, one from the Z chromosome, and three unmapped to any chromosome) (<xref rid="pone.0132345.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Since the female is the heterogametic sex in birds, female Z chromosomes must come from the father, explaining why the 1,470 SNPs on the female Z chromosome exhibited paternal allelic expression. When we merged offspring female and male data, we found that 11 SNPs conformed to the loose standards (eight SNPs from autosomes and three SNPs unmapped to any chromosome).</p>
<fig id="pone.0132345.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Ratio of reads aligned to parental genomes of all SNPs.</title>
<p>Points in this figure reflect the ratio of reads aligned to the maternal versus the paternal genomes under the loose standard (SNP sequencing depth greater than 2×). The horizontal axis is log<sub>2</sub> (m:f) in cross I, while the vertical axis is log<sub>2</sub> (m:f) in cross II. Red points indicate the candidate maternal imprinted SNPs, while the blue points indicate candidate paternal imprinted SNPs.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The SNPs selected separately from the male and female data corresponded to eight potential imprinted genes on female autosomes and nine on male autosomes. Among the candidate genes in female autosomes, four exhibited maternal allelic expression, while the others exhibited paternal allelic expression. Among the male candidate genes, seven exhibited maternal expression, and the remaining two exhibited paternal expression. In the merged data, we found 10 potential imprinted genes, with five exhibiting maternal expression and the remainder exhibiting paternal expression. Among the maternally expressed genes in males, one was located on the Z chromosome. Information on these genes is summarized in <xref rid="pone.0132345.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0132345.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Candidate imprinted genes filtered by bioinformatics analysis of RNA-seq data.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0132345.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chromosome</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNP position</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Imprinting type</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19414668</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VHL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T/G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH376330.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16268</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XLOC_047216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T/C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59858</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BFIV21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C/T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH375462.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3673</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XLOC_046149</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH375607.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9846</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENSGALG00000000194</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C/T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH375607.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13684</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENSGALG00000000194</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T/C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH375628.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3535</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3-IX</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH375832.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10462</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XLOC_046722</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2890483</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GABRP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH375328.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">424</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XLOC_046087</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">943913</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LMAN1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C/T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop codon gained</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4696581</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACAA1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T/C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6454653</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZSWIM7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G/T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH375328.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">366</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XLOC_046087</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T/C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23195463</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHF21A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6258175</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAM20B</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-synonymous coding</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>*No. 16 is the SNP filtered using the general standard.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In total, 2118 long, non-coding RNA transcripts were assembled from 1283 genes. Their average length was 2115 bps, and they contained 2.7 exons on average. However, none of these RNA transcripts showed any signs of imprinting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Verification experiments excluded all potential imprinted genes</title>
<p>Among the potential imprinted genes we identified, only two met the loose standards in both sexes (No. 1 <italic>VHL</italic> and No. 2 <italic>XLOC_047216</italic>). As imprinted genes may be expressed in a sex-specific pattern [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], we also verified 14 candidate genes that conformed to the loose standards in only one sex (<xref rid="pone.0132345.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). The results of our verification experiments on these 16 genes are reported below.</p>
<p>Our restriction endonuclease analysis revealed that four SNPs were heterozygous in certain parents (<xref rid="pone.0132345.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A, 3B</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0132345.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Three SNPs were confirmed heterozygous with Sanger sequencing of genes from the parent genomes (<xref rid="pone.0132345.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3C</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0132345.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), and two were confirmed with restriction endonuclease analysis. Pyrosequencing also verified five SNPs associated with four candidate genes, and monoclonal sequencing found that two SNPs associated with two candidate gene were heterozygous in the parent strains. In total, nine SNPs were confirmed heterozygous. Candidate genes associated with these SNPs were excluded.</p>
<fig id="pone.0132345.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Verification experiments excluded most of the candidate imprinted SNPs.</title>
<p>(A) Restriction endonuclease analysis. The cDNA pattern was similar to offspring DNA, which contained two bands of the same brightness (No. 4, gene <italic>XLOC_046149</italic>). (B) SNPs filtered using loose standards (sequencing depth &gt; 2×) show heterozygosity in some parents (No. 5, <italic>ENSGALG00000000194</italic>). We designed different primers for our cDNA analysis versus our DNA analysis, due to the presence of an intron region near some SNPs in the DNA. (C) Direct Sanger sequencing of parental DNA confirming the heterozygosity of some SNPs. Sequencing results for gene <italic>XLOC_046722</italic> (No. 8) are shown; the SNP is the third base. (D) Direct Sanger sequencing of offspring DNA and cDNA. Expression of some genes does not show evidence of imprinting. Sequencing results for gene <italic>ZSWIM7</italic> (No. 13) are shown; the SNP is the third base. (E) Pyrosequencing results reveal that the gene expression patterns of most candidate genes do not show evidence of imprinting. Results for the cDNA of gene <italic>ACAA1</italic> (No. 12) are shown.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pone.0132345.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Results of verification experiments at each SNP locus.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0132345.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sanger-offspring</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sanger-parents</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restriction enzyme digestion</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyrosequencing</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterozygous<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterozygous<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coincident</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of DNA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Coincident in female</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Coincident</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Coincident</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Coincident in female</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Suspicious (Sex-specific)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of DNA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression, parent heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequencing error</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression, parent heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coincident</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coincident</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of DNA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression, parent heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent heterozygous</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Coincident</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">\</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconformity of expression</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>The numbers in the first column correspond to those in <xref rid="pone.0132345.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p>*These two "Heterozygous" results were obtained via monoclonal sequencing.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn003"><p>"\"means that a verification experiment could not be performed at that SNP or results are not available.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn004"><p>"Inconformity of expression" indicates offspring expression patterns that were inconsistent with parent-of-origin specific expression. "Inconformity of DNA" indicates that the two kinds of base of SNPs in offspring DNA did not have equal content, which may be caused by heterozygosity in the parents. "Sequencing error" indicates the existence of complex structures beside the SNP that led to inaccurate Sanger sequencing results, which may have also caused errors in NGS.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>We expected that offspring cDNA patterns in restriction endonuclease analyses may be similar to the pattern found in one of their parents, or appear as two bands that form a light and dark contrast. However, we found that all of our candidate genes exhibited preferential allelic expression instead of monoallelic expression. Thus, we were unable to compare the relative quantity of the original template using PCR amplification and gel electrophoresis. Offspring cDNA patterns for most candidate genes contained two bands of similar brightness. Direct Sanger sequencing results were similar to our findings using restriction endonuclease analysis. In sum, these analyses failed to find evidence of imprinting in candidate gene expression (<xref rid="pone.0132345.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3D</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0132345.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<p>Monoclonal sequencing was performed on two candidate genes (No. 1 <italic>VHL</italic> and No. 2 <italic>XLOC_047216</italic>). The results revealed that one of them (No.1 <italic>VHL</italic>) was a heterozygote across the parent strains. The other candidate gene (No. 2 XLOC_047216) contained six bases that were either inserted or deleted next to the SNP. These indels may be the reason why the sequencing methods we chose were unsuitable, potentially causing errors in the reads statistic and the SNP filter.</p>
<p>Finally, the results of our pyrosequencing revealed that the expression patterns of most candidate genes were not in accord with the characteristics of genomic imprinting (<xref rid="pone.0132345.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3E</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0132345.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). One gene (No. 6, gene <italic>ENSGALG00000000194</italic>) did appear to show expression patterns indicative of imprinting, but as it only exhibited parent-of-origin effects in females (<xref rid="pone.0132345.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A and 4B</xref>), we believe it is more likely to be a sex-specific imprinted gene.</p>
<fig id="pone.0132345.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Results of further verification experiments on the SNP most likely to exhibit imprinting.</title>
<p>The sequence near the SNP is <monospace>CTCCCA/GAACGC</monospace>. (A) This gene appeared to be expressed in a way indicative of genomic imprinting when examined with direct Sanger sequencing. However, the parent-of-origin characteristics were exhibited only in females. The relevant SNP is the third base. Differences between parent and offspring sequences in the first base are due to the introduction of mismatch bases in the offspring for dCAPS assays. (B) Pyrosequencing results are consistent with direct Sanger sequencing results. (C) Cross III and Cross IV, two different reciprocally crossed families, had parents homozygous at that SNP locus. This is in accordance with data from the previous four parents and was confirmed by Sanger sequencing. We detected the brain cDNA of offspring individually, using pyrosequencing. Neither males nor females in crosses III and IV exhibited parent-origin-specific gene expression patterns.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>It is worth noting that there was another SNP (No. 5, <italic>ENSGALG00000000194</italic>) located in this sex-specific gene, although it was excluded due to heterozygosity in the parents. Nonetheless, the results of our restriction endonuclease analysis on cross I DNA support the sex-specific characteristics of this gene; offspring only expressed the allele of their father (<xref rid="pone.0132345.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3B</xref>). Further pyrosequencing of the candidate sex-specific imprinted gene revealed that individual brain cDNA expression patterns roughly correspond to patterns indicative of imprinting in females at that SNP locus. In contrast, gene expression in other sampled tissues exhibited an irregular pattern (<xref rid="pone.0132345.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). For the other two reciprocally crossed families (cross III and cross IV), we did not find patterns of genomic imprinting in the gene expression of either male or female offspring brain cDNA (<xref rid="pone.0132345.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4C</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0132345.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Absence of genomic imprinting in chickens</title>
<p>Genomic imprinting is a phenomenon characterized by parent-of-origin-specific, monoallelic gene expression in offspring. Imprinting exhibits temporal-, tissue- [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], and probably even sex-specificity [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. However, it is not dependent on parent genotype and does not vary among individuals, because imprinted genes are epigenetically marked and expressed only from the maternal or the paternal allele [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p>
<p>Although a previous study confirmed the presence of a parent-of-origin-specific QTL on the chicken genome [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], we were unable to locate any imprinted SNPs in those regions, although we did note some false positives. The lack of evidence for imprinting suggests other reasons for the parent-of-origin characteristics of the QTL, such as paramutation and position-effect variegation [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Additionally, we speculate that the generation of false candidate imprinted genes in this study was caused by the random error that occasionally occurs with NGS technology.</p>
<p>Another notable factor that affects our experimental outcome involves the use of a 75% read alignment standard in filtering imprinted SNPs. We chose this strict standard because we have observed that typical imprinted genes in other species are very strongly expressed (e.g., <italic>IGF2</italic> and <italic>H19</italic> gene in mammals) [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Given that we have identified false positives even with this standard, we felt that a more lenient criterion would yield unreliable results. Although our standard is admittedly arbitrary, we have found that there is currently no set standard in the literature. For example, a previous study on genomic imprinting in the chicken whole embryo chose a fold-change threshold of ≥2.5 [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Another study on developing maize endosperm (with two maternal allele copies and one paternal allele) considered gene imprinting to be present if an allele exhibits at least 5× the expression levels of the candidate imprinted allele [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Still other research on genomic imprinting employ a statistical test (typically the chi-square) as a threshold [<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0132345.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Clearly, there is a need for a standard definition of genomic imprinting, in order to facilitate comparison of results across multiple studies.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Our current results suggest that genomic imprinting is absent in 1-day-old chicken brains. However, our findings are not generalizable across all growth stages and all tissues types, due to the temporal and tissue specificity of genomic imprinting, and the stricter standards we have chosen to impose in our analysis. Further studies in different tissues and at various developmental stages are required to confirm the existence of genomic imprinting in chickens and other oviparous organisms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0132345.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.s001" mimetype="application/x-rar-compressed" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 File</label>
<caption>
<title>Sequencing and alignment quality.</title>
<p>This figure shows the overall sequencing quality, we randomly selected one of the re-sequencing libraries to be representative of all the other libraries (Figure A). Quality of the randomly selected RNA-seq library, we found that the base quality was very high, even at the end of reads (Figure B). This figure displays read alignment quality, the horizontal axis shows the proportion of reads aligned to the maternal genome, whereas the vertical axis shows the number of SNPs. Overall, the proportion of aligned reads at most SNP loci was 0.5 (Figure C).</p>
<p>(RAR)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0132345.s002" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Number of reads aligned to parents at each SNP locus.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0132345.s003" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0132345.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Further pyrosequencing of the most promising candidate imprinted gene in four tissues of individual chickens.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We are grateful for animal breeding support from the team at the National Engineering Laboratory.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregg</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissbourd</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schroth</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haig</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>High-resolution analysis of parent-of-origin allelic expression in the mouse brain</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>329</volume>: <fpage>643</fpage>–<lpage>648</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1190830" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1190830</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20616232</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Susiarjo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolomei</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Imprinting and epigenetic changes in the early embryo</article-title>. <source>Mamm Genome</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00335-009-9225-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00335-009-9225-2</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19760320</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genomic imprinting: the emergence of an epigenetic paradigm</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrg3032" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrg3032</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21765458</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fresard</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morisson</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brun</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pain</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minvielle</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Epigenetics and phenotypic variability: some interesting insights from birds</article-title>. <source>Genet Sel Evol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1297-9686-45-16" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1297-9686-45-16</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23758635</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pask</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Insights on imprinting from beyond mice and men</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>925</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-1-62703-011-3_18" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/978-1-62703-011-3_18</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22907504</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolomei</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zemel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tilghman</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parental imprinting of the mouse H19 gene</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>351</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1709450</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeChiara</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Efstratiadis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parental imprinting of the mouse insulin-like growth factor II gene</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>849</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1997210</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kermicle</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dependence of the R-mottled aleurone phenotype in maize on mode of sexual transmission</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>1970</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17248508</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakey</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beechey</surname> <given-names>CV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Imprinted genes: identification by chromosome rearrangements and post-genomic strategies</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12127776</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raissig</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baroux</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grossniklaus</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation and flexibility of genomic imprinting during seed development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.110.081018" xlink:type="simple">10.1105/tpc.110.081018</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21278124</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munshi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duvvuri</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genomic imprinting—the story of the other half and the conflicts of silencing</article-title>. <source>J Genet Genomics</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17469781</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Extensive, clustered parental imprinting of protein-coding and noncoding RNAs in developing maize endosperm</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>20042</fpage>–<lpage>20047</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1112186108" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1112186108</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22114195</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholls</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knoll</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karam</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lalande</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic imprinting suggested by maternal heterodisomy in nondeletion Prader-Willi syndrome</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1989</year>; <volume>342</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2812027</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zapala</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hovatta</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellison</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wodicka</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Del Rio</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tennant</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Adult mouse brain gene expression patterns bear an embryologic imprint</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>10357</fpage>–<lpage>10362</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16002470</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riley-Berger</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harshman</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kopp</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vacha</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nuzhdin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Extensive sex-specific nonadditivity of gene expression in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>1791</fpage>–<lpage>1799</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342517</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coolon</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McManus</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graveley</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittkopp</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genomic imprinting absent in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> adult females</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2012.06.013" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.celrep.2012.06.013</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22840398</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuiskula-Haavisto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vilkki</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parent-of-origin specific QTL—a possibility towards understanding reciprocal effects in chicken and the origin of imprinting</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17675872</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadeau</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seitz</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>SENSE: a fast RNA-seq library preparation protocol with superior strand specificity</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>. <year>2012</year>; <fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fresard</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leroux</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Servin</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gourichon</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dehais</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cristobal</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Transcriptome-wide investigation of genomic imprinting in chicken</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>3768</fpage>–<lpage>3782</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkt1390" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkt1390</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24452801</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Korir</surname> <given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seoighe</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inference of allele-specific expression from RNA-seq data</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>1112</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-1-62703-773-0_4" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/978-1-62703-773-0_4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24478007</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>An EAV-HP insertion in 5' Flanking region of SLCO1B3 causes blue eggshell in the chicken</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e1003183</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003183" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003183</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23359636</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lein</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawrylycz</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ao</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayres</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bensinger</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Genome-wide atlas of gene expression in the adult mouse brain</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>445</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17151600</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isles</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Imprinted gene expression in the brain</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>430</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15820547</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durbin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fast and accurate long-read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp698" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp698</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080505</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenna</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanna</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sivachenko</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cibulskis</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kernytsky</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The Genome Analysis Toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1297</fpage>–<lpage>1303</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gr.107524.110" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/gr.107524.110</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20644199</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trapnell</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pachter</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>. <article-title>TopHat: discovering splice junctions with RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1105</fpage>–<lpage>1111</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp120" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp120</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19289445</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cingolani</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Platts</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang le</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coon</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A program for annotating and predicting the effects of single nucleotide polymorphisms, SnpEff: SNPs in the genome of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> strain w1118; iso-2; iso-3</article-title>. <source>Fly (Austin)</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez-Gonzalez</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leggett</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waite</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thanki</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drou</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caccamo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>StatsDB: platform-agnostic storage and understanding of next generation sequencing run metrics</article-title>. <source>F1000Res</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.2-248.v2" xlink:type="simple">10.12688/f1000research.2-248.v2</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24627795</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trapnell</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pertea</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortazavi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kwan</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Baren</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>515</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nbt.1621" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nbt.1621</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname> <given-names>ZQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>XQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>CPC: assess the protein-coding potential of transcripts using sequence features and support vector machine</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2007</year> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>W345</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17631615</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauder</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arthur</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunbrack</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names> <suffix>Jr.</suffix></name> <article-title>Large-scale comparison of protein sequence alignment algorithms with structure alignments</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10813826</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yona</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levitt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Towards a complete map of the protein space based on a unified sequence and structure analysis of all known proteins</article-title>. <source>Proc Int Conf Intell Syst Mol Biol</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10977100</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeVeale</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Kooy</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babak</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Critical evaluation of imprinted gene expression by RNA-Seq: a new perspective</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002600</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002600" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002600</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22479196</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neff</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neff</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chory</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pepper</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name>. <article-title>dCAPS, a simple technique for the genetic analysis of single nucleotide polymorphisms: experimental applications in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> genetics</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9628033</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregg</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haig</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dulac</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sex-specific parent-of-origin allelic expression in the mouse brain</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>329</volume>: <fpage>682</fpage>–<lpage>685</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1190831" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1190831</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20616234</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inherited epigenetic variation—revisiting soft inheritance</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16534512</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barlow</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoger</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname> <given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schweifer</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>The mouse insulin-like growth factor type-2 receptor is imprinted and closely linked to the Tme locus</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>349</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1845916</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cattanach</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beechey</surname> <given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Surani</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Embryological and molecular investigations of parental imprinting on mouse chromosome 7</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>351</volume>: <fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>670</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2052093</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0132345.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smits</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mungall</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beury</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Conservation of the H19 noncoding RNA and H19-IGF2 imprinting mechanism in therians</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>971</fpage>–<lpage>976</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.168" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ng.168</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18587395</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>