<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-17251</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Fibroblast Growth Factor (FGF-2) and Its Receptors FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 May Be Putative Biomarkers of Malignant Transformation of Potentially Malignant Oral Lesions into Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">FGF and FGFR in Oral Precancer and Cancer</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Nayak</surname>
<given-names>Seema</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Goel</surname>
<given-names>Madhu Mati</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Makker</surname>
<given-names>Annu</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bhatia</surname>
<given-names>Vikram</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Chandra</surname>
<given-names>Saumya</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>Sandeep</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Agarwal</surname>
<given-names>S. P.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Pathology, King George’s Medical University, Lucknow, U.P. - 226003, India</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>All India Institute of Medical Sciences Bhopal, M.P. – 462026, India</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, King George’s Medical University Lucknow, U.P. – 226003, India</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>Chih-Hsin</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>China Medical University, TAIWAN</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MMG. Performed the experiments: SN VB SC. Analyzed the data: SN VB SC MMG AM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MMG SK SPA. Wrote the paper: SN MMG AM.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">madhukgmc@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>14</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<elocation-id>e0138801</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>21</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>3</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Nayak et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<p>There are several factors like angiogenesis, lymphangiogenesis, genetic alterations, mutational factors that are involved in malignant transformation of potentially malignant oral lesions (PMOLs) to oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC). Fibroblast growth factor-2 (FGF-2) is one of the prototypes of the large family of growth factors that bind heparin. FGF-2 induces angiogenesis and its receptors may play a role in synthesis of collagen. FGFs are involved in transmission of signals between the epithelium and connective tissue, and influence growth and differentiation of a wide variety of tissue including epithelia. The present study was undertaken to analyze expression of FGF-2 and its receptors FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 in 72 PMOLs, 108 OSCC and 52 healthy controls, and their role in risk assessment for malignant transformation of Leukoplakia (LKP) and Oral submucous fibrosis (OSMF) to OSCC. Immunohistochemistry was performed using antibodies against FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3. IHC results were validated by Real Time PCR. Expression of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 was upregulated from PMOLs to OSCC. While 90% (9/10) of PMOLs which showed malignant transformation (transformed) expressed FGF-2, only 24.19% cases (15/62) of PMOLs which were not transformed (untransformed) to OSCC expressed FGF-2. Similarly, FGFR-2 expression was seen in 16/62 (25.81%) of untransformed PMOLs and 8/10 (80%) cases of transformed PMOLs. FGFR-3 expression was observed in 23/62 (37.10%) cases of untransformed PMOLs and 6/10 (60%) cases of transformed PMOLs. A significant association of FGF-2 and FGFR-2 expression with malignant transformation from PMOLs to OSCC was observed both at phenotypic and molecular level. The results suggest that FGF-2 and FGFR-2 may be useful as biomarkers of malignant transformation in patients with OSMF and LKP.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by Indian council of Medical Research, New Delhi, India-110029 (Grant No. 5/13/56/2008-NCDIII, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icmr.nic.in" xlink:type="simple">www.icmr.nic.in</ext-link>); and Council of Science and Technology (Uttar Pradesh), India (Grant No. CST/SERPD/D-1888(ii), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cstup.gov.in" xlink:type="simple">www.cstup.gov.in</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="4"/>
<table-count count="7"/>
<page-count count="19"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) is a multifactorial and complex disease. Several factors including angiogenesis, lymphangiogenesis, alterations in expression or structure of tumor suppressor genes and oncogenes and their proteins, etc are involved in malignant transformation of potentially malignant oral lesions (PMOLs) to OSCC [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p>
<p>The malignant transformation rates of PMOLs show a great variation; for example, 10–20% of hyperkeratosis or epithelial hyperplasia or epithelial dysplasia may transform to cancer and the estimated annual rate is 1.4–7% [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Lumerman in 1995 reported that 6.6%–36% of epithelial dysplasias may transform to invasive SCC [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The malignant transformation rate of leukoplakia (LKP) has been reported to range from 0.13 to 17.5% [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], 1.1% in Oral lichen planus [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and 2.3–7.6% in oral submucous fibrosis (OSMF), during 10–17 years of follow-up [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In a study from Taiwan [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], the malignant transformation rate in an average follow-up period of 42.6 months ranged from 1.9 to 5.4% for various types of PMOLs.</p>
<p>At present, histologic assessment of epithelial dysplasia is the gold standard for determining the malignant transformation risk of PMOLs. However, the problem of inter and intra observer variation is always there in the histopathologic assessment of presence and severity of epithelial dysplasia [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In spite of tremendous progress in the field of molecular biology, there is as yet no single marker or set of markers that reliably predict malignant transformation of LKP in individual patients [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Therefore, objective biomarkers which do not require the ability to recognize morphologic changes are needed to evaluate the risk of malignant transformation of PMOLs.</p>
<p>FGF-2 is one of the prototypes of a large family of growth factors which is expressed in several tissues and has a wide scope of biologic activities [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It binds to low affinity heparin sulfate proteoglycans that are involved in the interaction with high affinity receptors that in turn mediate the cellular response to FGF-2 [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The FGF receptor family consists of four members (FGFR-1(flg), FGFR-2 (bek), FGFR-3 and FGFR-4) that have 55–72% amino acid homology [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p>
<p>FGF-2 induces angiogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and its receptors may play a role in synthesis of collagen. It is involved in the transmission of signals between the epithelium and connective tissue, and influences growth and differentiation of a wide variety of tissue including epithelia [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p>
<p>Studies have reported FGF-2 overexpression in high grade malignant tumours and malignant transformation of normal cells transfected with FGF-2 gene [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. FGF-2 is involved in the invasion of cancer cells and the proliferation of fibroblasts around cancer cells in an autocrine or paracrine fashion [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The study of expression of this factor in head and neck carcinomas (HNC) has yielded controversial results [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. It has been suggested that deployment of FGFR-specific tyrosine kinase inhibitors as single agent or in combination with EGFR inhibitors may be one of the effective therapeutic strategies in Head and Neck squamous cell carcinoma [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p>
<p>The aim of present study was to analyze the expression of FGF-2 and its receptors FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 in PMOLs and OSCC and their role in risk assessment for malignant transformation of LKP and OSMF to OSCC.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Subjects and sample collection</title>
<p>Tissue biopsies were obtained from cases of 72 PMOLs which included 43 cases of LKP and 29 cases of OSMF, 108 OSCC and 52 healthy controls from the Departments of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery and Otorhinolaryngology, King George’s Medical University Lucknow after obtaining the Institutional Ethical approval and informed written consent from patients during the year 2007 to 2012. Healthy oral tissues were obtained from patients undergoing cosmetic surgery, who otherwise did not have any infective or inflammatory oral lesion. A small part of the tissue was snap frozen for molecular work and was stored at -80°C. The inclusion criteria followed for PMOLs patients was as described by Ho et al. (2009) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Relevant clinical and demographic details of each patient were recorded on a structured proforma.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Histopathological examination</title>
<p>All tissues were fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin and processed for histopathological examination as per standard procedure. 5μm thick sections were cut and stained with haematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E). Sections were reviewed by two independent pathologists and histological diagnosis was made as per WHO criteria and following the classification by Warnakulasuriya et al 2007 [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] where the clinically diagnosed cases of leukoplakia on histopathology of tissue biopsies, are divided into leukoplakia with dysplasia and leukoplakia without dysplasia. Among 29 cases of the OSMF group in the present study, 11 were without dysplasia, 4 showed mild dysplasia, 5 with moderate dysplasia and 9 cases showed severe dysplasia. Among 43 cases in the Leukoplakia group, 10 cases showed no dysplasia, 3 had mild dysplasia, 10 with moderate dysplasia and 20 cases showed severe dysplasia.</p>
<p>The patients were followed up every 2 months in the first year, every 3 months in the second year, and every 4 to 6 months thereafter. The patients were followed to a maximum of 5 years. Between the follow ups some patients with leukoplakic lesions and OSMF without dysplasia, underwent treatment at an early stage and were discontinued from the follow-up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
<p>Sections were deparaffinized in xylene followed by hydration in descending ethanol grades. Endogenous peroxidase was blocked in 3% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in methanol for 30 min. Antigen retrieval was performed by heating specimens for 15 min at 95°C in citrate buffer (pH 6.0) using an EZ antigen retriever system (BioGenex, USA). Sections were then incubated with power block (BioGenex, USA) for 10 min to reduce nonspecific antibody binding. The sections were incubated overnight at 4°C with primary antibodies. Mouse monoclonal antibodies against human FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc., Santa Cruz, CA) were used. Primary antibodies were detected using super sensitive polymer-HRP IHC detection system (BioGenex, USA). After thorough washing with Tris buffered saline (TBS; pH 7.4) sections were treated with super enhancer for 20 min at room temperature followed by incubation with poly-HRP reagent for 30 min at room temperature. After three washes with TBS, DAB substrate (3, 3’-diaminobenzidine tetra hydrochloride) was applied to the sections for 5–10 min in the dark. Sections were counterstained with hematoxylin, dehydrated with ascending ethanol grades and xylene and mounted permanently with DPX. Negative control sections were processed by omitting primary antibody and breast carcinoma tissue was used as positive control.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Evaluation of staining</title>
<p>The level of expression was assessed by semiquantitative scoring which included the overall percentage area of the lesion stained positive (0–100%), and the staining intensity (0–3). In all the cases, the expression in epithelium, endothelial cells and stroma was analyzed. Grading for percentage area positivity was done as follows: &lt;10% = 0, 10–25% = 1, 25–50% = 2, 50–75% = 3, &gt;75 = 4. To evaluate the intensity, grading was done as; 0 = none, 1 = mild, 2 = moderate, 3 = strong staining. The percentage score (0–4) was multiplied by the intensity score (0–3) and a final score was assigned, 0–4 as negative staining, 5–12 as positive staining [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. At least five best fields were taken for interpreting results of percentage area.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) for <italic>FGF-2</italic>, <italic>FGFR-2</italic> and <italic>FGFR-3</italic> genes</title>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Total RNA extraction</title>
<p>RNA was extracted from frozen tissue samples with Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). RNA purification was done by DNase1 treatment (Invitrogen, Amplification grade). In brief, 1μg of total RNA sample was treated with 10X DNase I reaction buffer and DNase I (1U/10μl) and incubated for 15 min at room temperature followed by inactivation of DNase I with 25mM EDTA at 65°C for 10 min. RNA was quantified by Qubit 2.0 fluorometer (Molecular Probes, Invitrogen, USA).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>cDNA synthesis</title>
<p>250 ng of the total RNA was subjected to reverse transcription using random hexamer primers with Gene AMP RNA PCR kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster city, CA) for cDNA synthesis, as per manufacturer’s instructions. Briefly, the 20μl reaction was performed in 3 steps. Step 1 at 25°C for 10 min, step 2 at 37°C for 2 hrs and finally step 3 at 85°C for 5min. cDNA was stored at -20°C for real time PCR.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Quanitative real time PCR (qPCR)</title>
<p>qPCR was performed using StepOne Real-time PCR system (Applied Biosystems, USA) in the presence of SYBR Green fluorescent dye according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Briefly, 20μl of the reaction mixture consisting of reverse transcribed cDNA, 2X SYBR Green master mix containing dNTPs, ROX dye and 10μM of forward and reverse primers was dispensed into a fast optical 48-well real time PCR reaction plate (Applied Biosystems, USA). The PCR primers for <italic>FGF-2</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], <italic>FGFR-2</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], and <italic>FGFR-3</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] genes were selected from a published article and synthesized by MWG, India. Primer sequences were rechecked using Primer Express software 3.0 (Applied Biosystems, USA) and checked for homology by Blast sequence analysis (National Centre for Biotechnology Information). Following primers sequences were used: β-actin (endogenous control): forward <monospace>5’-GAGACCTTCAACACCCCAGCC-3’</monospace>; reverse <monospace>5’-AGACGCAGGATGGCATGGG-3’</monospace>, FGF-2: <monospace>forward5’-ATGGCAGCCGGGAGCATCACCCACG-3’</monospace>; reverse: <monospace>5’TCAGCTCTTCGCAGACATTGGAAG-3’</monospace>, FGFR-2: forward <monospace>5’-TCCACATGGAGATATGGAACAGGA-3’</monospace>; reverse <monospace>5’-GGAGCTATTTATCCCCGAGTG-3’</monospace> FGFR-3 forward <monospace>5’- CCATCGGGCATTGACAAGGAC-3’</monospace>, reverse <monospace>5’- GCATCGTCTTTCAGCATCTTCAC-3’</monospace>. Thermal cycle conditions consisted of on initial denaturation incubation at 95°C for 10min followed by 40 cycle of 15sec incubation at 95°C and 60sec incubation at 60°C followed by the thermal dissociation (melt curve) protocol for fluorescence detection. Gene expression level was determined using the 2<sup>-ΔΔCt</sup> method using beta-actin as an endogenous control. A negative control without a template was run in parallel to assess the overall specificity of the reaction. All reactions were run in replicates. Data are presented as “relative gene expression”.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Statistical analysis was performed using version 17.0 SPSS software for windows (SPSS, INC, Chicago, IL). For assessing proportional data, chi-square test was carried out. Correlation between FGF-2, FGFR-2 &amp; FGFR-3 was determined by Spearman correlation coefficient. Logistic regression was applied to evaluate hazard ratios for the malignant transformed PMOLs. Odds ratios (OR) with 95% confidence interval (95% CI) was calculated and p-values were reported. For all the tests, a p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Clinicopathological features</title>
<p>The study population comprised of 172 (74.14%) males and 60 (25.86%) females with a median age of 42 years (range 8 to 85 years). In PMOL group dysplasia was present in 51 out of 72 cases. In OSCC group, histologically 8 cases were poorly differentiated, 25 cases were moderately differentiated and 75 cases were well differentiated. 62 tumors were clinical stage I or II, and 46 tumors were clinical stage III or IV. Lymph node involvement was found in 41 cases of OSCC.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Immunohistochemical expression of FGF-2 and its receptors (FGFR-2 and FGFR-3) in PMOLs and OSCC</title>
<p>Immunhistochemical expression of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 is shown in <xref rid="pone.0138801.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Expression of FGF-2 was cytoplasmic in basal, parabasal layers in tissues with lining epithelium, tumor cells and also in stroma as shown in “<xref rid="pone.0138801.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A, 1B, 1C and 1D</xref>”. FGF-2 positivity was observed in 49.08% (53/108) OSCC cases, 31.95% (23/72) PMOLs and in 26.92% (14/ 52) control cases. Expression of FGFR-2 was found to be cytoplasmic in full thickness of epithelium, tumor cells and stromal cells as shown in “<xref rid="pone.0138801.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2A, 2B and 2C</xref>”. FGFR-2 expression was observed in 57.41% (62/108) cases of OSCC, 33.33% (24/72) cases of PMOLs and 15.38% (8/52) cases of controls. Cytoplasmic FGFR-3 expression was observed in upper and midstratum layer of lining epithelium, stromal fibroblast cells, tumor cells and seldom in endothelium of tumor stroma as shown in “<xref rid="pone.0138801.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A, 3B and 3C</xref>”. 75% cases (81/108) of OSCC, 40.28% cases (29/72) of PMOLs and 36.54% (19/52) controls stained positive for FGFR-3.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0138801.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Immunohistochemical expression of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 in OSCC and PMOLs.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0138801.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF2Negative</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF-2 Positive</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P -value</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-2Negative</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-2 Positive</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P -value</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-3Negative</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-3 Positive</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P -value</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Controls</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38(73.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(26.92)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44(84.62)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(15.38)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33(63.46)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19(36.54)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PMOLs</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49(68.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(31.95)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.445</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48(66.67)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24(33.33)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.024</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43(59.72)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29(40.28)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSMF</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(68.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(31.03)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22(75.86)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(24.14)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.331</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(62.07)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(37.93)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LKP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29(67.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(32.56)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.402</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26(60.47)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17(39.53)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25(58.14)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(41.86)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.296</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OSCC</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55(50.92)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53(49.08)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46(42.59)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(57.41)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27(25)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81(75)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="pone.0138801.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Immunohistochemical staining of FGF-2.</title>
<p>(A-D). A, FGF-2 positivity in transformed case of Leukoplakia with dysplasia X 100. B, FGF-2 positivity in transformed cases of OSMF in fibrosis area X 100. C, FGF-2 positivity in epithelium of OSCC X 400. D, FGF-2 positivity in tumor cells OSCC X 400.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pone.0138801.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Immunohistochemical staining of FGFR-2 (A-C).</title>
<p>A, FGFR-2 positivity in transformed cases of Leukoplakia with dysplasia X 200. B, FGFR-2 positivity in transformed case of OSMF in fibrosis area X 100. C, FGFR-2 positivity in OSCC X 100.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pone.0138801.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Immunohistochemical staining of FGFR-3 (A-C).</title>
<p>A, FGFR-3 positivity in epithelium of Leukoplakia with dysplasia in transformed case X 200. B, FGFR-3 positivity in transformed case of subepithelial fibrosis area of OSMF X 100. C, FGFR-3 positivity in tumor cells of OSCC X 400.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Association of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 with clinicopathological parameters in PMOLs and OSCC</title>
<p>Association of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 with clinicopathological parameters in PMOLs and OSCC is shown in Tables <xref rid="pone.0138801.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0138801.t003" ref-type="table">3</xref>. FGF-2 expression was significantly associated with sex (p&lt;0.013) and tumor differentiation (p&lt;0.0001) in OSCC patients. While, FGFR-2 was not associated with any clinicopathological features in oral cancer, FGFR- 3 expression was significantly higher (p&lt;0.043) in stages I-II. No association of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 was found with clinicopathological parameters in PMOLs.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0138801.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Relation of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 expression with clinico-pathological parameters in PMOLs.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0138801.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF-2positive</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF-2 negative</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-2positive</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-2negative</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-3positive</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-3negative</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;42</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.809</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥42</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.564</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.677</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dysplasia</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.179</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tobacco chewing habit</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.734</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alcohol</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.494</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.732</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Smoking</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0138801.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Association of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 with clinico-pathological features in OSCC.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0138801.t003g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF-2 positive</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF-2Negative</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-2positive</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-2negative</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-3positive</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-3negative</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;42</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.756</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.440</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥42</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.013</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.371</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Lymph node</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.156</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Differentiation</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WD</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MD</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WD</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tumor stage</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage I-II</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.823</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.043</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">StageIII-IV</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tobacco chewing habit</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.410</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.405</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alcohol</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.339</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.374</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Smoking</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.344</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.384</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.766</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Quantitative real time PCR for <italic>FGF-2</italic>, <italic>FGFR-2</italic> and <italic>FGFR-3</italic></title>
<p>Real time PCR was performed to validate the results of immunohistochemistry as shown in <xref rid="pone.0138801.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, “<xref rid="pone.0138801.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>”. The same tissue specimens that overexpresed FGF-2 and receptors by IHC were subjected to PCR.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0138801.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Gene expression profile of <italic>FGF-2</italic>, <italic>FGFR-2</italic> &amp; <italic>FGFR-3</italic> by Quantitative Real—time PCR.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0138801.t004g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls(N = 11)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LKP(N = 8)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSCC(N = 11)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSMF(N = 29)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>FGF-2</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.75</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.62</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.79</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2730769</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45445</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6142065</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3886392</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>FGFR-2</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.79</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.21</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3936878</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6452975</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.496684</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9335131</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.322</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>FGFR-3</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.05</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.333856</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7594367</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6345427</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3587593</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="pone.0138801.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Real time PCR results of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 and frequency of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 malignant transformation rate (A-D).</title>
<p>Bar diagram showing fold change expression of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 by Real Time. <bold>A</bold>, PCR in OSMF, LKP, OSCC and healthy controls. B, Frequency of FGF-2 malignant transformation rate in PMOLs. C, Frequency of FGFR-2 malignant transformation rate in PMOLs. D, Frequency of FGFR-3 malignant transformation rate in PMOLs.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>We found that OSCC patients had significantly higher level of FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 expression followed by LKP and OSMF. In OSCC patients relative gene expression of FGF-2 was 28.62 fold higher, FGFR-2 was 20.21 fold higher and FGFR-3 was 7.05 fold higher as compared to healthy controls.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Correlation between FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 in PMOLs and OSCC</title>
<p>In PMOLs, FGF-2 was significantly correlated with FGFR-2 (rs = 0.313, p&lt;0.008). FGFR-2 showed significant correlation with FGFR-3 (rs = 0.260, p&lt;0.027). In OSCC, FGF-2 was significantly correlated with FGFR-2 (rs = 0.321, p&lt;0.001) and FGFR-3 (rs = 0.353, p&lt;0.000). As in PMOLs, FGFR-2 showed significant correlation with FGFR-3 (rs = 0.368, p&lt;0.000).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Malignant transformation (from PMOLs to OSCC) and association with FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-2</title>
<p>Malignant transformation of PMOLs to OSCC was observed in 13.89% (10/72) cases (3 OSMF and 7 LKP cases) as shown in <xref rid="pone.0138801.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. Some cases of both OSMF (n = 3) and LKP (n = 4) groups, with either no dysplasia or mild dysplasia regressed after the course of treatment.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0138801.t005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t005</object-id>
<label>Table 5</label> <caption><title>Patients characteristic of malignant transformed and untransformed cases in PMOLS.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0138801.t005g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients Characteristics</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Untransformed PMOLs (N = 62)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malignant transformed PMOLs (N = 10)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age (Years)</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.81± 11.98</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.60± 18.65</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20–80</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22–75</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex N (%)</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (27.42%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (72.58%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (90%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dysplasia</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (66.13%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (100%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.029</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Mild</italic></bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Moderate</italic></bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Severe</italic></bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (33.87%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tobacco chewing habit</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (64.52%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (80%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.335</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (35.48%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alcohol</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (38.71%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (40%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.938</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (61.29%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (60%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Smoke</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (46.77%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (70%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (53.23%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (30%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Follow—up</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.21</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.41</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.749</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range(months)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–55</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10–60</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FGF-2 expression</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (75.81%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (24.19%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (90%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FGFR-2 expression</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (74.19%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (25.81%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (80%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FGFR-3 expression</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (62.90%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (40%)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.171</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (37.10%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (60%)</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>FGF-2 expression was seen in 15/62 cases (24.19%) of untransformed PMOLs and 9/10 cases (90%) of transformed PMOLs as shown in “<xref rid="pone.0138801.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>”. FGFR-2 expression was observed in 16/62 (25.81%) of untranformed PMOLs and 8/10 (80%) transformed PMOLs as shown in “<xref rid="pone.0138801.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4C</xref>”. FGFR-3 expression was observed in 23/62 (37.10%) cases of untransformed PMOLs and 6/10 cases (60%) in transformed PMOLs as shown in “<xref rid="pone.0138801.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4D</xref>”. The characteristics of individual malignant transformed cases are described in <xref rid="pone.0138801.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>. FGF-2 and FGFR-2 expression was found to be significantly associated with malignant transformation of PMOLs to OSCC both at phenotypic (FGF-2 p&lt;0.000, FGFR-2 p&lt;0.001), and molecular level (FGF-2 p&lt;0.019, FGFR-2 p&lt;0.025). No association of FGFR-3 was found with malignant transformation.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0138801.t006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t006</object-id>
<label>Table 6</label> <caption><title>Characteristics of the malignant transformed cases.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0138801.t006g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CaseNo.</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site of lesion</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tobacco chewing habit</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dysplasia</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF-2</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-2</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-3</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow- up in months</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMF</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMF</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMF</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LKP</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LKP</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LKP</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LKP</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LKP</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LKP</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LKP</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t006fn001"><p>M, Male; F, Female; BM, Buccal mucosa; T, Tongue; G, Gingival buccal sulcus. P, Present; A, Absent.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>Logistic regression analysis of malignant transformation risk in PMOLs</title>
<p>To evaluate the risk of malignant transformation of PMOLs we analyzed clinicopathological parameters and FGF-2 and FGFR-2 expression by logistic regression. In the univariate regression analysis, FGF-2 and FGFR-2 expression was associated with 28.2-fold (95% CI, (3.29–241.72); P &lt;0.002) and 11.5-fold (95% CI, 2.20–59.91; P &lt;0.004) increased risk of malignant transformation, respectively as shown in <xref rid="pone.0138801.t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>. To further assess the influence of each factor, we did multivariate regression analysis. Both these factors retained statistical significance. The OR for transformation was 19.91 for FGF-2 (95% CI, 12.20–180.32; P &lt;0.008) and 7.22 for FGFR-2 (95% CI, 1.20–43.31; P &lt;0.031). Interestingly, when co-expression of FGF-2 and FGFR-2 was considered as cofactor, the risk of malignant transformation was considerably higher in PMOLs showing co-expression as compared to PMOLS without co-expression of FGF-2and FGFR-2 (OR, 4.19; 95% CI, 1.81–9.71; P &lt; 0.001).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0138801.t007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t007</object-id>
<label>Table 7</label> <caption><title>Logistic regression analysis of variables in PMOLs malignant transformation.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0138801.t007g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0138801.t007" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Univariate analysis</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (.98–1.08)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (.03–2.50)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tobacco</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 (.42–11.27)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.344</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (.27–4.13)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.938</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65 (.62–11.22)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF-2 expression</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.20 (3.29–241.72)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-2 expression</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 (2.20–59.91)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-3 expression</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54 (.64–9.97)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.180</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Multivariate analysis</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF-2 expression</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.91 (2.20–180.32)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGFR-2 expression</td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.22 (1.20–43.31)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.031</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Coexpression of FGF-2/FGFR-2</bold></td>
<td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19 (1.81–9.71)</td>
<td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t007fn001"><p>OR, Odds ratio; 95%CI, 95% confidence interval.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The transformation of oral precancerous lesions to cancer is a known fact. However it is difficult to predict which precancerous lesions will progress into malignancy. The present study evaluated the expression of FGF-2 and its receptors FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 in PMOLs and OSCC and their role in assessment for malignant transformation of PMOLs to OSCC.</p>
<p>FGF-2 is involved in induction of angiogenesis in several cancers; phaeochromocytoma, renal cell carcinoma, astrocytoma, bladder carcinoma, hepatocellular carcinoma, and prostate cancer [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and also in the signals between the epithelium and connective tissue, influencing growth and differentiation. We observed expression of FGF-2 and its receptors FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 in neoplastic progression from normal through stages of epithelial dysplasia to oral squamous cell carcinoma. FGF-2 immunohistochemical expression was observed in 49.08% (53/108) cases of OSCC, 31.95% (23/72) cases of PMOLs and 26.92% (14/52) of controls. The expression of FGF-2 was cytoplasmic in basal and parabasal layers with lining squamous epithelium, tumor cells and also in the tumor stroma. Our findings are similar to that of Raimondi et al. (2006) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] who have reported FGF-2 immunostaining only in cytoplasm of the basal layers of the epithelium in hamster cheek pouch model of oral cancer. Higher expression of FGF-2 in breast cancer stroma as compared to normal breast stroma has been reported [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p>
<p>FGF-2, besides being expressed in cancer and precancer, was also found in 26.92% cases of healthy controls in the present study. Wakulich et al (2002) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] noticed weak to intense staining of FGF-2 in basal and parabasal layers in normal epithelium of 78.57% (11/ 14) cases. They found no statistically significant difference in staining intensity between normal and carcinomatous tissue. Further the presence of FGF-2 expression in basal and parabasal layers suggested that this growth factor was involved in proliferation but not in differentiation of normal oral keratinocytes.</p>
<p>FGF-2 expression was significantly high (60.38%) in well differentiated tumors in the present study. Janot et al. (1995) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and Wakulich et al. (2002) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] have also reported increased FGF-2 staining in well differentiated tumors suggesting that it may be involved in mitosis seen in dysplasia, carcinoma in situ and OSCC.</p>
<p>In the present study, FGFR-2 expression was observed in 57.41% (62/108) cases of OSCC, 33.33% (24/72) cases of PMOLs and 15.38% (8/52) cases of controls. Wakulich et al. (2002) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] have also reported generalized increase in staining intensity at all levels in dysplasias and carcinomatous tissue. While we observed FGFR-2 expression in normal epithelium in only 8 control cases, Dellacono et al. (1997) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] found positive FGFR-2 staining in normal epithelium as well as in patches in OSCC. Forootan et al. (2000) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] have reported increased FGFR-2 expression in superficial layers of normal epithelium and in areas of keratinization in squamous cell carcinomas. Recently, overexpression of FGFR-2 in breast cancer cell lines was reported to lead to constitutive FGFR-2 activation. Inhibition of FGFR-2 signaling in these cells induced apoptosis [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Thus, constitutive FGFR-2 signaling due to FGFR-2 overexpression can lead to protection from apoptosis which is one of the hallmarks of cancer [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p>
<p>Cytoplasmic FGFR-3 expression was observed in upper and middle layers of lining epithelium, stromal fibroblast cells, tumor cells and sometimes in the endothelium of tumor stroma. We found FGFR-3 positivity in 75% cases (81/108) of OSCC, 40.28% cases (29/72) of oral PMOLs and 36.54% cases (19/52) of controls. Our findings of FGFR-3 expression in full thickness of normal epithelium and its significant expression (p&lt;0.008) in carcinomas are supported by the results of Raimondi et al. (2006) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] in experimental model of hamster cheek pouch. The authors found FGFR-3 expression in normal mucosa as well as its significant expression in carcinoma, predominantly in the basal layers. The presence of FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 receptors in epithelial cells, fibroblasts and endothelia are an evidence to their participation in normal epithelial growth and in the maintenance of connective tissue structures and of vascular network [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p>
<p>FGFR-3 has been shown to play an important role in bladder cancer growth and is suggested as a candidate for targeted therapy [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In human bladder cancer, the FGFR-3 mutations were observed to be strongly associated with non invasive, low grade and stage. A two pathway model of carcinogenesis (favorable and unfavorable) has been proposed in urinary bladder cancer [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The favorable pathway is characterized by mutations in FGFR-3 and a clinically unfavorable pathway characterized by mutations in p53. Further the detection of FGFR-3 mutations in urine from patients with FGFR-3 mutations in primary tumor indicating tumor recurrence has also been reported. Thus identification of FGFR-3 mutations may be a potential biomarker of prognosis and recurrence [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. This needs to be studied in oral cancer.</p>
<p>In the present study, we found that the FGFR-3 expression was significantly associated with tumor stage. FGFR-3 expression was observed in 51.85% of cases in stages I and II. Unlike our results, other workers have observed more pronounced staining in stages III and IV [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p>
<p>Over expression of a gene can be caused by its amplification or aberrant transcriptional regulation. Increased mRNA levels of <italic>FGF-2</italic> and its receptors were observed in oral cancer and precancer patients as compared to normal controls in the present study. Relative gene expression of <italic>FGF-2</italic> was 28.62 fold higher in OSCC, 21.75 fold in Leukoplakia and 6.79 fold higher in OSMF as compared to healthy controls. <italic>FGFR-2</italic> relative gene expression was 20.21 fold higher in OSCC, 16.79 fold higher in LKP and 9.72 fold higher in OSMF as compared to healthy controls. Relative gene expression of <italic>FGFR-3</italic> was 7.05 fold higher in OSCC, 4.45 fold higher in LKP and 3.95 fold higher in OSMF as compared to healthy controls. Elevated levels of FGFRs have been found in numerous cancers such as cancer of brain, head and neck, lung, stomach, breast, prostate and in sarcomas and multiple myeloma. However, an elevated level of a protein in cancer cell does not necessarily mean that this protein plays a role in carcinogenesis. Further it is not always clear that the FGFR alterations found in human cancers are “drivers” or “passengers” [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p>
<p>Several alterations, most often leading to increased FGFR signaling have been associated with human carcinogenesis and development of a malignant phenotype [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. FGFs/FGFRs are key regulators of mesenchymal-epithelial communication. In adults, FGFR signaling continues to regulate tissue homeostasis and is also involved in processes such as tissue repair, angiogenesis and inflammation. In angiogenesis and neovascularization, FGFR signaling is mainly thought to play an indirect role by influencing other growth factors such as VEGF and hepatocyte growth factor [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p>
<p>FGFRs have also been observed in several cancers suggesting a tumor suppressor role of FGFR signaling in these cases. However, it is currently not well understood how FGFR-2 signaling seems to exhibit tumor suppressing effects in some cells and oncogenic effects in others. The basic mechanisms of FGFR signaling have been discussed in an excellent review on roles of fibroblast growth factor receptors in carcinogenesis by Haugsten et al. (2010) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p>
<p>Imbalanced FGFR signaling could contribute to carcinogenesis and could thus be a potent therapeutic target in several human cancers. Several promising FGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors and FGFR-blocking antibodies have been developed and some of them are in early phases of clinical trials [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p>
<p>We found malignant conversion of PMOLs (OSMF, LKP) to OSCC in 13.89% (10/72) cases with mean follow up of 29.41 months. All the precancer cases 7 LKP (16.28%) and 3 OSMF (10.34%) which transformed into malignancy, had associated epithelial severe dysplasia. This number is an under-representation of the population because our study was restricted to only biopsy proven cases of pre-cancerous lesions, that too only in two categories i.e. LKP and OSMF. Further, the cases of OSMF are also limited, as all clinical cases which report to us, have not been included in the study. Only those cases of OSMF who underwent surgery as a part of their treatment were included in our study. FGF-2 was positive in 90% (9/10) and FGFR-2 was positive in 80% (8/10) of transformed cases, a finding of statistical significance (FGF-2 p&lt;.0001; FGFR-2 p&lt;.001). Myoken et al. (1994) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] in their immunohistochemical study, reported stronger expression of FGF-2 in OSCCs as compared to normal tissue, suggesting the possibility of its involvement in malignant transformation and self proliferation of cells. Fibroblasts transfected with <italic>FGF-2</italic> cDNA underwent malignant transformation thereby acquiring self proliferative ability.</p>
<p>OSMF is an established precancerous lesion prevalent in India [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. It is caused mainly due to the habit of chewing betel quid which subjects the oral mucosa to direct and frequent contact with chemical carcinogens. One third of OSMF cases slowly progress into squamous cell carcinoma. In experimental carcinogenesis model of oral cancer, when chemical cancerization solution is spread over the mucosa of hamster cheek pouch (one of the most widely accepted animal model of oral cancer), the first change observed is marked desmoplasia or fibrosis underlying the cancerized epithelium, even before the abnormal morphologic epithelial lesions occur. Fibrosis or desmoplasia in the oral cancer may be either a stromal component of the tumor itself or it may be associated with preceding OSMF [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p>
<p>The principal cells in OSMF implicated as a source of extracellular matrix in the areas of fibrosis are fibroblasts. Accumulation of connective tissue matrix is secondary to factors such as cytokines and growth factors. In the present study, 3 out of 29 (10.34%) cases of OSMF progressed into OSCC. In a report from southern India, 40% of oral cancer patients had OSMF. Incidence of 7.6% oral cancer in OSMF patients was reported by authors in a median follow-up period of 10-year. We however, had a follow up period of 5 years in this study. Increased FGF-2 expression can be explained due to an initial injury phase because of areca consumption, followed by cellular activation by chemotactic cytokines and other growth factors with eventual fibrosis occurring as a result of molecular alteration at the cellular level [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p>
<p>The univariate and multivariate analysis with logistic regression showed statistically significant expression of only FGF-2 and FGFR-2 and their combined co-expression in cases which transformed from precancer into malignancy in the present study. Tumor derived FGF-2 may promote cancer progression by elevating proteolytic enzymes and by paracrine stimulation of vascular endothelial cell growth [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].</p>
<p>Shi et al. (2010) [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] have reported immunohistochemical expression of 2 other modulators of angiogenesis; podoplanin and ABCG2 as markers for evaluating risk of malignant transformation of oral lichen planus. We however, did not have any case of oral lichen planus in our study.</p>
<p>In the present study, presence of dysplasia was found to be a significant clinico-pathologic predictor for malignant transformation in precancer [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Age, sex, tobacco, smoking, and alcohol intake were not predictors of malignant transformation. Our findings are in close conformity with previous reports [<xref rid="pone.0138801.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138801.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p>
<p>Our data showed up-regulated FGF-2, FGFR-2 and FGFR-3 expression both at phenotypic and molecular level from PMOLs to OSCC with statistically significant co-expression of FGF2 and FGFR2. Therefore, expression of FGF-2 and FGFR-2 may serve as an adjunct to histopathologic assessment of epithelial dysplasia for evaluating progression and malignant transformation in PMOLs. However, the study is limited by the overall numbers of converted patients. Further studies need to be done in a large cohort to draw a strong conclusion.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors wish to thank Indian Council of Medical Research, GOI (Project No. 5/13/56/2008-NCDIII) and Council of Science and Technology (UP, India) for financial support. We are grateful to all participants for their cooperation during the course of the study.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jorden</surname> <given-names>RCK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daley</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oral squamous cell carcinoma: new insights</article-title>, <source>J Can Dent Assoc</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9264211</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarnath</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhoite</surname> <given-names>LT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deo</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular lesions in human oral cancer: the Indian scene</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer B Oral Oncol</source>. <year>1993</year>; <volume>29B</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7910088</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schepman</surname> <given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Meij</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smeele</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Waal</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Malignant transformation of oral leukoplakia: a follow-up study of a hospital-based population of 166 patients with oral leukoplakia from The Netherlands</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9813722</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname> <given-names>S</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gorsky</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lozada</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oral leukoplakia and malignant transformation. A follow-up study of 257 patients</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>568</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6537892</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumerman</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerpel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oral epithelial dysplasia and the development of invasive squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7621010</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amagasa</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashiro</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uzawa</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oral premalignant lesions: from a clinical perspective</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10147-010-0157-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10147-010-0157-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21225307</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brouns</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baart</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karagozoglu</surname> <given-names>Kh</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aartman</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloemena</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Waal</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Malignant transformation of oral leukoplakia in a well-defined cohort of 144 patients</article-title>. <source>Oral Dis</source>. <year>2014</year> <month>Apr</month>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e19</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/odi.12095" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/odi.12095</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23521625</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <article-title>Malignant transformation of oral lichen planus: a retrospective study of 23 cases</article-title>. <source>Quintessence Int</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19417887</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murti</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhonsle</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pindborg</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daftary</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Malignant transformation rate in oral submucous fibrosis over a 17-year period</article-title>. <source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3866655</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pindborg</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murti</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhonsle</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daftary</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oral submucous fibrosis as a precancerous condition</article-title>. <source>Scand J Dent Res</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6589738</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsue</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>YK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Malignant transformation in 1458 patients with potentially malignant oral mucosal disorders: a follow-up study based in a Taiwanese hospital</article-title>. <source>J Oral Pathol Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17181738</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karabulut</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reibel</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Therkildsen</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Praetorius</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neilson</surname> <given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dabelsteen</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Observer variability in the histologic assessment of oral premalignant lesions</article-title>. <source>J Pathol Med</source>. <year>1995</year>; <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbey</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaugars</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gunsolley</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svirsky</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Intraexaminer and interexaminer reliability in diagnosis of oral epithelial dysplasia</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>. <year>1995</year>; <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7552884</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rattay</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McConkey</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helliwell</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehanna</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biomarkers in dysplasia of the oral cavity: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>653</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.oraloncology.2009.02.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2009.02.006</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19442563</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshitake</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishikawa</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Distribution of fibroblast growth factors in cultured tumor cells and their transplants</article-title>. <source>In Vito Cell Dev Biol</source>. <year>1992</year>; <volume>28A</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klagsbrun</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baird</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>A dual receptor system is required for basic fibroblast growth factor activity</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1655276</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coutts</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Receptor for fibroblast growth factor</article-title>. <source>Immunol Cell Biol</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Givol</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yayon</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Complexity of FGF receptors: genetic basis for structural diversity and functional specificity</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>3362</fpage>–<lpage>3369</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1464370</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dailey</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrosetti</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mansukhani</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basilico</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mechanisms underlying differential responses to FGF signaling</article-title>. <source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15863038</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanaka</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fries</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beger</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uchida</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onda</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Overexpression of acidic and basic fibroblast growth factors in human pancreatic cancer correlates with advanced tumor stage</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. <year>1993</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>5289</fpage>–<lpage>5296</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7693336</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukui</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nawashiro</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otani</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ooigawa</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yano</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Nuclear accumulation of basic fibroblast growth factor in human astrocytic tumors</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>3061</fpage>–<lpage>3067</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12784342</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bikfalvi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pintucci</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rifkin</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biological roles of fibroblast growth factor-2</article-title>. <source>Endocr Rev</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9034785</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaye</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyall</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mudd</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schlessinger</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarver</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Expression of acidic fibroblast growth factor cDNA confers growth advantage and tumorigenesis to Swiss 3T3 cells</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <year>1988</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>963</fpage>–<lpage>969</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2841120</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasda</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurokawa</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iwane</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Igarashi</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Transformation of mouse BALB/c 3T3 cells with human basic fibroblast growth factor cDNA</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2832728</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kilgour</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular pathways: fibroblast growth factor signaling: a new therapeutic opportunity in cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1855</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-11-0699" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-11-0699</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388515</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janot</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>el Naggar</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clayman</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Expression of basic fibroblast growth factor in squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck is associated with degree of histologic differentiation</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>. <year>1995</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7615354</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dellacono</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spiro</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisma</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kreutzer</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Expression of basic fibroblast growth factor and its receptors by head and neck squamous carcinoma tumor and vascular endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>174</volume>: <fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9374233</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakulich</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson-Boeters</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daley</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wysocki</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Immunohistochemical localization of growth factors fibroblast growth factor-1 and factors fibroblast growth factor-2 and factors fibroblast growth factor-3 in normal oral epithelium, epithelial dysplasias, and squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Oral surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>579</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12075207</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shareef</surname> <given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Majeed</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Immunohistochemical expression of Basic fibroblast growth factor-2 and Heparanase in oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Bagh College Dentistry</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hinz</surname> <given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kono</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singleton</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bichon</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor receptors are components of autocrine signaling networks in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma cells</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>5016</fpage>–<lpage>5025</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-11-0050" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-11-0050</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21673064</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname> <given-names>P-S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>P-L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warnakulasuriya</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shieh</surname> <given-names>T-Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y-K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>I-Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Malignant transformation of oral potentially malignant disorders in males: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2407-9-260" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2407-9-260</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19640311</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warnakulasuriya</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>NW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Waal</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nomenclature and classification of potentially malignant disorders of the oral mucosa</article-title>. <source>J Oral Pathol Med</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>36</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17944749</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karavasilis</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malamou-Mitsi</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briasoulis</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsanou</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitsou</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalofonos</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Angiogenesis in cancer of unknown primary: Clinicopathological study of CD34, VEGF and TSP-1</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15743540</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hase</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawashiri</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nozaki</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noguchi</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor-2 accelerates invasion of oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Oral Science international</source>. <year>2006</year>; <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giri</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ropiquet</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ittmann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Alerations in expression of basic fibroblast growth factor (FGF-2) and its receptor FGFR-1 in human prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1071</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10353739</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raimondi</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molinolo</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Itoiz</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor-2 expression during experimental oral carcinogenesis. Its possible role in the induction of pre-malignant fibrosis</article-title>. <source>J Oral Pathol Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16519768</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finak</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertos</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pepin</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sadekova</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Souleimanova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal> <article-title>Stromal gene expression predicts clinical outcome in breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>518</fpage>–<lpage>527</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nm1764" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nm1764</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18438415</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forootan</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helliwell</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Basic fibroblast growth factor and angiogenesis in squamous cell carcinoma of the tongue</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10964050</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haugsten</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiedlocha</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsnes</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wesche</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Roles of fibroblast growth factor receptors in carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer Res</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1439</fpage>–<lpage>1452</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1541-7786.MCR-10-0168" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1541-7786.MCR-10-0168</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21047773</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Knowles</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lloreta</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kogevinas</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amoros</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tardon</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Prospective study of FGFR3 mutations as a prognostic factor in non muscle invasive urothelial bladder carcinomas</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>3664</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16877735</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacLennan</surname> <given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montironi</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Molecular determinants of tumor recurrence in the urinary bladder</article-title>. <source>Future Oncol</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>857</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2217/fon.09.50" xlink:type="simple">10.2217/fon.09.50</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19663734</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo-Martin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Domingo-Domenech</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karni-Schmidt</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matos</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cordon-Cardo</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular pathways of urothelial development and bladder tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source>Urol Oncol</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.urolonc.2009.04.019" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.urolonc.2009.04.019</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20610278</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyake</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugano</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugino</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor receptor 3 mutation in voided urine is a useful diagnostic marker and significant indicator of tumor recurrence in non-muscle invasive bladder cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Sci</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1349-7006.2009.01334.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2009.01334.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19843069</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuiverloon</surname> <given-names>TCM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Aa</surname> <given-names>MNM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Kwast</surname> <given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steyerberg</surname> <given-names>EW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lingsma</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bangma</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor receptor 3 mutation analysis on voided urine for surveillance of patients with low-grade non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3011</fpage>–<lpage>3018</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-3013" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-3013</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20404005</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simons</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor regulation of neovascularization</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Hematol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MOH.0b013e3282f97d98" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/MOH.0b013e3282f97d98</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18391788</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grose</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor signaling: from development to cancer</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrc2780" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrc2780</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20094046</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knights</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>De-regulated FGF receptors as therapeutic targets in cancer</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>125</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pharmthera.2009.10.001" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pharmthera.2009.10.001</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19874848</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myoken</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okamoto</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Immunohistochemical localization of fibroblast growth factor -1 (FGF-1) and FGF-2 in oral squamous cell carcinoma (SCC)</article-title>. <source>J Oral Parhol Med</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrotra</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pradhan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Retrospective comparison of surgical treatment modalities in 100 patients with oral submucous fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>e1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishen</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Satyamoorthy</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of basic fibroblast growth factor in oral submucous fibrosis pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Oral Pathol Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0714.2008.00649.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1600-0714.2008.00649.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18298475</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname> <given-names>ZX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>GY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>ZT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Malignant transformation of oral epithelial dysplasia: clinicopathological risk factors and outcome analysis in a retrospective cohort of 138 cases</article-title>. <source>Histopathology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>733</fpage>–<lpage>740</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2559.2011.03938.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-2559.2011.03938.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21916948</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>ZT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>QB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname> <given-names>WW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Podoplanin and ABCG2: Malignant Transformation Risk Markers for Oral Lichen Planus</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>844</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-09-0699" xlink:type="simple">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-09-0699</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20200437</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>L-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname> <given-names>J-Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Oral Cancer Development in Patients with Leukoplakia—Clinicopathological Factors Affecting Outcome</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>e34773</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0034773" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0034773</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22514665</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0138801.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murti</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daftary</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhonsle</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pindborg</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Malignant potential of oral lichen planus: observations in 722 patients from India</article-title>. <source>J Oral Pathol</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3083065</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>