<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-09896</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0066631</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Mutation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic mutation</subject><subj-group><subject>Mutagenesis</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Human genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Autosomal dominant</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Mutation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetic screens</subject><subject>Genetics of disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic testing</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Surgery</subject><subj-group><subject>Pediatric surgery</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Genetic Analyses of a Three Generation Family Segregating Hirschsprung Disease and Iris Heterochromia</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Three Generation Family with Hirschsprung Disease</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Long</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>Emily Hoi-Man</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Guo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Firmato de Almeida</surname><given-names>Manoel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>Man-Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sham</surname><given-names>Pak-Chung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherny</surname><given-names>Stacey S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>Paul Kwong-Hang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Barceló</surname><given-names>Maria-Mercè</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Surgery, Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Psychiatry, Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Center for Genomic Sciences, Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Centre for Reproduction, Development, and Growth, Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Brain and Cognitive Sciences, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Faculdade de Medicina de Ciências Medicas de Minas Gerais, Belo Horizonte, Brazil</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toland</surname><given-names>Amanda Ewart</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Ohio State University Medical Center, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">mmgarcia@hku.hk</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MMGB PKHT PCS SSC. Performed the experiments: LC EHMW MTS MFDA. Analyzed the data: LC EHMW MMGB GC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MTS MFDA PKHT. Wrote the paper: LC EHMW MMGB.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e66631</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Cui et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We present the genetic analyses conducted on a three-generation family (14 individuals) with three members affected with isolated-Hirschsprung disease (HSCR) and one with HSCR and heterochromia iridum (syndromic-HSCR), a phenotype reminiscent of Waardenburg-Shah syndrome (WS4). WS4 is characterized by pigmentary abnormalities of the skin, eyes and/or hair, sensorineural deafness and HSCR. None of the members had sensorineural deafness. The family was screened for copy number variations (CNVs) using Illumina-HumanOmni2.5-Beadchip and for coding sequence mutations in WS4 genes (<italic>EDN3</italic>, <italic>EDNRB</italic>, or <italic>SOX10</italic>) and in the main HSCR gene (<italic>RET</italic>). Confocal microscopy and immunoblotting were used to assess the functional impact of the mutations. A heterozygous A/G transition in <italic>EDNRB</italic> was identified in 4 affected and 3 unaffected individuals. While in EDNRB isoforms 1 and 2 (cellular receptor) the transition results in the abolishment of translation initiation (M1V), in isoform 3 (only in the cytosol) the replacement occurs at Met91 (M91V) and is predicted benign. Another heterozygous transition (c.-248G/A; -predicted to affect translation efficiency-) in the 5′-untranslated region of <italic>EDN3</italic> (EDNRB ligand) was detected in all affected individuals but not in healthy carriers of the <italic>EDNRB</italic> mutation. Also, a <italic>de novo</italic> CNVs encompassing <italic>DACH1</italic> was identified in the patient with heterochromia iridum and HSCR</p>
<p>Since the <italic>EDNRB</italic> and <italic>EDN3</italic> variants only coexist in affected individuals, HSCR could be due to the joint effect of mutations in genes of the same pathway. Iris heterochromia could be due to an independent genetic event and would account for the additional phenotype within the family.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the HKU seed funding programme for basic research 201109159019 to MMGB. Support was also received from the University of Hong Kong Strategic Research Theme on Genomics. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Waardenburg-Shah syndrome, Waardenburg-Hirschsprung disease or Type IV Waardenburg syndrome (WS4; MIM #277580) is a congenital developmental disorder characterized by pigmentary abnormalities of the skin, eyes and/or hair, sensorineural deafness and aganglionosis of variable portions of the colon (Hirschsprung disease) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Shah1">[1]</xref>. WS4 is rare, with an incidence of ∼1/40,000–1/50,000 live-births, and occurs in all races. To the best of our knowledge, there are only 74 WS4 cases described (2012) in the English literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Sarin1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Tuysuz1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Jiang1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Jabeen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Karaca1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Jan1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Pingault1">[8]</xref>. WS4 can occur sporadically or it segregates in families in an autosomal dominant or recessive inheritance pattern with reduced penetrance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Pingault1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Read1">[9]</xref>.</p>
<p>WS4 is underlain by homozygous or heterozygous coding sequence (CDS) mutations affecting any of the three following genes, <italic>EDN3</italic> (20q13.2–q13.3), encoding the endothelin-3 peptide; <italic>EDNRB</italic> (13q22), encoding its receptor; and SRY (Sex determining region Y)-box 10 (<italic>SOX10</italic>) (22q13.1), encoding a transcription factor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Pingault1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Pingault2">[10]</xref>. Chromosomal abnormalities involving the regions where these genes map have also been described. These genes regulate the proliferation, migration and differentiation of the neural crest cells (NCCs) from which melanocytes, enteric and peripheral neurons derive. In human, <italic>SOX10</italic> CDS mutations account for about 50% of the WS4 patients and CDS mutations in <italic>EDN3</italic> or <italic>EDNRB</italic> for 20–30% of the WS4 patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Pingault1">[8]</xref>. However, 15–35% of the WS4 patients are devoid of CDS mutations in these 3 genes suggesting that mutations either in regulatory regions or CDSs of other genes may also lead to this disorder. Recently, a <italic>de novo</italic> deletion encompassing <italic>SOX10</italic> regulatory elements have been identified in a WS4 patient with no CDS mutations, underscoring the relevance of regulatory sequences in rare disorders <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Bondurand1">[11]</xref>. In addition, the intra- or inter- familial variability of the phenotype and incomplete penetrance observed in patients with mutations in the known WS4 genes, also suggest the involvement of additional unknown loci that may modify the effect of the mutations in the main WS4 genes.</p>
<p>Importantly, heterozygous mutations in <italic>EDNRB</italic> or <italic>EDN3</italic> are also known to cause isolated HSCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Auricchio1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Amiel1">[13]</xref>. Moreover, genetic interaction between <italic>EDNRB</italic> and <italic>RET</italic>, (the main HSCR gene) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Romeo1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Pasini1">[15]</xref> has been described in a kindred segregating both, isolated HSCR and WS4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Puffenberger1">[16]</xref> as well as in families or sporadic patients with isolated-HSCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-McCallion1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Carrasquillo1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Auricchio2">[19]</xref>. The fact that two mutated genes are needed for the manifestation of the disease also implies functional interaction, with additional molecules or “mediators” mediating the link between the RET and EDNRB signaling pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Barlow1">[20]</xref>. Interactions between <italic>Sox10</italic>, <italic>Edn3</italic> and <italic>Ednrb</italic> during enteric nervous system and melanocyte development have also been described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Stanchina1">[21]</xref> in mice. Indeed, the complexity and phenotypic variability already observed in genetically heterogeneous or oligogenic congenital disorders can be conceptually understood in the light large range of molecular and cellular interactions that take place during development. Thus, DNA alterations in any of the genes codifying for the signaling molecules that govern the fate of the melanocytes and enteric neurons precursors may represent a primary etiology for WS4. The WS4 phenotype may therefore result from i) single severe DNA alterations in coding or non-coding sequences of any genes encoding crucial molecules; ii) the combinatory effects of less severe mutations in several genes; iii) the former and the later combined. The existence of non-clinically affected individuals carrying mutations in major genes invokes a compensatory effect by other genes.</p>
<p>Here we present candidate gene screening, haplotype and copy number variation analyses on a three-generation family segregating Hirschsprung disease and WS4 features. We observed that while heterozygous mutations in two genes of the same pathway only coexisted in HSCR-affected individuals, a <italic>de novo</italic> CNV could account for the heterochromia iridum phenotype presented by the only family member displaying WS4 features.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Pedigree</title>
<p>A non-consanguineous three-generation white Brazilian family of European ancestry (14 individuals) with Hirschsprung phenotype was included in this study. Out of the fourteen individuals, three (II-1, II-3, III-3) were only affected with the most severe type of Hirschsprung disease (long segment aganglionosis; L-HSCR) and one (II-5) was affected with L-HSCR and complete heterochromia iridum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0066631-g001"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>). Adult family members gave written informed consent and for minors, written informed consent was obtained from their parents. The study was approved by the institutional review board of The University of Hong Kong together with the Hospital Authority (IRB:UW06-349/T/1374).</p>
<fig id="pone-0066631-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Pedigree of the three-generation family included in this study.</title>
<p>Slash: deceased. Solid black: individuals affected with HSCR only. Green: individual affected with HSCR and heterochromia iridum. Yellow: individual affected with HSCR and meningocele. + indicates <italic>EDNRB</italic> c.1A&gt;G; * indicates <italic>EDN3</italic> c.-248G&gt;A.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p><bold>II-1</bold> was born in 1965 with Hirschsprung disease from unaffected non-consanguineous parents. Duhamel procedure was performed in 1966, when he was 17 months old. Complications following the operation included stenosis and fistulas and, an emergency colostomy was performed. Finally, after a Soave operation, the patient was discharged (in 1968) in excellent conditions. Colonic biopsy showed aganglionosis. <bold>II3</bold>, born in 1968, was medically treated until the age of 3, when she was submitted to a Soave operation (without colostomy) and finally diagnosed with L-HSCR. <bold>II5</bold> was born (1970) with complete heterochromia iridum (the 2 irides are of different color, one blue and the other brown) and L-HSCR. He was treated medically till he was 3 years old when he was also submitted to a Soave procedure without colostomy. Colonic biopsy showed aganglionosis. <bold>III-3</bold> born in 2007 with L-HSCR, was operated at the age of 15 months. Colonic biopsy showed aganglionosis. III-3 has two siblings, <bold>III-1</bold>, a male born in 1994 with no HSCR or WS4 features, and <bold>III-2</bold>, a girl (born in 2004) who died aged 10 months. III-2 was born with myelomeningocele and megacolon. She developed post operatory mild hydrocephalus and passed away to septicaemia and urinary infection. No DNA sample is available from this family member. This is the only family member who had neurological problems.</p>
<p>Except for <bold>II5</bold>, no pigmentation anomalies were observed in any of the family members. Also, none of the individuals had sensorineural hearing impairment nor developmental/growth delay or dysmorphic features.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>DNA sequence analysis</title>
<sec id="s2b1">
<title>Direct sequencing of coding regions</title>
<p>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification and direct sequencing were used to screen for DNA variations in the coding and the 5′ and 3′ flanking regions of the known WS4 candidate genes <italic>EDN3</italic>, <italic>EDNRB</italic>, <italic>SOX10</italic>, as well as those of <italic>RET</italic> (the main HSCR gene). For the latter, the <italic>RET</italic> intron 1 SNP (rs2435357), highly associated with HSCR and known to interact with <italic>EDNRB</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Carrasquillo1">[18]</xref> was also amplified and sequenced. Primers and PCR conditions are described elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-So1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-GarciaBarcelo1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Sham1">[24]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b2">
<title>SNP genotyping array and CNV predictions</title>
<p>The 14 individuals were genotyped on the Illumina HumanOmni2.5-Quad Beadchip, which contains 2,443,177 markers throughout the genome. This allowed us to <bold>i)</bold> verify the familial relationships; <bold>ii)</bold> assess the presence of CNVs; <bold>iii)</bold> obtain accurate haplotypes.</p>
<p>Calls were provided by the Centre for Applied Genomics (TCAG; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tcag.ca" xlink:type="simple">www.tcag.ca</ext-link>; Toronto, Canada). CNV segments were predicted by two programs, PennCNV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Wang1">[25]</xref> and QuantiSNP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Colella1">[26]</xref>, which are two most efficient and publicly available CNV calling algorithms for Illumina data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Dellinger1">[27]</xref>. Both programs implement hidden Markov models based on normalized probe intensity value against expected intensity in terms of Log<sub>2</sub> R ratio and relative allelic copy in terms of B allele frequency. PennCNV integrates additional information in CNV prediction (i.e. population allele frequency and distance between adjacent SNPs). .</p>
<p>To obtain high-confidence calls, we only used the overlapping region of CNVs called by both programs. Before selecting the overlapping CNV regions, quality control were done separately (please refer to <bold>supplementary materials for details</bold>).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Haplotype reconstruction</title>
<p>The most likely haplotypes of the pedigree members were constructed using MERLIN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Abecasis1">[28]</xref>. The MERLIN haplotype output files were visualized with HaploPainter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Thiele1">[29]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Generation of expression constructs</title>
<p>Wild-type <italic>EDNRB</italic> variant 1 cDNA (RefSeq: NM_000115.1) cloned in a pCMV6 expression vector (pCMV6-<italic>EDNRB</italic>-v1-GFP) with a variant of green fluorescent protein tag at the C-terminal end (Turbo-GFP; Origene) and an empty pCMV6-GFP expression vector were obtained from Origene Technologies (Rockville, MD, USA). Reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR) was performed to isolate full-length coding region of <italic>EDNRB</italic> variant 4 (RefSeq: NM_001201397; isoform 3) from human melanoma cell lines and ligated into pGEM-T Easy vector (Promega). Primers with Sgf I and Mlu I restriction sites were designed to amplify full-length coding regions of <italic>EDNRB</italic> variant 4 (RefSeq: NM_001201397) which was then subcloned to pCMV6 entry vector to generate a pCMV6-<italic>EDNRB</italic>-v4-GFP vector. The <italic>EDNRB</italic> mutations vectors pCMV6-<italic>EDNRB</italic>-v1-M1V-GFP (M1V for isoforms 1) and pCMV6-<italic>EDNRB</italic>-v4-M91V-GFP (M91V for isoform 3) were generated by site-directed mutagenesis using the QuickChange XL Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene) according to the manufacturer's instructions. All the DNA fragments were verified by direct sequencing. Primer sequences are available upon request.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Cell lines and Transfection</title>
<p>Human Embryonic Kidney 293 cells (HEK293, Invitrogen) were grown in Dulbecco's modified Eagle medium (DMEM) supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum (FBS), penicillin (100 U/ml) and streptomycin (100 µg/ml) at 37°C with the presence of 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Cells were seeded in culture wells 24 hours prior to transfection. The plasmids, pCMV6-AC-GFP (empty vector), pCMV6-AC-<italic>EDNRB</italic>-v1-GFP (wild-type EDNRB isoform 1), pCMV6-AC-<italic>EDNRB</italic>-v4-GFP (wild-type EDNRB isoform 3), pCMV6-AC-<italic>EDNRB</italic>-v1-M1V-GFP (M1V) and pCMV6-AC-<italic>EDNRB</italic>-v4-M91V-GFP (M91V), were transfected into HEK293 cells according to Lipofectamine® 2000 transfection reagent (Invitrogen) instructions.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Immunofluorescence</title>
<p>HEK293 cells (2×10<sup>5</sup>), grown for 24 h in each 35 mm Petri-dish with 14 mm Bottom Microwell No. 1.5 coverglass (MatTek, USA), were transfected with 1.5 µg empty vector, wild-type EDNRB isoform 1, wild-type EDNRB isoform 3, M1V and M91V using Lipofectamine® 2000 transfection reagent (Invitrogen). The living cells were incubated overnight and GFP fluorescence were observed directly on the chamber slide under confocal laser scanning using a Zeiss LSM 700 confocal laser-scanning microscope (λ<sub>ex</sub> = 488 nm,λ<sub>em</sub>&gt;515 nm). Fluorescence intensity was measured using the eight-bit gray scale of the LSM 700 software.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Pedigree: pattern of inheritance</title>
<p>We considered the mode of inheritance or genetic mechanism that might give this pattern of affected family members. Two unaffected parents (I-1, I-2) had three affected children (II-1, II-3, II-5), one of whom (II-1) passed down the phenotype to two individuals (III-2, III-3) of the third generation in an <bold>apparently autosomal dominant manner</bold>. If that was the case, it would imply that one of the parents carried a mutation that, for whatever reason, was not fully penetrant. Other possibilities considered were <bold>i)</bold> one of the parents carried a <bold>balanced translocation</bold> that became unbalanced in the children in which case, miscarriages and multiple malformations in multiple organs would have been expected; and <bold>ii)</bold> <bold>autosomal recessive</bold> inheritance, in which case, <bold>I-1</bold>, <bold>I-2</bold> and <bold>II-2</bold> would all have to be carriers for the same autosomal recessive disease, which is extremely unlikely as this is a non-consanguineous family. Yet, the transmission of WS4 is described as neither fully recessive nor fully dominant. WS4 patients with different pathogenic mutations in the same gene (compound heterozygotes) have also been described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Pingault1">[8]</xref>.</p>
<p>Importantly, while only II-5 (heterochromia iridum) and III-2 (neurological problems) have with characteristics of WS4, the rest of the affected family members manifest isolated HSCR.</p>
<p>After all these considerations, we set out to investigate the genetic lesions underlying this variable phenotype. To this end, and, to cover all possibilities, the 14 family members were screened for small variations in the coding regions of <bold>i)</bold> the WS4 candidate genes; <bold>ii)</bold> the main HSCR gene; and <bold>iii)</bold> CNVs through the genome as deletions encompassing the candidate genes have been reported and translocations could also be considered in spite of all of the above.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>No<italic>SOX10</italic> deleterious variants</title>
<p>Sequencing of the complete CDS of the <italic>SOX10</italic> gene did not reveal any damaging variant that could have explained the phenotype. Two SNPs leading to synonymous changes were identified in non-affected members of the family (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0066631-t001">Table 1</xref>). These SNPs, rs73415876 (p.Y83Y) and rs139884 (p.H309H) have a global Minor Allele Frequency of 0.033 and 0.287 respectively.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0066631-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Sequence variants of<italic>EDNRB</italic>, <italic>EDN3</italic>, <italic>RET</italic> and <italic>SOX10</italic> identified.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0066631-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene and exon</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleotide change (s)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Codon position and amino acid change</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individuals</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>EDNRB</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1A/G</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M1V</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I-2, <bold>II-1, II-3</bold>, <italic>II-5</italic>, <bold>III-3</bold>, III-5, III-7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.831A/G (rs5351)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L277L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I-1, <bold>II-1</bold>, <bold>II-3</bold>, II-4, II-6, III-1, <bold>III-3</bold>, III-4, III-5, III-6, III-7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>EDN3</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′UTR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.-248G/A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I-1,<bold>II-1</bold>, <bold>II-3</bold>, <italic>II-5</italic>, <bold>III-3</bold>, III-4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RET</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.135G/A (rs1800858)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A45A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I-1, I-2, <bold>II-1</bold>, II-2, <bold>II-3</bold>, <italic>II-5</italic>, II-6, III-1, <bold>III-3</bold>, III-4, III-5, III-6, III-7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1296A/G (rs1800860)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A432A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I-2, II-2, <bold>II-3</bold>, <italic>II-5</italic>, II-4, II-6, III-1, <bold>III-3</bold>, III-4, III-5, III-6, III-7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon 13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.2307T/G (rs1800861)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L769L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I-1, I-2, <bold>II-1</bold>, <bold>II-3</bold>, II-4, <italic>II-5</italic>, III-1, <bold>III-3</bold>, III-4, III-5, III-6, III-7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SOX10</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.249C&gt;T (rs73415876)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y83Y</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II-6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.927T&gt;C (rs139884)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H309H</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II-6, II-4, III-6, III-7</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>In bold: HSCR affected individuals; In italics: individual affected with WS4.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Identification of a heterozygous mutation in<italic>EDNRB</italic></title>
<p>Sequencing of the complete CDS of the <italic>EDNRB</italic> gene revealed a c.1A&gt;G heterozygous DNA change in the NM_000115.3 sequence. The DNA variant was not only found in all affected individuals (II-1, II-3, II-5, III-3) but was also present in three unaffected individuals (I-2, III-5, III-7) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0066631-t001"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref><bold>; </bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0066631-g001"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>). c.1A&gt;G was passed down to the family members by the unaffected mother (I-2). This variant was not present in any of the databases searched (NCBI, dbSNP137, 1000 Genomes Project –release 13, December 2012-). This variant resulted in the replacement of the translation initiation codon methionine (Met) with a valine (Val) in the EDNRB isoforms 1 and 2 (NP_000106.1 and NP_003982.1; 442 and 436 amino acids, respectively) and such replacement (M1V) would theoretically abolish the use of the translation initiation codon (ATG-GTG, M1V). However, in EDNRB isoform 3 (NP_001188326.1; 532 amino acids) the replacement is at Met91 (M91V) and is predicted benign by PolyPhen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Sunyaev1">[30]</xref>.</p>
<p>At this point, the only explanation we could provide is that of reduced pentrance as direct sequencing of the other WS4 candidate genes or <italic>RET</italic> did not reveal any pathological mutation in their CDSs. Yet, we formulated several hypothesis to account for the intra-familial phenotypic variability: <bold>i)</bold> since different <italic>EDNRB</italic> transcripts are expressed concomitantly (at least in the still developing newborn's gut <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Tsutsumi1">[31]</xref> the phenotype manifestation could depend on the relative expression amounts of the mutated EDNRB isoforms (benign/damaging) at a given time point during the embryonic stages, provided that all isoforms play a similar role on neural crest cell development –enteric neurons/skin melanocytes-; <bold>ii)</bold> in carriers, in spite of having the initiation codon (M1V) mutated in isoform 1 and 2, the protein is translated using an alternative translation start site and the resulting protein, although shorter, still is functional <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Chatterjee1">[32]</xref>; <bold>iii)</bold> while the amount of protein expressed from the wild-type <italic>EDNRB</italic> allele is sufficient to maintain proper signalling in healthy carriers, it does not reach the necessary threshold for signalling in affected individuals; and/or <bold>iv)</bold> differential allelic expression (or imprinting) between carriers and affected individuals exists. Thus, variance in expression levels at different time points could account for the intra-familial variability, including that of individual II-5. Yet, no matter which of the mechanism hypothesized is proved or disproved, there must be additional genetic factors to account for the reduced penetrance of this mutation and the intra-familial variability of the phenotype. For obvious reasons, these postulations cannot be fully tested. Nevertheless, we set out to explore some of the possibilities mentioned with regards to the EDNRB mutation.</p>
<sec id="s3c1">
<title>The M1V mutation abolishes the EDNRB isoform 1</title>
<p>To investigate the translocation of the mutant EDNRB proteins within cells, we transiently transfected equal amounts (20 µg) of the wild-type or M1V mutant GFP-tagged <italic>EDNRB</italic> isoform 1 into HEK293 cells and analysed by confocal microscopy.</p>
<p>In cells transfected with wild-type EDNRB isoform 1/GFP, signals were detected at the plasma membrane only (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0066631-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). This indicates that EDNRB isoform 1 protein translocated to the cell surface and fulfilled its functional property as a cell surface receptor. On the other hand, the mutant EDNRB isoform 1 (M1V) displayed a clustered localization in the cytosol and a significantly reduced intensity on the membrane when compared with the wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0066631-g002"><bold>Figure 2A</bold></xref>). Our interpretation is that the mutation (M1V) abolishes the translation start site and that the mutated RNA could have been translated through an alternative translation initiation codon. Sequence inspection revealed that the alternative translation initiation codon is likely to be located between Gly26 and Arg64, where, within a sequence compatible with the Kozak consensus, there is a methionine in codon 46 (Met46). Thus, a shorter protein, that could not translocate onto the membrane due to the lack of the signal peptide, could have been generated and account for our observations. Reduced amount of EDNRB receptor might alter the signalling pathway and hence, the differentiation and development of neural crest cells could be affected.</p>
<fig id="pone-0066631-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Localization of C-terminally GFP-tagged EDNRB fusion proteins in HEK293 cells.</title>
<p>A: HEK293 cells were transiently transfected with wild-type EDNRB isoform 1 (Iso 1) or mutant EDNRB isoform 1 (M1V). Signals were observed at the plasma membrane in cells expressing wild-type isform 1 while signals were detected in the cytosol in cells transfected with mutant isoform 1. B: HEK293 cells were transiently transfected with wild-type EDNRB isoform 3 (Iso 3) or mutant EDNRB isoform 3 (M91V). Signals were found in the cytosol in cells transfected with either wild-type or mutant isoform 3. C. HEK293 cells were transiently transfected with GFP vector only. Shown are the representative iamges. Bars, 50 µm.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c2">
<title>Role of the<italic>EDNRB</italic> isoform 3</title>
<p>We then investigated whether indeed the mutation was innocuous to EDNRB isoform 3 as predicted by PolyPhen. Confocal microscopy showed that both wild-type EDNRB isoform 3 and mutant EDNRB isoform 3 (M91V) were imperceptible on the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0066631-g002">Figure 2B</xref>), which implies that this isoform may not function as a cellular receptor. We then resorted to TargetP 1.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Emanuelsson1">[33]</xref> and MitoProt II v1.101 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Scharfe1">[34]</xref> for <italic>in silico</italic> prediction of the EDNRB isoform 3 subcellular location (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0066631.s007">Table S1</xref>). TargetP assigns the location in accordance with the predicted presence of any of the N-terminal presequences including mitochondrial targeting peptide (mTP) and secretory pathway signal peptide (SP) and MitoProt is designed to identify mitochondrial signal sequences. Both programs predicted the presence of a 115 residues long mTP in the N terminal of EDNRB isoform 3 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0066631.s001">Figure S1</xref>). Moreover, according to MitoProt, the probability of being exported to mitochondria hardly differed between the wild-type and mutated EDNRB isoform3 (92.41% and 89.60% respectively). Importantly, no mTP were predicted for EDNRB isoforms 1 or 2. Therefore, it would appear that M91V would not affect the putative role of the EDNRB isoform 3 in the cytoplasma organelle. Thus, the EDNRB isoform 3 might not play a role as a cellular receptor and, consequently, nor in the EDNRB signaling controlling the neural crest cells fate.</p>
<p>While we cannot demonstrate whether variation in expression levels of EDNRB isoform 1 (mutated or while type) during development played a role in the manifestation of the phenotype, it seems that postulations <bold>i)</bold> and <bold>ii)</bold> are to be dismissed. Still, the effect of more than one gene is patent by the transmission and variability of the phenotype in this family.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>No interaction between<italic>RET</italic> and <italic>EDNRB</italic> alleles in this family</title>
<p>Given the significant association between the transmission of the <italic>EDNRB</italic> Trp276Cys mutation and an HSCR-susceptibility <italic>RET</italic> haplotype reported in HSCR-trios <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Carrasquillo1">[18]</xref> as well as the finding of two functionally significant <italic>EDNRB</italic> and <italic>RET</italic> mutations in a patient with isolated HSCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Auricchio2">[19]</xref>, we investigated the CDS of the <italic>RET</italic> gene and the HSCR-risk haplotype in all 14 family members.</p>
<p>No <italic>RET</italic> CDS pathological variants or mutations were detected in these individuals. Next, to find out whether a link could be established between the presence of the <italic>RET</italic> risk haplotype and the <italic>EDNRB</italic> mutation with regards to the penetrance of the latter, we constructed 4 markers <italic>RET</italic> haplotypes and investigated their transmission within the family (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0066631.s002">Figure S2</xref></bold>). The <italic>RET</italic> risk haplotype consists of the HSCR-associated alleles “TAGG” of rs2435357; rs1800858, rs1800860, and rs1800861 polymorphisms. Importantly, it has been shown that rs2435357T allele (<italic>RET</italic> intron 1) as well as the <italic>RET</italic> risk haplotype are linked to reduced <italic>RET</italic> expression both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-GarciaBarcelo2">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-GarciaBarcelo3">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Miao1">[37]</xref>. Therefore, the joint presence of the <italic>EDNRB</italic> mutation and the <italic>RET</italic> risk haplotype in affected individuals could account for the phenotypic differences between healthy and affected <italic>EDNRB</italic> mutation carriers. Yet, we found that the <italic>RET</italic> risk haplotype (both in homo- and heterozygosis states) was indistinctly present in affected and non-affected carriers as well as in non-carriers (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0066631.s002">Figure S2</xref></bold>). Therefore, it seems that the phenotypic variability cannot be explained by the interaction of these two <italic>RET</italic> and <italic>EDNRB</italic> alleles.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Joint effect of the<italic>EDNRB</italic> and <italic>EDN3</italic> alleles</title>
<p>As no CDS pathogenic variants had been found in <italic>EDN3</italic>, we paid attention to a G to A change (c.-248G/A) in the 5′ untranslated region (5′UTR) of the gene. Importantly, all <bold>affected individuals carrying the </bold><bold><italic>EDNRB</italic></bold><bold> mutation</bold> (II-1, II-3, II-5 and III-3; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0066631-g001"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>) also had this <italic>EDN3</italic> variant. The c.-248G/A <italic>EDN3</italic> change was not present in healthy <bold><italic>EDNRB</italic></bold> carriers (III5, III7) but present in two healthy non-carriers, one of whom, I-1 (unaffected father) passed it down. Haplotype reconstruction (<bold>Figure</bold> S<bold>3</bold>) clearly showed the transmission of the -248G/A <italic>EDN3</italic> variant in the pedigree from the unaffected father (I-1). This <italic>EDN3</italic> variant is not reported in dbSNP137, or in the 1000 Genomes Project database (release 13, December 2012).</p>
<p>As post-transcriptional regulation is mediated by <italic>cis</italic>-acting regulatory motifs in the 5′ and 3′UTRs, we used bioinformatic tools to find out if the c-248G/A overlapped with any of such motifs and whether the replacement of a G with an A would be detrimental. Importantly, the -248G/A transition occurred in a highly evolutionary conserved site (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0066631.s004">Figure S4</xref></bold>). Such degree of conservation for a non-translated base suggests that this 5′UTR guanine may be critical for the binding of regulatory proteins, and any disruption of this process would destabilise the mRNA and/or affect translation efficiency. While according to ENCODE , this position resides in the binding site of transcription factor SUZ12, JASPAR, a transcription factor binding profile database <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jaspar.genereg.net/" xlink:type="simple">http://jaspar.genereg.net/</ext-link> did not identify any on the site itself, but several in the neighbourhood. Thus, the variant might reduce access to those neighboring predicted sites. Next, to investigate if -248G/A could interfere with RNA folding, hence, affect the overall regulation process, we used Mfold <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Zuker1">[38]</xref> to simulate the RNA structures with either allele. The allele A lead to a strikingly different RNA structure that that of allele G (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0066631.s005">Figure S5</xref></bold>). Altogether, data suggest that the c-248 G/A transition may affect the <italic>EDN3</italic> expression levels. Functional studies on this <italic>EDN3</italic> variant were not performed. Regulatory functional activity may vary from to cell to cell type and even if the <italic>EDN3</italic> variant were functional <italic>in vitro</italic>, we would never be able to ascertain its function <italic>in vivo</italic>, especially given the relevance of spatial-temporal regulation during developmental stages.</p>
<p>Importantly, Kenny and colleagues reported lower <italic>EDN3</italic> mRNA levels in ganglionic and aganglionic gut of HSCR patients devoid of CDS mutations compared to those in gut of non-HSCR individuals and suggested <italic>EDN3</italic> transcriptional deficit as a possible cause of aganglionosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Kenny1">[39]</xref>.</p>
<p>Given that the <italic>EDNRB</italic> and <italic>EDN3</italic> variants only coexist in affected individuals (with both the EDNRB receptor and its ligand EDN3 compromised), it would appear that their joint effect is needed for the phenotype to manifest. This is in line with the essentiality of the interaction between EDN3 with ENDRB for the development of epidermal melanocytes and enteric neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Baynash1">[40]</xref>. Thus, it is tempting to speculate that the transmission of the trait results from two independent mutations in two different genes of the same pathway. This family would exemplify a case of non-allelic non-complementation which occurs when recessive mutations in two different loci fail to complement one another and consequently, the double heterozygote exhibits a phenotype. Importantly, such mechanism has already been described in HSCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-McCallion1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Carrasquillo1">[18]</xref>.</p>
<p>Yet, while all individuals carrying both the <italic>EDNRB</italic> and the <italic>EDN3</italic> heterozygous mutations have virtually the same HSCR phenotype (isolated long segment), only one (II-5) member of the family has pigmentation problems. After an exhaustive literature search, we identified only three reports of HSCR patients with heterochromia iridum as the sole associated anomaly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Lai1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Liang1">[42]</xref>. No mutation screening had been done.</p>
<p>The <italic>EDNRB</italic> and <italic>EDN3</italic> mutations reported here have been submitted to the Leiden Open Variation Database (LOVD) v.3.0.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>CNV analysis</title>
<p>We also scanned the whole genome for rare CNVs. A total of 529 CNV regions and two chromosomal aberrations (CNV&gt;1 Mb) were identified in this family. The chromosomal aberrations were transmitted by non-affected individuals to also non-affected individuals.</p>
<p>Of the 529 CNVs identified, 160 intersected with genes (genic-CNVs; 131 genes disrupted) and 369 CNVs were in non-coding regions of the genome. Among the genic-CNVs, 18 CNVs (35 genes disrupted) were present in at least one affected individual but also in unaffected family members. Likewise, among the non-genic CNVs, 62 were present in at least one affected individual but also in unaffected family members.</p>
<p>As a CNV reported in a healthy individual would be less likely to be pathogenic, all CNVs present in at least one affected individual were checked against the Database of Genomic Variants (DGV), a catalog of structural variations gathered from the analysis of 11,943 healthy individuals. All but 26 CNV regions (37 CNVs) and all chromosomal aberrations identified in this family had been also been detected among the DGV controls. None of the CNVs (including those no reported in DGV) were shared by the four affected individuals and carriers of the <italic>EDNRNB</italic> or <italic>EDN3</italic> mutations. Our data ruled out a direct role of CNVs in this familial disorder. Expectedly, no CNVs encompassing any of the WS4 candidate genes were detected.</p>
<p>Since II-5 is the only family member born with heterochromia iridum in addition to HSCR, we considered the possibility of the pigmentation problem being due to a genetic event independent of the <italic>EDNRB/EDN3</italic> mutations harboured by this individual.</p>
<p>We made use of the data provided by the CNV analysis to search for any specific feature that could account for the heterochromia iridum in that individual, bearing in mind that the search for another genetic lesion would require the scrutiny of the whole genome and that therefore, our CNV analysis is limited. Thus, we inspected the CNV profile of individual II-5 and paid attention to <bold><italic>de novo</italic></bold><bold> or inherited CNVs that were not present in any other family members (except for II-5 parents; I-1 and I-2) and had not been passed down to the next generation</bold>. II-5 had 5 genes intersected by CNVs, 2 of which were <italic>de novo</italic> and 4 inherited (<bold>Table</bold> S2). Except for <italic>ALDH2</italic>, these genes were not only reported intersected in DGV but also in the Database of Chromosomal Imbalance and Phenotype in Humans Using Ensembl Resources (DECIPHER), which contains data on over 10,000 patients suffering from developmental disorders who harbor submicroscopic deletions or duplications. Interestingly, one of the <bold><italic>de novo</italic></bold><bold> CNV duplication (45.5 kb)</bold> involved <italic>DACH1</italic> (dachshund homolog 1 (Drosophila); Attenuation of Forkhead signaling by t<bold>he retinal determination factor</bold>), a gene in chromosome 13q22 (6 Mb apart from <bold><italic>EDNRB</italic></bold>) reported deleted in Decipher patient<bold>s</bold> affected with fullness of peri-orbital region or retinoblastoma. As for the non-genic CNVs present in II-5, we identified 3 inherited and 10 <italic>de novo</italic> CNVs (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0066631.s009">Table S3</xref></bold>). Among the latter, a 38.5 kb duplication and a 20.9 kb deletion were detected in chromosome 13, 16.7 and 15.3 Mb upstream <italic>DACH1</italic> respectively. Importantly, iris heterochromia has been reported in a 13q-deletion syndrome patient without HSCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0066631-Conrad1">[43]</xref> as well as in infants with retinoblastoma. Whether these CNVs affecting <italic>DACH1</italic> or surroundings in chromosome 13q contribute to heterochromia iridum is unknown.</p>
<p>Overall, many of the CNVs reported in DGV are also reported in DECIPHER patients which indicate that the contribution of each CNV to the phenotype, if any, would be limited to the individual bearing them and this could account for the intra-familial variability observed, as exemplified by the phenotype presented by individual II-5. Of course, we cannot prove or disprove whether heterochromia iridum results from the CNVs unique to II-5 or/and from the <italic>EDNRB/EDN3</italic> mutations as reported in other patients with WS4. These CNVs may affect regulatory regions anywhere in the genome offsetting the synchronization and balance of the signaling network implicated in the disorder. Also, it should be born in mind that the heterochromia iridum phenotype could be due to a genetic mosaicism, that is, an independent event occurred during developmental stages, affecting only the embryonic cell lineage from which the eye pigmentation cells derive (in which case, we could not have detected the genetic lession).</p>
<p>In sum, our exhaustive genetic analysis shows that, in this Brazilian family of European ancestry, the manifestation of the HSCR phenotype may require mutations in two genes of the same pathway. The additional feature -iris heterochromia- presented by one affected individual could have resulted from an independent genetic event, such a <italic>de novo</italic> CNV affecting genes involved in eye development.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0066631.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Genomic structure and differential splicing of human </bold><bold><italic>EDNRB</italic></bold><bold> gene.</bold> Black arrow indicates the ATG start site for isoform 3. Red arrow indicates the ATG start site for isoform 1 and 2 and is the location of the mutation found in the Brazilian family. SP: signal peptide.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0066631.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>The most likely </bold><bold><italic>RET</italic></bold><bold> haplotypes of the pedigree (A, C, G, T to 1, 2, 3, 4).</bold> Individuals carrying the <italic>EDNRB</italic> mutation are indicated.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0066631.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>The most likely </bold><bold><italic>EDN3</italic></bold><bold> haplotypes of the pedigree were shown (A, C, G, T to 1, 2, 3, 4).</bold> It showed that the c.-248G/A variation was transmitted from the I-1 and shared by all four affected individuals, II-1, II-3, II-5, and III-3 and one unaffected individual III-4.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0066631.s004" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Nucleic acid multiple sequence alignment of mammalian 5′UTR of </bold><bold><italic>EDN3</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> The UCSC genome browser was used to identify sequence conservation features in the 5′UTR of <italic>EDN3</italic>. The red rectangle indicates the nucleotide c.-248G and it is highly conserved among species.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0066631.s005" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p><bold>Predicted RNA secondary structures for the wild-type and mutated (-248G/A) 5′UTR of the </bold><bold><italic>EDN3</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> The <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">GGGGUGGU</named-content> structure in the mutated 5′UTR of the <italic>EDN3</italic> formed a loop instead of a stem compared in the wild-type 5′UTR of the <italic>EDN3</italic>.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0066631.s006" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>File S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Supplementary material text.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0066631.s007" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>TargetP 1.1 server prediction results.</bold> Subcellular locations of different EDNRB isoform proteins were predicted by using TargetP 1.1 server. <bold>SP</bold>, a signal peptide; <bold>mTP</bold>, a mitochondrial targeting peptide; <bold>M</bold>, Mitochondrion; <bold>S</bold>, Secretory pathway; <bold>RC</bold>: Reliability class, from 1 to 5, where 1 indicates the strongest prediction.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0066631.s008" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.s008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold><italic>Genes disrupted by CNVs in II-5.</italic></bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0066631.s009" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0066631.s009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Non-genic regions disrupted by CNVs in II-5.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Shah1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dalal</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheth</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>White forelock, pigmentary disorder of irides, and long segment Hirschsprung disease: possible variant of Waardenburg syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Sarin1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarin</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manchanda</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Shah Waardenburg syndrome</article-title>. <source>Indian Pediatr</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>452</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Tuysuz1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuysuz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arapoglu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suyugul</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Clinical variability of Waardenburg-Shah syndrome in patients with proximal 13q deletion syndrome including the endothelin-B receptor locus</article-title>. <source>Am J Med Genet A</source> <volume>149A</volume>: <fpage>2290</fpage>–<lpage>2295</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Jiang1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Novel mutations in the SOX10 gene in the first two Chinese cases of type IV Waardenburg syndrome</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source> <volume>408</volume>: <fpage>620</fpage>–<lpage>624</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Jabeen1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabeen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babar</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Awan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Novel mutations of endothelin-B receptor gene in Pakistani patients with Waardenburg syndrome</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Rep</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>788</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Karaca1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karaca</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ortac</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandirici</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Waardenburg syndrome with extended aganglionosis: report of 3 new cases</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Surg</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>E9</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Jan1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stroedter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haq</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Din</surname><given-names>ZU</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Association of Shah-Waardenburgh syndrome: a review of 6 cases</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Surg</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>744</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Pingault1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pingault</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ente</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dastot-Le Moal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Review and update of mutations causing Waardenburg syndrome</article-title>. <source>Hum Mutat</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Read1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Waardenburg syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Med Genet</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>656</fpage>–<lpage>665</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Pingault2"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pingault</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bondurand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemort</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sancandi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ceccherini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A heterozygous endothelin 3 mutation in Waardenburg-Hirschsprung disease: is there a dosage effect of EDN3/EDNRB gene mutations on neurocristopathy phenotypes?</article-title> <source>JMedGenet</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Bondurand1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bondurand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fouquet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baral</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecerf</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loundon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Alu-mediated deletion of SOX10 regulatory elements in Waardenburg syndrome type 4</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>990</fpage>–<lpage>994</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Auricchio1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Auricchio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casari</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staiano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballabio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Endothelin-B receptor mutations in patients with isolated Hirschsprung disease from a non-inbred population</article-title>. <source>HumMolGenet</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Amiel1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amiel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Attie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pelet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edery</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Heterozygous endothelin receptor B (EDNRB) mutations in isolated Hirschsprung disease</article-title>. <source>HumMolGenet</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Romeo1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronchetto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Point mutations affecting the tyrosine kinase domain of the RET proto-oncogene in Hirschsprung's disease</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>367</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Pasini1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pasini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ceccherini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>RET mutations in human disease</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Puffenberger1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puffenberger</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosoda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>deWit</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>A missense mutation of the endothelin-B receptor gene in multigenic Hirschsprung's disease</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>1257</fpage>–<lpage>1266</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-McCallion1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCallion</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stames</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conlon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chakravarti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Phenotype variation in two-locus mouse models of Hirschsprung disease: tissue-specific interaction between Ret and Ednrb</article-title>. <source>ProcNatlAcadSciUSA</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>1826</fpage>–<lpage>1831</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Carrasquillo1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrasquillo</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCallion</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puffenberger</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kashuk</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nouri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide association study and mouse model identify interaction between RET and EDNRB pathways in Hirschsprung disease</article-title>. <source>NatGenet</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Auricchio2"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Auricchio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griseri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carpentieri</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Betsos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staiano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Double heterozygosity for a RET substitution interfering with splicing and an EDNRB missense mutation in Hirschsprung disease</article-title>. <source>AmJHumGenet</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>1216</fpage>–<lpage>1221</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Barlow1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Graaff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pachnis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Enteric nervous system progenitors are coordinately controlled by the G protein-coupled receptor EDNRB and the receptor tyrosine kinase RET</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>905</fpage>–<lpage>916</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Stanchina1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanchina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baral</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pingault</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemort</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Interactions between Sox10, Edn3 and Ednrb during enteric nervous system and melanocyte development</article-title>. <source>DevBiol</source> <volume>295</volume>: <fpage>232</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-So1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>RET mutational spectrum in Hirschsprung disease: evaluation of 601 Chinese patients</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e28986</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-GarciaBarcelo1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Barcelo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sham</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Highly Recurrent RET Mutations and Novel Mutations in Genes of the Receptor Tyrosine Kinase and Endothelin Receptor B Pathways in Chinese Patients with Sporadic Hirschsprung Disease</article-title>. <source>ClinChem</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Sham1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sham</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Novel mutations of SOX10 suggest a dominant negative role in Waardenburg-Shah syndrome</article-title>. <source>JMedGenet</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>E30</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Wang1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glessner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>PennCNV: an integrated hidden Markov model designed for high-resolution copy number variation detection in whole-genome SNP genotyping data</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1665</fpage>–<lpage>1674</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Colella1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>QuantiSNP: an Objective Bayes Hidden-Markov Model to detect and accurately map copy number variation using SNP genotyping data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>2013</fpage>–<lpage>2025</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Dellinger1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dellinger</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seielstad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Comparative analyses of seven algorithms for copy number variant identification from single nucleotide polymorphism arrays</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>e105</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Abecasis1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abecasis</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cherny</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cookson</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cardon</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Merlin–rapid analysis of dense genetic maps using sparse gene flow trees</article-title>. <source>NatGenet</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Thiele1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurnberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>HaploPainter: a tool for drawing pedigrees with complex haplotypes</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1730</fpage>–<lpage>1732</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Sunyaev1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunyaev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramensky</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lathe</surname><given-names>W</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kondrashov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Prediction of deleterious human alleles</article-title>. <source>HumMolGenet</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>591</fpage>–<lpage>597</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Tsutsumi1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Novel endothelin B receptor transcripts with the potential of generating a new receptor</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>228</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Chatterjee1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eapen</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A truncated form of RGS3 negatively regulates G protein-coupled receptor stimulation of adenylyl cyclase and phosphoinositide phospholipase C</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>272</volume>: <fpage>15481</fpage>–<lpage>15487</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Emanuelsson1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Locating proteins in the cell using TargetP, SignalP and related tools</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>953</fpage>–<lpage>971</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Scharfe1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scharfe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaccaria</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoertnagel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaksch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klopstock</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>MITOP: database for mitochondria-related proteins, genes and diseases</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-GarciaBarcelo2"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Barcelo</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sham</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Chinese patients with sporadic Hirschsprung's disease are predominantly represented by a single RET haplotype</article-title>. <source>J MedGenet</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>e122</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-GarciaBarcelo3"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Barcelo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganster</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>TTF-1 and RET promoter SNPs: regulation of RET transcription in Hirschsprung's disease</article-title>. <source>HumMolGenet</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Miao1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ngan</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Reduced RET expression in gut tissue of individuals carrying risk alleles of Hirschsprung's disease</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1461</fpage>–<lpage>1467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Zuker1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Mfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization prediction</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>3406</fpage>–<lpage>3415</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Kenny1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofstra</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buys</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaillant</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Reduced endothelin-3 expression in sporadic Hirschsprung disease</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>580</fpage>–<lpage>585</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Baynash1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baynash</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosoda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giaid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Interaction of endothelin-3 with endothelin-B receptor is essential for development of epidermal melanocytes and enteric neurons</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>1277</fpage>–<lpage>1285</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Lai1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Bilateral iris sector heterochromia with or without Hirschsprung's disease</article-title>. <source>Eye (Lond)</source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>Pt 6</issue>) <fpage>1024</fpage>–<lpage>1027</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Liang1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Juarez</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Bilateral bicolored irides with Hirschsprung's disease. A neural crest syndrome</article-title>. <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0066631-Conrad1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Redon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feuk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gokcumen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Origins and functional impact of copy number variation in the human genome</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>464</volume>: <fpage>704</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>