<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-04811</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019891</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cancer genetics</subject>
              <subject>Genetic screens</subject>
              <subject>Genetics of disease</subject>
              <subject>Genome-wide association studies</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genomics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Comparative genomics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Model organisms</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal models</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Rat</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Obstetrics and gynecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Breast cancer</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Oncology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cancer risk factors</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic causes of cancer</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cancers and neoplasms</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Breast tumors</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Oncology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Physical Confirmation and Mapping of Overlapping Rat Mammary Carcinoma Susceptibility QTLs, <italic>Mcs2</italic> and <italic>Mcs6</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Mapping of Rat <italic>Mcs2</italic> and <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTLs</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sanders</surname>
            <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Haag</surname>
            <given-names>Jill D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Samuelson</surname>
            <given-names>David J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Louisville School of Medicine, Louisville, Kentucky, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>McArdle Laboratory for Cancer Research, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>James Graham Brown Cancer Center, University of Louisville School of Medicine, Louisville, Kentucky, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Center for Genetics and Molecular Medicine, University of Louisville School of Medicine, Louisville, Kentucky, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Center for Environmental Genomics and Integrative Biology, University of Louisville School of Medicine, Louisville, Kentucky, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Toland</surname>
            <given-names>Amanda Ewart</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Ohio State University Medical Center, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">david.samuelson@louisville.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JDH DJS. Performed the experiments: JS JDH. Analyzed the data: JS DJS. Wrote the paper: JS JDH DJS.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e19891</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sanders et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>Only a portion of the estimated heritability of breast cancer susceptibility has been explained by individual loci. Comparative genetic approaches that first use an experimental organism to map susceptibility QTLs are unbiased methods to identify human orthologs to target in human population-based genetic association studies. Here, overlapping rat <italic><underline>m</underline>ammary <underline>c</underline>arcinoma <underline>s</underline>usceptibility</italic> (<italic>Mcs</italic>) predicted QTLs, <italic>Mcs6</italic> and <italic>Mcs2,</italic> were physically confirmed and mapped to identify the human orthologous region. To physically confirm <italic>Mcs6</italic> and <italic>Mcs2,</italic> congenic lines were established using the Wistar-Furth (WF) rat strain, which is susceptible to developing mammary carcinomas, as the recipient (genetic background) and either Wistar-Kyoto (WKy, <italic>Mcs6</italic>) or Copenhagen (COP, <italic>Mcs2</italic>), which are resistant, as donor strains. By comparing Mcs phenotypes of WF.WKy congenic lines with distinct segments of WKy chromosome <italic>7</italic> we physically confirmed and mapped <italic>Mcs6</italic> to ∼33 Mb between markers <italic>D7Rat171</italic> and <italic>gUwm64-3</italic>. The predicted <italic>Mcs2</italic> QTL was also physically confirmed using segments of COP chromosome <italic>7</italic> introgressed into a susceptible WF background. The <italic>Mcs6</italic> and <italic>Mcs2</italic> overlapping genomic regions contain multiple annotated genes, but none have a clear or well established link to breast cancer susceptibility. <italic>Igf1</italic> and <italic>Socs2</italic> are two of multiple potential candidate genes in <italic>Mcs6.</italic> The human genomic region orthologous to rat <italic>Mcs6</italic> is on chromosome <italic>12</italic> from base positions <italic>71,270,266 to 105,502,699</italic>. This region has not shown a genome-wide significant association to breast cancer risk in pun studies of breast cancer susceptibility.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grants CA137052, CA077494, and ES014443. J.S. was supported by the University of Louisville Integrated Programs in Biomedical Sciences. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="6"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Breast cancer susceptibility is a complex trait controlled by genetic, epigenetic, and environmental components. Susceptibility to breast cancer is comprised of low, moderate, and high penetrance risk alleles. Linkage analysis in high incidence families and population-based genetic association studies using cases and controls have identified breast cancer risk alleles; however, a large portion of the estimated heritability in breast cancer susceptibility remains to be explained <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Mavaddat1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Ioannidis1">[2]</xref>. Laboratory rats (<italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>) have been used to identify human breast cancer risk alleles using comparative genetics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Samuelson1">[3]</xref>. To identify loci for comparative studies, rat strains that exhibited phenotypic variation in susceptibility to chemical and hormone induced mammary carcinogenesis have been used to predict <italic><underline>m</underline>ammary <underline>c</underline>arcinoma <underline>s</underline>usceptibility</italic> (<italic>Mcs</italic>) and <italic>estrogen-induced mammary cancer</italic> QTLs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Shull1">[4]</xref>. Rats were chosen to identify <italic>Mcs</italic> QTLs because chemically induced rat mammary carcinomas have similar histopathology to human breast carcinomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Russo1">[5]</xref>. The Wistar Furth (WF) rat strain is susceptible to developing mammary carcinomas, while the Wistar Kyoto (WKy) and Copenhagen (COP) rat strains are resistant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Shepel1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Lan1">[7]</xref>. A QTL linkage analysis of rat Mcs in females from [WF x WKY]<sub>F1</sub> x WF backcrosses predicted four <italic>Mcs</italic> QTLs named <italic>Mcs5, Mcs6, Mcs7,</italic> and <italic>Mcs8</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Lan1">[7]</xref>. The <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL displayed a peak linkage at marker <italic>D7Mit28</italic> and significant linkage was found between markers <italic>D7Mit28</italic> and <italic>D7Rat45.</italic> The predicted <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL region overlapped with <italic>Mcs2,</italic> a <italic>Mcs</italic> QTL predicted using the mammary cancer resistant Copenhagen (COP) rat strain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Shepel1">[6]</xref>. The peak LOD score for the predicted <italic>Mcs2</italic> QTL was at genetic marker <italic>D7Uwm11.</italic> Here, we physically confirm both <italic>Mcs2</italic> and <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTLs, and map <italic>Mcs6</italic> to an approximately 33 Mb region of rat chromosome <italic>7</italic>, which is orthologous to a region on human chromosome <italic>12</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Congenics physically confirm and map <italic>Mcs6</italic> to a 33Mb region on rat chromosome <italic>7</italic></title>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019891-g001">Figure 1</xref> depicts the WF.WKy congenic lines used to physically confirm and map the predicted <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL to a location on rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> between markers <italic>D7Rat171</italic> and <italic>gUwm64-3</italic>. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0019891-t001">Table 1</xref> summarizes mammary carcinoma susceptibility (Mcs) phenotypes from lines shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019891-g001">Figure 1</xref>. Respectively, WF.WKy lines A, B, and F had mammary carcinoma multiplicity phenotypes (mean ± SD carcinomas <italic>per</italic> rat) of 3.5±2.5, 3.9±2.6, and 3.4±2.1. These lines developed significantly less mammary carcinomas compared to susceptible WF control animals, which had a mean ± SD of 7.3±3.6 carcinomas <italic>per</italic> rat (Mann-Whitney test <italic>post hoc</italic> p-values = 0.0012, 0.0007, and 0.0001). Females from WF.WKy lines A, B, and F had similar mammary carcinoma multiplicity phenotypes when compared to each other (Kruskal-Wallis test p-value = 0.8171). WF.WKy line C had a mean ± SD of 8.0±4.1 mammary carcinomas <italic>per</italic> rat, and line E had a mean ± SD of 7.2±3.0. Neither line C nor line E was significantly different from WF control animals (Mann-Whitney test <italic>post hoc</italic> p-values = 0.7521 and 0.7893, respectively). Decreased susceptibility WF.WKy lines A, B, and F overlapped maximally from markers <italic>D7Rat171</italic> to <italic>D7Rat45,</italic> and minimally from <italic>gUwm64-24</italic> to <italic>gUwm64-3.</italic> We conclude that these lines physically confirm <italic>Mcs6</italic> as an independently acting <italic>Mcs</italic> QTL.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019891-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019891.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Congenic lines used to physically confirm <italic>Mcs6</italic> and <italic>Mcs2</italic> QTLs and map the <italic>Mcs6</italic> locus to ∼33 Mb on rat chromosome <italic>7</italic>.</title>
            <p>Informative genetic markers between WF and WKy rat strains used in the genotyping of WF.WKy chromosome <italic>7</italic> lines are shown on the right of the y-axis, which represents the region of rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> that contains <italic>Mcs6</italic>. Congenic lines were established using genetic marker genotype selection and backcrossing to WF homozygous females, which was followed by brother-sister mating to fix homozygous congenic lines in the chromosomal segments shown. Superscript letters indicate which line the respective superscripted line was derived from. WF.WKy chromosome <italic>7</italic> lines A, B, and F (red bars) all showed a statistically significant decrease in mean tumor number compared to WF control females (respective Mann-Whitney <italic>post hoc</italic> p-values were = 0.0012, 0.0007, and 0.0001), while lines C and E (yellow bars) were not significantly different from the susceptible WF phenotype (Mann-Whitney <italic>post hoc</italic> p-values = 0.7521and 0.7893, respectively). The gray bars at the ends of congenic line segments denote regions of unknown genotype. WF.COP chromosome <italic>7 Mcs2</italic> congenic lines A and B that physically confirm the <italic>Mcs2</italic> QTL and overlap the <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL are shown with brown bars that represent the segment of COP chromosome <italic>7</italic> contained in each line. The arrows at the end of <italic>Mcs2</italic> congenic line segments indicate that the COP chromosome <italic>7</italic> segment continues off this map. WF.COP chromosome <italic>7 Mcs2</italic> lines A and B developed significantly less mammary carcinomas than WF control females (Mann-Whitney <italic>post hoc</italic> p-values &lt;0.0001).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019891.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0019891-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019891.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Summary of mammary carcinoma multiplicity phenotypes from WF.WKy and WF.COP rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> congenic lines used to map <italic>Mcs6</italic> and <italic>Mcs2</italic>.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0019891-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019891.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">WF.WKy Congenic Line</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">WF.COP Congenic Line</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WF</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Congenic Region</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">1</xref> <bold><italic>Marker/Marker</italic></bold></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>D7Rat171/D7Rat128</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>D7Rat171/D7Rat128</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>D7Rat51/D7Rat128</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>gUwm64-12/D7Rat128</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>D7Rat171/D7Rat45</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>D7rat39/D7Uwm12</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>D7rat39/D7Uwm12</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Mean (SD) Mammary Carcinomas </bold>
                  <bold>
                    <italic>per</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <bold> Rat</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5 (2.5)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9 (2.6)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0 (4.1)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2 (3.0)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.4 (2.1)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4 (1.6)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0 (1.5)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3 (3.6)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>N</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>p-value</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">2</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0012</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0007</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7521</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7893</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>1</label>
              <p>Markers spanning the maximal WKy or COP Chr <italic>7</italic> segment that was introgressed onto a susceptible WF genetic background are given.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>2</label>
              <p>p-values are from Mann-Whitney nonparametric <italic>post hoc</italic> tests comparing each congenic line to the WF phenotype after a statistically significant Kruskal-Wallis test with a p-value &lt;0.0001.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>WF.WKy line C, which was not significantly different from susceptible WF control animals, overlapped the distal end of the <italic>Mcs6</italic> region demarked by lines A, B, and F from markers <italic>gUwm64-3</italic> to <italic>D7Rat128.</italic> This ruled out that this region contained <italic>Mcs6</italic> or independently acting susceptibility QTLs. The susceptible phenotype of line E, which partially overlapped susceptible line C, confirmed that the region from <italic>gUwm64-12</italic> to <italic>D7Rat128</italic> did not contain an independently acting <italic>Mcs</italic> QTL. When considered together, our results from WF.WKy congenic lines delimited <italic>Mcs6</italic> to a 33 Mb region of rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> from markers <italic>D7Rat171</italic> to <italic>gUwm64-3.</italic></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title><italic>Mcs6</italic> overlaps <italic>Mcs2</italic> a Copenhagen rat QTL associated with mammary cancer susceptibility</title>
        <p><italic>Mcs2</italic> is a Copenhagen (COP) rat <italic>Mcs</italic> QTL that was also predicted to reside on chromosome <italic>7</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Shepel1">[6]</xref>. The original QTL scans of <italic>Mcs2</italic> (COP) and <italic>Mcs6</italic> (WKy) predicted regions of significant linkage on rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> that overlapped from markers <italic>D7Mgh15</italic> to <italic>D7Mgh10</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Lan1">[7]</xref>. We physically confirmed <italic>Mcs2</italic> using WF.COP congenic lines A and B that each contained a COP segment of rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> from markers <italic>D7rat39</italic> to <italic>D7Uwm12</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019891-g001">Figure 1</xref>). These markers corresponded to rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> base positions 4,936,704-86,028,057. WF.COP lines A and B had similar mammary carcinoma multiplicity phenotypes of 2.4±1.6 and 2.0±1.5 mean ± SD carcinomas <italic>per</italic> rat (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0019891-t001">Table 1</xref>, Mann-Whitney test p-value 0.4510). Both lines were significantly less than the WF susceptible phenotype (Mann-Whitney <italic>post hoc</italic> test p-values &lt;0.0001). The confirmed <italic>Mcs2</italic> QTL overlapped the delimited <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL between markers <italic>D7Rat171</italic> and <italic>gUwm64-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019891-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The pooled phenotypes of <italic>Mcs2</italic> (WF.COP lines A and B) and <italic>Mcs6</italic> (WF.WKy lines A, B, and F) females were, respectively, 2.2±1.5 and 3.6±2.4 mean ± SD mammary carcinomas <italic>per</italic> rat. These phenotypic values were statistically different (Mann-Whitney test p-value = 0.0030) suggesting that the <italic>Mcs2</italic> COP allele may have additional genetic variation contributing to mammary carcinoma resistance.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>The human ortholog to rat <italic>Mcs6</italic> is on chromosome <italic>12</italic></title>
        <p>Using the UCSC rat and human genome browsers (genome.ucsc.edu) we determined that the <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL from markers <italic>D7Rat171</italic> to <italic>gUwm64-3</italic> (chr<italic>7</italic>:22,382,725-55,364,398) aligns to a contiguous 34.2 Mb region of human chromosome <italic>12</italic> from base positions 71,299,117 to 105,502,699, which was inverted with respect to the rat genome assembly. Within these orthologous regions 37.7% of the bases over 99.9% of the span were identical. Rat genomic sequence flanking <italic>Mcs6</italic> aligned to human chromosome <italic>12</italic> up to rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> base positions 22,310,240 on one flank and <italic>55</italic>,442,351 on the other flank. Moving out past these syntenic regions of rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> and human chromosome <italic>12</italic> resulted in rat genomic sequence that aligned to human chromosome <italic>16</italic> on one flank and chromosome <italic>X</italic> on the other.</p>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019891-g002">Figure 2</xref> shows annotated genes in the <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL between markers <italic>D7Rat171</italic> and <italic>gUwm64-3.</italic> These genes were on the UCSC rat November 2004 assembly (build 3.4/rn4). Not including pseudogenes, this region contained 111 annotated genes including two microRNAs (<italic>Mir135</italic> and <italic>Mir331</italic>). There were 137 annotated genes found in <italic>Mcs6</italic> using the Rat Genome Database (rgd.mcw.edu), and 215 found using the Ensembl Genome Browser (uswest.ensembl.org) rat database. Independent searches of <italic>Mcs6</italic> potential candidate genes using gene ontology terms limited to mammary, hormone, estradiol, or DNA repair resulted in the following gene list: <italic>Socs2, Igf1, Nr1h4, Osbpl8, Nr2c1, Pmch, Stab2, Nts, Lgr5, Btg1, Lta4h,</italic> and <italic>Ube2n.</italic> All genes located in rat <italic>Mcs6</italic> were also annotated in the human orthologous region. There were a total of 243 genes listed in the human orthologous region when the UCSC human genome browser was queried and 226 genes when the Ensembl browser was used.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019891-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019891.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Transcript map of the delimited rat <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL.</title>
            <p>Map of the <italic>Mcs6</italic> locus showing known and predicted transcripts in the <italic>Mcs6</italic> region that were annotated on the UCSC Rat Nov. 2004 (Baylor3.4/rn4) Genome Browser. The x-axis represents rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> from genetic markers <italic>D7Rat171</italic> to <italic>gUwm64-3;</italic> a rat chromosome <italic>7</italic> region from bp 22,382,725-55,364,398 that contains <italic>Mcs6.</italic> The dashed vertical lines demark the respective maximal and minimal rat genomic regions that contain <italic>Mcs6.</italic> Transcripts are shown by NCBI gene symbol at approximate genomic positions within <italic>Mcs6</italic>. Genetic markers within the region are shown as labeled tick marks on the x-axis. WF.WKy chromosome <italic>7</italic> lines F (red horizontal bar, resistant Mcs phenotype) and C (yellow horizontal bar, susceptible Mcs phenotype) are included to serve as reference points. The gray horizontal bars at the ends of congenic lines denote a segment of unknown genotype for the respective line.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019891.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We queried the Oncomine 4.4 database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oncomine.org" xlink:type="simple">www.oncomine.org</ext-link>, Compendia Bioscience) to identify <italic>Mcs6</italic> human orthologs that may have been reported as differentially expressed between non-diseased breast tissue and ductal breast carcinomas. A list of the studies included can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019891.s003">References S1</xref> (S1-S7). Results from this search are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019891.s001">Table S1</xref>. There were twenty-nine transcripts reported with p-values &lt;0.05, and six of these had p-values &lt;0.001 <italic>Mcs6</italic> human orthologs with p-values &lt;0.001 were <italic>ALX1, DUSP6, EPYC, PPP1R12A, TXNRD1,</italic> and <italic>ZDHHC17.</italic></p>
        <p>To determine if genetic variation in the <italic>Mcs6</italic> orthologous human genomic region from chromosome <italic>12:71,270,266-105,502,699</italic> might be associated with breast cancer susceptibility we searched the NCBI dbGAP database using the association results browser set to “breast neoplasms” and chromosome 12 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap" xlink:type="simple">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap</ext-link>). We also searched published breast cancer risk GWA studies for positive associations in this region. A list of the association studies included can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019891.s003">References S1</xref> (S8-S23). While five human SNPs were identified that potentially associated with breast cancer susceptibility, tested genetic variants did not reach a genome-wide significance level of P&lt; 10<sup>-7</sup> proposed by Thomas <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Thomas1">[8]</xref>. A summary of human SNPs in the <italic>Mcs6</italic> orthologous region that potentially associate with breast cancer risk can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019891.s002">Table S2</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Both mammary cancer susceptibility QTL mapping in rats and low-penetrance breast cancer risk associated allele identification in humans are in early stages of discovery. Results of human population-based and rat genetic studies completed to date indicate that a majority of breast cancer risk alleles are low-penetrance, and pathways in addition to DNA repair and hormonal regulation control susceptibility. Furthermore, a majority of the risk associated polymorphisms that have been identified reside in non-protein coding DNA. Given the commonalities of low-penetrance, novel pathways, and non-protein-coding risk alleles, it is possible that there is some degree of overlap in susceptibility loci between these two organisms. There may be shared susceptibility loci that can be more easily identified in rats than by current human GWAS methods. If this is the case, resolving rat mammary carcinoma susceptibility QTLs to single loci so that the human orthologs can be extensively tested in human population-based genome-targeted association studies may continue to be fruitful. This was the case for Gould and colleagues who used rat <italic>Mcs5a</italic> to successfully target the orthologous human genomic region to identify two breast cancer susceptibility alleles on human chromosome <italic>9</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Samuelson1">[3]</xref>. Quan <italic>et al.</italic> have shown that rodent susceptibility QTLs identified for a specific tumor type may also be useful to identify common susceptibility alleles for other tumor types <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Quan1">[9]</xref>. Thus, the amount of overlap between rodent and human common disease susceptibility loci may be appreciable.</p>
      <p>Here, predicted rat mammary carcinoma susceptibility QTLs <italic>Mcs6</italic> and <italic>Mcs2</italic> were physically confirmed using congenics. In our study <italic>Mcs2</italic> and <italic>Mcs6</italic>, respectively, reduced the mammary carcinoma susceptibility phenotype of the WF strain by 70 and 50% when homozygous. In the original QTL studies, one <italic>Mcs2</italic> COP or one <italic>Mcs6</italic> WKy allele was predicted to reduce tumor multiplicity by 43% or 40%, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Shepel1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Lan1">[7]</xref>. While those studies were not completed using congenics, and we have not tested heterozygous females, comparing the results of tumor numbers of homozygous <italic>Mcs2</italic> and <italic>Mcs6</italic> congenics with heterozygous females from the previous studies suggests there may be some degree of dominance from the WF allele at this locus. However, these differences may also be explained by background COP and WKy alleles that would have been present in females used for the QTL linkage studies. The stronger effect of the <italic>Mcs2</italic> COP allele compared to the <italic>Mcs6</italic> WKy allele may indicate that the Copenhagen strain has additional genetic variation within the region that contributes to reducing the Mcs phenotype.</p>
      <p>In this study <italic>Mcs6</italic> was mapped to a 33 Mb region from markers <italic>D7Rat171</italic> to <italic>gUwm64-3</italic>, which corresponds to rat chromosome 7 base positions 22,382,725-55,364,398. The peak LOD scores for genetic markers in the predicted <italic>Mcs6</italic> and <italic>Mcs2</italic> QTLs were at <italic>D7Mit28</italic> and <italic>D7Uwm11</italic>, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Shepel1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Lan1">[7]</xref>. Both peak QTL markers fall within the narrowed interval confirmed here with congenics. <italic>D7Mit28</italic> is at base position Chr<italic>7:</italic>29,204,226, and <italic>D7Uwm11</italic> is at base position Chr<italic>7:</italic>50,160,469. This supports using QTL linkage analysis of rat complex phenotypes to identify regions of the genome on which to focus targeted human genome association studies.</p>
      <p>Alignment of the rat <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL region to the human genome reference sequence revealed that the human orthologous region is entirely positioned on 34.2 Mb of chromosome <italic>12,</italic> and is inverted compared to rat <italic>Mcs6</italic>. To our knowledge no polymorphisms in the human genome region orthologous to rat <italic>Mcs6</italic> have shown a genome-wide significant association to breast cancer risk in a GWAS. An intriguing potential candidate gene in <italic>Mcs6</italic> is <italic>insulin-like growth factor 1</italic> (<italic>Igf1</italic>). Human candidate-gene association studies that have tested <italic>IGF1</italic> locus polymorphisms reported mixed results ranging from significant low-penetrance to null associations between <italic>IGF1</italic> alleles and breast cancer risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-AlZahrani1">[10]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Gu1">[15]</xref>. Increased IGF1 levels have been associated with breast cancer and increased breast cancer susceptibility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Peyrat1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Endogenous1">[17]</xref>. Common genetic variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> has been associated with circulating levels of IGF1 in a population-based study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Gu1">[15]</xref>. Other <italic>Mcs6</italic> potential candidates have human orthologs that have been associated with cancer or other human diseases. <italic>SLC5A8</italic> and <italic>GLIPR1</italic> are predicted tumor repressor genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Li1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Thompson1">[19]</xref>. <italic>METAP2</italic> is predicted to be anti-angiogenic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Datta1">[20]</xref>. A human genome-wide linkage analysis of posterior amorphous corneal dystrophy identified a region of human chromosome <italic>12</italic> that is orthologous to a <italic>Mcs6</italic> region that contains genes <italic>DCN, LUM, KERA</italic>, and <italic>EPYC</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Aldave1">[21]</xref>. <italic>PCTK2</italic> has been shown to be upregulated in sporadic breast cancer biopsies in women of Mexican ancestry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Valladares1">[22]</xref>. <italic>Suppressor of cytokine signaling 2</italic> (<italic>Socs2</italic>) is also a promising potential candidate gene in <italic>Mcs6.</italic> Higher SOCS2 levels have been associated with better breast cancer prognosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Farabegoli1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Sasi1">[25]</xref>. <italic>Socs2</italic> is an important mediator of prolactin regulated mammary gland development in the mouse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Harris1">[26]</xref>. <italic>SOCS2</italic> is upregulated by 17β-estradiol in cancer cell lines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Leung1">[27]</xref>, and <italic>SOCS2</italic> expression was found to be higher in breast carcinomas compared to non-diseased breast tissue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Raccurt1">[28]</xref>.</p>
      <p><italic>Mcs6</italic> human orthologous transcripts that have been reported as differentially expressed between non-diseased breast tissue and ductal carcinoma tissue encode for two phosphatases (DUSP6, PPP1R12A), a proteoglycan (EPYC), a redox regulator (TXNRD1), and two uncharacterized proteins (ALX1, ZDHHC17). These findings suggest that the rat <italic>Mcs2</italic> and <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTLs control potentially novel mechanisms contributing to mammary cancer susceptibility that could translate to breast cancer.</p>
      <p>Human genetic variation in the <italic>Mcs6</italic> orthologous genomic region has been reported to be associated with breast cancer susceptibility, but tested polymorphisms have not reached genome-wide level significance. This highlights the importance of this region to breast cancer genetics. It suggests, as many have, that Bonferroni correction based methods may be too stringent to control for multiple comparison testing in human population-based association studies. The confirmed rat <italic>Mcs2</italic> and <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTLs support that some or all of the potential human breast cancer risk associations are true positives and warrant further investigation.</p>
      <p>We conclude that the human genomic region on chromosome <italic>12</italic> from base positions <italic>71,270,266 - 105,502,699</italic> is orthologous to rat <italic>Mcs6</italic>. This region may be a good target for extensive population-based genetic association studies to determine if humans have a concordant breast cancer susceptibility allele. Rat <italic>Mcs6</italic> and <italic>Mcs2</italic> congenic lines will be useful to study breast cancer genetic susceptibility mechanisms.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Congenic Breeding and Genotyping</title>
        <p>Congenic lines were established using previously described methods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Samuelson2">[29]</xref> and are defined as rats with specified WKy chromosome <italic>7</italic> segments from the predicted <italic>Mcs6</italic> QTL or the specified COP chromosome <italic>7</italic> segments from the predicted <italic>Mcs2</italic> QTL introgressed into a WF genetic background. Rats were housed in an AALACC approved facility and protocols were approved by a University of Louisville institutional animal care and use committee under protocol number 07118. Genotyping was performed at the markers shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019891-g001">Figure 1</xref> according to methods previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Samuelson2">[29]</xref>. Primer and sequence information for most genetic markers used is available at the Rat Genome Database (rgd.mcw.edu) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Twigger1">[30]</xref>. The following primer sequence pairs are for genetic markers that were submitted to the NCBI probe database, but may not yet be publicly available: <italic>gUwm64-24,</italic> <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-TGTCCTCTCATACCACTTCC-3′</named-content>, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CGGTGGTCATACTCTGAAT-3′</named-content>; <italic>gUwm64-3</italic>, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-AACAGTTCTCCTTTCCCTTC-3′</named-content>, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-TCTCTTTGCCAGTCTGTTTT-3′</named-content>, <italic>gUwm64-12,</italic> <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CTGGTCATTCAACAGGAAAT-3′</named-content>, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CCTATCCCTGTTCTTCCTCT-3′</named-content>; and <italic>gUwm64-19,</italic> <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-AACAATAGGCACAGTGAT-3′</named-content>, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-ATGCTGTCAGAACGGTAAGT-3′</named-content>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Phenotyping</title>
        <p>Female congenic and WF (Harlan) rats at 50-55 days of age were treated with a single dose of 7,12-Dimethylbenz(a)anthracene (DMBA, ACROS Organics, Fisher Scientific) in sesame oil by gastric intubation at 65 mg DMBA/kg body mass. Mammary carcinomas ≥3×3 mm<sup>2</sup> were counted at 15 weeks following DMBA treatment. Mammary carcinoma multiplicity data were analyzed to compare congenic line phenotypes to susceptible WF control females. WF.WKy chromosome <italic>7</italic> congenic phenotypes for each line were from the following generations: line A, N11F2 and N11F4 (total n = 17); line B, N11F2 and N11F3 (total n = 32); line C, N14F2, N14F3, and N14F4 (total n = 23); line E, N14F2 and N14F4 (total n = 43); and line F, N14F3 and N14F4 (total n = 28). WF.COP chromosome <italic>7</italic> congenic phenotypes were from generations: line A, N10F5 (n = 16); and line B, N11F3 and N11F4 (total n = 16).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>To compare mammary carcinoma susceptibility phenotypes, mammary carcinoma multiplicity data were analyzed using Statview (SAS Institute). Mammary carcinoma multiplicity phenotypes for more than two groups were compared using the Kruskal-Wallis nonparametric test. If this test was statistically significant (p value &lt;0.05) multiple Mann-Whitney nonparametric tests were performed by comparing each congenic line phenotype to the susceptible WF control group. To correct for multiple comparisons a p-value ≤0.007 (α = 0.05/7 comparisons) was required for statistical significance. For analysis of two groups, Mann-Whitney nonparametric tests were performed and p-values ≤0.05 were required for statistical significance.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Bioinformatics</title>
        <p>Identification of the human orthologous region and transcripts mapping to human and rat regions of interest were performed using the RGD, UCSC, and Ensembl genome browsers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Twigger1">[30]</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019891-Flicek1">[32]</xref>. The genome assemblies used were <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> version GRCh37/hg19 and <italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic> version 3.4/rn4. The percent sequence identity between human and rat was determined using the “Convert” option at the UCSC Genome Browser. The gene ontology search was completed by downloading from the Rat Genome Database gene ontology terms for genes annotated in <italic>Mcs6</italic> and searching this database by terms: “mammary”, “hormone”, “estradiol”, or “DNA repair”.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0019891.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019891.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Results of a query using Oncomine to identify human <italic>Mcs6</italic> orthologous transcripts that have been shown to be differentially expressed between non-diseased and ductal carcinoma breast tissues.</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0019891.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019891.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Human polymorphisms located in the <italic>Mcs6</italic> orthologous region that have not reached genome-wide significance, but are potentially associated with breast cancer susceptibility.</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0019891.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019891.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>References S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Citations for supplemental references.</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors thank Aaron Puckett, Cordes Cooper, and Paula Ginter for their assistance with phenotyping and genotyping animals used in this study.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Mavaddat1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mavaddat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniou</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AC</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Easton</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DF</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Closas</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M</surname></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Genetic susceptibility to breast cancer.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Oncology</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>174</fpage>             <lpage>191</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Ioannidis1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>JPA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castaldi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evangelou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>A Compendium of Genome-Wide Associations for Cancer: Critical Synopsis and Reappraisal.</article-title>             <source>Journal of the National Cancer Institute</source>             <volume>102</volume>             <fpage>846</fpage>             <lpage>858</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Samuelson1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuelson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hesselson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aperavich</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Rat <italic>Mcs5a</italic> is a compound quantitative trait locus with orthologous human loci that associate with breast cancer risk.</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>6299</fpage>             <lpage>6304</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Shull1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shull</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The Rat Oncogenome: Comparative Genetics and Genomics of Rat Models of Mammary Carcinogenesis.</article-title>             <source>Breast Disease</source>             <volume>28</volume>             <fpage>69</fpage>             <lpage>86</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Russo1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Atlas and Histologic Classification of Tumors of the Rat Mammary Gland.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Mammary Gland Biology and Neoplasia</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>187</fpage>             <lpage>200</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Shepel1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shepel</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brasic</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gheen</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Genetic Identification of Multiple Loci That Control Breast Cancer Susceptibility in the Rat.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>149</volume>             <fpage>289</fpage>             <lpage>299</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Lan1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendziorski</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shepel</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newton MA et</surname><given-names>al</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Genetic Loci Controlling Breast Cancer Susceptibility in the Wistar-Kyoto Rat.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>157</volume>             <fpage>331</fpage>             <lpage>339</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Thomas1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haile</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duggan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Recent developments in genomewide association scans: a workshop summary and review.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>77</volume>             <fpage>337</fpage>             <lpage>345</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Quan1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stassen</surname><given-names>APM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruivenkamp</surname><given-names>CAL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Wezel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fijneman</surname><given-names>RJA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Most Lung and Colon Cancer Susceptibility Genes Are Pair-Wise Linked in Mice, Humans and Rats.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <issue>2</issue>             <fpage>e14727</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0014727" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0014727</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-AlZahrani1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Zahrani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandhu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luben</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baynes C et</surname><given-names>al</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>IGF1 and IGFBP3 tagging polymorphisms are associated with circulating levels of IGF1, IGFBP3 and risk of breast cancer.</article-title>             <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>10</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Canzian1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Canzian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dossus</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biessy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Polymorphisms of genes coding for insulin-like growth factor 1 and its major binding proteins, circulating levels of IGF-I and IGFBP-3 and breast cancer risk: results from the EPIC study.</article-title>             <source>Br J Cancer</source>             <volume>94</volume>             <issue>2</issue>             <fpage>299</fpage>             <lpage>307</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Cleveland1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gammon</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edmiston</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teitelbaum</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>IGF1 CA repeat polymorphisms, lifestyle factors and breast cancer risk in the Long Island Breast Cancer Study Project.</article-title>             <source>Carcinogenesis</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <issue>4</issue>             <fpage>758</fpage>             <lpage>65</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Patel1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canzian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Marchand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thun</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Breast and Prostate Cancer Cohort Consortium. IGF-1, IGFBP-1, and IGFBP-3 polymorphisms predict circulating IGF levels but not breast cancer risk: findings from the Breast and Prostate Cancer Cohort Consortium (BPC3).</article-title>             <source>PLoS One</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <issue>7</issue>             <fpage>e2578</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Neuhausen1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuhausen</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brummel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfeiler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Genetic variation in insulin-like growth factor signaling genes and breast cancer risk among BRCA1 and BRCA2 carriers.</article-title>             <source>Breast Cancer Res</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <issue>5</issue>             <fpage>R76</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Gu1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canzian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albanes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Eighteen Insulin-like Growth Factor Pathway Genes, Circulating Levels of IGF-I and Its Binding Protein, and Risk of Prostate and Breast Cancer.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Epidemiology Biomarkers &amp; Prevention</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>2877</fpage>             <lpage>2887</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Peyrat1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peyrat</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonneterre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vennin</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jammes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beuscart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Insulin-like growth factor 1 receptors (IGF1-R) and IGF1 in human breast tumors. </article-title>             <source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <issue>6</issue>             <fpage>823</fpage>             <lpage>7</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Endogenous1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">Endogenous Hormones and Breast Cancer Collaborative Group, Key TJ, Appleby PN, Reeves GK, Roddam AW</collab>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF1), IGF binding protein 3 (IGFBP3), and breast cancer risk: pooled individual data analysis of 17 prospective studies.</article-title>             <source>Lancet Oncol</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>530</fpage>             <lpage>542</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Li1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myeroff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smiraglia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretlow</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title><italic>SLC5A8,</italic> a sodium transporter, is a tumor suppressor gene silenced by methylation in human colon aberrant crypt foci and cancers.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>100</volume>             <fpage>8412</fpage>             <lpage>8417</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Thompson1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Glioma Pathogenesis-Related Protein 1: Tumor-Suppressor Activities and Therapeutic Potential.</article-title>             <source>Yonsei Med J</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>479</fpage>             <lpage>483</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Datta1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Roles of P67/MetAP2 as a tumor suppressor.</article-title>             <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - Reviews on Cancer</source>             <volume>1796</volume>             <fpage>281</fpage>             <lpage>292</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Aldave1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldave</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenwasser</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yellore</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobel</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Linkage of Posterior Amorphous Corneal Dystrophy to Chromosome 12q21.33 and Exclusion of Coding Region Mutations in KERA, LUM, DCN, and EPYC.</article-title>             <source>Investigative Ophthalmology and Visual Science</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>4006</fpage>             <lpage>4012</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Valladares1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valladares</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernández</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curiel-Quezada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madrigal-Bujaidar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Genetic expression profiles and chromosomal alterations in sporadic breast cancer in Mexican women.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Genetics and Cytogenetics</source>             <volume>170</volume>             <fpage>147</fpage>             <lpage>151</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Farabegoli1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farabegoli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceccarelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taffurelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Suppressor of cytokine signalling 2 (SOCS-2) expression in breast carcinoma.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Pathol</source>             <volume>58</volume>             <fpage>1046</fpage>             <lpage>1050</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Haffner1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haffner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petridou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peyrat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Revillion</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller-Holzner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Favorable prognostic value of SOCS2 and IGF-I in breast cancer.</article-title>             <source>BMC Cancer</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>136</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Sasi1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mokbel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Higher expression levels of SOCS 1,3,4,7 are associated with earlier tumour stage and better clinical outcome in human breast cancer.</article-title>             <source>BMC</source>             <volume>Cancer.10</volume>             <fpage>178</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Harris1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanford</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakes</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Socs2 and elf5 mediate prolactin-induced mammary gland development.</article-title>             <source>Mol Endocrinol</source>             <volume>20</volume>             <fpage>1177</fpage>             <lpage>1187</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Leung1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballesteros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjogren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Estrogen inhibits GH signaling by suppressing GH-induced JAK2 phosphorylation, an effect mediated by SOCS-2.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source>             <volume>100</volume>             <fpage>1016</fpage>             <lpage>1021</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Raccurt1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raccurt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mertani</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Suppressor of cytokine signalling gene expression is elevated in breast carcinoma.</article-title>             <source>Br J Cancer</source>             <volume>89</volume>             <fpage>524</fpage>             <lpage>532</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Samuelson2">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuelson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shultz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Physical evidence of <italic>Mcs5</italic>, a QTL controlling mammary carcinoma susceptibility, in congenic rats.</article-title>             <source>Carcinogenesis</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>1455</fpage>             <lpage>1460</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Twigger1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Twigger</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimoyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bromberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwitek</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <collab xlink:type="simple">RGD Team</collab>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The Rat Genome Database, update 2007 – easing the path from disease to data and back again.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>D658</fpage>             <lpage>D662</lpage>             <comment>The Rat Genome Database is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rgd.mcw.edu" xlink:type="simple">http://rgd.mcw.edu</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Kent1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugnet</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furey</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roskin</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <source>Genome Res</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>996</fpage>             <lpage>1006</lpage>             <comment>The human genome browser at UCSC</comment>             <comment>UCSC Genome Browser is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu" xlink:type="simple">http://genome.ucsc.edu</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019891-Flicek1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flicek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amode</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Ensembl 2011</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>D800</fpage>             <lpage>D806</lpage>             <comment>The Ensembl Genome Browser is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ensembl.org" xlink:type="simple">http://ensembl.org</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>