<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-02451</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Signal transduction</subject><subj-group><subject>Signaling cascades</subject><subj-group><subject>Akt signaling cascade</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Signaling in cellular processes</subject><subj-group><subject>STAT signaling family</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cell death</subject><subject>Cell growth</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics</subject><subj-group><subject>Biostatistics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Basic cancer research</subject><subj-group><subject>Metastasis</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cancer treatment</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemotherapy and drug treatment</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cancers and neoplasms</subject><subj-group><subject>Genitourinary tract tumors</subject><subj-group><subject>Renal cell carcinoma</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Urology</subject><subj-group><subject>Renal cancer</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Simvastatin Inhibits Renal Cancer Cell Growth and Metastasis via AKT/mTOR, ERK and JAK2/STAT3 Pathway</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Anti-Cancer Effects of Simvastatin in Renal Cancer</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Zhiqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Yueqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Juanjuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Zunlin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Zhaoquan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Zhaoxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Xiaoyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Weichang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Zhonghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Zhaoxu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Urology, Qilu Hospital of Shandong University, Ji'nan, Shandong, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>The Key Laboratory of Cardiovascular Remodeling and Function Research, Chinese Ministry of Education and Chinese Ministry of Public Health, Qilu Hospital of Shandong University, Ji'nan, Shandong, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Anesthesiology, Wucheng People's Hospital, Wucheng, Shandong, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>School of Nursing, Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Zhongjun</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">zhaoxvl@sdu.edu.cn</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: ZF YT ZZ Z. Xu ZL. Performed the experiments: ZF Z. Xing ZG XG. Analyzed the data: ZF YT. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: WW JF WJ. Wrote the paper: ZF ZL.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e62823</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Fang et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Renal cell carcinoma (RCC) is the most lethal type of genitourinary cancer due to its occult onset and resistance to chemotherapy and radiation. Recently, accumulating evidence has suggested stains, inhibitors of 3-hydroxy-3-methyl glutaryl coenzyme A (HMG-CoA) reductase, were associated with the risk reduction of cancer. In the present study, we aimed to investigate the potential effects of simvastatin on RCC cells and the underlying mechanisms by which simvastatin exerted its actions. With cell viability, colony formation, and flow cytometric apoptosis assays, we found that simvastatin potently suppressed cell growth of A498 and 786-O cells in a time- and dose- dependent manner. Consistently, the xenograft model performed in nude mice exhibited reduced tumor growth with simvastatin treatment. In addition, the inhibitory effects of simvastatin on migration and invasion were also observed in <italic>vitro</italic>. Mechanically, we presented that simvastatin could suppress the proliferation and motility of RCC cells via inhibiting the phosphorylation of AKT, mTOR, and ERK in a time- and dose- dependent manner. Further investigation of the underlying mechanism revealed simvastatin could exert the anti-tumor effects by suppressing IL-6-induced phosphorylation of JAK2 and STAT3. In conclusion, these findings suggested that simvastatin-induced apoptosis and its anti-metastasis activity in RCC cells were accompanied by inhibition of AKT/mTOR, ERK, and JAK2/STAT3 pathways, which imply that simvastatin may be a potential therapeutic agent for the treatment of RCC patients.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81172435). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Renal cell carcinoma (RCC) is the most common type of renal cancer, accounting for approximately 90–95% kidney neoplasms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Bex1">[1]</xref>. Worldwide, mortality due to RCC has exceeded 100,000 patients each year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Basso1">[2]</xref>. About 25–30% of patients develop metastases at diagnosis of RCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Lam1">[3]</xref>, with survival ≥5 years ranging from 5% to 10%, and overall median survival of less than one year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Linehan1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Motzer1">[5]</xref>. Surgical intervention is the primary treatment for localized RCC, but alone it has limited benefit in patients with aggressive disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Bex1">[1]</xref>. In addition, traditional cytotoxic chemotherapy and immunotherapy have failed to demonstrate a benefit in patients in the adjuvant setting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Thillai1">[6]</xref>. Recent years have seen a rapid development of molecular targeted therapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Herrmann1">[7]</xref>. Amongst the first-line targeted therapies, sunitinib and temsirolimus are the most representative, which can block the signaling pathway of multiple receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs) and mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Escudier1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Miyake1">[9]</xref>. Nevertheless, none of the interventions would be considered cost-effective at a willingness-to-pay threshold of 30,000 pounds per quality-adjusted life-year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-ThompsonCoon1">[10]</xref>. Thus, there is a great demand for treatments that can prolong survival without greatly increasing costs or eroding the quality of patients' lives.</p>
<p>Statins (or 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl coenzyme A [HMG-CoA] reductase inhibitors) are a group of drugs, which are structural analogues of HMG-CoA that inhibit conversion of HMG-CoA to mevalonate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Thurnher1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Takahashi1">[12]</xref>. Beyond their cholesterol-reducing properties, statins exhibit numerous pleiotropic effects, including anti-inflammation and immunomodulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Schonbeck1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Blum1">[14]</xref>, reduction in the risk for various forms of dementia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Jick1">[15]</xref>, and a decrease in proteinuria and the progression of kidney disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Campese1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Fried1">[17]</xref>. Of significance, emerging evidence revealed that statins could exhibit antineoplastic effects in a variety of cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Sassano1">[18]</xref>, including prostate cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Goc1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Sekine1">[22]</xref>, breast cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Sanchez1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Kotamraju1">[25]</xref>, hepatic cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Relja1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Jiang1">[27]</xref> and colon cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Savas1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Cho1">[29]</xref>. Encouragingly, a retrospective nested case-control study that involved 500,000 veterans reported a protective role of statins against the development of RCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Khurana1">[30]</xref>. However, the precise effect of simvastatin against RCC cells and the underlying molecular mechanisms have not been well established.</p>
<p>In the present work, our data establish the growth inhibitory and pro-apoptotic effects of simvastatin on RCC cells both in <italic>vitro</italic> and in <italic>vivo</italic>. Meanwhile, we also find that simvastatin can potently decrease the migration and invasion of RCC cells. Further investigation of the underlying mechanisms indicates AKT/mTOR, ERK and JAK2/SAT3 pathways play key roles in these actions. Our findings suggest the clinical implications of simvastatin in the treatment of RCC patients.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p>The animal experimental protocol complied with the Animal Management Rules of the Chinese Ministry of Health (Document No. 55, 2001) and was approved by Animal Care and Use Committee of Shandong University. Pathogen-free BALB/c nude mice (weighing 19±2 g, SPF grade, certificate SCXK2011-0012) of 4–5 week old were purchased from Department of Laboratory Animal Science of Peking University (Beijing, China). All animals were maintained at the key Laboratory of Cardiovascular Remodeling and Function Research in Qilu Hospital of Shandong University.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Cell lines and reagents</title>
<p>Human A498 and 786-O cell lines were obtained from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) and cultured in DMEM high Glucose medium (HyClone) with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) under the conditions of 5% CO2 at 37°C. Simvastatin (sodium salt, C25H39O6·Na) was purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA), which was activated according to the manufacturer' instructions. Human IL-6 was purchased from R&amp;D Systems (Minneapolis, MN, USA). Antibodies against phospho-mTOR, mTOR, phospho-AKT(Ser473), AKT, phospho-JAK2, JAK2, phospho- STAT3 (Tyr705 and Ser727), STAT3, PARP, GAPDH, and HRP-conjugated goat anti-rabbit and anti-mouse IgG were obtained from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA, USA). Antibodies against casepas-3, bax, bcl-2 and survivin were obtained from Immuno-way (Newark, DE, USA). Antibodies against phospho-ERK, ERK were obtained from Anbo (San Francisco, CA, USA).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Cell viability assay</title>
<p>Cell viability was determined by 3-(4, 5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2, 5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay. Briefly, A498 (2×10<sup>3</sup> cells/well) and 786-O (1×10<sup>3</sup> cells/well) in 100 µl medium were seeded in 96 well plates. After 12 hours, the medium in each well was replaced with the medium containing different concentrations of simvastatin and the plate was incubated for 48, 72 and 96 hours. Subsequently, 20 µl of MTT (5 mg/ml) was added into each well. After incubation at 37°C for 4 h, the supernatant was removed and 200 µl of DMSO was added to each well. After the precipitation was fully dissolved, the absorbance values were determined with the Microplate Reader (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Effect of simvastatin on cell morphology</title>
<p>When A498 and 786-O cells reached 70% of confluence, the cells were washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and then exposed to 16 µM simvastatin for 48 hours. The morphology of treated cells was observed under microscope and photomicrographs were taken with Olympus digital camera.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Clone formation assay</title>
<p>A498 and 786-O cells were seeded at density of 1×10<sup>3</sup> cells/well in 6-well plates. After incubation overnight, each well was added of simvastatin (8 and 16 µM) and incubated for 24 hours. Then the medium was replaced with complete medium without simvastatin and incubated under the conditions of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and 37°C for two weeks. When visible clones formed on the plates, the incubation was terminated. The clones were washed with PBS and then fixed with methanol and stained with 0.1% crystal violet for 30 min. The colony containing more than 50 cells was counted under a microscope.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title><italic>In vitro</italic> scratch assay</title>
<p><italic>In vitro</italic> scratch assay was performed as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Yan1">[31]</xref>. A498 and 786-O cells were seeded in 24-well plates. After incubation for 24 hours, each well was manually scratched with a 200 µl pipette tip, washed with PBS three times and incubated at 37°C with simvastatin (8 and 16 µM). The scratch area was photographed 18 hours later. The distance between two cell edges were analyzed by ImageJ software.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Invasion and migration assay</title>
<p>The transwell system (24 wells, 8 µm pore size with poly-carbonate membrane; Corning Costar, Lowell, MA, USA) coated with 2 mg/ml Matrigel (BD Biosciences) was used for the in <italic>vitro</italic> invasion assays. A total of 5×10<sup>5</sup> cells were suspended in 100 µl serum-free medium and were added to the upper chambers. DMEM containing 20% FBS and simvastatin (8 and 16 µM) was then added to the lower chamber. After 24 hours, cells remaining on the upper chambers were removed with a cotton swab whereas the cells attaching to the lower surface were fixed with methanol and stained with 0.1% crystal violet. The number of cells migrated to the lower side was counted in five randomly fields under a light microscope. The cell number was counted and analyzed statistically.</p>
<p>For migration assay, the cells were seeded in upper chambers without coated Matrigel. The rest of assay was performed as the invasion assay. After 18 hours, the cells on lower surface were also counted in five randomly fields, then the cell number was analyzed statistically.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2h">
<title>Apoptosis assay</title>
<p>This assay was performed to detect cell apoptosis with an Annexin V-FITC Apoptosis Detection Kit (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA). In brief, harvested cells were resuspended in 100 µl of the binding buffer to achieve a concentration of 1×10<sup>6</sup>/mL. Then, 5 µl Annexin V-FITC and 5 µl propidium iodide (PI, 20 µg/mL) were added and the tubes were incubated for 15 min at room temperature in dark. Finally, binding buffer (400 µl) was added to each reaction tube and the cells were analyzed by flow cytometry. The data was analyzed by WinMDI V2.9 software (The Scripps Research Institute, San Diego, CA, USA).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2i">
<title>RNA interference and transient transfection</title>
<p>Small interfering RNA (siRNA) targeting human AKT, ERK1/2 and STAT3 were obtained from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA, USA). A498 cells (2×10<sup>5</sup> cells/well in 6-well plates) were transfected with AKT, ERK1/2 and STAT3 using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions respectively. After transfection, the cells were incubated for 24 h and then treated with simvastatin (8 µM) for MTT, migration, invasion and western blotting assays.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2j">
<title>Western blot analysis</title>
<p>Cells were collected and lysed in RIPA buffer in the presence of protease inhibitors. Protein (50 µg) was separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred onto a PVDF membrane using a wet transfer apparatus (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). Membranes were blocked with 5% non-fat milk and incubated overnight at 4°C with the primary antibodies, followed by incubation with the secondary antibodies labeled with horseradish peroxidase. Protein bands were visualized with enhanced chemiluminescence (Millipore). Protein levels were detected using chemiluminescence reader ImageQuant LAS4000 (GE, USA). Protein levels were analyzed by ImageJ software.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2k">
<title>Tumor xenograft model</title>
<p>In brief, a total of 5×10<sup>6</sup> of A498 cells were mixed with Matrigel and then injected subcutaneously in the flank of nude mice. The mice were randomly divided into two groups (10 of each group). Then mice were given of simvastatin at dose of 5 mg/kg/d by oral gavage for 5 weeks. Control mice were given the same volume of normal saline. Tumor volume and mice weight was measured every week. All of the mice were killed 50 days after inoculation of the cancer cells and the tumors were collected.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2l">
<title>Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling (TUNEL) assay</title>
<p>Xenograft tumors were formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded and then sliced into 6-µm section for TUNEL assay to identify the apoptotic cells. TUNEL Apoptosis Assay kit (Beoytime, Beijing, China) was used to stain apoptotic cells. These cells were visualized with red fluorescent under a fluorescence microscope (Olympus).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2m">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>The student's two-tailed t-test was used to determine statistical differences between treatment and control values. Differences were considered statistical significant when p&lt;0.05. All data are presented as the mean ± SD of three independent experiments.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Simvastatin inhibits cell proliferation of renal cancer cells</title>
<p>To study the effects of simvastatin on the proliferation of RCC cells, A498 and 786-O cells were exposed to different concentrations of simvastatin for 48, 72 and 96 h in MTT assay. Consequently, simvastatin significantly inhibited the proliferation of A498 and 786-O cells in a time- and dose-dependent manner (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g001">Fig. 1A and 1B</xref>). The viability of A498 and 786-O cells was reduced to 52.6% and 38.8% after treatment with simvastatin (16 µM) for 72 hours, with the IC50 of 18.434±1.26 µM and 16.311±1.21 µM, respectively.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062823-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Simvastatin suppressed cell viability of A498 and 786-O cells.</title>
<p>The effect of simvastatin on cell viability was measured by MTT assay. (A) A498 cells and (B) 786-O cells were treated with simvastatin for 48, 72 and 96 h. Simvastatin significantly inhibited cell viability of both cell lines in a dose-and time-dependent manner. Morphological changes of A498 and 786-O cells induced by simvastatin were displayed. Images of (C) A498 and (D) 786-O cells before and after addition of simvastatin (16 µm) were taken at 48 h. After treated with simvastatin for 48 h, apoptotic bodies in (C) A498 and (D) 786-O cells can be observed by optical microscope. (E) Inhibitory effect of simvastatin on colony formation. (F) The colony number was counted under microscope and colony is defined to consist of at least 50 cells. The results represent as mean ± SD of three independent experiments and the corresponding standard error. *P&lt;0.05; **P&lt;0.01.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Effect of simvastatin on cell morphology of renal cancer cells</title>
<p>Consistent with the previous findings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Menter1">[32]</xref>, we also observed a two-phased response in tumor cells to simvastatin treatment. The early phase saw a dramatic change in cell morphology within the first 6 h to 24 h. The later phase of the response occurred between 24 h to 72 h, which involved the loss of plasma membrane integrity. Morphology change of A498 and 786-O cells after treatment with simvastatin (16 µM) for 48 hours was shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g001">Fig. 1C and 1D</xref>. As represented, simvastatin caused cells to retract their processes and lose plasma membrane integrity. Shrinkage of the central cell body around the nuclei was observed at the plasma membrane, indicating apoptosis was happening in these cells. The apoptotic body was clearly visible after treatment with simvastatin (16 µM) for 48 h.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Simvastatin inhibits colony formation in renal cancer cells</title>
<p>We also examined the effects of simvastatin on cell colony formation of the RCC cells. Our study showed that simvastatin inhibited the colony formation of A498 and 786-O cells in a dose-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g001">Fig. 1E</xref>). The colony number was significantly decreased after RCC cells treated with simvastatin (8 and 16 µM), compared with the control cells (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g001">Fig. 1F</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Simvastatin induces apoptosis in renal cancer cells</title>
<p>To verify and quantify the apoptotic cells induced by simvastatin, we used Annexin V-conjugated Alexa Fluor 488 and propidium iodide staining to analyze the percentage of apoptotic cells. The percentages of early and later apoptotic cells were shown in the lower right (LR) and upper right (UR) quadrant of the histograms respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g002">Fig. 2A and 2B</xref>). The total percentage of apoptotic cells (UR+LR) increased from 2.64% in non-simvastatin treated A498 cells to 7.82% and 10.15% in simvastatin-treated cells (8 and 16 µM, respectively) after 48 hours (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>). We found the similar phenomenon in 786-O cells, and the total percentage of apoptotic cells was increased from 6.32% to 9.68% and 17.6% (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>). Treatment of A498 and 786-O cells with 8 and 16 µM simvastatin for 48 hours induced apoptosis in both cell lines, and it was in a dose-dependent manner. The significant induction of apoptosis after simvastatin treatment indicated its anti-cancer effect on RCC cells.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062823-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Simvastatin induced dose-dependent apoptosis in A498 and 786-O cells.</title>
<p>(A) A498 and (B) 786-O cells were treated with simvastatin (0, 8 and 16 µM) for 48 hours and stained with FITC-annexinV and PI. The percentage of surviving cells was shown in the lower left quadrant; the percentage of early stage of apoptosis and late stage of apoptosis cells were shown in the lower right and upper right quadrants, respectively. (C, D) The quantification of apoptosis induced by simvastatin was calculated. Data is presented as mean ± SD of three independent experiments. * P&lt;0.05, ** P&lt;0.01.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Migration and invasion are inhibited by simvastatin in renal cancer cells</title>
<p>The scratch assay was implemented to detect the effect of simvastatin on the migration of renal cancer cell. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g003">Fig. 3A and 3B</xref>, migration of A498 cells was restrained by simvastatin in a dose-dependent manner. And the similar effect was also observed in 786-O cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g003">Fig. 3C and 3D</xref>). To further test the influence of simvastatin on cell migration and invasion, A498 cells treated with the increasing concentration of simvastatin were applied to the transwell migration and Matrigel-underpinning transwell invasion assays. Our result showed that simvastatin could significantly inhibit renal cancer cell migration and invasion (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g004">Fig. 4A and 4B</xref>) in a dose-dependent manner. We found the same effect of simvastatin in 786-O cells (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g004">Fig. 4C and 4D</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0062823-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>The scratch assay showed the effect of simvastatin on cell migration.</title>
<p>(A) Scratch assay of A498 cells treated with 0, 8 and 16 µm of simvastatin. (B) The migration inhibition was transformed to the percentage of the initial distance between the two edges. The simvastatin-treated A498 cells showed a lower rate of wound closure than the control cells. (C) Scratch assay of 786-O cells treated with 0, 8 and 16 µm of simvastatin. (D) The simvastatin-treated 786-O cells showed a lower rate of wound closure than the control cells.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0062823-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Cell migration and invasion ability were inhibited by increasing concentrations of simvastatin.</title>
<p>(A) Treatment with 0, 8 and 16 µm of simvastatin showed inhibited migration and invasion of A498 cells. (B) The number of A498 cells that successfully migrated and invaded was counted. (C) Migration and invasion of 786-O cells was inhibited after treatment with different concentrations of simvastatin. (D) The decreased number of 786-O cells indicated the great inhibitory effect of simvastatin on cell mobility. Data is presented as mean ± SD of three independent experiments. * <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, ** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Simvastatin inhibits tumor growth and induce tumor cells apoptosis in a xenograft model</title>
<p>To determine whether simvastatin inhibits tumor growth in <italic>vivo</italic>, A498 cells (5×10<sup>6</sup>) were injected subcutaneously into each flank of nude mice. Tumor growth inhibition was distinct in mice treated with simvastatin at 5 mg/kg/d, compared with mice treated with PBS (*P&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g005">Fig. 5A, 5B and 5C</xref>). Furthermore, there was no significant toxicity to mice treated with simvastatin (5 mg/kg/d) by assessing mice weight of 2 groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g005">Fig. 5D</xref>). To gain insight whether simvastatin could induce apoptosis of RCC cells in <italic>vivo</italic>, paraffin sections of A498 tumor xenografts from nude mice were applied to the terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling (TUNEL) assay. The increased number of TUNEL-positive cells clearly demonstrated that the simvastatin could induce apoptosis of RCC in <italic>vivo</italic> (*p&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g005">Fig. 5E and 5F</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0062823-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Simvastatin inhibited the growth and induced cell apoptosis in RCC tumor xenografts.</title>
<p>Images of the excised tumors (A) and the nude mice (C) were taken from the control and treatment group. The arrows point to the xenografts. (B) Graphs representing the average tumor volumes of A498 xenografts treated with or without simvastatin. (D) Body weight curve of nude mice bearing A498 tumors treated with simvastatin. (E) Representative TUNEL staining (red fluoresence) of A498 renal cancer xenografts. (F) Bar graph showing quantification of the TUNEL positive A498 cells in tumor xenogafts. Data are presented as mean ± SD, *p&lt;0.05.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3g">
<title>Effects of simvastatin on expression of cell apoptosis-related proteins</title>
<p>The expression of pro-apoptotic protein Bax has been often associated with the increased apoptosis, while the anti-apoptotic protein Bcl-2 has been associated with the inhibition of apoptosis in target cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Oltvai1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Marzo1">[34]</xref>. After treated with increased concentrations of simvastatin for 48 h, we detected the expression of Bax and Bcl-2 in RCC cells. Consistent with the increased apoptosis in A498 and 786-O, the level of Bax was elevated while the level of Bcl-2 was decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>). The ratio of Bax/Bcl-2 protein level is the decisive factor to transmit the apoptosis signal. By comparing the intensity of their bands, we found the ratio of Bax/Bcl-2 was increased in a dose-dependent manner (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>). With the elevated ratio of Bax/Bcl-2, the downstream casepase-3 for apoptosis was activated. As is shown, the expression of survivin and pro-caspase-3 was decreased, while the expression of cleaved caspase-3 and cleavage of PARP was elevated.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062823-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Effects of simvastatin on the protein levels of Bcl-2, Bax, caspase 3, PARP, mTOR, AKT, and ERK in A498 and 786-O cells.</title>
<p>(A) A498 and 786-O cells were assayed for Bcl-2, Bax, full length caspase 3 and cleaved caspase 3, full length PARP and cleaved PARP by western blotting analysis with GAPDH as a control. (B) Bax/Bcl-2 ratios of A498 and 786-O cells. The densitometry value of each band was determined with ImageJ. Data was presented as mean ± SD of three independent experiments. * P&lt;0.05, ** P&lt;0.01. (C–H) The levels of mTOR, AKT, ERK and their phosphorylated forms were analyzed by western blotting. Quantitation of the p-mTOR/mTOR, p-AKT/AKT and p-ERK/ERK ratio was determined by densitometry analysis.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3h">
<title>Simvastatin inhibits proliferation and metastasis of RCC cells via AKT/mTOR and ERK pathway</title>
<p>Western blotting was used to detect the underlying mechanism by which simvastatin exerted its actions. mTOR is frequently dysregulated in cancer cells, which is under research as a potential target for RCC patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Bjornsti1">[35]</xref>. AKT, as the upstream of mTOR, plays a critical role in the proliferation, survival and motility of cancer cells and it can directly phosphorylate mTOR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Vivanco1">[36]</xref>. Therefore, we investigate the effect of simvastatin on regulation of AKT/mTOR pathway. After A498 and 786-O cells were treated with simvastatin (8 and 16 µM) for 24 and 48 hours, the phosphorylation levels of AKT and mTOR were effectively suppressed. The ratios of p-AKT/AKT as well as p-mTOR/mTOR were also decreased in a time- and dose- dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g006">Fig. 6C, 6D, 6E and 6F</xref>). ERK, which is frequency aberrantly activated in cancer cells, promotes cancer cell proliferation and metastasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Roberts1">[37]</xref>. Then we tested the effects of simvastatin on ERK activation, and found simvastatin inhibited phosphorylation of ERK in a time- and dose- dependent manner in both A498 and 786-O cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g006">Fig. 6G and 6H</xref>).</p>
<p>To investigate the role of AKT and ERK in proliferation and mobility of RCC cells, we used siRNA to knockdown AKT and ERK1/2 gene expression in A498 cells. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g007">Fig. 7A and 7B</xref>, the western blotting analysis indicated a significant reduction in protein levels of AKT and ERK1/2 in the cells transfected with AKT and ERK1/2 campared to the cells transfected with mock siRNA. Next, we evaluated simvastatin-induced apoptosis and its anti-metastasis activity in A498 cells which were tranfected with AKT or ERK1/2 siRNA. The results showed that knockdown of AKT or ERK1/2 significantly suppressed cell proliferation, migration and invasion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g007">Fig. 7C, 7D, 7E and 7F</xref>), indicating that AKT and ERK1/2 play important roles in proliferation, migration and invasion in RCC cells. In addition, simvastatin significantly inhibited the proliferation and motility in AKT or ERK1/2 knockdown cells, which suggest that inhibition of the AKT or ERK signaling pathway could enhance the anti-cancer effect of simvastatin.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062823-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Simvastatin depressed proliferation and metastasis of A498 cells that were transfected with AKT or ERK siRNA compared with the control cells (Mock).</title>
<p>(A, B) A498 cells were transfected and treated with simvastatin (8 µM), and the levels of AKT and ERK were analyzed by western blotting with GAPDH as a control. After transfected with AKT or ERK siRNA, A498 cells were incubated in the absence or presence of simvastatin (8 µM) for 48 h. The cell viability was measured by MTT assay (C, D), and cell migration and invasion was measured by transwell assay (E, F). * p&lt;0.05 or ** p&lt;0.01, compared with the untreated cells (Mock). # p&lt;0.05 or ## p&lt;0.01, compared with the cells transfected with AKT or ERK siRNA.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3i">
<title>Simvastatin inhibits proliferation and metastasis of RCC cells via IL-6 induced JAK2/STAT3 pathway</title>
<p>Previously, statins have been reported to exert pleiotropic effects on cellular signalings and functions involved in inflammation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Zhou1">[38]</xref>. Thus, we speculate whether simvastatin exerts tumor suppressive effect via modulating the tumor-promoting inflammation. Accumulating evidence has reported the pro-inflammatory JAK2/STAT3 pathway plays an critical role in cancer metastasis, apoptosis and angiogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Yu1">[39]</xref>. Notably, IL-6 is a cytokine that can activate JAK2/STAT3 signaling in cancer cells, which has an important effect on oncogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Naka1">[40]</xref>. To evaluate whether IL-6 could induce proliferation and metastasis of RCC cancer cells, we serum-starved A498 cells for 12 h and then cultured them in the absence or presence of IL-6 for 48 h. Then cell viability was measured by MTT assay, while cell metastasis ability was measured by transwell assay. We found that IL-6 could significantly induce proliferation and metastasis of A498 cells. In addition, IL-6 induced proliferation and metastasis in A498 cells could be suppressed by simvastatin (8 µM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g008">Fig. 8A and 8B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0062823-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Simvastatin inhibited IL-6 induced proliferation, migration and invasion of A498 cells via inhibition of JAK2/STAT3 pathway.</title>
<p>(A, B) A498 cells were treated with IL-6 (10 ng/ml) for 48 h, and cell vitality and motility was estimated using the MTT and transwell assay respectively. Each bar represents the mean±SD of three independent experiments. *p&lt;0.05 or ** p&lt;0.01, compared with cells treated without IL-6. (C–H) Simvastatin inhibited the phosphorylation of Jak2, STAT3 (Tyr705) and STAT3 (Ser727) in renal cancer cells in a dose- and time-dependent manner. Quantitative analysis of the p-JAK2/JAK2, p-STAT3 (Tyr705)/STAT3 and p-STAT3 (Ser727)/STAT3 ratio was displayed in each lower panel.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Next, we investigate whether simvastatin inhibits the phosphorylation of JAK2 and STAT3 induced by IL-6 in RCC cells. A498 and 786-O cells were pre-treated with simvastatin (8 and 16 µM) for 12, 24 and 48 hours, and then these cells were incubated with IL-6 (10 ng/ml) for 10 min. Western blotting analyses showed that simvastatin significantly inhibited IL-6 induced phosphorylation of JAK2 and STAT3 at both Tyr705 and Ser727 site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g008">Fig. 8C–8H</xref>).</p>
<p>To assess whether STAT3 is involved in simvastatin-induced apoptosis and anti-metastasis of RCC cells. We applied siRNA to knockdown STAT3 gene expression in A498 cells. After transfected with STAT3 siRNA or control oligonucleotides, the A498 cells were treated with simvastatin (8 µM) or control. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g009">Fig. 9A</xref>, knockdown of STAT3 significantly suppressed the proliferation, migration and invasion of A498 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g009">Fig. 9B and 9C</xref>), indicating that STAT3 plays an important role in proliferation and motility in A498 cells. In addition, combined treatment with simvastatin (8 µM) and STAT3 siRNA decreased cell viability and motility of A498 cells, compared to the cells treated with STAT3 siRNA alone. Therefore, these results suggested that IL-6 induced JAK2/STAT3 pathway was associated with survival and metastasis in RCC cells, and inhibition of IL-6 induced JAK2/STAT3 signaling pathway could sensitize RCC cells to simvastatin treatment.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062823-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption>
<title>Simvastatin suppressed proliferation and metastasis of A498 cells that were transfected with STAT3 siRNA.</title>
<p>(A) A498 cells were transfected with STAT3 siRNA and treated with simvastatin (8 µM), and the levels of STAT3 was analyzed by western blotting with GAPDH as a control. (B, C) After transfected with STAT3 siRNA, A498 cells were incubated in the absence or presence of simvastatin (8 µM) for 48 h. The cell viability was measured by MTT assay, (B), and cell migration and invasion was measured by transwell assay (C). * p&lt;0.05 or ** p&lt;0.01, compared with the untreated cells (Mock). # p&lt;0.05 or ## p&lt;0.01, compared with the cells transfected with STAT3 siRNA.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3j">
<title>Simvastatin inhibits phosphorylation of AKT, ERK and STAT3 in xenograft tumors</title>
<p>To determine whether the effect of simvastatin on the growth of A498 tumor xenograft involves the inhibition of AKT, ERK1/2 and STAT3 activity. Western blotting analysis of AKT, ERK1/2 and STAT3 activation indicated that the phosphorylation levels of AKT, ERK1/2 and STAT3 were effectively suppressed in A498 xenograft after treatment with simvastatin in <italic>vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062823-g010">Fig. 10</xref>). Overall, our study indicated that simvastatin could inhibit renal tumor growth in <italic>vivo</italic> involving the inhibition of AKT, ERK1/2 and STAT3 activity.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062823-g010" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption>
<title>Anti-tumor effects of simvastatin on A498 tumor xenograft were associated with the inhibition of AKT, ERK and STAT3 activity.</title>
<p>Western blotting analysis for the phosphorylated AKT, ERK and STAT3 levels in tumor xenograft collected from nude mice treated with or without simvastatin. Quantitation of p-AKT/AKT, p-ERK/ERK and p-STAT3/STAT3 ratio was determined by densitometry analysis. *P&lt;0.05 compared with control.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062823.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Stains are inhibitors of HMG-CoA reductase, which are widely used in the treatment of lipid disorders, especially hypercholesterolemia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Clendening1">[41]</xref>. Recently, numerous experimental data have shown that statins exhibit anti-tumor effects against various cancer cells of different origins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Osmak1">[42]</xref>. Clinical trials evaluating statins either as a single agent or in combination with other agents have also been conducted, and safety of statins has been documented extensively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Osmak1">[42]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Khanzada1">[45]</xref>. The statin family consists of various members, including lovastatin, simvastatin, fluvastatin, pravastatin, atorvastatin and so on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Roy1">[46]</xref>. Of these drugs, pravastatin failed to induced any effect in cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Menter1">[32]</xref>, whereas other stains could inhibit the proliferation of a wide variety of cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Osmak1">[42]</xref>. The observed differences in anti-tumor potential of these stains may be due to their different physicochemical properties. Specifically, their hydrophilic or lipophilic nature is of significance since variations in lipophilicity closely correlated with statins' potential to cross the cellular membrane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Osmak1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Zhang1">[47]</xref>. Considering the lipophilic nature of simvastatin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Brown1">[21]</xref>, we aim to investigate its potential effects on renal cancer cells.</p>
<p>In the present study, we showed that simvastatin could potently inhibit renal cancer cell proliferation and mobility in <italic>vitro</italic>. Accordingly, we observed the growth inhibitory and pro-apoptotic effect of simvastatin on renal cancer cells with xenograft model. Furthermore, we examined the apoptotic markers after exposure of different concentrations of simvastatin. The results indicated that simvastatin could induce cleavage of caspase-3 and PARP, down-regulate the pro-apoptotic survivin and Bax as well as up-regulate the anti-apoptotic Bcl-2. Cell cycle arrest was reported to contribute to the growth suppression of statins in cancer cells; however, we find no significant effect of simvastatin on cell cycle distribution in RCC cells (data not shown).</p>
<p>Molecular mechanisms by which statins elicit anti-tumor effects have been a recent focus of investigation. Recent studies have implicated ERK1/2 signaling pathways as mediators of statin-dependent pro-apoptotic effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Pelaia1">[48]</xref>. It has been reported that fluvastatin could suppress the proliferation of human pancreatic cancer MIAPaCa-2 cells and inhibit the phosphorylation of ERK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Bocci1">[49]</xref>. It has also been reported that lovastatin could inhibit cell growth by inhibiting the ERK activation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Johnson1">[50]</xref>. We therefore examined the change of ERK phosphorylation caused by the administration of simvastatin. Consistent with these results, we showed that the levels of phosphorylated ERK were remarkably decreased both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. To determine whether simvastatin played its anti-tumor effects via ERK pathway, we applied siRNA to knockdown ERK expression. After transfected with siRNA of ERK, the cell viability and motility were significantly decreased. These results demonstrated that knockdown of ERK could sensitize renal cancer cells to simvastatin-induced anti-cancer effect.</p>
<p>To clarify the signaling pathways underlying simvastatin-mediated responses in renal cancer cells, we further examined the effect of simvastatin on the activation of the AKT/mTOR, pathways. AKT/mTOR was involved in a number of important cellular processes including cellular survival and tumor metastasis pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Steelman1">[51]</xref>, which is frequently activated in RCC patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Thillai1">[6]</xref>. Consistently, we found that the AKT/mTOR pathway is activated in both renal cancer cell lines, suggesting that the activation of the AKT/mTOR pathway is a common event in renal cancer. In our study, we found simvastatin could significantly suppress the phosphorylation/activation of AKT, as well as inhibited its downstream effectors, mTOR. To further investigate whether the pro-apoptotic and anti-metastatic effects are mediated by targeting AKT/mTOR pathway, we applied siRNA to knockdown the expression of AKT. We found that inhibition of AKT activation by knockdown of AKT expression sensitized renal cancer cells to simvastatin-induced anti-cancer effect. Furthermore, it has been reported that AKT exerts its biological effect by phosphorylating its downstream substrates including mTOR. Phosphorylated mTOR becomes activated, leading to increased proliferation, motility and survival of cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Campese1">[16]</xref>. In addition to inhibition of AKT activity, we found that simvastatin treatment can inhibit mTOR phosphorylation. Thus, these data suggest that simvastatin may inhibit the AKT/mTOR axis to induce anti-cancer effect. It is noteworthy that the dose at which statins enhance AKT activation and survival in endothelial cells is the same dose that inhibits AKT activity in cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Kochuparambil1">[52]</xref>. This character of statins will be extremely crucial in avoiding side effects when stains are used as cancer therapeutics.</p>
<p>In the last decade, tumor-associated inflammation has become the focus of attention with good reason <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Yu2">[53]</xref>. Inflammation can contribute to multiple hallmark capabilities of cancer by supplying bioactive molecules to the tumor microenvironment, including inflammatory cytokines, and inductive signals that lead to cell proliferation and metastasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Hanahan1">[54]</xref>. Signal transducer and activator of transcription (STAT) proteins play central role in regulating cytokine-dependent inflammation and immunity. Amongst all the STATs signals, persistently activated STAT3 via IL-6 induced JAK2 activation promotes cancer cell proliferation, survival and invasion by promoting pro-oncogenic inflammatory pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Bowman1">[55]</xref>.</p>
<p>IL-6 is one of the most common cytokines in cancer, and it is overexpressed in patients with metastatic renal carcinoma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Blay1">[56]</xref>. IL-6 has been found to play important role in cell migration, invasion, proliferation, apoptosis, angiogenesis and differentiation in cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062823-Guo1">[57]</xref>. STAT3, a new oncogenic target in the setting of renal cell carcinoma, plays a critical role in promoting cell proliferation, metastasis and angiogenesis. Accumulating clinical data suggest that human RCC cell lines are sensitive to JAK2/STAT3 pathway inhibitors. Moreover, the first-line targeted drug sunitinib has recently been shown to elicit its anti-tumor activity by STAT3 inhibition.</p>
<p>To date, there is no data on the effects of simvastatin on regulating IL-6-induced JAK2/STAT3 signaling in renal cancer cells. For the first time, we found that simvastatin could significantly inhibit IL-6 induced proliferation and metastasis of RCC cells, attenuate IL-6-induced JAK2 activation, and subsequently decrease the phosphorylation of STAT3 both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. Further knockdown of STAT3 with siRNA showed significantly decreased cell proliferation and mobility. All these findings suggest JAK2/STAT3 pathway may play a crucial role in simvastatin-induced anti-tumor effects in RCC cells.</p>
<p>Taken altogether, our study demonstrates that simvastatin can markedly exhibit pro-apoptotic and metastasis inhibitory effect on RCC cells. Mechanically, we found AKT/mTOR, ERK, as well as JAK2/STAT3 pathways account for the anti-tumor effects of simvastatin. All these results imply that simvastatin may be a promising therapeutic drug for renal cancer patients.</p>
</sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Bex1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bex</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jonasch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkali</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mejean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulders</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Integrating surgery with targeted therapies for renal cell carcinoma: current evidence and ongoing trials</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>–<lpage>828</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Basso1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cassano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A survey of therapy for advanced renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Urol Oncol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Lam1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leppert</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belldegrun</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Figlin</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Novel approaches in the therapy of metastatic renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>World J Urol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Linehan1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linehan</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zbar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Focus on kidney cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Cell</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Motzer1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motzer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Systemic therapy for renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source> <volume>163</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Thillai1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thillai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rudman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Neoadjuvant and adjuvant treatment of renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Expert Rev Anticancer Ther</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>765</fpage>–<lpage>776</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Herrmann1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bierer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wulfing</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Update on systemic therapies of metastatic renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>World J Urol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Escudier1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Escudier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szczylik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oudard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Sorafenib in advanced clear-cell renal-cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>356</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Miyake1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kusuda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Efficacy and safety of temsirolimus in Japanese patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma on hemodialysis</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Oncol</source> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10147-012-0492-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10147-012-0492-7</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-ThompsonCoon1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson Coon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Bevacizumab, sorafenib tosylate, sunitinib and temsirolimus for renal cell carcinoma: a systematic review and economic evaluation</article-title>. <source>Health Technol Assess</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>184, iii–iv</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Thurnher1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thurnher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nussbaumer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruenbacher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Novel aspects of mevalonate pathway inhibitors as antitumor agents</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>3524</fpage>–<lpage>3531</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Takahashi1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishibori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The antitumour activities of statins</article-title>. <source>Curr Oncol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>246</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Schonbeck1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schonbeck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Libby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Inflammation, immunity, and HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors: statins as antiinflammatory agents?</article-title> <source>Circulation</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>II18</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Blum1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shamburek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The pleiotropic effects of statins on endothelial function, vascular inflammation, immunomodulation and thrombogenesis</article-title>. <source>Atherosclerosis</source> <volume>203</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Jick1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zornberg</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jick</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drachman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Statins and the risk of dementia</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>356</volume>: <fpage>1627</fpage>–<lpage>1631</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Campese1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campese</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors and the kidney</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1215</fpage>–<lpage>1222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Fried1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Effects of HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors (statins) on progression of kidney disease</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>576</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Sassano1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sassano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Platanias</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Statins in tumor suppression</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>260</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Goc1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kochuparambil</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Husein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Azayzih</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Simultaneous modulation of the intrinsic and extrinsic pathways by simvastatin in mediating prostate cancer cell apoptosis</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>409</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Hoque1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Statin induces apoptosis and cell growth arrest in prostate cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Brown1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tawadros</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sangar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The differential effects of statins on the metastatic behaviour of prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>1689</fpage>–<lpage>1696</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Sekine1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekine</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Furuya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Simvastatin inhibits the proliferation of human prostate cancer PC-3 cells via down-regulation of the insulin-like growth factor 1 receptor</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source> <volume>372</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Sanchez1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varela</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Statin-induced inhibition of MCF-7 breast cancer cell proliferation is related to cell cycle arrest and apoptotic and necrotic cell death mediated by an enhanced oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Cancer Invest</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>698</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Gopalan1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gopalan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Simvastatin inhibition of mevalonate pathway induces apoptosis in human breast cancer cells via activation of JNK/CHOP/DR5 signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>329</volume><supplement>(1)</supplement>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Kotamraju1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotamraju</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalyanaraman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Statin-induced breast cancer cell death: role of inducible nitric oxide and arginase-dependent pathways</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>7386</fpage>–<lpage>7394</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Relja1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Relja</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meder</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marzi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Simvastatin inhibits cell growth and induces apoptosis and G0/G1 cell cycle arrest in hepatic cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Med</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>741</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Jiang1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson-Ehle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Influence of liver cancer on lipid and lipoprotein metabolism</article-title>. <source>Lipids Health Dis</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Savas1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azorsa</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarjanazi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim-Zada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>NCI60 cancer cell line panel data and RNAi analysis help identify EAF2 as a modulator of simvastatin and lovastatin response in HCT-116 cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e18306</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Cho1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Simvastatin induces apoptosis in human colon cancer cells and in tumor xenografts, and attenuates colitis-associated colon cancer in mice</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>951</fpage>–<lpage>957</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Khurana1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caldito</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ankem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Statins might reduce risk of renal cell carcinoma in humans: case-control study of 500,000 veterans</article-title>. <source>Urology</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Yan1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Somatostatin Derivative (smsDX) Targets Cellular Metabolism in Prostate Cancer Cells after Androgen Deprivation Therapy</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e55790</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Menter1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menter</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsauer</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harirforoosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Differential effects of pravastatin and simvastatin on the growth of tumor cells from different organ sites</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e28813</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Oltvai1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oltvai</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milliman</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korsmeyer</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Bcl-2 heterodimerizes in vivo with a conserved homolog, Bax, that accelerates programmed cell death</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>609</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Marzo1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marzo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zamzami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jurgensmeier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Susin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Bax and adenine nucleotide translocator cooperate in the mitochondrial control of apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>2027</fpage>–<lpage>2031</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Bjornsti1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjornsti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The TOR pathway: a target for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Vivanco1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vivanco</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sawyers</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The phosphatidylinositol 3-Kinase AKT pathway in human cancer</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>489</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Roberts1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Der</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Targeting the Raf-MEK-ERK mitogen-activated protein kinase cascade for the treatment of cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>3291</fpage>–<lpage>3310</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Zhou1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Pleiotropic effects of statins. - Basic research and clinical perspectives</article-title>. <source>Circ J</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>818</fpage>–<lpage>826</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Yu1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jove</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The STATs of cancer–new molecular targets come of age</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Naka1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Structure and function of a new STAT-induced STAT inhibitor</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>387</volume>: <fpage>924</fpage>–<lpage>929</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Clendening1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clendening</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Targeting tumor cell metabolism with statins</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>4967</fpage>–<lpage>4978</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Osmak1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osmak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Statins and cancer: current and future prospects</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>324</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Karp1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Behlouli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lelorier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pilote</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Statins and cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>302</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Katz1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minsky</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saltz</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riedel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chessin</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Association of statin use with a pathologic complete response to neoadjuvant chemoradiation for rectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1363</fpage>–<lpage>1370</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Khanzada1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanzada</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Downward</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seckl</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Potent inhibition of small-cell lung cancer cell growth by simvastatin reveals selective functions of Ras isoforms in growth factor signalling</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>887</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Roy1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Statins and prostate cancer: role of cholesterol inhibition vs. prevention of small GTP-binding proteins</article-title>. <source>Am J Cancer Res</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>542</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Zhang1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Statins, autophagy and cancer metastasis</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source> <volume>45</volume><supplement>(3)</supplement>: <fpage>745</fpage>–<lpage>752</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Pelaia1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelaia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Renda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fratto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falcone</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Effects of statins and farnesyl transferase inhibitors on ERK phosphorylation, apoptosis and cell viability in non-small lung cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Prolif</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Bocci1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fioravanti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orlandi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collecchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Fluvastatin synergistically enhances the antiproliferative effect of gemcitabine in human pancreatic cancer MIAPaCa-2 cells</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Johnson1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woodard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okediji</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toms</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Lovastatin is a potent inhibitor of meningioma cell proliferation: evidence for inhibition of a mitogen associated protein kinase</article-title>. <source>J Neurooncol</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Steelman1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steelman</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kempf</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Roles of the Raf/MEK/ERK and PI3K/PTEN/Akt/mTOR pathways in controlling growth and sensitivity to therapy-implications for cancer and aging</article-title>. <source>Aging (Albany NY)</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Kochuparambil1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kochuparambil</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Husein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Somanath</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Anticancer efficacy of simvastatin on prostate cancer cells and tumor xenografts is associated with inhibition of Akt and reduced prostate-specific antigen expression</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source> <volume>336</volume>: <fpage>496</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Yu2"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pardoll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jove</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>STATs in cancer inflammation and immunity: a leading role for STAT3</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>798</fpage>–<lpage>809</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Hanahan1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Hallmarks of cancer: the next generation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>646</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Bowman1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turkson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jove</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>STATs in oncogenesis</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2474</fpage>–<lpage>2488</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Blay1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blay</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Negrier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Combaret</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Attali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goillot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Serum level of interleukin 6 as a prognosis factor in metastatic renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>3317</fpage>–<lpage>3322</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062823-Guo1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Interleukin-6 signaling pathway in targeted therapy for cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Treat Rev</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>904</fpage>–<lpage>910</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>